<!DOCTYPE article
 PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" article-type="preprint"><?all-math-mml yes?><?use-mml?><?origin ukpmcpa?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">bioRxiv</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>bioRxiv : the preprint server for biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub"/></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">EMS189662</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2023.10.13.562202</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="archive">PPR741708</article-id><article-version-alternatives><article-version article-version-type="status">preprint</article-version><article-version article-version-type="number">1</article-version></article-version-alternatives><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="europepmc-category"><subject>Covid-19</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Antiviral and Antibacterial Efficacy of Nanocomposite Amorphous Carbon Films with Copper Nanoparticles</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bakhet</surname><given-names>Shahd</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tamulevičienė</surname><given-names>Asta</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Vasiliauskas</surname><given-names>Andrius</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Meškinis</surname><given-names>Šarūnas</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tamulevičius</surname><given-names>Sigitas</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kašėtienė</surname><given-names>Neringa</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Malakauskas</surname><given-names>Mindaugas</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lelešius</surname><given-names>Raimundas</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zienius</surname><given-names>Dainius</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Šalomskas</surname><given-names>Algirdas</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tamulevičius</surname><given-names>Tomas</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CR1">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Institute of Materials Science of Kaunas University of Technology, K. Baršausko St. 59, LT- 51423, Kaunas, Lithuania</aff><aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Department of Physics, Kaunas University of Technology, Studentų St. 50, LT -51368, Kaunas, Lithuania</aff><aff id="A3"><label>3</label>Department of Food Safety and Quality, Lithuanian University of Health Sciences, Til žės St. 18, LT-47181 Kaunas, Lithuania</aff><aff id="A4"><label>4</label>Department of Veterinary Pathobiology, Lithuanian University of Health Sciences, Tilžės St. 18, LT-47181 Kaunas, Lithuania</aff><aff id="A5"><label>5</label>Institute of Microbiology and Virology, Lithuanian University of Health Sciences, Tilžės St. 18, LT-47181 Kaunas, Lithuania</aff><author-notes><corresp id="CR1">
<label>*</label>Corresponding author: Tel: +370 (37) 313 432, Fax: +370 (37) 314 423, T. Tamulevičius: <email>tomas.tamulevicius@ktu.lt</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted"><day>17</day><month>10</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="preprint"><day>13</day><month>10</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><permissions><ali:free_to_read/><license><ali:license_ref>https://europepmc.org/downloads/openaccess</ali:license_ref><license-p>This preprint is made available via the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://europepmc.org/downloads/openaccess">Europe PMC open access subset</ext-link>, for unrestricted research re-use and secondary analysis in any form or by any means with acknowledgement of the original preprint source.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p id="P1">Copper compound-rich films and coatings are effective against widespread viruses and bacteria. Even though the killing mechanisms are still debated it is agreed that the metal ion, nanoparticle release, and surface effects are of paramount importance in the antiviral and antibacterial efficacy of the surfaces. In this work we have investigated the behaviour of the reactive magnetron sputtered nanocomposite diamond-like carbon thin films with copper nanoparticles (DLC:Cu). The films were etched employing oxygen plasma and/or exposed to ultra-pure water aiming to investigate the differences of the Cu release in the medium and changes in film morphology. Pristine films were more effective in the Cu release reaching up to 1.3 mg/L/cm<sup>2</sup> concentration. Plasma processing resulted in the oxidation of the films which released less Cu but after exposure to water, their average roughness increased more, up to 5.5 nm. Pristine and O2 plasma processed DLC:Cu films were effective against both model coronavirus and herpesvirus after 1-hour contact time and reached virus reduction up to 2.23 and 1.63 log10, respectively. Pristine DLC:Cu films were more effective than plasma-processed ones against herpesvirus, while less expressed difference was found for coronavirus. A bactericidal study confirmed that pristine DLC:Cu films were effective against gram-negative <italic>E. coli</italic> and gram-positive <italic>E. faecalis</italic> bacteria. After 3 hours 100% antibacterial efficiency (ABE) was obtained for <italic>E. coli</italic> and 99.83% for <italic>E. faecalis.</italic> After 8 hours and longer exposures, 100% ABE was reached. The half-life inactivation of viruses was 8.10 – 11.08 minutes and for <italic>E. faecalis</italic> 19.5 – 30.2 minutes.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Antiviral surface</kwd><kwd>Antibacterial surface</kwd><kwd>amorphous carbon with copper nanoparticles</kwd><kwd>reactive magnetron sputtering</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="S1" sec-type="intro"><label>1</label><title>Introduction</title><p id="P2">In recent years, the emergence and spread of antibiotic-resistant bacteria have posed significant challenges to healthcare and public health systems worldwide [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref>]. Moreover, the recent COVID-19 pandemic illustrated the importance and need for efficient antiviral surfaces, especially on high- touch surfaces [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">2</xref>]. Intense research efforts have been applied to develop efficient antibacterial strategies. Among the various approaches explored, the utilization of novel materials with inherent antibacterial properties has shown great promise. It has been shown that silver, copper, and their compounds are among the most popular materials used for different antimicrobial and biomedicine applications [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">4</xref>] because of their high bactericidal performance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref>]. It should be noted that Cu was recognized by the United States Environmental Protection Agency (EPA) as the first metallic antimicrobial agent in 2008 but with ongoing waterborne hospital-acquired infections and antibiotic resistance, research on Cu as an antimicrobial agent is booming again [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref>]. It is commonly proven that the antimicrobial properties of metals depend very much on their size and shape, and they are most efficient when the metal is in the form of nanoparticles (NPs). Recent studies on Ag and Cu NPs have shown that there is a strong influence of metal particle size, shape, surface charge, and other factors on the release of metal ions that are critical to bactericidal and virucidal properties. Smaller metal NPs oxidize more easily, releasing more metal ions which in turn increases the bactericidal effect [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref>]. Cu is less expensive than Ag, but it is also a very practical choice because it possesses not only bactericidal but also virucidal properties at the same time and can serve as a multifunctional protecting coating [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">8</xref>].</p><p id="P3">Different approaches are used to produce nanocomposite antimicrobial surfaces with embedded metal nanoparticles where vacuum deposition methods provide excellent controllability and repeatability of the process [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref>]. One such material widely used by researchers is amorphous diamond-like (DLC) nanocomposite coating with IB group metal nanoparticles (Au, Ag, Cu), which combines the desirable mechanical properties of DLC and the bactericidal properties of metal nanoparticles. DLC is an amorphous carbon (a-C) material that exhibits exceptional mechanical, chemical, and biocompatible properties, making it an attractive candidate for various applications. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>]. On the other hand, metal nanoparticles, and especially Cu have been extensively studied for their potential for antimicrobial activity. By combining these two materials, the amorphous diamond-like carbon-copper (DLC:Cu) nanocomposite coatings offer a unique opportunity to enhance the antibacterial properties beyond what each material can achieve individually [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">3</xref>].</p><p id="P4">Probably the most popular way to produce such nanocomposites is different modes of magnetron (either reactive magnetron) sputtering where different targets (or different hydrocarbon gases) are applied. This versatile method enables the production of coatings with a controllable composition resulting in efficient bactericidal and other (optical, electrical, mechanical) properties [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref>].</p><p id="P5">The efficacy of the metal nanoparticle films and coatings depends on their ability to release the metal ions and nanoparticles in the aqueous media. It was reported that DLC:Cu [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref>], plasma- processed DLC:Ag nanocomposite films [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref>], and ultra nanocrystalline diamond protective films on Ag nanoparticles formed by the dewetting process release metal ions in aqueous media after days of immersion in water [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref>]. Studies of polyethylene nanocomposites with Ag or Cu nanoparticles indicated significant differences in the absolute amount of metal release Cu being hundreds of times more effective [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref>]. Metal release studies were not limited to ultra-pure water but included immersion in standard simulated body fluid [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref>], artificial seawater [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref>], and different pH biological solutions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">20</xref>]. In most cases, the metal release follows saturation behaviour over time and the release is understood not only as a surface phenomenon but also governed by a diffusion process in which the active metal entities must move from the interior of the coating specimen to the surface to be released [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">21</xref>].</p><p id="P6">In our previous work, we have demonstrated that DLC:Ag films are effective against <italic>Campylobacter jejuni</italic> and <italic>Listeria monocytogenes</italic> on food preparation surfaces [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">22</xref>] and <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> including methicillin-resistant strains aiming for development of antimicrobial bandages [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref>] and patches [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">23</xref>]. While gentle oxygen plasma processing was essential for the high antibacterial efficacy of DLC:Ag films [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">23</xref>] use of a harsh CF4/O2 mixture resulted in the removal of DLC matrix leaving only the agglomerated Ag filler [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref>].</p><p id="P7">Despite the broad range of DLC:Cu antibacterial studies there is still a very limited number of works investigating antiviral applications of such coatings [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">25</xref>]. Moreover, the combined antiviral and antimicrobial behaviour is often obtained using more complex compositions like, for example, Ag and Cu alloys [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">8</xref>] while in this work Cu metal filler was confirmed efficient against both types of germs alone.</p><p id="P8">In this work, we demonstrate that reactive magnetron sputtered nanocomposite amorphous diamond-like carbon films with copper nanoparticles have expressed not only the virucidal properties against animal-derived model viruses, including ribonucleic acid (RNA) containing coronavirus and deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA) containing herpesvirus but at the same time they demonstrate antibacterial effect against gram-negative <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> and gram-positive <italic>Enterococcus faecalis</italic> bacteria. The detailed studies of the Cu release in aqueous media, surface morphology evolution, and elemental changes of oxygen plasma processed, and ultra-pure water- exposed films helped in understanding their possible antibacterial and antiviral properties.</p></sec><sec id="S2" sec-type="methods"><label>2</label><title>Methods</title><sec id="S3"><label>2.1</label><title>Deposition of DLC Films</title><sec id="S4"><label>2.1.1</label><title>Deposition of DLC:Cu Films</title><p id="P9">The hydrogenated amorphous diamond-like carbon films with copper nanoparticles (DLC:Cu or otherwise a-C:H:Cu) films were deposited on crystalline silicon substrates (p-type (100), MicroChemicals GmbH, Germany) by unbalanced reactive magnetron sputtering of the 3” diameter pure Cu target (99.99% purity, Testbourne B.V., The Netherlands) using high-power impulse magnetron sputtering (HIPIMS) mode in a custom made vacuum deposition system [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>]. Argon gas was used for sputtering (99.999%, Linde Gass, Lithuania), and acetylene (99.6%, Linde Gass, Lithuania) was used as a reactive gas with 63 sccm and 10 sccm flow rates, respectively. The base pressure was 8·10<sup>-4</sup> Pa and the work pressure of 7 ± 1·10<sup>-1</sup> Pa was maintained in the chamber throughout the deposition process. The average magnetron target current was <italic>I</italic><sub>av</sub>=0.12 A, voltage <italic>V</italic>=687 V, while the pulse current was <italic>I</italic><sub>pulse</sub>=26 A with on-time <italic>t</italic><sub>on</sub>=100 μs and off-time <italic>t</italic><sub>off</sub>=10 000 μs. The substrates were grounded and the distance between the magnetron target and the samples was 0.1 m. The thickness of the nanocomposite films was monitored with a quartz microbalance and resulted in 100 nm.</p></sec><sec id="S5"><label>2.1.2</label><title>Deposition of Cu-free DLC Films</title><p id="P10">Copper-free DLC films for reference virucidal testing were deposited employing a closed drift ion beam source with an annular discharge channel from acetylene gas (99.6%. Linde Gas, Lithuania). The supplied gas is ionized close to the anode due to the discharge channel, and further ions are accelerated in a magnetic field and form a layer on the substrates mounted on the water-cooled cathode. The deposition was performed at 0.7 keV ion beam energy and working pressure 1·10<sup>-2</sup> Pa. Thickness of the film was set to 170 nm. Deposition resulted in hydrogenated amorphous diamond-like carbon (DLC) films. More details about the deposition procedure can be found in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">26</xref>].</p></sec></sec><sec id="S6"><label>2.2</label><title>O2 plasma processing of the DLC:Cu films</title><p id="P11">Some of the DLC:Cu samples were dry-etched using a Plasma-600-T (AO Kvarts, USSR) device. The samples were placed inside the processing chamber and were etched by radio frequency (RF; 13.56 MHz) oxygen plasma (99.999%, Linde Gass, Lithuania) in 133 Pa pressure and 0.3 W/cm<sup>2</sup> power for 5 s or 20 s. The RF oxygen plasma etching was intended for the removal of the thin amorphous DLC carbon layer from the Cu NP surface.</p></sec><sec id="S7"><label>2.3</label><title>Cu release in aqueous media</title><p id="P12">Cu release from the pristine and O2 plasma processed DLC:Cu films on 0.9x0.9 cm<sup>2</sup> silicon substrates into ultra-pure water (ChromAR HPLC, pH = 5.0 – 8.0, Macron Fine Chemicals, Avantor, USA) was investigated by immersing samples in 20 ml for different periods of 24 hours and 168 hours and kept at constant temperature of 5°C and 37°C. A preliminary study of Cu release in cell growth media was conducted at room temperature immersing samples for different durations from 5 to 120 minutes, more details are provided in the supplements. The released Cu compound content in the liquids was determined with a double-beam atomic absorption spectrometer (AAS) AAnalyst 400 (Perkin Elmer, USA). The Cu amount was determined from the reference solution calibration curve. The measured optical densities were normalized to the calibration curve obtaining the released Cu concentrations. The concentrations were normalized to the sample surface area.</p></sec><sec id="S8"><label>2.4</label><title>Physical Characterization of the DLC:Cu Films</title><p id="P13">Field emission gun scanning electron microscope (SEM) Quanta 200 FEG (FEI, USA) with energy dispersive X-ray spectrometer (EDS) XFlash 4030 (Bruker, Germany) was used for the imaging and surface composition analysis of DLC:Cu samples, respectively, after the deposition as well as RF oxygen plasma etching and immersion experiments. 10 kV accelerating voltage was used for the microanalysis and the obtained results were averaged from three measurements.</p><p id="P14">Focused ion beam (FIB) milling was used in SEM Helios NanoLab 650 (FEI, Netherlands) for preparation of the DLC:Cu thin film sample lamella for cross-section inspection under transmission electron microscope (TEM) Tecnai G2 F20 X-TWIN (FEI, Netherlands) with a Schottky type field emission electron source operated at 200 kV. The atomic force microscope (AFM) NanoWizard®<sup>3</sup> NanoScience (JPK instruments AG, Germany) operating in a tapping mode was used for the quantitative studies of the roughness of the pristine and water-immersed samples. An I-shaped silicon cantilever with a 13-77 N/m spring constant and a 10.0 nm typical tip curvature radius was used for the measurements.</p><p id="P15">The structure and carbon phases of the DLC matrix were probed employing a micro Raman scattering spectrometer inVia (Renishaw, United Kingdom) that is equipped with a 532 nm solid-state laser, x50 objective. Each sample was measured twice at two different locations, the final Raman spectrum of a sample is the mean result of 3 scans. The laser power on the sample was 1.75 mW, integration time was set to 10 s. The Raman Stokes signal was dispersed with a diffraction grating (2400 grooves/mm) and data was registered using a Peltier-cooled charge- coupled device (CCD) 1024×256 pixels detector. Silicon was used to calibrate the Raman setup in both Raman wavenumber and spectral intensity. Analysis of spectra was performed to reveal <italic>sp</italic><sup>2</sup> and <italic>sp</italic><sup>3</sup> carbon phases in the DLC matrix of the nanocomposite films. Peaks were fitted using two Gaussian functions and characteristic parameters such as D and G peak intensity ratio as well as G peak position and full width at half maximum (FWHM) were revealed.</p></sec><sec id="S9"><label>2.5</label><title>Antiviral Testing</title><p id="P16">The antiviral testing covered pristine DLC:Cu films, 5 s processed DLC:Cu films, and Cu-free DLC films as well as Si substrate for control.</p><sec id="S10"><label>2.5.1</label><title>Model Viral Strains Used and Cultivation of Cells</title><p id="P17">The avian infectious bronchitis virus (IBV) Beaudette strain was obtained from Dr. M. H. Verheije (Utrecht University, The Netherlands). The agent of bovine herpesvirus infection virus (BoHV-1) 4016 strain was provided by Dr. I. Jacevičienė (National Food and Veterinary Risk Assessment Institute, Lithuania).</p><p id="P18">Vero (ATCC CCL-81™) and MDBK (NBL-1, Bov.90050801) cell lines were obtained from Dr. I. Jacevičienė. Vero and MDBK/NBL-1 cells were cultured in Dulbecco’s modified eagle’s medium (DMEM, Gibco, UK) and DMEM/Nutrient Mixture F-12 (DMEM / F-12, Gibco, UK), respectively with 10% fetal bovine serum (FBS, Gibco, UK) at 37°C in a 5% CO2 incubator. Nystatin (100 units/ml) and Gentamicin (50 μg/ml) were used to prevent microbial contamination for Vero cells, while Penicillin (100 units/ml) and Streptomycin (100 μg/ml) were used to prevent microbial contamination for MDBK/NBL-1 cell. The tests were performed at temperatures of 20±2°C and 37±1°C depending on the method used.</p></sec><sec id="S11"><label>2.5.2</label><title>Cytotoxicity Control</title><p id="P19">Specific cytotoxicity was determined with Vero and MDBK cells by microscopic observation of the cells and the MTT assay as described in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27">27</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="S12"><label>2.5.3</label><title>Virucidal Efficacy Testing</title><sec id="S13"><label>2.5.3.1</label><title>Virus Treatment</title><p id="P20">The potential effectiveness of the virucidal effect of the DLC:Cu thin films and the change in viral load was evaluated by determining the tissue culture infectious dose (TCID<sub>50</sub>) of intact viruses (control) and after their exposure to films (affected viruses). Suspensions of coronaviruses and herpesviruses in 0.01 ml were incubated for 1 h at room temperature with investigated samples. Cultivation and propagation of IBV were performed by infecting Vero cells while BoHV-1 strain 4016 was cultivated in MDBK/NBL-1 cell culture [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">28</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="S14"><label>2.5.3.2</label><title>Virus Quantification</title><p id="P21">Virucidal efficiency was evaluated by comparing changes in the concentration of viruses before and after contact with the surface of DLC:Cu coatings. After 48-120 hours of incubation, the cytopathogenic effect (CPE) in cells was assessed with an optical microscope. Viral titre, mean and standard deviation (M±σ), were estimated employing Marc Binder’s TCID<sub>50</sub> calculator based on the Sperman-Kerber method[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">29</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">30</xref>]. The half-life of the viruses was calculated employing <bold>eq. S1</bold>.</p></sec><sec id="S15"><label>2.5.3.3</label><title>Viral Nucleic Acid Quantification</title><p id="P22">For IBV real-time TaqMan reverse transcription polymerase chain reaction (PCR) was performed according to Meir [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31">31</xref>]. The sequences of the conserved region of the N gene of strain IBV H120 at nucleotide positions 741–1077, consisting of 336 base pairs, were used to design primers (GenBank no. AM260960). For the reaction, StepOne™ Plus real-time PCR mix (Applied Biosystems, UK) was used. Amplification plots were evaluated, and threshold cycle (Ct) values were determined using a Mastercycler RealPlex2 (Eppendorf, Germany). The reaction is carried out at 45°C for 10 minutes and 95°C for 10 minutes, 40 cycles consisting of a denaturation step at 95°C for 15 s, and an elongation step at 60°C for 45 s.</p><p id="P23">For BoHV-1 real-time PCR was performed according to Abril <italic>et al.</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32">32</xref>]. BoHV-1 glycoprotein B gene sequences were amplified for quantitative real-time PCR (TaqMan). Oligonucleotide primers and MGB-labelled probes were synthesized by Invitrogen (USA). Amplifications were performed using TaqMan Universal Master Mix II (catalogue no. 4440038, Applied Biosystems, USA). Mastercycler RealPlex2 (Eppendorf, Germany) was used to record amplification plots that were analysed for determining Ct. Isolation of DNA was performed using the Genomic DNA purification kit (K0721, Thermo Fisher Scientific, USA) following the manufacturer’s instructions. Primers and probes for quantitative real-time PCR were generated with Primer Express equipment (version 1.0, Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA) to amplify BoHV-1 glycoprotein B sequences with an open reading frame (ORF). Oligonucleotide primers and MGB-labelled probes were synthesized by Invitrogen (USA). Extensions were performed according to a standard protocol. PCR reaction conditions: 2 min at 50°C, 10 min at 95°C, followed by 40 cycles consisting of a denaturation step at 95°C for 15 s and an elongation step at 60°C for 1 min.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="S16"><label>2.6</label><title>Antibacterial Testing</title><p id="P24">The antimicrobial efficacy of the DLC:Cu films was tested employing ATCC 25922 strain of gram-negative <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> and ATCC 29212 strain of gram-positive <italic>Enterococcus faecalis</italic> bacteria. The bacteria were kept in -80°C brain-heart infusion (BHI, Oxoid, UK) broth with a 30% glycerol supplement before the test. <italic>E. coli</italic> and <italic>E. faecalis</italic> bacteria were inoculated on Lysogeny (LB, Liofilchem, Italy) agar and grown for 24 h at 35°C. PBS broth was used to prepare the suspension (6.7-12 ·10<sup>6</sup> Colony forming units/ml). The pristine DLC:Cu films were disinfected in 70% w/w ethanol before the test, dried in a biosafety cabinet, and then sterilized with a UV lamp for 24 hours. Sterile samples were placed in a 24-well plate, 1 ml of <italic>E. coli</italic> or <italic>E. faecalis</italic> bacterial suspension was poured on them and 1 ml <italic>of E. coli</italic> and <italic>E. faecalis</italic> bacterial culture suspensions were incubated in wells without the samples as control. The samples were incubated for 24 h at 35°C. After 3, 8, and 24 hours, a 100 μl sample was taken from each well. Tenfold dilutions (up to 10<sup>-3</sup> in PBS broth) were prepared and plated on LB agar plates. The inoculations were repeated three times. The plates were incubated for 24 hours at 35°C. The antibacterial activity (ABE, %) of DLC:Cu films against <italic>E. coli</italic> and <italic>E. faecalis</italic> bacteria was calculated normalizing to the reference sample (<bold>eq. S2</bold>) after 3, 8, and 24 hours. The half-life employing <bold>eq. S1</bold>. The tests were repeated twice.</p></sec><sec id="S17"><label>2.7</label><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p id="P25">The experimental results were analysed with OriginPro 2015 (OriginLab) and the mean comparative studies of TCID<sub>50</sub>, and Ct estimation were done by two-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) with the quantitative data expressed as the M±σ. A statistical significance was considered at *<italic>p</italic> &lt;0.0001.</p></sec></sec><sec id="S18" sec-type="results"><label>3</label><title>Results</title><sec id="S19"><label>3.1</label><title>Properties of the DLC:Cu films in Aqueous Media</title><p id="P26">Reactive magnetron sputtered DLC:Cu films had nanoparticles visible by the SEM. The SEM micrograph analysis indicated that the mean nanoparticle diameter is 20.5±5.2 nm (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1 a</xref>). The TEM film cross-section analysis of the FIB cut lamella revealed that nanoparticles are distributed over the whole 100 nm thickness of the film and are <italic>ca.</italic> 2 times smaller than nanoparticles visible on the surface (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1 b, d, f, h</xref>). Some layering is seen at the initial stage of the film growth that was earlier observed experimentally by Jurkevičiūtė <italic>et al.</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33">33</xref>] and analysed theoretically by Kairaitis <italic>et al.</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34">34</xref>] where it is explained as a dominating layered growth mechanism over columnar one at lower substrate temperatures due to the lower diffusion coefficient.</p><p id="P27">For the antimicrobial analysis the experiments are usually carried out in aqueous environments mimicking the natural environment and human temperature therefore it is important to investigate their behaviour in similar time frames and temperature ranges [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref>]. Moreover, as was reported earlier for Ag nanoparticles containing nanocomposite films, they released met al ions more effectively after short O<sub>2</sub> plasma processing [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">23</xref>]. The effect of short plasma processing duration appears as contrast at the nanoparticle edges in the SEM micrographs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1 c</xref>), while in the TEM analysis, no obvious differences are seen (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1 d</xref>). Pristine film immersion in ultra-pure water results in well-expressed contrast change over the film thickness (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1 f</xref>) that could be attributed to the decrease in Cu content compared to the lightweight amorphous DLC matrix. Plasma-processed films seem to release Cu only from the very top layers (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1 h</xref>) although their surface morphology became more pronounced after exposure to water (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1 g</xref>).</p><p id="P28">Elemental analysis obtained with EDS indicated that plasma processing increases the oxygen content in the films and decreases the relative amount of Cu (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2 a</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD3">Table S1</xref>) but changes are minor. Immersion in water makes a bigger change in decreasing copper content whereas in combination with plasma pre-processing immersion makes an extra effect on the increased oxygen content.</p><p id="P29">The changes seen in the electron microscope micrographs are in line with the released Cu compound concentrations in ultra-pure water where after 24 h exposure at 37°C pristine sample released more met al content than 5 s plasma processed one (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2 b</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD3">Table S2</xref>). In most of the cases, longer immersions resulted in a bigger met al release. Longer plasma processing did not increase the Cu release as was initially expected.</p><p id="P30">Oxygen plasma processed DLC:Cu sample visually appears almost identical to pristine samples, <italic>i.e.,</italic> copper red, but after exposure to water they change their colour into green shades characteristic of colored surface films (patina) that form on copper alloys [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35">35</xref>] (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD3">Figure S1</xref>). These color changes are related to copper oxidation to cuprous oxide in air and further reaction into cupric oxide that in the presence of carbon dioxide and humidity turns into copper carbonate hydroxide or otherwise malachite [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36">36</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39">39</xref>].</p><p id="P31">As seen from the SEM micrographs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>) both O2 plasma processing and exposure to water modify the surface therefore the roughness of the samples was also inspected with AFM, and it was confirmed that pristine samples have lower average and root mean square roughness than water exposed samples (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>). Immersion duration has a bigger effect on the increasing roughness than the durations of plasma processing.</p><p id="P32">After exposure to water changes in the nanocomposite films resulted in the changes not only in the loss in met al filler but also in some slight modification of the DLC matrix. As seen from the Raman spectra (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4 a, b, c</xref>) and their deconvolution parameter using two typical D and G bands representing <italic>sp</italic><sup>2</sup> and <italic>sp</italic><sup>3</sup> bonded carbon phases (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4 d, e, f</xref>) the DLC matrix is stable. The oxygen plasma treatment does not influence the G peak position (1546-1547 cm<sup>-1</sup>). It was previously observed that DLC film processing by O<sub>2</sub> plasma can increase the <italic>sp</italic><sup>3</sup><italic>/sp</italic><sup>2</sup> ratio [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40">40</xref>]. Compared to pristine film the G peak tends to redshift by a maximum of 15 cm<sup>-1</sup> and it is more prominent under higher immersion temperatures (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4 d</xref>). According to the 3-stage model described by J. Robertson [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41">41</xref>], the initial G peak position is in Stage 3 which shows the evolution of the structure from a-C carbon to ta-C carbon. The shift of G peak position is related to the increase of <italic>sp</italic><sup>3</sup> amount in the films. The G peak FWHM is a measure of disorder and increases with an increase of disorder [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42">42</xref>]. The biggest changes in the peak width are observed at higher temperatures but the GFWHM varies only by 12 cm<sup>-1</sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4 e</xref>). The variation is uneven as at shorter periods (24h) and lower temperatures (5°C) the G<sub>FWHM</sub>slightly increases, whereas keeping in water for longer periods decreases the values of GFWHM. When samples were kept at a higher temperature in water, the variation of G<sub>FWHM</sub> is more expressed which can be related to the rearrangement of surface layers as more oxygen is incorporated into the surface and less copper is released into the water. The peak intensity ratio ID/IGvaries depending on the applied treatment. Tendencies are changing depending on the applied temperature. For low temperatures independently of plasma treatment, the ID/IGratio is increasing indicating a decrease of <italic>sp</italic><sup>3</sup> fraction in the films [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42">42</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R44">44</xref>] which is contraversary to the redshift of G peak position. The intensity ratio fluctuates more when samples are kept at higher temperatures. The variation in ID/IG ratio (0.45 – 0.65) could be attributed to the signal enhancement of copper NPs observed on the surface after oxygen plasma treatment. Copper incorporation into DLC affects its structure and a higher concentration of Cu reveals in <italic>sp<sup>2</sup></italic> richer structure [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref>]. The observed minimal changes in the peak shape (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4 a-c</xref>) and revealed parameters like G peak position, FWHM, and ID/IG ratio support the idea that despite microscopic and visual changes of the films which are mainly related to Cu oxidation the DLC matrix stays almost intact with minor structural change compared to pristine DLC:Cu films.</p></sec><sec id="S20"><label>3.2</label><title>Cytotoxicity test</title><p id="P33">It can be stated that all investigated film samples (DLC:Cu, DLC:Cu+O<sub>2</sub>, and DLC) and Si substrate did not have an active destructive effect on the tested VERO and MDBK cell cultures during cytotoxicity tests - no changes in cell morphology and monolayer, no change in pH and transparency of the medium were observed after 1 hour of exposure.</p></sec><sec id="S21"><label>3.3</label><title>Virucidal efficacy</title><p id="P34">DLC:Cu and DLC:Cu+O<sub>2</sub> samples showed virucidal effects against both model viruses (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>). In the case of IBV as depicted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5 a</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD3">Table S3</xref> DLC:Cu and DLC:Cu+O<sub>2</sub> samples showed the same amount of decrease in the number of coronaviruses by 2.23 log<sub>10</sub>/ml TCID<sub>50</sub>/ml compared to the IBV control or 99.41%. The decrease in BoHV-1 titre was 1.63 log<sub>10</sub>/ml TCID<sub>50</sub> or 97.7% for DLC:Cu sample, and 0.80 log<sub>10</sub>/ml TCID<sub>50</sub> or 84.2% for the DLC:Cu+O<sub>2</sub> samples compared to BoHV-1 control (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5 a</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD3">Table S4</xref>). For the Si control sample, the titre of IBV and BoHV-1 decreased by 1.77 log<sub>10</sub>/ml TCID<sub>50</sub> and 0.13 log<sub>10</sub>/ml TCID<sub>50</sub>, respectively.</p></sec><sec id="S22"><label>3.4</label><title>Real-time PCR test</title><p id="P35">The comparative analysis of IBV and BoHV-1 inactivation and viral bioactivity properties of the investigated samples by evaluating post-contact quantification of TCID<sub>50</sub> titre (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5 a</xref>) and RT- PCR threshold cycle Ct values (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5 b</xref>) showed similar tendencies. The PCR Ct values for IBV ranged from 33.2 for DLC to 34.6 for DLC:Cu (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5b</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD3">Table S3</xref>). The investigation of DLC:Cu sample showed statistically reliable (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.0001) rates of IBV RNA degradation and directly influenced the PCR Ct value. While Ct for the BoHV-1 ranged from 28.9 for DLC:Cu+O<sub>2</sub> (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.001) to 29.8 (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.0001) for DLC:Cu. The increase in Ct value can be attributed to virus inactivation properties of DLC:Cu sample, which passively reduces the number of viruses in control samples when they come into contact with virus particles.</p><p id="P36">For a better impression of the Cu release from the DLC:Cu in the virucidal study, the preliminary analysis of the aqueous medium volume and thickness above the immersed sample influence on the released Cu concentration was conducted in DMEM. Two different film area samples, namely 2.1 cm<sup>2</sup> and 55.1 cm<sup>2</sup> were immersed in the same 5 ml volume of liquid and different size Petri dishes. The AAS measurement results depicted in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD3">Figure S2</xref> indicated that accumulated Cu concentration is bigger and approaching 2.5 mg/L/cm<sup>2</sup> when the liquid volume was relatively big compared to the area. For the big area samples where aqueous medium was just covering the sample surface the Cu release was almost 10 times smaller in the same solvent volume. If compared with the Cu release in ultra-pure water (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2b</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD3">Table S2</xref>) the release in DMEM is faster. And that might contribute to positive virucidal and antibacterial results.</p></sec><sec id="S23"><label>3.5</label><title>Antibacterial properties</title><p id="P37">As the plasma pre-processed DLC:Cu films exhibited a lower virucidal effect than the pristine DLC:Cu films the antibacterial study was limited only to the latter. The antibacterial study showed that the DLC:Cu films had an expressed negative effect on the survival of both investigated bacteria strains. The results were confirmed by the identical tests which gave very similar results. No gram-negative <italic>E. coli</italic> bacteria were found in all samples after 3 hours as well as over longer periods, resulting in 100% antibacterial efficiency (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD3">Table S5 and Table S6</xref>).</p><p id="P38">The study employing gram-positive <italic>E. faecalis</italic> bacteria after 3 hours in Test 1 resulted in 99.83±0.01% antibacterial efficacy and bacteria-killing half-life of 19.52±0.23 min (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD3">Table S7</xref>) and in Test 2 resulted in 98.38±0.25% and 30.21±1.15 min (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD3">Table S8</xref>). After longer investigated durations no <italic>E. faecalis</italic> bacteria were found in all samples and 100% antibacterial efficiency was obtained.</p><p id="P39">The silicon substrates used as a reference had a smaller effect on tested bacteria and a decrease in the number of bacteria was less pronounced over longer testing periods (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD3">Table S5-S8</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="S24" sec-type="discussion"><label>4</label><title>Discussion</title><p id="P40">The electron and atomic force microscopies confirmed the changes in the DLC:Cu films after exposure to ultra-pure water depending on the plasma pre-processing that was primarily recognized as changes in colour seen by the naked eye. The Cu nanoparticle filler tends to be released from the pristine samples faster than compared to the plasma-processed ones and over 24 h it is released more effectively at human temperature than in a cool environment. These differences could be beneficial where controlled release over longer periods is expected and, in such cases, short surface modification with O<sub>2</sub> plasma could prolong the use of nanocomposite DLC:Cu films. Over a longer period of 168 h more Cu is released in the cool environment because probably it is already saturated over the same period at 37°C. The concentration range of Cu released in water was up to 1 mg/L/cm<sup>2</sup> and it is at a similar level as it was reported for carbonaceous matrix nanocomposite films with silver where Juknius <italic>et al.</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref>] measured up to 0.4 mg/L/cm<sup>2</sup> Ag release from O<sub>2</sub> plasma processed DLC:Ag film after 2-day soaking in 35°C 10 ml water, while Merker <italic>et al.</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref>] obtained up to 0.1 mg/L/cm<sup>2</sup> of Ag in 20 ml water at 7-days immersion at 37°C depending on the protective ultra nanocrystalline diamond film thickness. The study of Tamayo <italic>et al.</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref>] covered longer time immersion periods in 10 ml of water extending over 3 months and resulting in Ag release of 0.35 mg/L/cm<sup>2</sup> for polyethylene nanocomposites with Ag nanoparticles and 90 mg/L/cm<sup>2</sup> with Cu. A big difference between Ag and Cu was addressed by the fact that Cu is susceptible to oxidation.</p><p id="P41">Differences in the Cu compound release in the case of plasma-processed samples indicate different surface properties of oxidised Cu. This might be related to differences in solubility as reported by Wei <italic>et al.</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R45">45</xref>] where Cu salt fillers tended to release more Cu than met allic filler. Based on the elemental changes after water exposure detected by EDS and changes in sample colour, it suggests that oxidation and maybe hydroxide formation took place [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35">35</xref>]. Dissolution and depletion of met allic NPs were explained theoretically by Quezada <italic>et al.</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R46">46</xref>] employing a shrinking core model where it is assumed that while the NP reacts with the environment it forms a soluble product and a porous layer called shell, which is formed around a solid core of the NPs.</p><p id="P42">The actual virucidal and bactericidal testing experiments are usually performed not in ultra-pure water but in different media. Therefore, Cu ion release experiments were reported previously in a range of solvents, for example, Wu <italic>et al.</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref>] investigated Cu release from mesoporous silica xerogels in standard simulated body fluid, and the released concentration correlated with the initial Cu content. It was also reported that alloyed composite implants tend to release their compounds differently depending on the solvent pH [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">20</xref>]. In our study, a bigger Cu concentration registered by AAS after immersion in DMEM containing 2.0% of bovine fet al serum compared to ultra-pure water could be attributed to the influence of the different aqueous medium composition and therefore differences in the surface effects. The observed saturation of released Cu over time is related to the volume of the solvent and concentration gradient in the liquid layer. The observed logarithmic release trends were reported by others as well [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">21</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R45">45</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R46">46</xref>] and could be related to limited-source diffusion in the case of thin films with low total met al volume fraction. This preliminary study of short-duration immersion in DMEM confirmed that Cu release from DLC:Cu film is not momentarily, and it also suggests that a significant amount of Cu should have been released during the 1-hour antiviral testing. Nevertheless, having in mind a small aqueous medium gap in the actual experiment, <italic>c.a.</italic> 100 μm and a small volume (10 μl) the Cu release might be limited similarly to the big-sample-thin-layer example. While in the antimicrobial testing, where samples were immersed in PBS broth Cu release should have been more pronounced. This hypothesis cannot be directly confirmed with the AAS measurements because it requires bigger sampling volumes than available in the actual virucidal testing experiments.</p><p id="P43">Summing up, the expected improvement in oxygen plasma processing observed for DLC: Ag films did not translate in the DLC:Cu study and the obtained differences could be addressed to the very different stability of the Ag and Cu met als and changes of the Cu compound release after oxidation. Most of the studies suggested that the generation of reactive oxygen species (ROS), protein oxidation, lipid peroxidation, and DNA degradation in bacteria are the major mechanisms of antibacterial action of the Cu NPs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R47">47</xref>]. The Cu ions released from surfaces was confirmed having a direct action on a variety of targets and/or result in the production of ROS, leading to the nucleic acids denaturation and damaged virion integrity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R48">48</xref>]. Such mechanisms of action could also contribute to the inactivation of viruses. It was reported that during the incubation of the virus-containing droplet on investigated coatings, the virus particles may be inactivated both by their direct interaction with the surface and by their interaction with the released Cu ions. Upon consideration of the differences in sizes of the virus particle and the ions released in the liquid solution, their diffusion coefficients (Stokes-Einstein equation) and resulting transport speeds will be very different, where the virus particle migration is much slower than that of ions, indicating that any antiviral effect from the ions would occur faster [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R49">49</xref>].</p><p id="P44">The decrease in virus titre and quantity of nucleic acid detected after contact with DLC:Cu films were obtained. The differences in virus titre reduction after BoHV-1 treatment on DLC:Cu, DLC:Cu+O2, DLC, and Si control showed the key role of Cu. The comparison of virucidal efficacy of DLC:Cu and DLC:Cu+O<sub>2</sub> showed the importance of quicker Cu release and concentration leading to a difference of 0.83 log<sub>10</sub> (up to 7 times) in virus reduction. The Cu influence in virucidal efficacy for BoHV-1 was also confirmed by RT-PCR. The real-time PCR detected a difference up to 2 times in the rate of DNA degradation after treatment on surfaces of pristine DLC:Cu compared to slower Cu-releasing plasma pre-processed films. The analysis of these results suggests that BoHV-1 proteins and nucleic acids are targeted by Cu nanoparticles or ions, but damaged at different speeds. BoHV-1 proteins located on the surface are probably targeted first and the DNA genome is affected later. A similar effect of Cu ions was detected by investigation of human herpes simplex virus DNA, envelope, and capsid biomolecules [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R50">50</xref>].</p><p id="P45">The reduction of virus titre after IBV treatment also indicated the key role of Cu.</p><p id="P46">The comparison of the virucidal efficacy of pristine DLC:Cu and plasma pre-processed film indicated similar virus reduction results despite the difference in the amount of released Cu indicated by the AAS analysis. The importance of the released Cu on the virucidal effect on IBV was confirmed by RT-PCR. The RT-PCR detected up to 1.5 times difference in the rate of RNA degradation after treatment on surfaces of pristine DLC:Cu compared to plasma-pre-processed film. Similarly like for herpes virus, the study for IBV suggests that proteins and nucleic acids are targeted by Cu nanoparticles or/and ions but might be damaged at different speeds. IBV protein capsid protects nucleic acid for replication, spike protein, membrane glycoprotein, envelope protein, and nucleocapsid proteins are located on the surface and are the first target while RNA genome sequences are affected later at significantly lower rates [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R51">51</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R55">55</xref>].</p><p id="P47">In general, a bigger decrease in viruses in the case of pristine DLC:Cu films compared to O<sub>2</sub> plasma processed indicates the role of bigger released Cu content in the medium. Differences in the IBV and BoHV-1 titre reduction for investigated films imply that IBV is more dependent on the surface as a tremendous decrease was noticed on the film-free silicon surface. While BoHV-1, despite smaller virus reduction in absolute number was following the expected Cu release trend.</p><p id="P48">Bactericidal studies showed different kinetics of inactivation for bacteria possessing different types of cell walls. The tested bacteria, gram-negative <italic>E coli,</italic> and gram-positive <italic>E. faecalis</italic> are the most widely used indicators of faecal contamination [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R56">56</xref>]. The main components of the <italic>E. faecalis</italic> cell wall are a thick layer of peptidoglycan, wall teichoic acids, and lipoteichoic acids, while <italic>E. coli</italic> cell wall has an inner and outer membrane, separated by a thin peptidoglycan layer. The different structures of bacterial cell walls can be a key factor in a different susceptibility or resistance to various factors and it might lead to the different kinetics of inactivation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R47">47</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R57">57</xref>].</p><p id="P49"><italic>E. coli</italic> bacteria were more sensitive (100% or 6.94 log<sub>10</sub> reduction in 3 hours) to the bactericidal effect of DLC:Cu than <italic>E. faecalis</italic> but the hypothesis that investigated films are more effective against gram-negative bacteria would require a wider scope study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R58">58</xref>].</p><p id="P50">Our research, evaluating the antiviral and antibacterial effectiveness of nanocomposite DLC:Cu films, demonstrated that surfaces containing copper nanoparticles showed a strong effect on both model viruses and bacteria.</p></sec><sec id="S25" sec-type="conclusions"><label>5</label><title>Conclusions</title><p id="P51">Reactive magnetron-sputtered nanocomposite amorphous diamond-like carbon films with copper nanoparticles (DLC:Cu) effectively release the Cu compounds in the aqueous media and the total amount depends on the storing temperature, liquid film over the sample, and the medium itself.</p><p id="P52">Oxygen plasma pre-processing of the deposited DLC:Cu films oxidise the Cu and prolong the met al compound release in the medium which could be beneficial when controlled instead of immediate release is expected.</p><p id="P53">The DLC matrix remains almost intact despite the different exposures to plasma and followed immersion in ultra-pure water as confirmed by the <italic>sp</italic><sup>2</sup>/<italic>sp</italic><sup>3</sup> phase studies via Raman spectroscopy analysis.</p><p id="P54">DLC:Cu films were effective against both tested model RNA-containing coronavirus and DNR- containing herpesvirus as well as both tested gram-positive <italic>E. faecalis</italic> and gram-negative <italic>E. coli</italic> bacteria although differences in efficacy were observed.</p><p id="P55">The differences in the amount of released Cu from pristine and plasma-processed DLC:Cu films were directly seen in virucidal efficacy for both investigated viruses, but it was more expressed for BoHV-1 where it was observed as a decrease in virus titre and PCR cycle threshold value. While for IBV the released Cu concentration-related tendency was obtained only in Ct value.</p><p id="P56">The preliminary study indicated that no <italic>E.coli</italic> were found after 3 hours of contact with pristine DLC:Cu films while for <italic>E. faecalis</italic> up to 99.83±0.01% antibacterial efficiency was obtained and 19.52±0.23 min bacteria killing half-life was determined. The differences could be addressed by the differences in the bacteria cell walls, but a wider range of bacteria should be tested to confirm the hypothesis.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="SM"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1"><label>Graphical abstract</label><media xlink:href="EMS189662-supplement-Graphical_abstract.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" id="d2aAdFbB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD2"><label>Research Highlights</label><media xlink:href="EMS189662-supplement-Research_Highlights.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" id="d2aAdFcB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD3"><label>Supplementary information</label><media xlink:href="EMS189662-supplement-Supplementary_information.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" id="d2aAdFdB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack id="S26"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>A special thanks go to project No. 13.1.1-LMT-K-718-05-0018 members Dr. S. Račkauskas, Dr. R. Mardosaitė, M. A. Baba, G. Khatmy, M. Ilickas, Dr R. Zykus, Dr A. Urbas, M. Mikutis, O. Ulčinas, J. Baltrukonis, E. Nacius, M. Vainoris, D. Mazur from the Kaunas University of Technology, Lithuanian University of Health Sciences, and Altechna R&amp;D for their technical assistance.</p><sec id="S27"><title>Funding</title><p>This project has received funding from the European Regional Development Fund (project No. 13.1.1-LMT-K-718-05-0018) under a grant agreement with the Research Council of Lithuania (LMTLT). Funded as the European Union’s measure in response to the COVID-19 pandemic.</p></sec></ack><sec id="S28" sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data Availability</title><p id="P57">The datasets used or analysed during the current study are available from the corresponding author upon reasonable request.</p></sec><fn-group><fn id="FN1" fn-type="con"><p id="P58"><bold>Author Contributions</bold></p><p id="P59">Conceptualization and methodology – T.T., A.Š., M. M.; Investigation – A.T., A.V., N.K., R.L., A.Š.; Data analysis N.K., M.M., R.L., A.Š., D.Z., S.B., A.T., T.T., Writing – original draft D.Z., S. B., M.M., N.K., T.T., S.T.; Writing – review &amp; editing; D.Z., S.B., R.L., A.Š., Š.M., M.M., S.T., T.T., Supervision – T.T., A.Š., M.M.; Funding acquisition – T.T.</p><p id="P60">All authors have read and agreed to the published version of the manuscript.</p></fn><fn id="FN2" fn-type="conflict"><p id="P61"><bold>Conflicts of Interest</bold></p><p id="P62">The authors declare no conflict of interest.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><ref id="R1"><label>[1]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nwobodo</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Antibiotic resistance: The challenges and some emerging strategies for tackling a global menace</article-title><source>Journal of Clinical Laboratory Analysis</source><year>2022</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>10</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9459344</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35949048</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jcla.24655</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>[2]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saud</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Richards</surname><given-names>CAJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Stanton</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anti-viral organic coatings for high touch surfaces based on smart-release, Cu2+ containing pigments</article-title><source>Progress in Organic Coatings</source><year>2022</year><volume>172</volume><fpage>6</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9393488</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36035655</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.porgcoat.2022.107135</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>[3]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jastrzebski</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Induced Biological Response in Contact with Ag-and Cu-Doped Carbon Coatings for Potential Orthopedic Applications</article-title><source>Materials</source><year>2021</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>22</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8070217</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33918582</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ma14081861</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>[4]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Birkett</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Multi-functional bioactive silver- and copper-doped diamond-like carbon coatings for medical implants</article-title><source>Acta Biomaterialia</source><year>2023</year><volume>167</volume><fpage>54</fpage><lpage>68</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37392935</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>[5]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sanzone</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Antimicrobial and Aging Properties of Ag-, Ag/Cu-, and Ag Cluster-Doped Amorphous Carbon Coatings Produced by Magnetron Sputtering for Space Applications</article-title><source>Acs Applied Materials &amp; Interfaces</source><year>2022</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>10154</fpage><lpage>10166</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35179883</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>[6]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vincent</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hartemann</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Engels-Deutsch</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antimicrobial applications of copper</article-title><source>International Journal of Hygiene and Environmental Health</source><year>2016</year><volume>219</volume><fpage>585</fpage><lpage>591</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27318723</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>[7]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shigetoh</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirao</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Ishida</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Durability and Surface Oxidation States of Antiviral Nano-Columnar Copper Thin Films</article-title><source>Acs Applied Materials &amp; Interfaces</source><year>2023</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>20398</fpage><lpage>20409</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10141257</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36947007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acsami.3c01400</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>[8]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meister</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Nanoscale copper and silver thin film systems display differences in antiviral and antibacterial properties</article-title><source>Scientific Reports</source><year>2022</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>10</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9063624</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35505071</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-022-11212-w</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>[9]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Merker</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Antimicrobial propensity of ultrananocrystalline diamond films with embedded silver nanodroplets</article-title><source>Diamond and Related Materials</source><year>2019</year><volume>93</volume><fpage>168</fpage><lpage>178</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.diamond.2019.02.003</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>[10]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tamulevicius</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Meskinis</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Tamulevicius</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Rubahn</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diamond like carbon nanocomposites with embedded metallic nanoparticles</article-title><source>Reports on Progress in Physics</source><year>2018</year><volume>81</volume><fpage>31</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29076461</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>[11]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meskinis</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Optical properties of diamond like carbon films containing copper, grown by high power pulsed magnetron sputtering and direct current magnetron sputtering: Structure and composition effects</article-title><source>Thin Solid Films</source><year>2015</year><volume>581</volume><fpage>48</fpage><lpage>53</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tsf.2014.11.045</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>[12]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khamseh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Magnetron-sputtered copper/diamond-like carbon composite thin films with super anti-corrosion properties</article-title><source>Surface &amp; Coatings Technology</source><year>2018</year><volume>333</volume><fpage>148</fpage><lpage>157</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.surfcoat.2017.11.012</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>[13]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lan</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name><name><surname>Ou</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Ou</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Development of silver-containing diamond-like carbon for biomedical applications. Part I: Microstructure characteristics, mechanical properties and antibacterial mechanisms</article-title><source>Ceramics International</source><year>2013</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>4099</fpage><lpage>4104</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21598123</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>[14]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>AY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dependence of piezoresistive behavior upon Cu content in Cu-DLC nanocomposite films</article-title><source>Diamond and Related Materials</source><year>2023</year><volume>136</volume><fpage>10</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.diamond.2023.109935</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>[15]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Developing transparent copper-doped diamond-like carbon films for marine antifouling applications</article-title><source>Diamond and Related Materials</source><year>2016</year><volume>69</volume><fpage>144</fpage><lpage>151</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.diamond.2016.08.012</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>[16]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Juknius</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Antimicrobial Properties of Diamond-Like Carbon/Silver Nanocomposite Thin Films Deposited on Textiles: Towards Smart Bandages</article-title><source>Materials</source><year>2016</year><volume>9</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5503000</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28773494</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ma9050371</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>[17]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tamayo</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Release of silver and copper nanoparticles from polyethylene nanocomposites and their penetration into Listeria monocytogenes</article-title><source>Materials Science and Engineering C-Materials for Biological Applications</source><year>2014</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>24</fpage><lpage>31</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24857461</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>[18]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>XH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Antibacterial properties of mesoporous copper-doped silica xerogels</article-title><source>Biomedical Materials</source><year>2009</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>6</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19605960</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>[19]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Joseph</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Israel</surname><given-names>OK</given-names></name><name><surname>Edet</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparative Evaluation of Metal Ions Release from Titanium and Ti-6Al-7Nb into Bio-Fluids</article-title><source>2009</source><year>2009</year><volume>6</volume><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://drj.mui.ac.ir/index.php/drj/article/view/76">http://drj.mui.ac.ir/index.php/drj/article/view/76</ext-link> (Visited August 29, 2023)</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3075453</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21528023</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>[20]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mutlu-Sagesen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Ergun</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Karabulut</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ion release from metal-ceramic alloys in three different media</article-title><source>Dental Materials Journal</source><year>2011</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>598</fpage><lpage>610</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21946479</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>[21]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Benhacine</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Hadj-Hamou</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Habi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Development of long-term antimicrobial poly (epsilon-caprolactone)/silver exchanged montmorillonite nanocomposite films with silver ion release property for active packaging use</article-title><source>Polymer Bulletin</source><year>2016</year><volume>73</volume><fpage>1207</fpage><lpage>1227</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00289-015-1543-9</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>[22]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zakariene</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Diamond like carbon Ag nanocomposites as a control measure against Campylobacter jejuni and Listeria monocytogenes on food preparation surfaces</article-title><source>Diamond and Related Materials</source><year>2018</year><volume>81</volume><fpage>118</fpage><lpage>126</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.diamond.2017.12.007</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>[23]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Juknius</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Preclinical Study of a Multi-Layered Antimicrobial Patch Based on Thin Nanocomposite Amorphous Diamond Like Carbon Films with Embedded Silver Nanoparticles</article-title><source>Materials</source><year>2020</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>14</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7412193</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32708717</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ma13143180</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>[24]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tamulevicius</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Structuring of DLC:Ag nanocomposite thin films employing plasma chemical etching and ion sputtering</article-title><source>Nuclear Instruments &amp; Methods in Physics Research Section B-Beam Interactions with Materials and Atoms</source><year>2014</year><volume>341</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.nimb.2013.09.052</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>[25]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Purwar</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Novel sustainable filter for virus filtration and inactivation</article-title><source>Scientific Reports</source><year>2022</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>9</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9156824</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35650235</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-022-13316-9</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>[26]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meskinis</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Ion beam energy effects on structure and properties of diamond like carbon films deposited by closed drift ion source</article-title><source>Vacuum</source><year>2010</year><volume>84</volume><fpage>1133</fpage><lpage>1137</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vacuum.2010.01.047</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>[27]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mosmann</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rapid colorimetric assay for cellular growth and survival: Application to proliferation and cytotoxicity assays</article-title><source>Journal of Immunological Methods</source><year>1983</year><volume>65</volume><fpage>55</fpage><lpage>63</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6606682</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>[28]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lisov</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Vrublevskaya</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Lisova</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Leontievsky</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Morenkov</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A 2,5-Dihydroxybenzoic Acid-Gelatin Conjugate: The Synthesis, Antiviral Activity and Mechanism of Antiviral Action Against Two Alphaherpesviruses</article-title><source>Viruses-Basel</source><year>2015</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>5343</fpage><lpage>5360</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4632386</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26501311</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/v7102878</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>[29]</label><element-citation publication-type="web"><source>TCID50 calculator v2 17 01 20 MB - Excel sheet to calculate TCID50 titers (Spearman &amp; Kärber method) by Marco Binder</source><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.klinikum.uni-heidelberg.de/zentrum-fuer-infektiologie/molecular-virology/welcome/downloads">https://www.klinikum.uni-heidelberg.de/zentrum-fuer-infektiologie/molecular-virology/welcome/downloads</ext-link> (Visited August 29, 2023)</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>[30]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wulff</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name><name><surname>Tzatzaris</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Monte Carlo simulation of the Spearman-Kaerber TCID<sub>50</sub></article-title><source>Journal of Clinical Bioinformatics</source><year>2012</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>5</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3331834</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22330733</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/2043-9113-2-5</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>[31]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meir</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Maharat</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Farnushi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Simanov</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Development of a real-time TaqMan (R) RT-PCR assay for the detection of infectious bronchitis virus in chickens, and comparison of RT-PCR and virus isolation</article-title><source>Journal of Virological Methods</source><year>2010</year><volume>163</volume><fpage>190</fpage><lpage>194</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7112792</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19781572</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jviromet.2009.09.014</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><label>[32]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abril</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Both viral and host factors contribute to neurovirulence of bovine herpesviruses 1 and 5 in interferon receptor-deficient mice</article-title><source>Journal of Virology</source><year>2004</year><volume>78</volume><fpage>3644</fpage><lpage>3653</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC371052</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15016885</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JVI.78.7.3644-3653.2004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><label>[33]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jurkeviciute</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Structure and density profile of diamond-like carbon films containing copper: Study by X-ray reflectivity, transmission electron microscopy, and spectroscopic ellipsometry</article-title><source>Thin Solid Films</source><year>2017</year><volume>630</volume><fpage>48</fpage><lpage>58</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tsf.2016.10.015</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><label>[34]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kairaitis</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Galdikas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mechanisms and Dynamics of Layered Structure Formation During Co-Deposition of Binary Compound Thin Films</article-title><source>Coatings</source><year>2020</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>18</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/coatings10010021</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><label>[35]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fredj</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Burleigh</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transpassive Dissolution of Copper and Rapid Formation of Brilliant Colored Copper Oxide Films</article-title><source>Journal of the Electrochemical Society</source><year>2011</year><volume>158</volume><fpage>C104</fpage><lpage>C110</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1149/1.3551525</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><label>[36]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nassau</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Gallagher</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Graedel</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The characterization of patina components by X-ray diffraction and evolved gas analysis</article-title><source>Corrosion Science</source><year>1987</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>669</fpage><lpage>684</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0010-938X(87)90049-7</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R37"><label>[37]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Adeloju</surname><given-names>sB</given-names></name><name><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>YY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Corrosion resistance of CU2O and CuO on copper surfaces in aqueous media</article-title><source>British Corrosion Journal</source><year>1994</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>309</fpage><lpage>314</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1179/000705994798267485</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R38"><label>[38]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nakayama</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Notoya</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Osakai</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Highly Selective Determination of Copper Corrosion Products by Voltammetric Reduction in a Strongly Alkaline Electrolyte</article-title><source>Analytical Sciences</source><year>2012</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>323</fpage><lpage>331</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22498457</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R39"><label>[39]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>D’Amario</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Dau</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Copper Carbonate Hydroxide as Precursor of Interfacial CO in CO<sub>2</sub> Electroreduction</article-title><source>Chemsuschem</source><year>2022</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>13</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9314821</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35289108</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cssc.202102506</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R40"><label>[40]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yun</surname><given-names>DY</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of H-2 and O-2 plasma etching treatment on the surface of diamond-like carbon thin film</article-title><source>Applied Surface Science</source><year>2008</year><volume>254</volume><fpage>7925</fpage><lpage>7928</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.apsusc.2008.03.170</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R41"><label>[41]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ferrari</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Interpretation of Raman spectra of disordered and amorphous carbon</article-title><source>Physical Review B</source><year>2000</year><volume>61</volume><fpage>14095</fpage><lpage>14107</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1103/PhysRevB.61.14095</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R42"><label>[42]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ferrari</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Raman spectroscopy of amorphous, nanostructured, diamondlike carbon, and nanodiamond</article-title><source>Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society a-Mathematical Physical and Engineering Sciences</source><year>2004</year><volume>362</volume><fpage>2477</fpage><lpage>2512</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15482988</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R43"><label>[43]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dwivedi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Investigation of properties of Cu containing DLC films produced by PECVD process</article-title><source>Journal of Physics and Chemistry of Solids</source><year>2012</year><volume>73</volume><fpage>308</fpage><lpage>316</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jpcs.2011.10.019</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R44"><label>[44]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>AY</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>QM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Microstructure and mechanical property of diamondlike carbon films with ductile copper incorporation</article-title><source>Surface &amp; Coatings Technology</source><year>2015</year><volume>272</volume><fpage>33</fpage><lpage>38</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.surfcoat.2015.04.027</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R45"><label>[45]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>XJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>ZD</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>YX</given-names></name><name><surname>Tay</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Polymer antimicrobial coatings with embedded fine Cu and Cu salt particles</article-title><source>Applied Microbiology and Biotechnology</source><year>2014</year><volume>98</volume><fpage>6265</fpage><lpage>6274</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24705507</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R46"><label>[46]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Quezada</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Quintero</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Salgado</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Estay</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Garcia</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Understanding the Phenomenon of Copper Ions Release from Copper-Modified TFC Membranes: A Mathematical and Experimental Methodology Using Shrinking Core Model</article-title><source>Nanomaterials</source><year>2020</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>18</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7353439</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32521633</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/nano10061130</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R47"><label>[47]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chatterjee</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Chakraborty</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Basu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mechanism of antibacterial activity of copper nanoparticles</article-title><source>Nanotechnology</source><year>2014</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>12</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24584282</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R48"><label>[48]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Warnes</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Summersgill</surname><given-names>EN</given-names></name><name><surname>Keevil</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inactivation of Murine Norovirus on a Range of Copper Alloy Surfaces Is Accompanied by Loss of Capsid Integrity</article-title><source>Applied and Environmental Microbiology</source><year>2015</year><volume>81</volume><fpage>1085</fpage><lpage>1091</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4292492</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25452290</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.03280-14</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R49"><label>[49]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Merkl</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name><surname>McInerney</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Sotiriou</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antiviral Activity of Silver, Copper Oxide and Zinc Oxide Nanoparticle Coatings against SARS-CoV-2</article-title><source>Nanomaterials</source><year>2021</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>9</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8155969</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34067553</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/nano11051312</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R50"><label>[50]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sagripanti</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Routson</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonifacino</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Lytle</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mechanism of copper-mediated inactivation of herpes simplex virus</article-title><source>Antimicrobial Agents and Chemotherapy</source><year>1997</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>812</fpage><lpage>817</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC163800</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9087495</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/aac.41.4.812</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R51"><label>[51]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ishida</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antiviral Activities of Cu2+ Ions in Viral Prevention, Replication, RNA Degradation, and for Antiviral Efficacies of Lytic Virus, ROS-Mediated Virus, Copper Chelation</article-title><source>World Scientific News</source><year>2018</year><volume>99</volume><fpage>148</fpage><lpage>168</lpage><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.worldscientificnews.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/04/WSN-99-2018-148-168.pdf">http://www.worldscientificnews.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/04/WSN-99-2018-148-168.pdf</ext-link> (Visited August 29, 2023)</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="R52"><label>[52]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mantlo</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></name><name><surname>Paessler</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Seregin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Luminore CopperTouch Surface Coating Effectively Inactivates SARS-CoV-2, Ebola Virus, and Marburg Virus In Vitro</article-title><source>Antimicrobial Agents and Chemotherapy</source><year>2021</year><volume>65</volume><fpage>5</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8218611</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33903111</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.01390-20</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R53"><label>[53]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Behzadinasab</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Chin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hosseini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Poon</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Ducker</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A Surface Coating that Rapidly Inactivates SARS-CoV-2</article-title><source>Acs Applied Materials &amp; Interfaces</source><year>2020</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>34723</fpage><lpage>34727</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7385996</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32657566</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acsami.0c11425</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R54"><label>[54]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gurunathan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Antiviral Potential of Nanoparticles-Can Nanoparticles Fight Against Coronaviruses?</article-title><source>Nanomaterials</source><year>2020</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>29</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7557932</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32825737</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/nano10091645</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R55"><label>[55]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hutasoit</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Sars-CoV-2 (COVID-19) inactivation capability of copper-coated touch surface fabricated by cold-spray technology</article-title><source>Manufacturing Letters</source><year>2020</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>93</fpage><lpage>97</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7455544</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32904558</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mfglet.2020.08.007</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R56"><label>[56]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thevenon</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Characterization of fecal indicator bacteria in sediments cores from the largest freshwater lake of Western Europe (Lake Geneva, Switzerland)</article-title><source>Ecotoxicology and Environmental Safety</source><year>2012</year><volume>78</volume><fpage>50</fpage><lpage>56</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22209635</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R57"><label>[57]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>XM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Copper-based nanoparticles against microbial infections</article-title><source>Wiley Interdisciplinary Reviews-Nanomedicine and Nanobiotechnology</source><year>2023</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>25</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37037205</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R58"><label>[58]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Characterization of RNA damage under oxidative stress in Escherichia coli</article-title><source>Biological Chemistry</source><year>2012</year><volume>393</volume><fpage>123</fpage><lpage>132</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3404489</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22718628</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1515/hsz-2011-0247</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>DLC:Cu film surface SEM (a, c, e, g) and cross-section TEM (b, d, f, h) micrographs of pristine film (a, b), 5 s O<sub>2</sub> plasma processed (c, d), immersed in pure water for 24 hours at 37°C (e, f), and affected by both, plasma processed and exposed to water, with the identified length scale bars. The inset in (a) depicts nanoparticle diameter distribution. The insets in TEM micrographs depict a higher magnification view of the area close to the surface. The uniform colour area in (d) is due to the rotation of the original micrograph.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS189662-f001"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Pristine DLC:Cu and O<sub>2</sub> plasma processed film elemental composition in atomic percent obtained by EDS before and after exposure to ultra-pure water for 24 h at 37°C (a) and AAS measured copper content released in ultra-pure water after plasma processing and immersion exposure condition indicated below the histogram (b). Asterix indicates results close to the measurement detection limit.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS189662-f002"/></fig><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Pristine (a) and ultra-pure water exposed DLC:Cu film 2.5 μm x 2.5 μm sized area topographies obtained with AFM depending on the plasma processing durations 5 s (b, d) and 20 s (c, e) and immersion temperatures 5°C (b, c) and 37°C (d, e). Samples were immersed for 168 h. Numerical values in the top right corner indicate average roughness (R<sub>a</sub>) and root mean square roughness (R<sub>q</sub>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS189662-f003"/></fig><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>DLC matrix structure Raman analysis of pristine (a), 5 s (b), and 20 s (c) oxygen plasma processed DLC:Cu films after exposure in ultra-pure water at different conditions as indicated in the legends. The deconvoluted spectra into <italic>sp</italic><sup>2</sup> and <italic>sp</italic><sup>3</sup> phases expressed as G position (G<sub>pos</sub>) (d) and G peak full width at half maximum (G<sub>FWHM</sub>)(e), G and D peak intensity ratio (ID/IG)(f) after different sample exposure indicated below the histograms.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS189662-f004"/></fig><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Antiviral efficacy of DLC, DLC:Cu, DLC:Cu+O<sub>2</sub> films and controls, (a) virus titre log<sub>10</sub> reduction of IBV, and BoHV-1 after 1 h of contact with films (**<italic>p</italic> = 0.004 and ***<italic>p</italic> ≤ 0.0001). (b) RT-PCR cycle threshold (Ct) values (**<italic>p</italic> = 0.001 and ***<italic>p</italic> ≤ 0.0001).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS189662-f005"/></fig><fig id="F6" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Antibacterial efficacy of the DLC:Cu obtained after immersion in <italic>E. faecalis</italic> and <italic>E. coli</italic> PBS broth and sampling after different periods from 3 to 24 hours. The impact of silicon substrate alone is indicated for reference.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS189662-f006"/></fig></floats-group></article>