<!DOCTYPE article
 PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" article-type="preprint"><?all-math-mml yes?><?use-mml?><?origin ukpmcpa?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">bioRxiv</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>bioRxiv : the preprint server for biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2692-8205</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">EMS193153</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2023.12.30.573521</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="archive">PPR780800</article-id><article-version-alternatives><article-version article-version-type="status">preprint</article-version><article-version article-version-type="number">2</article-version></article-version-alternatives><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Transient power-law behaviour following induction distinguishes between competing models of stochastic gene expression</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nicoll</surname><given-names>Andrew G.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Szavits-Nossan</surname><given-names>Juraj</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>Martin R.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Grima</surname><given-names>Ramon</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CR1">*</xref></contrib><aff id="A1"><label>1</label>School of Biological Sciences, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/01nrxwf90</institution-id><institution>University of Edinburgh</institution></institution-wrap>, <city>Edinburgh</city><postal-code>EH9 3BF</postal-code>, <country country="GB">United Kingdom</country></aff><aff id="A2"><label>2</label>School of Physics and Astronomy, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/01nrxwf90</institution-id><institution>University of Edinburgh</institution></institution-wrap>, <city>Edinburgh</city><postal-code>EH9 3FD</postal-code>, <country country="GB">United Kingdom</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="CR1">
<label>*</label>Correspondence: <email>ramon.grima@ed.ac.uk</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted"><day>01</day><month>01</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="preprint"><day>30</day><month>12</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><permissions><ali:free_to_read/><license><ali:license_ref>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is licensed under a <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">CC BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p id="P1">What features of transcription can be learnt by fitting mathematical models of gene expression to mRNA count data? Given a suite of models, fitting to data selects an optimal one, thus identifying a probable transcriptional mechanism. Whilst attractive, the utility of this methodology remains unclear. Here, we sample steady-state, single-cell mRNA count distributions from parameters in the physiological range, and show they cannot be used to confidently estimate the number of inactive gene states, i.e. the number of rate-limiting steps in transcriptional initiation. Distributions from over 99% of the parameter space generated using models with 2, 3, or 4 inactive states can be well fit by one with a single inactive state. However, we show that for many minutes following induction, eukaryotic cells show an increase in the mean mRNA count that obeys a power law whose exponent equals the sum of the number of states visited from the initial inactive to the active state and the number of rate-limiting post-transcriptional processing steps. Our study shows that estimation of the exponent from eukaryotic data can be sufficient to determine a lower bound on the total number of regulatory steps in transcription initiation, splicing, and nuclear export.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec id="S1" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p id="P2">A broad molecular-level picture of transcription in eukaryotes is well established [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">3</xref>]. This picture involves the opening of chromatin which allows RNA polymerase II (RNAP) to access the promoter region, the sequential binding of several transcriptional factors and of RNAP to the promoter leading to the closed preinitiation complex (PIC), the unwinding of promoter DNA to create an open PIC that starts productive elongation of nascent RNA and finally the detachment of the RNAP leading to a mature RNA molecule. Despite this detailed molecular knowledge, it has thus far proved difficult to understand the large degree of heterogeneity in gene expression observed in a population of cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">4</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref>].</p><p id="P3">Mathematical modelling provides a potential approach to understand how the observed statistics of gene expression emerge from the molecular description of transcription [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref>]. While in principle, models can be constructed that encapsulate each and every biochemical reaction step that is relevant to transcription, in practice this strategy is futile, because given the huge parameter space, its numerical exploration via simulations would require prohibitive amounts of computational power. A practical way forward is through the use of much simpler models composed of a (relatively) small set of effective reactions, where each reaction captures the overall effect of a large number of elementary reactions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">8</xref>]. These reactions often correspond to the rate-limiting steps (the slowest steps of the mechanism) since these are principal determinants of a model’s output.</p><p id="P4">A large variety of such minimal models of stochastic gene expression have been developed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>]. Once a model is formulated, its output can be fit to experimental data, thus leading to the estimation of the rate constants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref>]. Moreover, by assessing the relative goodness of fit between a suite of models, one can potentially arrive at a best model that captures salient features of the data [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref>]. This model selection holds great promise since in principle it can be used to sift between competing mechanisms that at first sight appear equally likely to explain a set of measurements.</p><p id="P5">The majority of the published minimal stochastic models of transcription are either special cases of, or can be reduced to, the following <italic>N</italic>-state model:</p><p id="P6"><disp-formula id="FD1"><label>(1)</label><mml:math id="M1"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable columnalign="left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:msub><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:msub><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>…</mml:mo><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:msub><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>N</mml:mtext><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:msub><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mtext>N</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:msub><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:msub><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>∅</mml:mo><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="P7">Here <italic>G</italic><sub>1</sub> to <italic>G</italic><sub><italic>N</italic>−1</sub> (for <italic>N</italic> &gt; 1) are inactive states from which mRNA (<italic>M</italic>) synthesis is not possible and <italic>G</italic><sub><italic>N</italic></sub> is an active state from which it is. The rate (constant) parameters governing the transition from gene state <italic>i</italic> to <italic>i</italic> + 1, mRNA synthesis in gene state <italic>N</italic> and mRNA degradation are <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub>, <italic>ρ</italic>, and <italic>d</italic>, respectively. Each of the various reactions represents an important rate-limiting step in the transcriptional process (the rates of each reaction are shown above the reaction arrows). We note that while an extension of this model to include reversible reactions between gene states or transcription from multiple gene states is likely more realistic [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref>] (this will be considered later on), nevertheless it has many more rate parameters than the irreversible model and hence the latter is in more common usage [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">21</xref>]. It can be shown that the irreversible model corresponding to reaction scheme (1) predicts the Fano factor (variance divided by the mean) of mRNA counts to be greater than or equal to 1, which is the case for most genes; however this means that it cannot describe the sub-Poissonian expression (Fano factor less than 1) measured for a few eukaryotic and prokaryotic genes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">22</xref>]. The case <italic>N</italic> = 1, i.e. no inactive states, is that of constitutive (non-regulated) expression. Bursty expression, i.e. where transcription occurs only in short bursts, separated by intervals of inactivity implies the presence of at least one inactive state, i.e. <italic>N</italic> ≥ 2. For example, the commonly used telegraph model, also called the 2-state model, is a special case of this model with <italic>N</italic> = 2 (one inactive state and one active state) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">23</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">26</xref>]. Many genes seemingly exhibit bursty expression [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27">27</xref>]. For these there is evidence that generally the number of active states is just one (since the distribution of the total time spent in the active states is measured to be exponential [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">28</xref>]) but the number of inactive states can be greater than one (since the distribution of the total time spent in the inactive states can be non-monotonic with a peak at a non-zero value [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">29</xref>]). Most experimental evidence suggests that the number of inactive states is just one for prokaryotic genes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref>]. On the other hand, for eukaryotic genes, some studies make the case that it is larger than one [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">21</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">29</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31">31</xref>] while others are consistent with one [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">28</xref>]. In particular the telegraph model, with one active and one inactive state, well fits the statistics of mRNA counts for thousands of sequenced mammalian genes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">25</xref>], seemingly contradicting studies that make a case for models with more inactive states. We emphasize that because the number of inactive states can be interpreted as the number of rate-limiting steps in initiation, their determination is of biological importance since these are often the likely points of gene regulation.</p><p id="P8">Unfortunately, commonly used methods to determine the number of rate-limiting steps present several challenges. These methods can be divided into two types according to the type of data used: (i) direct or indirect measurements of the distribution of the total time spent in the inactive states [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">28</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31">31</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33">33</xref>]; (ii) measurements of the time-dependent distribution of mRNA counts following a perturbation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref>]. Methods of type (i) are the most reliable because if the distribution of time in the inactive state is measured to be non-exponential then the number of active states is greater than one. However, direct measurements of this type are challenging because live-cell measurements are low-throughput and require genome-editing [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34">34</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35">35</xref>]. Methods of type (ii) while indirect are often the preferred choice since mRNA count data per cell can nowadays be easily obtained for several genes using single molecule fluorescence <italic>in situ</italic> hybridization (smFISH) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36">36</xref>] or single-cell sequencing (scRNA-Seq) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">25</xref>]. These require measurements of the distribution of mRNA counts at several time points, each of which is calculated from an independent sub-population of cells. Inference methods using this type of data maximize the likelihood [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37">37</xref>] or utilise a Bayesian framework [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref>] to fit stochastic models of gene expression with varying number of inactive states to temporal count data, in the process selecting an optimal, best-fit model. It is currently unclear how far away from steady state does one need to be for these methods to perform robustly – if the shape or another property of the steady-state distribution of mRNA counts encapsulates information about the number of inactive states then the latter could be estimated. There is some evidence from comparison of the telegraph and the <italic>N</italic>-state model with <italic>N</italic> = 3 that it is not easy to estimate the number of gene states from steady-state count data [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38">38</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39">39</xref>] but a systematic analysis, especially one for larger values of <italic>N</italic>, remains missing.</p><p id="P9">These methods also suffer from some notable disadvantages: they are not easy to use because of their technical sophistication and the quality of inference is highly dependent on how well one can correct the data for static extrinsic noise, i.e. cell-to-cell variability in the rate parameters. The latter is a particularly significant issue because static extrinsic noise tends to increase the variance of the distribution of mRNA counts (relative to its mean) and hence can lead to the incorrect estimation of rate parameters [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40">40</xref>]; in addition, it can lead to wrong deduction of one or more inactive states when actually there are none. For example, in Ref. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41">41</xref>] it was shown that for 150 mammalian genes after correcting for cellular phenotypic states such as size and cell cycle stage, the variance of fluctuations was reduced to that of a Poisson distribution which is obtained from a model with no inactive states.</p><p id="P10">Summarising, we have identified two open questions: (i) is steady-state count data sufficient to estimate the number of inactive states? (ii) can one devise an estimation method that is very simple to use, does not need large volumes of temporal data and which is robust to static extrinsic noise? A schematic summarising these questions and the whole model deduction process is illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>.</p><p id="P11">In this paper we provide answers to these two questions. We consider the model (1) with one active state and a general number of inactive states, i.e. <italic>N</italic> ≥ 2. We first conclusively show that steady-state mRNA count data is not typically sufficient to distinguish between the <italic>N</italic> = 2 model [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">23</xref>] and more complex models with <italic>N</italic> = 3, 4 and 5 gene states. In particular we identify a mapping of rate parameters between the telegraph model and the other types of models that leads to distributions of mRNA counts that in the vast majority of cases are practically model-independent. Next we devise a simple method to overcome the difficulties of the inference method based on steady-state data and other methods in the literature that utilise the time-dependent distribution of mRNA counts. We analytically show that following induction, the initial increase of the mean mRNA count with time is described by a power law whose exponent is solely dependent on the number of gene states between the initial inactive state and the active state. We confirm the accuracy of the theoretical result using simulations and then apply it to data collected for various cell types to provide a robust estimate of a lower bound for the total number of inactive gene states. Interestingly, our results show that this bound: is not affected by static extrinsic noise due to cell-to-cell variability; <italic>is</italic> valid for a large class of networks of gene states (of which (1) is a special case); and in principle <italic>is</italic> sufficient to accurately infer the number of gene states using bulk data, rather than single-cell data.</p></sec><sec id="S2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="S3"><title>Theoretical limitations of inference from steady-state mRNA count data</title><p id="P12">We first remark that there are two fundamental limitations to what can be inferred from the steady-state distribution of the number of mRNA counts of the <italic>N</italic>-state model defined by reaction scheme (1). The steady-state distribution of mRNA counts, <italic>P</italic>(<italic>m</italic>), is dependent only on the values of <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub><italic>/d</italic> and <italic>ρ/d</italic>, i.e. the rate parameters normalised by the mRNA degradation rate parameter. Hence, if by means of some fitting algorithm we had to achieve a perfect match between the theoretical and an experimentally measured distribution of mRNA counts, it would not be possible to infer the absolute values of <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub> and <italic>ρ</italic> unless the degradation rate <italic>d</italic> was also estimated by means of a separate experiment. A second limitation is that the steady-state distribution <italic>P</italic>(<italic>m</italic>) is invariant to permutations of the set of rate constants <italic>k</italic><sub>1</sub>, <italic>k</italic><sub>2</sub>, …, <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>N</italic>−1</sub>, i.e. the rate constants of the reactions from one inactive state to another or to the active state are interchangeable. For example, this means that by matching of the steady-state mRNA distributions measured experimentally to that of an <italic>N</italic>-state model, we cannot distinguish between a model where there is fast transcription factor binding to the promoter followed by slow RNAP binding from a model where the speeds of these two processes are reversed. See <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Note 1</xref> for a queuing theory based derivation of the steady-state distribution of mRNA counts of the <italic>N</italic>-state model (see also [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42">42</xref>]) and a proof of the two aforementioned results.</p></sec><sec id="S4"><title>A physically meaningful mapping between the rate parameters of the telegraph and <italic>N</italic>-state (<italic>N</italic> &gt; 2) models</title><p id="P13">We note that the steady-state distribution of reaction scheme (1) is not invariant with respect to <italic>N</italic> and hence in principle it might be possible to distinguish between models with different total number of states. Of course, there is always the possibility that two models with different <italic>N</italic> have very similar steady-state distributions of mRNA counts for particular choices of rate parameter values, in which case they would be practically indistinguishable. In particular since the telegraph model is the commonest model in the literature, it is of interest to understand whether it can accurately match the steady-state mRNA distributions of gene expression models with more than 2 states, i.e. with multiple inactive states.</p><p id="P14">The natural way to investigate this question would be to (i) generate a large number of rate parameters sets of the <italic>N</italic>-state model; (ii) for each of these sets, use an optimization algorithm to find rate parameters of the telegraph model which minimize the distance between its steady-state mRNA distributions and that of a given <italic>N</italic>-state model. If this procedure identifies rate parameters for which the minimal distribution distance is very small then it means that the telegraph and the <italic>N</italic>-state model are essentially indistinguishable. While desirable, this procedure is computationally expensive and would be difficult to employ to explore large swathes of parameter space.</p><p id="P15">To avoid these difficulties we devise a different method. We define the distribution <italic>f</italic><sub><italic>N</italic></sub> (<italic>τ</italic>) of the waiting time <italic>τ</italic> between two successive transcription events of the <italic>N</italic>-state model, its mean denoted ⟨<italic>τ</italic>⟩<sub><italic>N</italic></sub> and variance <inline-formula><mml:math id="M2"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. The procedure then consists of the following steps: (i) generate thousands of rate parameters sets of the <italic>N</italic>-state model with <italic>N</italic> = 3, 4, 5; (ii) for each parameter set, calculate the rate parameters of an effective telegraph model by matching its waiting time statistics to that of the <italic>N</italic>-state model. In particular we enforce <italic>f</italic><sub><italic>N</italic></sub>(0) = <italic>f</italic><sub>2</sub>(0), ⟨<italic>τ</italic>⟩<sub><italic>N</italic></sub> = ⟨<italic>τ</italic>⟩<sub>2</sub> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M3"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. This means that the rate parameters of the effective telegraph model (denoted by a star superscript) are given in terms of the rate parameters of the <italic>N</italic>-state model by:</p><p id="P16"><disp-formula id="FD2"><label>(2)</label><mml:math id="M4"><mml:msup><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:mo>∗</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="1em"/><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>∗</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mo>⟨</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>⟩</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>⋅</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>CV</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="1em"/><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>∗</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>⋅</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>CV</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:math></disp-formula> where <italic>τ</italic><sub>1→<italic>N</italic></sub> is the random time it takes to go from state 1 to state <italic>N</italic> in the <italic>N</italic>-state model and CV<sub>1→<italic>N</italic></sub> is its coefficient of variation (ratio of the standard deviation to the mean). For a derivation of <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD1">Eq. (2)</xref> see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Note 1</xref> and for their interpretation see the Discussion section. Finally, step (iii), using the rate parameters calculated in the previous step, calculate the Wasserstein distance (WD) between the cumulative mRNA count distribution of the effective telegraph model (<italic>P</italic><sup><italic>c</italic></sup>) and that of the <italic>N</italic>-state model (<italic>Q</italic><sup><italic>c</italic></sup>) defined as <inline-formula><mml:math id="M5"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>WD</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:mi>∑</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>|</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>|</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> where <italic>i</italic> is the number of mRNA counts. If the WD is small over the whole scanned parameter space then we know that generally there exists an effective telegraph model that captures, to a good degree, the salient features of the mRNA count distribution of the <italic>N</italic>-state model. We note that our choice of the WD as a measure of similarity is motivated by the fact that it has a simple interpretation (it considers how much and how far probability mass has to be moved to reshape a histogram into another [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43">43</xref>]) and that it does not suffer from well-known issues of other common metrics [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R44">44</xref>].</p><p id="P17">The theoretical justification of step (ii) is as follows. Using queuing theory, in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Note 1</xref> we show that the steady-state mRNA count distribution of the <italic>N</italic>-state model is completely determined by the Laplace transform of <italic>f</italic><sub><italic>N</italic></sub> (<italic>τ</italic>), which we shall denote by <inline-formula><mml:math id="M6"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo>∗</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, where <italic>s</italic> is the variable in Laplace space. Now <inline-formula><mml:math id="M7"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>lim</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mi>∞</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo>∗</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, which implies that the condition <italic>f</italic><sub><italic>N</italic></sub>(0) = <italic>f</italic><sub>2</sub>(0) forces <inline-formula><mml:math id="M8"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo>∗</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M9"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>∗</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> to agree in the limit of large <italic>s</italic>. In addition, by matching the first two moments of the waiting distribution, ⟨<italic>τ</italic>⟩<sub><italic>N</italic></sub> = ⟨<italic>τ</italic>⟩<sub>2</sub> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M10"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, we effectively are matching <inline-formula><mml:math id="M11"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo>∗</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M12"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>∗</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> for small <italic>s</italic>. This is because by the definition of the Laplace transform the <italic>r</italic>th moment of <italic>f</italic><sub><italic>N</italic></sub>(<italic>τ</italic>) is determined by the <italic>r</italic>th derivative of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M13"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo>∗</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> with respect to <italic>s</italic>, hence the series expansion (and Pade approximation) of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M14"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo>∗</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M15"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>∗</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> must agree for small <italic>s</italic>. Thus by step (ii), we are guaranteed that <inline-formula><mml:math id="M16"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo>∗</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M17"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>∗</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> agree for both small and large <italic>s</italic> which in turn implies that the steady-state mRNA count distribution of the <italic>N</italic>-state and the telegraph models are also matched to a good degree. Further justifications for step (ii) are that it is very quick to compute since it requires only the evaluation of analytical formulae and that the procedure guarantees that the rate constants of the effective telegraph model are positive and hence physically meaningful (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Note 1</xref> for a proof). Whilst this is not the only matching procedure that will accomplish this, common alternative matching procedures cannot guarantee this; for example, matching of the first three moments of the waiting time distributions or the first three moments of the mRNA count distributions of the <italic>N</italic>-state and telegraph models can lead to negative rate parameter values.</p></sec><sec id="S5"><title>The number of inactive gene states of the <italic>N</italic>-state model is difficult to estimate from steady-state data</title><p id="P18">In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref> the steady-state mRNA count distributions of thousands of rate parameter sets for the <italic>N</italic> = 3, 4, 5 state models are compared with those of their effective telegraph models (computed using the three-step procedure detailed in the previous section). Note that to ensure biological relevance, the rate parameter ranges for each model were chosen to comfortably cover the bounds of the telegraph model rate parameters estimated using a range of eukaryotic data in various published studies (see Table 1 of [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R45">45</xref>] for these estimates and see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Note 5.1</xref> for further details on generating the rate parameter sets).</p><p id="P19"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2A-C</xref> shows the probability-probability (P-P) plots comparing cumulative distribution functions of the effective telegraph and the <italic>N</italic>-state models for the 500 rate parameter sets with the largest WD of those sampled. Distributions which are very similar fall very close to the dashed red line, which represent identical distributions, whereas greater deviations from this line represent distributions that significantly disagree. For each of the <italic>N</italic> = 3, 4, 5 state models we see minor deviations from this line, indicating broad agreement between the compared distributions. As the number of states increases, we see greater, but not significantly so, deviations as the bulge around this line broadens. Overall these P-P plots show that even for the most statistically distinct distributions, the difference between these distributions is not very large. This suggests that in many cases the telegraph model provides an excellent approximation to the <italic>N</italic>-state models with <italic>N</italic> &gt; 2.</p><p id="P20">To obtain a deeper insight into the deviations, we categorised the <italic>N</italic> = 3, 4, 5 state rate parameter sets according to the shape and statistical properties of their mRNA count distributions. All sampled distribution shapes fell into the following four groups: shape I - unimodal with Fano factor &lt; 2; shape II - unimodal with Fano factor ≥ 2; shape III - bimodal with one zero and one non-zero mode; shape IV - bimodal with two non-zero modes. Note that the single mode of both shapes I and II can be either at zero or at a non-zero value. A typical distribution of each shape is seen in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2D-G</xref>, along with the WD between the 5-state and the effective telegraph distribution. A comparison of the WD of these four shapes suggests that the quality of the effective telegraph model fits decrease with increasing shape number, being best for shape I and worst for shape IV.</p><p id="P21">In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2H</xref> we show by means of box plots that this is indeed the picture that emerges when considering all rate parameter sets sampled: comparing box plots of the same color, i.e. same number of states, we see that shape I distributions are associated with the lowest median WD, followed by shapes II and III distributions which have similar median WDs that are approximately 5-10 times larger than those of shape I, followed further by shape IV distributions which have median WDs that are 3-20 times larger than of shapes II and III. These trends become less clear when considering not just the medians but also the whiskers of the box plots which shows that there is still considerable variation of the WD within each shape type (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S1</xref>). In particular for the 3-state model (the commonest <italic>N</italic>-state model with <italic>N</italic> &gt; 2 in the literature) the lower whisker of the box plots extends nearly to 10<sup>−3</sup> for shapes I-III; this suggests that a substantial portion of the parameter space of this model is very well approximated by the effective telegraph model, since WDs of this magnitude are essentially indistinguishable by eye (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2D</xref>). Within each of shapes I, II and III, the median WD increases with the number of states of the <italic>N</italic>-state model (compare the three differently colored box plots for each category). Hence, as expected, the telegraph model fit worsens as the number of gene states increases, though the worst fits (Shape III for the <italic>N</italic> = 5 model), when visually inspected, still manage to capture the main features of the <italic>N</italic>-state distribution (the two peaks and their positions; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2F</xref>). Note that while in principle this suggests that as we increase <italic>N</italic>, the effective telegraph model will eventually become glaringly distinguishable from the <italic>N</italic>-state model, in reality this is unlikely because until now, the maximum number of states estimated from experimental data is 6 and this was an isolated case [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">21</xref>].</p><p id="P22">Therefore, for mRNA count distributions of shapes I-III, our results strongly suggest that the actual number of gene states cannot be reliably inferred from steady-state mRNA count distributions. One possible explanation is that perhaps the log-uniform sampling procedure tended to select parameter sets where one of the <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub> values (<italic>i</italic> = 1, .., <italic>N</italic> − 1) is particularly small compared to the others; this would imply one rate-limiting step describes gene activation which is consistent with the telegraph model. In <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">SI Fig. 14</xref> we verify that this is not the case: mRNA count distributions from <italic>N</italic>-state models with <italic>N</italic> &gt; 2 and <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub> = <italic>a</italic> for <italic>i</italic> = 1, .., <italic>N</italic> − 1 where <italic>a</italic> is some constant are well fit by an effective telegraph model. This strengthens our earlier conclusion that for shapes I-III, steady-state data is not sufficient to distinguish between <italic>N</italic>-state models with <italic>N</italic> = 2, 3, 4 or 5.</p><p id="P23">While our comparison of distributions was done assuming an infinite number of cells, the similarity of the <italic>N</italic>-state and effective telegraph model means that the maximum likelihood of each distribution computed using mRNA count data from each cell in a finite cell population would also be similar. Hence using common model selection criteria such as the Akaike Information Criterion (AIC) (which penalises more strongly models with a larger number of parameters), the telegraph model would often be selected as the optimal one, even if the <italic>N</italic>-state model is the correct one. This intuition has recently been verified in Ref. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39">39</xref>] were it was shown that a common model selection procedure applied to simulated count data from the 3-state model incorrectly selected the telegraph model (over the 3-state model) for over 90% of parameter sets if the sample size was 100 cells (typical for scRNA-seq data), and for over 40% of parameter sets for samples with 10, 000 cells (larger than for most smFISH datasets).</p><p id="P24">We now discuss in detail the comparison of distributions of the <italic>N</italic>-state model of shape IV and those of the effective telegraph model. This shape presents an interesting case as it is the only shape out of the four considered for which the telegraph model cannot even qualitatively capture the shape of the distribution of the <italic>N</italic>-state model. As we see for the example in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2G</xref>, the number and position of the modes differs between the 5-state model (blue) and the effective telegraph model (red) - while the former has two modes both at non-zero values, the effective telegraph model has a single, non-zero mode. Now it has been proved that when the steady-state distribution of the telegraph model is bimodal then one of its peaks must lie at zero [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R46">46</xref>]. Hence clearly for shapes of type IV, it is impossible for the telegraph model to provide an adequate approximation of the models with <italic>N</italic> &gt; 2. It is also interesting to consider that while slow promoter switching compared to the mRNA degradation rate is a necessary condition for the telegraph model (<italic>k</italic><sub>1</sub><italic>/d</italic> &lt; 1, <italic>k</italic><sub>2</sub><italic>/d</italic> &lt; 1) to display bimodal distributions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R47">47</xref>], this is not the case for the emergence of bimodal distributions of shape IV in the models with <italic>N</italic> &gt; 2; in particular we found this distribution shape can be obtained when <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>N</italic></sub>/<italic>d</italic> &lt; 1 and <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub><italic>/d</italic> ≥ 1 for <italic>i</italic> = 1, …, <italic>N</italic> − 1. Hence we conclude that shape IV distributions are associated with an intermediate switching regime.</p><p id="P25">Of course, the relevance of our results depend on the actual frequency of the four distribution shapes in the biologically relevant parameter space for eukaryotic transcription. In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2I-K</xref> we see how many of each distribution shape were sampled in the parameter sweep for each <italic>N</italic> = 3, 4, 5 state model. Despite the aforementioned distinction of distributions of shape IV, we actually see that for each <italic>N</italic> = 3, 4, 5 the percentage of shape IV distributions sampled was incredibly low, at 0.1%, 0.3%, and 0.5% respectively. Therefore, even though shape IV distributions are distinguishable from their effective telegraph model distributions in steady-state, since they appear so infrequently within the relevant parameter space, we do not expect them to appear commonly from experimental data. Hence our overall conclusion is that the number of gene states is difficult, if not impossible, to reliably estimate from steady-state mRNA count distributions.</p></sec><sec id="S6"><title>The number of gene states can be estimated from short-time mean count data following induction</title><p id="P26">Now that we have established the difficulty of telling apart the telegraph model from the <italic>N</italic>-state model with <italic>N</italic> = 3, 4, 5 using steady-state distributions, we look at how this can instead be achieved by considering time-dependent statistics. Inference of the gene state number <italic>N</italic> from distributions of the mRNA counts measured at several points in time has been previously shown using the method of maximum likelihood [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref>] and also using a Bayesian approach [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref>]. In what follows we will describe a much simpler method which requires only the application of regression on the mean mRNA count computed for a short interval of time following gene induction.</p><p id="P27">Consider an experimental setup whereby some gene of interest is inactive before induction by an inducer molecule. From application of the stimulus to the binding of the relevant transcription factor(s) to the DNA, there is a time lag due to translocation of molecules from the cytoplasm to the nucleus and other processes. Hence we shall consider <italic>t</italic> = 0 to be the point at which transcription initiation starts in the nucleus, i.e. we shall assume that the time lag can be experimentally measured by some means and hence its value is known. For simplicity, we shall also assume that the mean mRNA count at <italic>t</italic> = 0 is zero and that in all cells the inactive state of the gene prior to induction is <italic>j</italic> where <italic>j</italic> ∈ 1, .., <italic>N</italic> − 1. This is an idealised setup that is useful for calculation purposes and which we shall later extend to increase the degree of biological realism.</p><p id="P28">We seek to understand what information about the number of gene states <italic>N</italic> can be deduced from the the moments of the mRNA counts measured a short time after induction. To this end, in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Note 2</xref> starting from the chemical master equation (CME) for the <italic>N</italic>-state model, we use perturbation theory to show that in the limit of short times, the mean ⟨<italic>m</italic>(<italic>t</italic>)⟩ of mRNA counts at time <italic>t</italic> is given by:</p><p id="P29"><disp-formula id="FD3"><label>(3)</label><mml:math id="M18"><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">⟨</mml:mo><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">⟩</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mo>Π</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>!</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:msup><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="P30">In this equation both time and the rate parameters are non-dimensional since they are rescaled by the mRNA degradation rate parameter, i.e. <italic>t → td, k</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub> → <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub><italic>/d</italic> and <italic>ρ → ρ/d</italic>.</p><p id="P31">The expression for the mean, <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD3">Eq. (3)</xref>, suggests a simple method to extract information about the number of inactive states. For short times after induction, a log-log plot of the mean mRNA count versus time leads to a straight line with slope equal to <italic>N</italic> − <italic>j</italic> + 1. Since <italic>j</italic> = 1, .., <italic>N</italic> − 1, the slope provides a lower bound on the total number of gene states <italic>N</italic>. Specifically the slope estimates the “distance” between the initial inactive state <italic>j</italic> and the active state <italic>N</italic>. This result also means that it is difficult to distinguish <italic>N</italic>-state models for which <italic>j</italic> = <italic>N</italic> − 1 from the 2-state telegraph model because in both cases the measured power law exponent is 2. In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3A</xref> we confirm the derived power law by direct numerical integration of the time-evolution equations for the first moment of mRNA numbers of a 5-state model of gene expression – since the system (1) is composed of purely first-order reactions, these equations whilst derived from the CME, in this case they are none other than the deterministic rate equations.</p><p id="P32">As expected, the power law behavior is valid only for short times (less than 0.1 in non-dimensional time units) and hence one may question its usefulness in practice. In <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Note 2</xref> we derive a condition for how short the observation time should be so that the <italic>t</italic><sup><italic>N</italic>−<italic>j</italic>+1</sup> scaling law for the mean is valid. As a rule of thumb, the power law for the mean can be considered to be valid over time intervals that are much smaller than the mRNA degradation timescale (<italic>t</italic> = 1 in non-dimensional time units). For mammalian cells, the median half-life of mRNA molecules is many hours, e.g. it is about 9 hours for NIH3T3 mouse fibroblasts cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R48">48</xref>], and hence the power law should in this case be observable for many minutes. For prokarytic cells and simple eukaryotes, the half-lives of mRNA are much less (typically ranging from a few minutes to about an hour and a half for <italic>E. coli</italic> and budding yeast [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R49">49</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R50">50</xref>]) and hence the power law may be more difficult to observe for these organisms.</p><p id="P33">In <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Note 3</xref> we extend the analytical results to the variance <inline-formula><mml:math id="M19"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and Fano factor <italic>FF</italic> (variance divided by the mean) of mRNA counts:</p><p id="P34"><disp-formula id="FD4"><label>(4)</label><mml:math id="M20"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mtext>Π</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>!</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:msup><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>〈</mml:mo><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>〉</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="P35">Note that the short-time law for the variance is precisely the same as that for the mean. In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs. 3B and C</xref> we confirm the accuracy of these expressions for short times by comparison with the results obtained by direct numerical integration of the time-evolution equations for the first and second moment of mRNA numbers obtained from the CME. This confirms that a log-log plot of the variance of mRNA counts versus time does not provide more information than the mean does and that from the exponent of the Fano factor minus 1 scaling law it is not possible to obtain any information on the number of states. By comparing <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs. 3A and B</xref>, we also note that the true time-evolution of the variance of mRNA counts deviates quicker from the short-time power law than that for the mean of mRNA counts – in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Note 3</xref> we provide a general theoretical proof of this property. In fact this is a consequence of a general property of any Markovian system, i.e. the approach to the steady-state form of the variance occurs asymptotically at twice the rate of approach of the mean [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R51">51</xref>]. The implication of this is that practically speaking, the method for extracting the number of states from short-time data is likely only useful when the mean counts are used.</p><p id="P36">We note that our results also point to a simple method by which some of the rate parameters of the <italic>N</italic>-state model can be estimated. In particular, from simultaneous short-time measurements of the mean and the Fano factor it is possible to estimate the transcription rate <italic>ρ</italic> and the product of rate constants <inline-formula><mml:math id="M21"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:msubsup><mml:mo>∏</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. The procedure is to first estimate <italic>N − j</italic> + 1 from the slope of a log-log plot of the mean versus time (or from non-linear regression fit of a power law to the data). Using this value and the slope of the FF versus time graph, we obtain <italic>ρ</italic>. Finally given the latter and the earlier estimate of <italic>N − j</italic> + 1, the product of rate constants is obtained from the intercept of the log-log plot of the mean versus time.</p><p id="P37">We note that power laws similar to <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD3">Eq. (3)</xref> have been previously reported for the short-time behavior of the distribution of the first-passage time from an initial state to a target state [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R52">52</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R54">54</xref>]. Experiments have shown that this power-law regime encodes information about the number of intermediate states associated with colloidal dynamics in confinement, transport through a biological pore, and the folding kinetics of DNA hairpins [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R55">55</xref>]. However this method is difficult to apply to gene expression as direct measurement of the first-passage time distribution from induction to the first transcription event is not straightforward. In contrast, our method based on mean mRNA measurements is practical since these are routinely done using smFISH, single-cell and bulk sequencing.</p></sec><sec id="S7"><title>The short time results are valid for more general models that include post-transcriptional mRNA processing, cell-to-cell parameter variability and complex networks of gene state interactions</title><p id="P38">Post-transcriptional processing of mRNA may affect the power law exponent. It is simple to show that if splicing and nuclear export can each effectively be described by a single first-order reaction then the short-time exponent deduced from unspliced nuclear mRNA is one less and two less than the exponents deduced from spliced nuclear mRNA data and cytoplasmic mRNA, respectively. Similarly if we interpret the mRNA species (<italic>M</italic>) in the <italic>N</italic>-state model as the cytoplasmic mRNA, a first-order processing step to describe its translation to protein would imply that the short-time power law exponent for the latter is one more than that for the cytoplasmic mRNA (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Note 2.1</xref>). By comparison of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3A and D</xref>, it is clear that these results are verified by simulations (direct numerical integration of the time-evolution equations for the means of the mRNA and of the species following from it due to processing). On the other hand, if splicing and export can be described by fixed-delay reactions then there is no difference in the exponents deduced from different types of mRNA. In practice the effect of mRNA post-processing on the exponent might not be highly relevant since often only the total mRNA counts are measured. But if count data is available for mRNA at different stages of its lifecycle then a comparison of the exponents of the short-time power laws for each stage can reveal information about the effective reactions describing processing.</p><p id="P39">Realistically, the rate parameters of the <italic>N</italic>-state model will generally vary from one cell to another one, a phenomenon called static extrinsic noise [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40">40</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R56">56</xref>]. This means that the mean mRNA measured in an experiment is in reality described by ⟨<italic>m</italic>(<italic>t</italic>)⟩ <sub><italic>e</italic></sub> = ∫ ⟨<italic>m</italic>(<italic>t</italic>)⟩<italic>P</italic>(<italic>k</italic><sub>1</sub>, .., <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>n</italic></sub>, <italic>ρ</italic>)<italic>dk</italic><sub>1</sub>..<italic>dk</italic><sub><italic>N</italic></sub> <italic>dρ</italic> where <italic>P</italic>(<italic>k</italic><sub>1</sub>, .., <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>n</italic></sub>, <italic>ρ</italic>) is the joint distribution of all rate parameters in the <italic>N</italic>-state model. Given the solution <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD3">Eq. (3)</xref> it immediately follows that while static extrinsic noise changes the prefactor in front of the power law it does not change the exponent and hence it follows that the lower bound of <italic>N</italic> estimated from a log-log plot of the mean versus time is insensitive to static extrinsic noise. In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3E</xref> we confirm using stochastic simulations the robustness of the short-time power law to static extrinsic noise. Here we use the stochastic simulation algorithm (SSA) to simulate mRNA count data in 10<sup>6</sup> cells, assuming that the time-independent rate parameters for each cell were drawn from independent gamma distributions. This distribution is useful because it is defined on the positive real line, has a simple functional form, and its mean and variance can be tuned independently of each other. Note that while static extrinsic noise has no impact on the short-time dynamics, it does change the long-time behaviour (compare points obtained using the SSA with static extrinsic noise vs solid lines obtained by numerical integration of the time-evolution equations for the mean mRNA counts, with rate parameter values equal to the mean of the gamma distributions used for the SSA). Note that here we have assumed that the initial state <italic>j</italic> at <italic>t</italic> = 0 does not vary from cell to cell. This variability may not be large because transcriptional repressors can sustain a particular inactive state [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R57">57</xref>]. More general initial gene state distributions are discussed later. Unless otherwise stated, in the rest of the paper, we consider the initial gene state to be the same in all cells (Dirac delta initial gene state distribution).</p><p id="P40">Thus far we have derived results for short-time behaviour assuming the <italic>N</italic>-state model. Whilst fairly general, one could argue that this model can be extended further to account for complex initiation mechanisms. Thus we consider a model of the type:</p><p id="P41"><disp-formula id="FD5"><label>(5)</label><mml:math id="M22"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:munder><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mo>⇌</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:munder><mml:msub><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>…</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="1em"/><mml:msub><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="1em"/></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:msub><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="1em"/><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>∅</mml:mo><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="P42">Here we have <italic>N</italic> gene states of which only one is active (state <italic>N</italic>). Reversible reactions are allowed between any of pair of states and when transcription occurs the state changes from <italic>N</italic> to <italic>K</italic> where the latter can be any integer between 1 and <italic>N</italic>. This state change models reinitiation where some of the essential transcription factors (but not all) remain bound to the promoter [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref>]; this can also model promoter proximal-pausing [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R58">58</xref>]. The <italic>N</italic>-state model (1) is a special case of this model where all gene state reactions are irreversible and no state changes are allowed upon synthesis of a transcript. In <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Note 4</xref> we show using queuing theory that for short times after induction, the model also predicts a mean mRNA count that increases with time as a power law. In this case, the exponent is equal to the minimal number of states that are visited between the initial inactive state and the state from which the synthesis of mRNA occurs – hence independent of the connectivity of the reaction pathway describing initiation, the exponent is a lower bound on the number of gene states <italic>N</italic>. In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3F</xref> we show that the theoretical results are in good agreement with numerical integration of the time-evolution equations for the mean mRNA counts for two special cases of reaction scheme (5), one where there is an extra reaction (compared to the <italic>N</italic>-state model) between states 2 and 5 and another one with reversible reactions between states 1 and 2 and a gene state change from 5 to 2 upon transcription.</p></sec><sec id="S8"><title>Synthetic data generated using biologically relevant parameter values validates the method’s practical use for eukaryotic cells, even for time regimes where the power law breaks down</title><p id="P43">To test more directly the practical utility of the theory, we use simulations to mimic the measurement of the mean mRNA count from experimental data. We assumed five measurements of the mean mRNA at regularly spaced time points and that the maximum time point was much less than the median half life of mRNA in mammalian cells (several hours). The parameters of the <italic>N</italic>-state model were then chosen such that the mean mRNA at the largest time point was within the biologically meaningful range (less than a few tens of mRNA molecules per cell). For further details on the selection procedure see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Note 5.3</xref>.</p><p id="P44">For each of the rate parameter sets, we integrated the time-evolution equations for the mean mRNA counts of the <italic>N</italic>-state model with an initial condition of zero mRNA and starting from inactive state <italic>j</italic> to calculate the mean mRNA at each of the five time points. Finally we applied linear regression to estimate the slope of a log-log plot of mean vs time which estimates the exponent of the power law. In all cases, the coefficient of determination of the best linear fit through the data points was larger than 0.99 thus firmly establishing the existence of a power law – however as clear from the example shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4A</xref>, because of the length of the time interval used, the fitted power law was different than the theoretical one and hence it is of interest to understand the relationship between the two.</p><p id="P45">In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4B-K</xref> we show histograms of the exponent (computed over all rate parameter sets) for <italic>N</italic>-state models with <italic>N</italic> = 2 − 5 and <italic>j</italic> = 1, .., <italic>N</italic> − 1. The distributions of exponent values are wide but the maximum value of the exponents is always less than the theoretical exponent <italic>N</italic> − <italic>j</italic> + 1 (shown by a vertical red dashed line). This is because the next-to-leading order term in the series expansion of the mean in powers of time has a negative sign (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Note 2</xref>) and hence the leading-order term proportional to <italic>t</italic><sup><italic>N</italic>−<italic>j</italic>+1</sup> always overestimates the true mean mRNA count. Hence we have shown using biologically realistic rate parameter constraints that independent of <italic>N</italic>, <italic>j</italic> and the time interval over which the data is collected, the slope calculated from log-log plots of the mean versus time is a reliable means to estimate the lower bound of the number of gene states <italic>N</italic>.</p><p id="P46">However, it is important to remember that these results rest on four main assumptions: (i) the number of cells is infinite — this is implicit in the calculation of the mean mRNA count from the CME; (ii) linear regression on the log-log plots is the optimal method to infer the exponent; (iii) all mRNA molecules in each cell are detected; (iv) the initial distribution of gene states is a Dirac delta function centered on one of the inactive states.</p><p id="P47">To address the limitations (i) and (ii) we used the following simulation protocol. We first chose a subset of 20 different parameter sets from those previously analyzed in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>. These are distinguished from each other by the mean mRNA count at the last time point which varies between 1 and 25 to capture the realistic range of mRNA abundance in mammalian cells (the median mRNA count per cell for a population of exponentially growing mouse fibroblasts is approximately 17 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R48">48</xref>]). For each parameter set, we used the SSA to generate a dataset of mean versus time (sampled at 5 time points) for a finite population of <italic>M</italic> cells and linear regression was used to obtain the exponent from the log-log plots, as before. Repeating this procedure 5000 times leads to a distribution of exponent values. In <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S2</xref> we summarise these distributions by means of boxplots for the <italic>N</italic>-state model with <italic>N</italic> = 5, <italic>j</italic> = 4 and for populations of sizes <italic>M</italic> = 100, 500, 1000 and 10000. The medians of all boxplots are in good agreement with the exponent estimated assuming an infinite population size (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>). Except for populations of 100 cells, the statistical dispersion as measured by the interquartile range is small indicating that for sample sizes of 500 or more cells, uncertainty in the exponent estimates due to finite sample size effects are negligible. Note that this conclusion is valid independent of the mean mRNA count at the last time point, i.e. the method is robust even if the mean count is of order 1. Similar results are obtained if the inference is repeated using non-linear regression applied to the mean count versus time plots (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S3</xref>) and for the <italic>N</italic>-state model with <italic>N</italic> = 5, <italic>j</italic> = 1 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figs. S4 and S5</xref>).</p><p id="P48">To address limitation (iii) we repeated the analysis for the case of non-perfect capture of mRNAs by single-cell mRNA measurements using smFISH or scRNA-seq. Given an integer mRNA count <italic>n</italic> for a cell at a time point from the SSA, we generated the corresponding observed mRNA count by drawing a binomial random number with success probability <italic>p</italic> and number of trials equals to <italic>n</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R59">59</xref>]. Note that the success probability is a measure of detection efficiency — it is over 80% for FISH experiments [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R60">60</xref>] and about 5 − 32% for single-cell sequencing experiments [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R61">61</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R64">64</xref>]. In <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figs. S6-S9</xref> we show that for a typical sample size of 1000 cells, the estimated exponent obtained by linear or non-linear regression from simulated data for the <italic>N</italic>-state model with <italic>N</italic> = 5, <italic>j</italic> = 1 and <italic>N</italic> = 5, <italic>j</italic> = 4 is practically independent of the success probability <italic>p</italic> and is similar to that estimated for an infinite number of cells with perfect detection efficiency in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>.</p><p id="P49">To address limitation (iv) we consider cell-to-cell variability in the initial gene state (non-Dirac-delta initial state distributions). The theory shows that the exponent of the power law describing the short-time dynamics sensitively depends on the initial gene state distribution, specifically on which inactive gene states are inaccessible pre-induction (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Note 2.2</xref>). However, by simulating the post-induction measurement of mRNA count data over realistic time regimes and sample sizes, we show that independent of the width and type of the initial gene state distribution, the exponent estimated from linear or non-linear regression is still bounded from above by the total number of gene states <italic>N</italic> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Note 6.8 and Figs. S15-16</xref>).</p><p id="P50">In summary, we make two crucial assumptions of our idealised experimental setup, i.e. the time delay for the stimulus to reach the nucleus is known or can be separately measured, and the mean mRNA prior to induction is very small. If additionally the sample size is at least several hundreds of cells, the inferred exponent (and hence a lower bound on the number of gene states) is accurately inferred by means of linear or non-linear regression. This conclusion holds even if the mean expression levels at the last time point are very low or if the measurement method has low detection efficiency.</p></sec><sec id="S9"><title>Confirmation of the power law in eukaryotic data and its use to estimate the number of rate-limiting steps for initiation, splicing and export</title><p id="P51">To verify that the predicted power law is indeed observed in experimental data, we considered the data set from Ref. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R65">65</xref>] which we now briefly describe.</p><p id="P52">This data set consists of simultaneous measurements of nuclear and cytoplasmic mRNA following the induction of two genes, CTT1 and STL1, involved in the osmotic stress response of <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R65">65</xref>] — for an illustration of the main processes mediating this response see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5A</xref>. The experiment used 0.2mol and 0.4mol NaCl to induce this response. To quantify the number of mRNA molecules for each gene, in the nucleus and the cytoplasm of each imaged cell, smFISH was used at several time points over 60 minutes. This led to a total of eight data sets (2 stress conditions × 2 genes × 2 RNA species). The number of cells per time point is over a thousand and hence based on previous simulations, in principle this dataset is large enough for accurate gene state inference using our method.</p><p id="P53">However, in this case we cannot directly fit the power law given by <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD3">Eq. (3)</xref> to the mean count versus time data because (i) the time delay from osmotic shock to DNA binding of the transcription factor/s mediating the response is unknown and (ii) the mean mRNA is not exactly zero initially. In <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Note 4</xref> we extend the model to take into account these features. The equation for the mean mRNA count for short times is now modified to</p><p id="P54"><disp-formula id="FD6"><label>(6)</label><mml:math id="M23"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>〈</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>〉</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>〈</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>〉</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mtable columnalign="left"><mml:mtr columnalign="left"><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>&lt;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr columnalign="left"><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>≥</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="P55">where <italic>t</italic><sub>0</sub> is a deterministic time delay, ⟨<italic>m</italic>(0)⟩ is the mean mRNA at time 0 (when the stimulus is first applied), <italic>d</italic> is the degradation rate of the mRNA and <italic>A</italic> is some constant. As before, the exponent <italic>n</italic> equals the number of states visited from the initial inactive state to transcript production. <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD6">Eq. (6)</xref> cannot be reduced to the form of a straight line in log-log space and hence in this case we can only estimate the exponent <italic>n</italic> using non-linear regression. Hence in principle, we need to simultaneously estimate 5 parameters: <italic>d, t</italic><sub>0</sub>, <italic>n, A</italic> and ⟨<italic>m</italic>(0)⟩. Note that we cannot simply use the initial mean measured in experiments as the value for ⟨<italic>m</italic>(0)⟩ because there is uncertainty in this value due to the finite number of cells. However we can safely assume <italic>d</italic> = 0 and only infer 4 parameters which enhances the accuracy of the rest of estimated parameters. The reasons for this are as follows. From <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD6">Eq. (6)</xref> we see that the effect of degradation manifests most clearly on the mean mRNA count for <italic>t &lt; t</italic><sub>0</sub> because for later times the power law will dominate. However an inspection of the mean mRNA curves vs time for nuclear (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5C-F</xref>) and cytoplasmic data (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5K-N</xref>) shows that the delay time is roughly <italic>t</italic><sub>0</sub> ≈ 2 − 4 mins and over this time there is no appreciable degradation of the initial mRNA. This is because the initial mean mRNA count is very small and also because the median mRNA lifetime in yeast is about 11 mins [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R66">66</xref>] which is considerably longer than <italic>t</italic><sub>0</sub>.</p><p id="P56">Hence the final estimation procedure involves (i) fitting <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD6">Eq. (6)</xref> with <italic>d</italic> = 0 to the means calculated from the experimental dataset using non-linear regression (for an illustration see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5B</xref>); (ii) repeating the procedure using replicas of the single-cell data generated using bootstrapping. Specifically by fitting the model to the mean mRNA vs time dataset calculated from each bootstrapped sample, we can estimate the uncertainty in the parameters. Note that we do not use all data points for the fitting; the optimal number of points is selected by an automated procedure based on the residual sum of squares (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S10</xref>).</p><p id="P57">The best fit models resulting from step (i) of the fitting procedure are shown by the coloured curves in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5C-F</xref> for nuclear data and in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5K-N</xref> for cytoplasmic data for the two genes in two different stress conditions. The sampling distributions of the exponent <italic>n</italic> resulting from step (ii) of the fitting procedure are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5G-J</xref> for nuclear data and in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5O-R</xref> for cytoplasmic data. The sampling distributions for the rest of the parameters are shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S11</xref>. In all cases, the experimental data is well fit by the model given by <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD6">Eq. (6)</xref> with <italic>d</italic> = 0 thus verifying that mRNA kinetics follows a power law for a short time after transcription initiation starts in the nucleus. The presence of a single power law also suggests that the distribution of initial states prior to induction is narrow, an assumption that we have made throughout the paper (see discussion about extrinsic noise prior to <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD5">Eq. (5)</xref>).</p><p id="P58">Our results show that the incorporation of an explicit time delay is important and that neglecting it leads to a larger estimate of the exponent and hence an inflated estimate of the number of gene states. For example in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S12</xref> we show that if we do not account for the time delay then the exponents for <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5C,K</xref> are estimated to be 3.66 and 4.39 respectively (instead of 1.92 and 2.90, respectively).</p><p id="P59">The median nuclear exponents for CTT1 and STL1 in 0.2 mol NaCl were 1.92 and 1.95. From the results of simulated data we know that a median exponent of about 2 is consistent with either 3 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4D</xref>) or more gene states (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4F,I</xref>). The median nuclear exponents for CTT1 and STL1 in 0.4 mol NaCl were 1.50 and 3.15. Again using the results of simulated data we see that CTT1 is consistent with at least 2 gene states (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4B,C,E,H</xref>) while STL1 is consistent with at least 4 states (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4G,J</xref>). Hence the simplest model that can explain all the four nuclear datasets is one with four states. We also note that the difference between the median cytoplasmic and nuclear exponents is approximately one implying that nuclear export kinetics is a first-order process (compare <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3A and D</xref>, and also see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Note 2.1</xref>).</p><p id="P60">In Ref. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref>] a multi-state stochastic model with multiple active gene states (connected by reversible reactions) was successfully fitted to data very similar to that of the yeast data used in our analysis, except that the mRNA was not separated into nuclear and cytoplasmic components. By means of a maximum likelihood estimation procedure with cross-validation, they found that two- and three-state models are too simple, while a five-state model structure was prone to over-fitting; hence they settled on an optimal model with four states. In a later study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37">37</xref>] the model (with four states) was refined by performing inference using the measured joint distribution of nuclear and cytoplasmic mRNA counts – the values for the inferred rate parameters can be found in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Tables S3 and S4</xref> in Ref. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37">37</xref>]. An inspection of the inferred transcription rates from each gene state for both CTT1 and STL1 shows that the rate from one gene state is approximately 5 − 1000 times larger than the rate from the three other gene states. Hence the four-state model with four active states is well approximated by a simpler model in which there are three inactive states and one active state which is the 4-state model suggested by the fitting of the power law model above.</p><p id="P61">We have also analyzed a second dataset consisting of simultaneous measurements of (unspliced) pre-mRNA and (spliced) mRNA following tumor necrosis factor (TNF) induced expression of several inflammatory genes in mouse fibroblasts and bone marrow-derived macrophages (BMDM) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R67">67</xref>]. Using quantitative PCR (qPCR) to detect a distinction between pre-mRNA and mRNA, the induction curves for several inflammatory genes were measured (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S2</xref> of Ref. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R67">67</xref>]). It was more challenging to fit <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD6">Eq. (6)</xref> to this data for the following reasons. For three of the induction curves, the estimation gave us the non-physical result of zero delay between stimulus and the start of transcription initiation in the nucleus and a correspondingly high value of the power law exponent. This issue stems from the low number of measurements in the period of time between induction and the setting in of non-power law dynamics. In <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S13</xref> we show three examples where the fitting was successful. Comparing <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S13 A and B</xref> (pre-mRNA and mRNA of gene Cxcl1) we find the difference in exponents to be 0.82. By the theoretical results of <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Note 2.1</xref>, since the difference in exponents is close to 1 (not zero) it follows that splicing, like nuclear export, is consistent with a first-order process and not one with deterministic delay. <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S13 C</xref> shows that the exponent from fitting the mRNA data of Icam1 is 2.75 ± 0.36; this suggests that the exponent for unspliced mRNA is approximately 2 which, by the results of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4 D,F,I</xref>, implies 3 or more gene states.</p></sec></sec><sec id="S10" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p id="P62">In this paper we have shown that (i) in most cases, steady-state mRNA count data is not sufficient to estimate the number of inactive states in transcription; (ii) when the steady-state mRNA distribution of the telegraph model distribution well fits the distribution of the <italic>N</italic>-state model (<italic>N</italic> &gt; 2), there exists a simple relationship between the rate parameters of the two models; (iii) for a short time after induction, the increase in the mean mRNA counts follows a universal power law whose exponent provides a lower bound on the number of gene states — this is valid for a large family of models of gene expression, and it is independent of the values of the rate parameters of the gene expression model and the size of static extrinsic noise. We confirm this power law by analyzing published yeast and mammalian data. In agreement with estimation using other methods [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">20</xref>], our results suggest that the number of inactive eukaryotic gene states can be larger than one.</p><p id="P63">We note that while (i) was previously suspected, until now there has been no conclusive evidence for it. The success of the telegraph model to fit mRNA count distribution measured for a large number of genes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">26</xref>] could be due to two distinct reasons. Either, in reality, the number of rate-limiting steps for most genes is very small, i.e. one for gene inactivation and one for gene activation or else the number of rate-limiting steps is larger but the telegraph model is the simplest of the <italic>N</italic>-state models that can describe the shape of the steady-state distribution of mRNA counts that are commonly measured. In support of the latter reasoning, Ref. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38">38</xref>] showed that the maximum Hellinger distance (HD) computed between the steady-state count distribution of the 3-state model and an effective telegraph model (which spent the same mean time in the active and inactive states as the 3-state model) was quite small (less than 0.06; note that the HD can vary between 0 and 1). In further support of this apparent flexibility of the telegraph model, in Ref. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R68">68</xref>] a mapping was developed between the rate parameters of this model and those of more complex models with the same number of gene states but involving feedback loops which led to good agreement between the time-dependent distributions of both models. As well, more recently it was found that the telegraph model well fits the steady-state distributions of the same model but with static extrinsic noise [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40">40</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R69">69</xref>]. Our results add further evidence suggesting a significant difficulty in distinguishing between the telegraph model and more complex models. We found that for 3 of the 4 possible types of distribution shapes of the <italic>N</italic>-state models with <italic>N</italic> &gt; 2, i.e. unimodal with Fano factor &lt; 2 (shape I), unimodal with Fano factor ≥ 2 (shape II) and bimodal distributions with zero and non-zero peaks (shape III), the telegraph model provides a good fit. One may hypothesize that the underlying theoretical reasons for this are that perhaps for shapes I-III, the distributions of the <italic>N</italic>-state model look like simple distributions which are limiting cases of the telegraph model, e.g. the Poisson distribution with Fano factor = 1 (zero inactivation rate), the negative binomial distribution with Fano factor &gt; 1 (the inactivation rate is much larger than the activation rate) and the sum of a Dirac delta function and a Poisson distribution with a non-zero mode (small activation and inactivation rates, combined with large enough transcription rate). While these distributions may explain the agreement between the <italic>N</italic>-state and the telegraph model in some cases, generally this explanation is not sufficient because we have shown that within each shape type there is quite a variation in distribution type (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S1</xref>). What is perhaps more intriguing is that we found the existence of a distribution shape of the <italic>N</italic>-state models with <italic>N</italic> &gt; 2 (shape IV) which to our knowledge has not been described before and which cannot be fit by any rate parameter choice of the telegraph model – this distribution has two peaks, both of them at a non-zero value. We note that an extension of the telegraph model to include transcription from both gene states (the leaky telegraph model [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R70">70</xref>]) can predict a qualitatively similar distribution shape (in the limit of slow switching between the two states). This implies that fitting such a model to steady-state count data characterised by distributions of shape IV may erroneously lead one to infer two active states when in reality there is only one active state.</p><p id="P64">We also established a novel relationship between the rate parameters of the 2-state and <italic>N</italic>-state models with <italic>N</italic> &gt; 2 when the steady-state mRNA count distributions of the two models are similar. In particular <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD2">Eq. (2)</xref> provides an interesting insight: the inverse of the activation rate of the telegraph model underestimates the total time spent in the inactive states 1, .., <italic>N</italic> − 1 of the <italic>N</italic>-state model, i.e. ⟨<italic>τ</italic><sub>1→<italic>N</italic></sub>⟩. Similarly, the inverse of the inactivation rate of the telegraph model underestimates the time spent in the active state <italic>N</italic> of the <italic>N</italic>-state model, i.e. 1<italic>/k</italic><sub><italic>N</italic></sub>. The underestimation is because of the factor <inline-formula><mml:math id="M24"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mtext>CV</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> which is bounded between 1 and 2 because <inline-formula><mml:math id="M25"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mtext>CV</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>≥</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and lim<sub><italic>N</italic>→∞</sub> CV<sub>1→<italic>N</italic></sub> = 0. This also implies that the relative error in the estimates of the time spent in the inactive and active states is at most 50%. We note that the factor <inline-formula><mml:math id="M26"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mtext>CV</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> naturally emerges from requiring the variance of the interarrival time between successive mRNA synthesis events of the 2 and <italic>N</italic>-state models to be matched, which as we argued earlier is a necessary condition to ensure matching of the distribution of mRNA counts. Our results hence suggest that fitting the telegraph model to steady-state mRNA count data from a gene with a larger number of states leads to a systematic bias in the estimated speed of promoter switching. We note that an alternative way of thinking about the <italic>N</italic>-state model is as a simple birth-death model with fixed degradation rate but an mRNA synthesis rate that randomly alternates in time between 0 and a positive constant <italic>ρ</italic>, i.e. a type of dynamic extrinsic noise [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R71">71</xref>] whereby a rate parameter varies randomly not only from cell to cell but also in time for the same cell. Hence from this perspective, our results point to a systematic overestimation of certain rate parameters in the presence of dynamic extrinsic noise, which is interesting considering that static extrinsic noise has also recently been shown to lead to systematic over- or underestimation of rate parameters inferred from steady-state count data [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40">40</xref>]. Overall these studies imply that generally reliable rate parameter estimation from steady-state count data is difficult unless extrinsic noise sources are identified and properly taken into account.</p><p id="P65">Clearly, the best way to overcome the limitations of steady-state data is to use temporal data. Previously, a few methods have utilised the information contained in the distributions of mRNA counts measured at various time points [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37">37</xref>] to simultaneously estimate the rate parameters and the number of gene states. Motivated by the fact that this data is not commonly available and the inference methods used are rather intricate, we here developed a much simpler method which utilises only the mean mRNA count measured for a short time after gene induction. With regard to whether dynamical low-order moment data is sufficient to distinguish between gene expression models with varying number of states, we are not aware of any study which has studied this question before; an exhaustive study of moment-based and distribution-based inference approaches compared their accuracy to estimate rate parameters at a fixed number of gene states [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37">37</xref>]. The main advantages of our method are the ease with which the input data (the mean mRNA counts) can be measured (qPCR, smFISH, single-molecule and bulk RNA sequencing) and with which the number of gene states is estimated. In particular the latter follows directly from the exponent of the power law inferred by regression analysis on mean mRNA levels over time. The method can only estimate a lower bound for the number of gene states, not the true number of states — this limitation is common to all inference methods since it is only possible to identify the simplest <italic>N</italic>-state model that is consistent with the data. The accuracy of the inferred lower bound is high provided: (i) the time delay between the application of the stimulus and the start of transcription initiation can be well estimated; (ii) the number of cells is at least several hundred; (iii) a sufficiently large number of measurements is taken in the short period of time following gene induction. If these conditions are met then the method retains its accuracy even if the mean expression levels at the largest time point are very low (naturally or because of low detection efficiency) or if there is considerable static extrinsic noise. Of the three aforementioned limitations, the most challenging is the first — we found the easiest way to overcome this is to incorporate an explicit description of time delay in the model and then to use non-linear regression to estimate this quantity simultaneously with the lower bound for gene states. The exponents from nuclear and cytoplasmic mean count data suggest four gene states (three inactive states) for two yeast genes (in agreement with inference by a far more complex inference method [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref>]), and one rate-limiting steps for nuclear export (in agreement with observations using single molecule microscopy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R72">72</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R73">73</xref>]). Furthermore the exponent from spliced and unspliced mRNA count data for a mammalian gene suggests one rate-limiting step for splicing. We found no evidence that nuclear export or splicing can be described by an effective reaction step with a fixed time delay. These results are broadly in agreement with a recent model-based analysis of single-cell and single-nucleus RNA sequencing data [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R74">74</xref>]. Importantly, our analysis shows that failing to account for post-transcriptional processing and the delay between stimulus and initiation will lead to an overestimation of the number of gene states.</p><p id="P66">Finally, one may ask what is the practical utility of determining a lower bound on the number of gene states using the method that we have here developed. Transcriptional regulation involves several distinct steps, and it remains unclear which of these are targets of regulation and how these steps have emerged. As noted earlier, the number of inactive states can be seen as being equal to the number of rate-limiting reaction steps in initiation which are likely the key control points of transcriptional regulation. The method described allows one to rapidly estimate a lower bound for the number of these points. If the experiment is repeated with different perturbations then one can possibly establish a biological interpretation for each of the discrete gene states. So for example, say we wanted to understand the rate-limiting steps in mammalian transcription. <italic>In vitro</italic> experiments have identified six transcription factors (TFIID, TFIIA, TFIIB, TFIIF, TFIIE and TFIIH) that must bind in a certain order before the preinitiation complex begins elongation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref>]. The fact that the number of essential transcription factors is significantly larger than the number of states of models commonly fit to mammalian gene expression data [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">25</xref>] suggests that only the binding of a few transcription factors is rate-limiting. We can then setup a series of induction experiments which differ from each other only by the overexpression of one transcription factor. In all of these experiments we assume the same inducer is used such that the distribution of the initial gene state remains narrow and centered on the same value. If a transcription factor is under normal conditions associated with a rate-limiting step, when it is over expressed it will not be anymore since the reaction will be sped up. In this case, we expect the number of gene states to decrease by one (compared to that in normal conditions) which will result in a similar decrease in the exponent of the power law estimated from the short-time kinetics.</p><p id="P67">Concluding, we have shown that important details of transcription such as the number of rate-limiting steps in initiation have signatures in the mean mRNA data collected a short time after gene induction. The method’s simplicity, particularly its avoidance of the need for the distribution of mRNA counts and of sophisticated inference techniques, shows that simple mathematical tools can also be used to gain insight from transcriptomic data.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="SM"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1"><label>Supplementary Information</label><media xlink:href="EMS193153-supplement-Supplementary_Information.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" id="d20aAcDbB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack id="S11"><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>This work was supported by a BBSRC EASTBIO PhD studentship to AGN (BB/T00875X/1) and a Leverhulme Trust research award to RG. (RPG-2020-327). We thank Peter Swain for his advice and comments in pursuing models of gene induction. For the purpose of open access, the authors have applied a Creative Commons Attribution (CC BY) licence to any Author Accepted Manuscript version arising from this submission.</p></ack><sec id="S12" sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data Availability</title><p id="P68">All experimental and simulated data used in this study are available online at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/agnflame/PowerLaw">https://github.com/agnflame/PowerLaw</ext-link>.</p></sec><sec id="S13" sec-type="data-availability"><title>Code Availability</title><p id="P69">Code to generate various figures is available online at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/agnflame/PowerLaw">https://github.com/agnflame/PowerLaw</ext-link>.</p></sec><ref-list><ref id="R1"><label>[1]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sainsbury</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bernecky</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Cramer</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structural basis of transcription initiation by rna polymerase ii</article-title><source>Nature reviews Molecular cell biology</source><year>2015</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>129</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25693126</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>[2]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roeder</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>50+ years of eukaryotic transcription: an expanding universe of factors and mechanisms</article-title><source>Nature structural &amp; molecular biology</source><year>2019</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>783</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6867066</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31439941</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41594-019-0287-x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>[3]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jonkers</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Lis</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Getting up to speed with transcription elongation by rna polymerase ii</article-title><source>Nature reviews Molecular cell biology</source><year>2015</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>167</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4782187</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25693130</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrm3953</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>[4]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Swain</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name><surname>Elowitz</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Siggia</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Intrinsic and extrinsic contributions to stochasticity in gene expression</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</source><year>2002</year><volume>99</volume><elocation-id>12795</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC130539</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12237400</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.162041399</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>[5]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nicolas</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></name><name><surname>Naef</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>What shapes eukaryotic transcriptional bursting?</article-title><source>Molecular BioSystems</source><year>2017</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>1280</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28573295</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>[6]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tunnacliffe</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Chubb</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>What is a transcriptional burst?</article-title><source>Trends in Genetics</source><year>2020</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>288</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32035656</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>[7]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kingston</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Modeling eukaryotic transcriptional activation</article-title><source>Current Biology</source><year>1994</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>325</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7922341</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>[8]</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ingalls</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name></person-group><source>Mathematical modeling in systems biology: an introduction</source><year>2013</year><publisher-name>MIT press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>[9]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Paulsson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Models of stochastic gene expression</article-title><source>Physics of life reviews</source><year>2005</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>157</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.plrev.2005.03.003</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>[10]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Munsky</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Neuert</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Oudenaarden</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Using gene expression noise to understand gene regulation</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2012</year><volume>336</volume><fpage>183</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3358231</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22499939</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1216379</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>[11]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Halpern</surname><given-names>KB</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanami</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Landen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Chapal</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Szlak</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Hutzler</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Nizhberg</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Itzkovitz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bursty gene expression in the intact mammalian liver</article-title><source>Molecular cell</source><year>2015</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>147</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4500162</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25728770</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molcel.2015.01.027</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>[12]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Skinner</surname><given-names>SO</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagarkar-Jaiswal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Freire</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name><name><surname>Zwaka</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name><name><surname>Golding</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Single-cell analysis of transcription kinetics across the cell cycle</article-title><source>Elife</source><year>2016</year><volume>5</volume><elocation-id>e12175</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4801054</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26824388</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.12175</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>[13]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>HP</given-names></name><name><surname>Coppola</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Lenstra</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name><surname>Grima</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quantifying how post-transcriptional noise and gene copy number variation bias transcriptional parameter inference from mrna distributions</article-title><source>Elife</source><year>2022</year><volume>11</volume><elocation-id>e82493</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9648968</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36250630</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.82493</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>[14]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Neuert</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Munsky</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>RZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Teytelman</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Khammash</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Oudenaarden</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Systematic identification of signal-activated stochastic gene regulation</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2013</year><volume>339</volume><fpage>584</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3751578</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23372015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1231456</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>[15]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kilic</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Schweiger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Moyer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Shepherd</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Pressé</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gene expression model inference from snapshot rna data using bayesian non-parametrics</article-title><source>Nature Computational Science</source><year>2023</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>174</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10732567</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38125199</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s43588-022-00392-0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>[16]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weidemann</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Holehouse</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Grima</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Hauf</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The minimal intrinsic stochasticity of constitutively expressed eukaryotic genes is sub-poissonian</article-title><source>Science Advances</source><year>2023</year><volume>9</volume><elocation-id>eadh5138</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10411910</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37556551</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/sciadv.adh5138</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>[17]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analytical distribution and tunability of noise in a model of promoter progress</article-title><source>Biophysical Journal</source><year>2012</year><volume>102</volume><fpage>1247</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3309289</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22455907</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bpj.2012.02.001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>[18]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analytical time-dependent distributions for gene expression models with complex promoter switching mechanisms</article-title><source>SIAM Journal on Applied Mathematics</source><year>2023</year><volume>83</volume><fpage>1572</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1137/22M147219X</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>[19]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Szavits-Nossan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Grima</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Steady-state distributions of nascent rna for general initiation mechanisms</article-title><source>Physical Review Research</source><year>2023</year><volume>5</volume><elocation-id>013064</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1103/PhysRevResearch.5.013064</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>[20]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Suter</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Molina</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Gatfield</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Schibler</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Naef</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mammalian genes are transcribed with widely different bursting kinetics</article-title><source>science</source><year>2011</year><volume>332</volume><fpage>472</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21415320</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>[21]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zoller</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Nicolas</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Molina</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Naef</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structure of silent transcription intervals and noise characteristics of mammalian genes</article-title><source>Molecular systems biology</source><year>2015</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>823</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4547851</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26215071</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15252/msb.20156257</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>[22]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Muthukrishnan</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Kandhavelu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lloyd-Price</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kudasov</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Chowdhury</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yli-Harja</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Ribeiro</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dynamics of transcription driven by the teta promoter, one event at a time, in live escherichia coli cells</article-title><source>Nucleic acids research</source><year>2012</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>8472</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3458540</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22730294</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gks583</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>[23]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peccoud</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ycart</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Markovian modeling of gene-product synthesis</article-title><source>Theoretical population biology</source><year>1995</year><volume>48</volume><fpage>222</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/tpbi.1995.1027</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>[24]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zenklusen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Larson</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Singer</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Single-rna counting reveals alternative modes of gene expression in yeast</article-title><source>Nature structural &amp; molecular biology</source><year>2008</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>1263</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3154325</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19011635</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nsmb.1514</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>[25]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Larsson</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnsson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hagemann-Jensen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hartmanis</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Faridani</surname><given-names>OR</given-names></name><name><surname>Reinius</surname><given-names>Å</given-names></name><name><surname>Rivera</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Sandberg</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genomic encoding of transcriptional burst kinetics</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2019</year><volume>565</volume><fpage>251</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7610481</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30602787</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41586-018-0836-1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>[26]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ochiai</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Sugawara</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakuma</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Stochastic promoter activation affects nanog expression variability in mouse embryonic stem cells</article-title><source>Scientific reports</source><year>2014</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>7125</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4238020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25410303</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep07125</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>[27]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dar</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Razooky</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Trimeloni</surname><given-names>TV</given-names></name><name><surname>McCollum</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Simpson</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Weinberger</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transcriptional burst frequency and burst size are equally modulated across the human genome</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</source><year>2012</year><volume>109</volume><elocation-id>17454</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3491463</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23064634</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1213530109</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>[28]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Donovan</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></name><name><surname>Huynh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ball</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>HP</given-names></name><name><surname>Poirier</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Larson</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferguson</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Lenstra</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Live-cell imaging reveals the interplay between transcription factors, nucleosomes, and bursting</article-title><source>The EMBO journal</source><year>2019</year><volume>38</volume><elocation-id>e100809</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6576174</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31101674</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15252/embj.2018100809</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>[29]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harper</surname><given-names>CV</given-names></name><name><surname>Finkenstädt</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Woodcock</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Friedrichsen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Semprini</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ashall</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Spiller</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Mullins</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Rand</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Dynamic analysis of stochastic transcription cycles</article-title><source>PLoS biology</source><year>2011</year><volume>9</volume><elocation-id>e1000607</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3075210</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21532732</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.1000607</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>[30]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bartman</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamagami</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Giardine</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Hardison</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Blobel</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Raj</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transcriptional burst initiation and polymerase pause release are key control points of transcriptional regulation</article-title><source>Molecular cell</source><year>2019</year><volume>73</volume><fpage>519</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6368450</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30554946</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molcel.2018.11.004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>[31]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tantale</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Mueller</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Kozulic-Pirher</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lesne</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Victor</surname><given-names>J-M</given-names></name><name><surname>Robert</surname><given-names>M-C</given-names></name><name><surname>Capozi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Chouaib</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Bäcker</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Mateos-Langerak</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A single-molecule view of transcription reveals convoys of rna polymerases and multi-scale bursting</article-title><source>Nature communications</source><year>2016</year><volume>7</volume><elocation-id>12248</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4974459</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27461529</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncomms12248</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><label>[32]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tantale</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Garcia-Oliver</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Robert</surname><given-names>M-C</given-names></name><name><surname>L’hostis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsanov</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Topno</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Gostan</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kozulic-Pirher</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Basu-Shrivastava</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Stochastic pausing at latent hiv-1 promoters generates transcriptional bursting</article-title><source>Nature communications</source><year>2021</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>4503</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8302722</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34301927</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-021-24462-5</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><label>[33]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Douaihy</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Topno</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Lagha</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bertrand</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Radulescu</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Burstdeconv: a signal deconvolution method to uncover mechanisms of transcriptional bursting in live cells</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Research</source><year>2023</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>e88</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10484743</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37522372</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkad629</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><label>[34]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brouwer</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>HP</given-names></name><name><surname>Meeussen</surname><given-names>JVW</given-names></name><name><surname>Pomp</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Lenstra</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Single-molecule fluorescence imaging in living saccharomyces cerevisiae cells</article-title><source>STAR protocols</source><year>2020</year><volume>1</volume><elocation-id>100142</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7757289</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33377036</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.xpro.2020.100142</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><label>[35]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lenstra</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name><surname>Larson</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Single-molecule mrna detection in live yeast</article-title><source>Current protocols in molecular biology</source><year>2016</year><volume>113</volume><fpage>14</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4835805</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27110320</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/0471142727.mb1424s113</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><label>[36]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Raj</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Peskin</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Tranchina</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Vargas</surname><given-names>DY</given-names></name><name><surname>Tyagi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Stochastic mrna synthesis in mammalian cells</article-title><source>PLoS biology</source><year>2006</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>e309</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1563489</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17048983</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.0040309</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R37"><label>[37]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Munsky</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>ZR</given-names></name><name><surname>Shepherd</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name><surname>Neuert</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Distribution shapes govern the discovery of predictive models for gene regulation</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</source><year>2018</year><volume>115</volume><fpage>7533</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6055173</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29959206</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1804060115</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R38"><label>[38]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Filatova</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Oyarzún</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Grima</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A stochastic model of gene expression with polymerase recruitment and pause release</article-title><source>Biophysical Journal</source><year>2020</year><volume>119</volume><fpage>1002</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7474183</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32814062</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bpj.2020.07.020</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R39"><label>[39]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jiao</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Che</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Bleris</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>What can we learn when fitting a simple telegraph model to a complex gene expression model?</article-title><source>PLOS Computational Biology</source><year>2024</year><volume>20</volume><elocation-id>e1012118</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11125521</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38743803</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1012118</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R40"><label>[40]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grima</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Esmenjaud</surname><given-names>P-M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quantifying and correcting bias in transcriptional parameter inference from single-cell data</article-title><source>Biophysical Journal</source><year>2024</year><volume>123</volume><fpage>4</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10808030</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37885177</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bpj.2023.10.021</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R41"><label>[41]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Foreman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Wollman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mammalian gene expression variability is explained by underlying cell state</article-title><source>Molecular systems biology</source><year>2020</year><volume>16</volume><elocation-id>e9146</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7011657</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32043799</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15252/msb.20199146</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R42"><label>[42]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analytical results for a multistate gene model</article-title><source>SIAM Journal on Applied Mathematics</source><year>2012</year><volume>72</volume><fpage>789</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1137/110852887</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R43"><label>[43]</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Villani</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>Optimal transport: old and new</source><year>2009</year><volume>338</volume><publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="R44"><label>[44]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Öcal</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Grima</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanguinetti</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Parameter estimation for biochemical reaction networks using wasserstein distances</article-title><source>Journal of Physics A: Mathematical and Theoretical</source><year>2019</year><volume>53</volume><elocation-id>034002</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1088/1751-8121/ab5877</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R45"><label>[45]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Grima</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analytical distributions for detailed models of stochastic gene expression in eukaryotic cells</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</source><year>2020</year><volume>117</volume><fpage>4682</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7060679</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32071224</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1910888117</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R46"><label>[46]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jiao</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Distribution modes and their corresponding parameter regions in stochastic gene transcription</article-title><source>SIAM Journal on Applied Mathematics</source><year>2015</year><volume>75</volume><fpage>2396</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1137/151005567</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R47"><label>[47]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Popović</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Grima</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phenotypic switching in gene regulatory networks</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</source><year>2014</year><volume>111</volume><fpage>6994</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4024914</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24782538</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1400049111</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R48"><label>[48]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schwanhäusser</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Busse</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Dittmar</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Schuchhardt</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolf</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Selbach</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Global quantification of mammalian gene expression control</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2011</year><volume>473</volume><fpage>337</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21593866</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R49"><label>[49]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Storey</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Tibshirani</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Herschlag</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>PO</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Precision and functional specificity in mrna decay</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</source><year>2002</year><volume>99</volume><fpage>5860</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC122867</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11972065</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.092538799</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R50"><label>[50]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Selinger</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Saxena</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheung</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Church</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosenow</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Global rna half-life analysis in escherichia coli reveals positional patterns of transcript degradation</article-title><source>Genome research</source><year>2003</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>216</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC420366</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12566399</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gr.912603</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R51"><label>[51]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Keizer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>On the solutions and the steady states of a master equation</article-title><source>Journal of Statistical Physics</source><year>1972</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>67</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF01023679</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R52"><label>[52]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Kolomeisky</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mechanisms and topology determination of complex chemical and biological network systems from first-passage theoretical approach</article-title><source>The Journal of chemical physics</source><year>2013</year><volume>139</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3808428</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24116602</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1063/1.4824392</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R53"><label>[53]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Kolomeisky</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Valleriani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Stochastic kinetics on networks: when slow is fast</article-title><source>The Journal of Physical Chemistry B</source><year>2014</year><volume>118</volume><elocation-id>10419</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4154737</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25140607</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jp506668a</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R54"><label>[54]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Valleriani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Kolomeisky</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Unveiling the hidden structure of complex stochastic biochemical networks</article-title><source>The Journal of chemical physics</source><year>2014</year><volume>140</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4108629</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24527894</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1063/1.4863997</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R55"><label>[55]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thorneywork</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Gladrow</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Qing</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Rico-Pasto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ritort</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Bayley</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kolomeisky</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Keyser</surname><given-names>UF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Direct detection of molecular intermediates from first-passage times</article-title><source>Science advances</source><year>2020</year><volume>6</volume><elocation-id>eaaz4642</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7195145</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32494675</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/sciadv.aaz4642</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R56"><label>[56]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ham</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Stumpf</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pathway dynamics can delineate the sources of transcriptional noise in gene expression</article-title><source>Elife</source><year>2021</year><volume>10</volume><elocation-id>e69324</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8608387</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34636320</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.69324</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R57"><label>[57]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Szczurek</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name><surname>Dimitrova</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelley</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Blackledge</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name><name><surname>Klose</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The polycomb system sustains promoters in a deep off state by limiting pre-initiation complex formation to counteract transcription</article-title><source>Nature Cell Biology</source><year>2024</year><volume>1</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39261718</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R58"><label>[58]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Braichenko</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Holehouse</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Grima</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Distinguishing between models of mammalian gene expression: telegraph-like models versus mechanistic models</article-title><source>Journal of the Royal Society Interface</source><year>2021</year><volume>18</volume><elocation-id>20210510</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8492181</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34610262</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rsif.2021.0510</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R59"><label>[59]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Mazutis</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Akartuna</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Tallapragada</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Veres</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Peshkin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Weitz</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kirschner</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Droplet barcoding for single-cell transcriptomics applied to embryonic stem cells</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2015</year><volume>161</volume><fpage>1187</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4441768</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26000487</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2015.04.044</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R60"><label>[60]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Emanuel</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhuang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Spatial transcriptome profiling by merfish reveals subcellular rna compartmentalization and cell cycle-dependent gene expression</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</source><year>2019</year><volume>116</volume><elocation-id>19490</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6765259</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31501331</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1912459116</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R61"><label>[61]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ziegenhain</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Vieth</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Parekh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Reinius</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Guillaumet-Adkins</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Smets</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Leonhardt</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Heyn</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hellmann</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Enard</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparative analysis of single-cell rna sequencing methods</article-title><source>Molecular cell</source><year>2017</year><volume>65</volume><fpage>631</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28212749</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R62"><label>[62]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gruün</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kester</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Oudenaarden</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Validation of noise models for single-cell transcriptomics</article-title><source>Nature methods</source><year>2014</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>637</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24747814</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R63"><label>[63]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Salomon</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaczorowski</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Valdes-Mora</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Nordon</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Neild</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Farbehi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Bartonicek</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Gallego-Ortega</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Droplet-based single cell rnaseq tools: a practical guide</article-title><source>Lab on a Chip</source><year>2019</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>1706</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30997473</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R64"><label>[64]</label><element-citation publication-type="other"><collab>10XGenomics</collab><source>What fraction of mrna transcripts are captured per cell?</source></element-citation></ref><ref id="R65"><label>[65]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Neuert</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multiplex rna single molecule fish of inducible mrnas in single yeast cells</article-title><source>Scientific data</source><year>2019</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>94</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6572782</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31209217</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41597-019-0106-6</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R66"><label>[66]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwalb</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Maier</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Schulz</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Duümcke</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zacher</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Mayer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sydow</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Marcinowski</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Düolken</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Dynamic transcriptome analysis measures rates of mrna synthesis and decay in yeast</article-title><source>Molecular systems biology</source><year>2011</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>458</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3049410</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21206491</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/msb.2010.112</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R67"><label>[67]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Baltimore</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rna splicing regulates the temporal order of tnf-induced gene expression</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</source><year>2013</year><volume>110</volume><elocation-id>11934</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3718113</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23812748</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1309990110</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R68"><label>[68]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Grima</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Linear mapping approximation of gene regulatory networks with stochastic dynamics</article-title><source>Nature communications</source><year>2018</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>3305</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6098115</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30120244</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-018-05822-0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R69"><label>[69]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Shahrezaei</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Coordination of gene expression noise with cell size: analytical results for agent-based models of growing cell populations</article-title><source>Journal of the Royal Society Interface</source><year>2021</year><volume>18</volume><elocation-id>20210274</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8150024</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34034535</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rsif.2021.0274</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R70"><label>[70]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ham</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Brackston</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Stumpf</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Extrinsic noise and heavy-tailed laws in gene expression</article-title><source>Physical review letters</source><year>2020</year><volume>124</volume><elocation-id>108101</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32216388</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R71"><label>[71]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gorin</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Vastola</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pachter</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Interpretable and tractable models of transcriptional noise for the rational design of single-molecule quantification experiments</article-title><source>Nature Communications</source><year>2022</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>7620</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9734650</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36494337</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-022-34857-7</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R72"><label>[72]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Siebrasse</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaminski</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kubitscheck</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nuclear export of single native mrna molecules observed by light sheet fluorescence microscopy</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</source><year>2012</year><volume>109</volume><fpage>9426</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3386080</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22615357</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1201781109</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R73"><label>[73]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oeffinger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Zenklusen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>To the pore and through the pore: a story of mrna export kinetics</article-title><source>Biochimica et Biophysica Acta (BBA)-Gene Regulatory Mechanisms</source><year>2012</year><volume>1819</volume><fpage>494</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3345096</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22387213</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbagrm.2012.02.011</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R74"><label>[74]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gorin</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshida</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Pachter</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assessing markovian and delay models for single-nucleus rna sequencing</article-title><source>Bulletin of Mathematical Biology</source><year>2023</year><volume>85</volume><fpage>114</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37828255</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><title>Inference of the number of rate-limiting steps in transcription from mRNA count data using mathematical models of gene expression.</title><p>(A) Schematic of the key stages in eukaryotic transcription. This includes the opening of closed chromatin, exposing the transcription start site (TSS); the binding of various transcription factors (TF) to the promoter; recruitment of RNAP and assembly of the PIC; and successful elongation. From a detailed biological description, it is unclear what are the actual number of rate-limiting steps. (B) Schematic of single-cell population snapshot measurements of the mRNA count in time (including at steady-state) and the corresponding mRNA count distributions. Mathematical models (red lines) can be fitted to experimental data (histograms), obtained using smFISH and scRNA-Seq, with the aim of inferring probable transcriptional mechanisms. (C) It is currently unclear if by fitting steady-state distributions only, one can identify the number of rate-limiting steps and the network topology of the true transcriptional mechanism. For example, can we tell apart the telegraph model from various 3, 4, and 5-state models? Here OFF represents a transcriptionally inactive state and ON an active state. Equally unclear is the success of inference using time-dependent distributions due to static extrinsic noise stemming from cell-to-cell variability. In this article, we address these questions and devise an efficient, simple-to-use method that utilises only the mean mRNA count (dashed blue line) to overcome the limitations of current methods.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS193153-f001"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>The steady-state mRNA count distribution of the <italic>N</italic>-state model can often be well fit by an effective telegraph model. Thousands of rate parameter sets of the <italic>N</italic>-state model (<italic>N</italic> = 3, 4, 5) were sampled in the range relevant for eukaryotic gene expression. For each parameter set we use the mapping giving by <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD2">Eq. (2)</xref> to obtain the rate parameters of an effective telegraph model. (A-C) P-P plots comparing the cumulative distribution function of the <italic>N</italic>-state and effective telegraph models. These are constructed from the 500 rate parameter sets with the largest Wasserstein distance (WD) values between the distributions of the two models. Deviations from the line <italic>y</italic> = <italic>x</italic> (red) indicate differences between the distributions. (D-G) Typical steady-state mRNA count distributions of the 5-state (solid blue lines) and effective telegraph models (histograms) for four classes of distributions (Shape I: Unimodal with Fano factor &lt; 2; Shape II: Unimodal with Fano factor ≥ 2; Shape III: Bimodal with one peak at zero and another at a non-zero value; Shape IV: Bimodal with peaks at non-zero values. (H) Boxplots displaying summary statistics of the WD between the steady-state distribution of mRNA counts of the <italic>N</italic>-state and effective telegraph model. The horizontal line and the box show the median and the interquartile range, respectively; whiskers extend to the 10th and 90th percentiles. (I-K) Bar charts displaying the percentage of each distribution shape sampled across the parameter space. The agreement between the <italic>N</italic>-state and its effective telegraph model becomes worse as <italic>N</italic> increases and is worst for Shape IV because this shape is qualitatively impossible to capture by the telegraph model. See <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Note 5.1</xref> for implementation details.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS193153-f002"/></fig><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><title>Simulations confirm the theoretical predictions for the time-dependence of the statistics of mRNA counts following gene induction.</title><p>(A)-(C) Mean of mRNA counts, variance of mRNA counts and Fano factor of mRNA counts for the 5-state model, i.e. the system (1) with <italic>N</italic> = 5. (D) Mean of mRNA counts for the 5-state model with one extra step modeling the translation of mRNA (<italic>M</italic>) to protein (<italic>P</italic>). (E) Mean of mRNA counts for the 5-state model with cell-to-cell variation of rate parameters (static extrinsic noise); each rate parameter is drawn from a gamma distribution. (F) Mean mRNA count from extensions of the 5-state model that incorporate reversible reactions between gene states and state change upon mRNA synthesis; these are special cases of the system (5). The theory is shown by the dashed lines and simulations by solid lines (obtained by direct numerical integration of the moment equations of the CME). In (E) the simulations are done in two ways: solid lines are obtained by direct numerical integration of the moment equations of the CME with rate parameters fixed to the average of the gamma distributions and dots are from the SSA with rate parameters randomly drawn from these distributions. In all cases there is excellent agreement between theory and simulations for short times. All panels use a log-log scale hence a power-law relationship is represented by a straight line with gradient corresponding to the exponent of the power law. The colours: blue, pink, orange, and yellow, represent the initial inactive gene state after induction: <italic>j</italic> = 1, 2, 3, 4 respectively and are illustrated by the cartoon model diagram in each panel. The outward pointing green arrow represents mRNA synthesis and the other one shows the state after synthesis has occurred. The parameters were chosen to be within the range relevant for eukaryotic gene expression (the range used for <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref> and described in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Note 5.1</xref>). See <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Note 5.2</xref> for reaction network schemes.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS193153-f003"/></fig><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Synthetic data generated using biologically relevant rate parameter values for mammalian cells validates the practical use of the short-time mean mRNA count data to estimate a lower bound for the number of gene states <italic>N</italic>. By numerical integration of the time-evolution equations for the mean mRNA of the <italic>N</italic>-state model, we simulated measurements of the mean mRNA at 5 regularly spaced time points for approximately two million parameter sets. These time points varied for each parameter set and were chosen such that at the final time point the mean mRNA count per cell was in the biologically realistic range (a few tens). The final time point was also much less than the median half life of mRNA (several hours). (A) An example curve for one rate parameter set showing deviations of the true power law (dashed blue) from the theoretical power law (solid black) for biologically relevant times. Note that time is non-dimensional since it is multiplied by the mRNA degradation rate: hence <italic>t</italic> = 0.1 corresponds to about one hour for mammalian cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R48">48</xref>]. (B)-(K) For each parameter set, we used linear regression to extract the true power law exponent from the slope of the log-log plot of the mean versus time and then plotted the distributions of the exponent (blue histograms). The model diagram in each figure illustrates the active state (solid green circle), inactive states (open circles) and initial inactive state (solid red square) for each system. Note that <italic>N</italic> (the total number of gene states) varies between 2 and 5 while the initial inactive state <italic>j</italic> varies between 1 and <italic>N</italic> − 1. The exponent <italic>N</italic> − <italic>j</italic> + 1 estimated by our theory (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD3">Eq. (3)</xref>) is shown by a vertical red dashed line – in all cases the maximum value of the numerical exponent is below the theoretical value which itself is a lower bound for the number of gene states <italic>N</italic>. See <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Note 5.3</xref> for simulation details.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS193153-f004"/></fig><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><title>Non-linear regression fitting of mRNA induction curves confirms the short-time power law behaviour in eukaryotic cells.</title><p>(A) Schematic showing the induction of CTT1 and STL1 genes in <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> under osmotic stress [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R65">65</xref>]. This involves the translocation of a kinase (Hog1p) from the cytoplasm to the nucleus where it interacts with transcription factors and chromatin modifiers. (B) Fit of the model given by <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD6">Eq. (6)</xref> with <italic>d</italic> = 0 and <italic>m</italic>0 = ⟨<italic>m</italic>(0)⟩ using non-linear regression to a typical dataset allows the inference of the exponent <italic>n</italic> and the rest of the parameters. (C-F) Mean nuclear mRNA count induction curves (crosses joined by black dashed lines) and the best fit model using regression (colour) with the exponent shown next to it. Grey region shows the delay period prior to initiation. (G-J) Sampling distributions of nuclear mRNA exponents estimated using bootstrapping. (K-N) Mean cytoplasmic mRNA count induction curves (crosses joined by black dashed lines) and the best fit model using regression (colour) with the exponent shown next to it. (O-R) Sampling distributions of cytoplasmic mRNA exponents estimated using bootstrapping. The median of each distribution is shown by a vertical black line. Note that C, G, K and O are for CTT1 (0.2 mol NaCl); D, H, L and P are for CTT1 (0.4 mol NaCl); E, I, M and Q are for STL1 (0.2 mol NaCl); F, J, N and R are for STL1 (0.4 mol NaCl). See <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Note 5.4</xref> for technical details.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS193153-f005"/></fig></floats-group></article>