<!DOCTYPE article
 PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" article-type="preprint"><?all-math-mml yes?><?use-mml?><?origin ukpmcpa?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">bioRxiv</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>bioRxiv : the preprint server for biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub"/></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">EMS189582</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2023.10.11.561842</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="archive">PPR740232</article-id><article-version-alternatives><article-version article-version-type="status">preprint</article-version><article-version article-version-type="number">1</article-version></article-version-alternatives><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>A novel subgroup of light-driven sodium pumps with an additional Schiff base counterion</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Podoliak</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Lamm</surname><given-names>G.H.U.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Alekseev</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Marin</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Schellbach</surname><given-names>A.V.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN1">†</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fedotov</surname><given-names>D.A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A6">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Stetsenko</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Maliar</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A7">7</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bourenkov</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A8">8</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Balandin</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A9">9</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A10">10</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Baeken</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A9">9</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A10">10</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Astashkin</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A11">11</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>T.R.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A8">8</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bateman</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A12">12</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wachtveitl</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Schapiro</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A6">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Busskamp</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Guskov</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gordeliy</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A9">9</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A10">10</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A11">11</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kovalev</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A8">8</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CR1">#</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Department of Ophthalmology, University Hospital Bonn, Medical Faculty, Bonn, Germany</aff><aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Institute of Physical and Theoretical Chemistry, Goethe University Frankfurt, 60438 Frankfurt am Main, Germany</aff><aff id="A3"><label>3</label>Advanced Optogenes Group, Institute for Auditory Neuroscience and InnerEarLab, University Medical Center Göttingen, Göttingen, Germany</aff><aff id="A4"><label>4</label>Cluster of Excellence "Multiscale Bioimaging: from Molecular Machines to Networks of Excitable Cells" (MBExC), University of Göttingen, Göttingen, Germany</aff><aff id="A5"><label>5</label>Groningen Institute for Biomolecular Sciences and Biotechnology, University of Groningen, 9747AG, Groningen, the Netherlands</aff><aff id="A6"><label>6</label>Fritz Haber Center for Molecular Dynamics Research, Institute of Chemistry, The Hebrew University of Jerusalem, Jerusalem, 9190401, Israel</aff><aff id="A7"><label>7</label>Department of Biochemistry, University of Cambridge, 80 Tennis Court Road, Cambridge CB2 1GA, UK</aff><aff id="A8"><label>8</label>European Molecular Biology Laboratory, EMBL Hamburg c/o DESY, 22607, Hamburg, Germany</aff><aff id="A9"><label>9</label>Institute of Biological Information Processing (IBI-7: Structural Biochemistry), Forschungszentrum Jülich, Jülich, Germany</aff><aff id="A10"><label>10</label>JuStruct: Jülich Center for Structural Biology, Forschungszentrum Jülich, Jülich, Germany</aff><aff id="A11"><label>11</label>Univ. Grenoble Alpes, CEA, CNRS, Institut de Biologie Structurale (IBS), 38000, Grenoble, France</aff><aff id="A12"><label>12</label>European Molecular Biology Laboratory, European Bioinformatics Institute (EMBL-EBI), Wellcome Genome Campus, Hinxton, UK</aff><author-notes><fn id="FN1"><label>†</label><p id="P1">Present address: School of Chemistry, University of Edinburgh, Edinburgh, EH9 3FJ UK</p></fn><corresp id="CR1"><label>#</label> Correspondence to: <email>kirill.kovalev@embl-hamburg.de</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted"><day>14</day><month>10</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="preprint"><day>12</day><month>10</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><permissions><ali:free_to_read/><license><ali:license_ref>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is licensed under a <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">CC BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p id="P2">Light-driven sodium pumps (NaRs) are unique ion-transporting microbial rhodopsins. The major group of NaRs is characterized by an NDQ motif and has two aspartic acid residues in the central region essential for sodium transport. Here we identified a new subgroup of the NDQ rhodopsins bearing an additional glutamic acid residue in the close vicinity to the retinal Schiff base. We thoroughly characterized a member of this subgroup, namely the protein <italic>Er</italic>NaR from <italic>Erythrobacter sp. HL-111</italic> and showed that the additional glutamic acid results in almost complete loss of pH sensitivity for sodium-pumping activity, which is in contrast to previously studied NaRs. <italic>Er</italic>NaR is capable of transporting sodium efficiently even at acidic pH levels. X-ray crystallography and single particle cryo-electron microscopy reveal that the additional glutamic acid residue mediates the connection between the other two Schiff base counterions and strongly interacts with the aspartic acid of the characteristic NDQ motif. Hence, it reduces its pKa. Our findings shed light on a new subgroup of NaRs and might serve as a basis for their rational optimization for optogenetics.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><p id="P3">Light-driven sodium pumps (NaRs) were discovered in 2013 with the characterization of the microbial rhodopsin (MR) KR2 from the bacterium <italic>Krokinobacter eikastus</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref></sup>. NaRs are membrane proteins that actively transport sodium outside of the cell in response to light illumination<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">2</xref></sup>. Since 2013, numerous various NaRs have been identified<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">3</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref></sup>. Most of them have an NDQ motif (N112, D116, and Q123 residues in KR2 corresponding to D85, T89, and D96 residues of the proton pump bacteriorhodopsin (BR<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref></sup>)) in the helix C. Another group of MRs able to pump sodium was recently reported to have a DTG motif<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">8</xref></sup>.</p><p id="P4">As all other MRs, the structure of NDQ rhodopsins consists of seven transmembrane helices (A-G) encapsulating a retinal cofactor, covalently attached to the lysine residue of the helix G (K255 in KR2) via a Schiff base (RSB)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref></sup>. NDQ rhodopsins form pentamers in the membrane as was shown for KR2<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref></sup>. The transported substrate, sodium, is not bound inside these rhodopsins in the non-illuminated (resting) state, but was found at the oligomerization interface of KR2 coordinated by two neighboring protomers<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref></sup>. Upon light illumination, NDQ rhodopsins undergo a photocycle with several intermediate states, transitions between which result in sodium translocation across the membrane. Namely, there are the K, L, M, and O intermediates of a typical NDQ rhodopsin, where the O state was shown to be the only one associated with the transient sodium binding inside the protein<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref></sup>. For several NDQ rhodopsins, such as KR2 and the NaR from <italic>Indibacter alkaliphilus</italic> (<italic>Ia</italic>NaR), the O state was demonstrated to consist of several sub-states<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref></sup>.</p><p id="P5">There is still no complete understanding of the molecular mechanism of light-driven sodium pumping by NDQ rhodopsins despite the thorough characterization of KR2. For the latter it was shown that the conformational change in the RSB region takes place upon sodium binding in the O state<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref></sup>. N112 of the NDQ motif, which points outside of the protomer towards the pentamerization interface in the ground state, flips inside the protein to coordinate the transiently-bound sodium ion<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref></sup>. This considerable movement (˜5 Å in amplitude) is accompanied by the flip of the L74 side chain, creating sufficient space for N112 inside the KR2 protomer<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref></sup>. Such a synchronous switch of the N112-L74 pair is believed to be one of the key determinants of light-driven sodium pumping<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref></sup>. Surprisingly, while the role of N112 of that pair in the KR2 functioning was studied in detail<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">21</xref></sup>, the L74 residue often remained out of the focus despite its involvement in sodium-pumping-associated conformational changes. Nevertheless, it was evidenced by the L74A mutation, which dramatically decreases the sodium-pumping activity of KR2, suggesting its important role in the NDQ rhodopsin<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref></sup>.</p><p id="P6">Here, we bioinformatically analyzed the clade of NDQ rhodopsins and found that although the majority of the proteins possess leucine/isoleucine at the position of L74 in KR2, there is a subgroup of proteins bearing glutamate at this position. To see what effect it has on protein structure and function we investigated a rhodopsin from <italic>Erythrobacter sp. HL-111</italic>, <italic>Er</italic>NaR (Uniprot ID: A0A1H1XA63), belonging to this newly identified subgroup. <italic>Er</italic>NaR, in contrast to KR2, demonstrated unique spectroscopic properties with only a minor dependence of absorption spectra on pH. Furthermore, <italic>Er</italic>NaR is efficient in pumping sodium with high selectivity over protons even at acidic pH values as low as 5.0. Single particle cryo-electron microscopy (cryo-EM) and X-ray crystallography showed an unusual conformation of the rhodopsin in the resting state with a very short H-bond between E64 and D105 (corresponding to L74 and D116 in KR2, respectively). These findings provide essential information on the mechanisms of NDQ rhodopsins and natural ways of tuning of their functional properties.</p><sec id="S1" sec-type="results | discussion"><title>Results and Discussion</title><sec id="S2"><title>Two subgroups of NaRs</title><p id="P7">Initially, we performed a bioinformatic analysis of the rhodopsins possessing the NDQ motif in available gene databases (UniProtKB, UniParc, GenBank, and MGnify) to obtain the complete list of members of the clade. In total, we identified 351 unique complete sequences of NDQ rhodopsins which resulted in 219 sequences with less than 90% pairwise sequence identity. The proteins cluster into several branches in the phylogenetic tree (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1A</xref>). Closer analysis of these branches showed that, while there are some interesting features of their representatives, the overall clade of NDQ rhodopsins can be divided into two major subgroups, Subgroup 1 and Subgroup 2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1A</xref>). Members of the Subgroup 1 possess leucine or isoleucine at the position of L74 in KR2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1B</xref>). KR2 belongs to Subgroup 1, which is also the larger one. Members of Subgroup 2 possess glutamic acid at the position of L74 in KR2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1B</xref>). Importantly, this position is located close to the RSB and L74 is involved in conformational changes in KR2 associated with sodium translocation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref></sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1C</xref>). Thus, the introduction of glutamic acid might significantly affect the functional, spectroscopic, and structural properties of the NDQ rhodopsins belonging to Subgroup 2. In addition, although the internal polar and rechargeable residues are conserved within the entire NDQ rhodopsins clade (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1B</xref>, left), the amino acid residues at the surface, including those of the oligomerization interface, are significantly different between the two subgroups (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1B</xref>, right). For instance, the D102 residue, forming the interprotomeric sodium binding site on the extracellular surface of the KR2 pentamer<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref></sup>, is either absent or substituted with glutamic acid in the Subgroup 2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1B,D</xref>).</p><p id="P8">Most of the investigated NDQ rhodopsins belong to Subgroup 1. Our analysis shows that only one protein, a sodium pump from <italic>Salinarimonas rosea</italic> DSM21201 (<italic>Sr</italic>NaR), from Subgroup 2 was studied<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref></sup>. <italic>Sr</italic>NaR has been shown to differ from other NaRs. To date, the available data on <italic>Sr</italic>NaR and the members of Subgroup 2 are very limited. Therefore, to study the properties of the members of Subgroup 2, we selected another representative, an NDQ rhodopsin from <italic>Erythrobacter sp.</italic> HL-111 (<italic>Er</italic>NaR), and performed its thorough characterization. This allowed us to compare the properties and organization of <italic>Er</italic>NaR with known sodium pumps like KR2.</p></sec><sec id="S3"><title>Functional characterization of <italic>Er</italic>NaR</title><p id="P9">To study <italic>Er</italic>NaR in mammalian cells, we cloned a human-codon optimized gene of <italic>Er</italic>NaR to the previously published expression cassette that contained the enhanced yellow fluorescent protein (EYFP), membrane trafficking signal (TS) and endoplasmic reticulum (ES) export signal from potassium channel Kir2.1 and N-terminal part of channelrhodopsin (C2C1)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">22</xref></sup>. We transiently expressed <italic>Er</italic>NaR in this construct in HEK293T cells and evaluated its localization by confocal imaging. Subcellular expression of <italic>Er</italic>NaR was predominantly confined to the plasma membrane, with low to none at all amounts of protein in intracellular compartments (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2A</xref>).</p><p id="P10">Next, we used the whole cell patch-clamp technique to study the functional properties of <italic>Er</italic>NaR. Expecting <italic>Er</italic>NaR to be an outward sodium or proton pump, we measured the photocurrents at the same extracellular pH (pH<sub>e</sub>) 7.5 and 110 mM [Na<sup>+</sup>]<sub>e</sub> while varying intracellular pH (pH<sub>i</sub>) and [Na<sup>+</sup>]<sub>i</sub>. Indeed, <italic>Er</italic>NaR appeared to be an outwardly directed sodium pump, with photocurrent highly dependent on intracellular [Na<sup>+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2B-D</xref>). Notably, <italic>Er</italic>NaR showed a profound nonlinear voltage dependence at 130 mM [Na<sup>+</sup>]<sub>i</sub>, with near-zero currents in negative voltages (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2C</xref>, left). A voltage dependence was also reported in KR2<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">22</xref></sup>, but it was not as pronounced as observed in <italic>Er</italic>NaR.</p><p id="P11">To assess the capability of <italic>Er</italic>NaR to pump H<sup>+</sup>, for each [Na<sup>+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> we tested three pH<sub>i</sub> values (5.0, 7.5, and 9.0) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2C</xref>). In the presence of sodium in the intracellular solution (20 mM and 130 mM [Na<sup>+</sup>]<sub>i</sub>) we observed photocurrents at all studied pH<sub>i</sub>. A change in pH<sub>i</sub> from acidic (5.0) to alkaline (9.0) slightly increased the amplitude of photocurrent (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2C</xref>, left and middle plots). While at 20 mM [Na<sup>+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> this effect was not significant, at 130 mM [Na<sup>+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> the difference reached statistical significance (<italic>P</italic>=0.0349) when the photocurrents were compared at +60 mV (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2D</xref>). In addition, at 130 mM [Na<sup>+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> we determined the characteristic time of the photocurrent decay after the light was switched off (t<sub>off,</sub> monoexponential fit) in all tested pH<sub>i</sub> values (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2E</xref>). Acidic intracellular conditions led to slightly decelerated off-kinetics of <italic>Er</italic>NaR (statistically not significant).</p><p id="P12">In the absence of intracellular sodium, <italic>Er</italic>NaR exhibited immeasurably low photocurrents in all tested pH<sub>i</sub>. Under similar experimental conditions, when sodium was removed from the intracellular solution, KR2 was shown to pump protons<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">22</xref></sup>. In <italic>Er</italic>NaR, the proton currents were negligible even at pH<sub>i</sub> 5.0, suggesting that <italic>Er</italic>NaR and likely other members of Subgroup 2 of the NDQ rhodopsins are more selective to sodium than representatives of Subgroup 1. Besides, the difference in photocurrent amplitude at +60 mV was statistically significant between 130 mM and 20 mM [Na<sup>+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> (<italic>P</italic>=0.0142, <italic>P</italic>=0.0028 and <italic>P</italic>&lt;0.0001 at pH<sub>i</sub> 5.0, 7.5 and 9.0, respectively) and between 130 mM and 0 mM [Na<sup>+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> (<italic>P</italic>=0.0012, <italic>P</italic>&lt;0.0001 and <italic>P</italic>&lt;0.0001 at pH<sub>i</sub> 5.0, 7.5 and 9.0, respectively) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2D</xref>). However, the difference between 20 mM and 0 mM [Na<sup>+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> was not significant in all pH<sub>i</sub>, suggesting that <italic>Er</italic>NaR might require higher intracellular sodium concentrations to successfully function.</p><p id="P13">Next, we studied the spectroscopic properties of detergent-solubilized <italic>Er</italic>NaR. In contrast to KR2<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref></sup> and many other microbial rhodopsins<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">23</xref></sup>, <italic>Er</italic>NaR undergoes only a small spectral red-shift of 3 nm upon acidification from pH 8.0 (λ<sub>max</sub> 535.5 nm) to pH 4.3 (λ<sub>max</sub> 538.5 nm) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3A</xref>). An additional 6.5 nm red-shift is observed upon further acidification to pH 2.3 (λ<sub>max</sub> 545.0 nm) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S1</xref>). Usually, pH dependent spectral changes of the dark state absorption spectrum are caused by altered protonation states of either the RSB or its counterion<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">25</xref></sup>. For KR2, it was shown that the main counterion is the aspartate (D116) of the characteristic NDQ motif, which gets protonated upon acidification and the absorption spectra undergoes notable red-shift by more than 20 nm already at pH 4.3<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref></sup>. The protonation of D116 leads to the altered photocycle kinetics and strong decrease in ion-pumping activity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref></sup>. In <italic>Er</italic>NaR, D105 residue is located at this position, which is also the main RSB counterion directly H-bonded to the Schiff base in the resting state. Based on the spectroscopy data showing almost no spectral shift upon acidification, we conclude that D105 in <italic>Er</italic>NaR remains deprotonated in a wide range of pH values. This could be explained by the presence of an additional glutamate E64 in the RSB region of this rhodopsin. The pH titration of the dark state of the <italic>Er</italic>NaR absorption spectrum (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S1</xref>) yielded two pK<sub>a</sub> values (pK<sub>a,1</sub> = 3.34 ± 0.04 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S1B</xref>) and pK<sub>a,2</sub> = 5.71 ± 0.19 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S1C</xref>)). It should be noted that in the case of detergent-solubilized KR2, the protein dissociates to monomers upon acidification to pH 4.3<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref></sup>, which is also most likely reflected in the spectral properties of the rhodopsin<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref></sup>. On the contrary, the detergent-solubilized <italic>Er</italic>NaR remains pentameric at both pH 4.3 and 8.0 as clearly observed in size-exclusion chromatography and cryo-EM experiments. Thus, the observed minor spectral shift is the feature of the functionally-relevant oligomeric form of <italic>Er</italic>NaR.</p><p id="P14">A similar weak pH dependence was found for the ultrafast dynamics of <italic>Er</italic>NaR. For all measured conditions (pH 8.0 and 4.3), the ultrafast pattern looks similar to what was already shown for other microbial rhodopsins at neutral to alkaline pH values (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig.3B</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S2</xref>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">26</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">29</xref></sup>. Namely, after photo-excitation, the excited state decays on a sub-ps timescale and the formation of a hot ground state intermediate at ˜610 nm is observed. This intermediate is commonly termed as J and relaxes to form the first stable red-shifted photoproduct K<sub>1</sub> at ˜590 nm described by the lifetime distribution in the 1-4 ps range (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S2A</xref>).</p><p id="P15">We also studied the photocycle kinetics of <italic>Er</italic>NaR on the ns to s timescale under various conditions using flash photolysis. At pH 8.0, the photocycle, as well as the impact of different sodium concentrations on the <italic>Er</italic>NaR, are similar to what was observed for KR2<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">30</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31">31</xref></sup>. The K<sub>1</sub>-intermediate at the end of the ultrafast measurement (1.8 ns), remains present at the beginning of the flash photolysis time scale (450 ns), showing that K<sub>1</sub> is populated throughout the ns timescale and no photocycle intermediate is missed due to the experimental time gap (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3B,C</xref>). K<sub>1</sub> decays within the early µs-range (lifetime distribution in the range of 5-10 µs) to form the K<sub>2</sub>-intermediate. This intermediate state is considered to be K-like because of the more pronounced red-shift compared to the known L-intermediates of other microbial rhodopsins<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">30</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31">31</xref></sup>. The transition to the blue-shifted M-intermediate then occurs within ˜1 ms. In the absence of sodium, M is the last observed intermediate of the photocycle and the protein subsequently relaxes back to the parent state, represented in the lifetime distributions centered at 5-7 s (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S3A</xref>). In the presence of a sufficient amount of sodium ions, however, the duration of M is significantly shortened and, as was observed also for KR2<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref></sup>, a strong signal assigned to the red-shifted O-intermediate rises (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3D</xref> (left)) within 2-10 ms (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S3C</xref>). Comparison of the maximum signal intensity of the O-states for different NaCl concentrations allowed the determination of Kaffinity = 190 ± 20 mM for <italic>Er</italic>NaR, demonstrating that high sodium concentrations are required to observe the “sodium-pumping mode” (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3D</xref>). At 100 mM NaCl, <italic>Er</italic>NaR shows an equilibrium of M- and O-intermediates (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S3B</xref>), indicative for mixed kinetics of one subpopulation likely undergoing the “sodium-pumping mode” photocycle while the other subpopulation undergoes a long-living M-intermediate before directly relaxing back to the parent state. In the case of the sodium-pumping regime, an additional lifetime (10-25 ms) is needed to fully describe the O-intermediate kinetics indicated by the spectral shift within the positive lifetime distribution in the range of 10-55 ms (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S3C</xref>). As it was mentioned earlier, the existence of one or two O-intermediate components and the respective interpretation is currently under debate<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref></sup>. <italic>Er</italic>NaR shows two distinct O-intermediate components (O<sub>1</sub> and O<sub>2</sub>), with O<sub>2</sub> blue-shifted compared to O<sub>1</sub> and - according to the proposed retinal configuration marker band at ˜335 nm<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32">32</xref></sup> - O<sub>1</sub> contains 13-<italic>cis</italic> retinal, while O<sub>2</sub> has all-<italic>trans</italic> retinal (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S3</xref>). These observed experimental results are in line with the findings and interpretation of Fujisawa et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref></sup> for <italic>Ia</italic>NaR.</p><p id="P16">At pH 4.3, the photocycle kinetics of <italic>Er</italic>NaR differs from that at pH 8.0. The kinetics of the early photocycle intermediates up to the formation of M under all tested conditions are similar to that observed at pH 8.0. The M-intermediate and the two O-intermediates again exhibit sodium dependence but at pH 4.3 the effects are clearly weaker. For instance, at pH 4.3 the M state under all conditions shows a weak absorbance and a fast decay, similar to that found for <italic>Er</italic>NaR at pH 8.0 at the sodium concentration of 1000 mM. Such a fast decay of the M state, which corresponds to the reprotonation of the RSB, can be explained by the higher proton concentration at acidic conditions and was also observed for KR2<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33">33</xref></sup>.</p><p id="P17">While for KR2, the distinct red-shifted O-intermediate is present only in the sodium-pumping mode and was directly associated with the sodium binding during the photocycle<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref></sup>, this must not necessarily be the case for <italic>Er</italic>NaR. Indeed, the O<sub>1</sub> and O<sub>2</sub> states were observed for <italic>Er</italic>NaR at pH 4.3 for every sodium concentration including the sodium-free conditions. The spectral shapes of the O<sub>1</sub> and O<sub>2</sub> intermediates differ from those at pH 8.0. At pH 4.3, the spectra of both O states are clearly blue-shifted compared to those at pH 8.0, while the red-shift was more expected (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S4,S5</xref>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">30</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32">32</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34">34</xref></sup>. This indicates that in the late stages of the <italic>Er</italic>NaR photocycle the environment in the close vicinity to the retinal chromophore is likely significantly different at pH 4.3 and 8.0.</p><p id="P18">With increasing sodium concentration at pH 4.3, the kinetics of the two O-intermediates are influenced differently, leading to a spectral and temporal separation of O<sub>1</sub> and O<sub>2</sub> at 1000 mM NaCl (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1G</xref>). Additionally, the retinal isomerization marker band in the near-UV (SBS)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32">32</xref></sup> indicates that the retinal conformation is different in the two O-intermediates, namely a 13-<italic>cis</italic> configuration is suggested for O<sub>1</sub> and all-<italic>trans</italic> configuration for O<sub>2</sub>, respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>). To exclude possible ionic strength effects, measurements with 1000 mM KCl and 1000 mM N-Methyl-D-glucamine (NMG), an organic monovalent cation that is commonly used to replace sodium ions in electrophysiological experiments<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35">35</xref></sup>, were performed. The measurements at pH 4.3 with 1000 mM KCl showed a photocycle very similar to the one obtained for 0 mM and 100 mM NaCl at pH 4.3 (compare <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S4A,B and Fig. S6B</xref>) lacking the clear spectral differences observed for 1000 mM NaCl (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S4C and S6B</xref>). With 1000 mM NMG at pH 4.3, the photocycle is very similar to the one with 1000 mM KCl and 0 mM NaCl at pH 4.3. The obtained lifetime densities for 1000 mM KCl and 1000 mM NMG are in good agreement as well (compare <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S4A and S6</xref>). Therefore, this allowed us to rationalize that under acidic conditions the observed separation of the O<sub>1</sub> and O<sub>2</sub> states in response to the increase of sodium concentration is a direct result of the sodium binding close to the RSB.</p></sec><sec id="S4"><title>Cryo-EM structure of the pentameric <italic>Er</italic>NaR</title><p id="P19">In order to investigate the molecular basis of the unique functional and spectral properties of <italic>Er</italic>NaR and the effect of Leu to Glu replacement in rhodopsins, we used single-particle cryo-electron microscopy (cryo-EM) to determine the structure of the protein in different conditions. We obtained the structures of <italic>Er</italic>NaR at acidic (4.3) and neutral (8.0) pH values at the resolution of 2.50 and 2.63 Å, respectively (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S7</xref>). Cryo-EM maps allowed us to model residues 1-272 of <italic>Er</italic>NaR. The overall organization of the pentamer is similar to that of KR2 and other MRs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4A</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S7</xref>). Namely, the nearby protomers interact via helices A and B and BC loop containing a β-sheet (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S8</xref>).</p><p id="P20">At the same time, the concavity in the central part of the pentamer at the extracellular side is organized differently in <italic>Er</italic>NaR and KR2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4B</xref>). In general, while in KR2 this region is polar and interacts with numerous water molecules identified using X-ray crystallography (PDB ID: 6YC3<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref></sup>), in <italic>Er</italic>NaR it is more hydrophobic (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4B</xref>). Moreover, the cryo-EM maps reveal the presence of fragments of hydrophobic chains in this region of <italic>Er</italic>NaR (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4B</xref>).</p><p id="P21">Notably, the cryo-EM data strongly suggest that the interprotomeric sodium binding site found in the KR2 pentamer<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref></sup> is absent in <italic>Er</italic>NaR (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4C</xref>). Although the maps show the spherical density at a position similar to that of the sodium ion in KR2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1D, 4C</xref>), the coordination is unlikely to favor sodium binding. In KR2 the sodium binding site is formed by two neighboring protomers; namely, by the side chains of D102’ and Y25 as well as carbonyl oxygens of T83 and F86 and two water molecules (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1D</xref>). In <italic>Er</italic>NaR, E91 (corresponding to D102 in KR2) is located 2.5 Å further from the position of the probable sodium binding site and thus is unlikely to coordinate the ion (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4C</xref>). Moreover, E91 directly interacts with the positively charged R19, located within only 5.5 Å from the possible sodium binding site (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4C</xref>). The end of BC loop of <italic>Er</italic>NaR is also arranged slightly differently from that of KR2 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S8</xref>). The sequence alignment also indicates that the region of the interprotomeric sodium binding site is organized differently in Subgroups 1 and 2 of NDQ rhodopsins (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1B</xref>, right). Thus, we speculate that the interprotomeric sodium binding site found in KR2 is likely a feature of only Subgroup 1 but not Subgroup 2 of NDQ rhodopsins.</p><p id="P22">Another feature of <italic>Er</italic>NaR is the presence of a detergent (n-Dodecyl-beta-Maltoside, DDM) molecule in the cleft between the rhodopsin protomers (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4D</xref>). The DDM molecule is found at the cytoplasmic leaflet of the membrane and its polar head is located near the pore in the <italic>Er</italic>NaR surface likely serving as the entrance for sodium ions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4D</xref>). The polar head also interacts with the C-terminus of the protein (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4D</xref>). Nevertheless, the DDM molecule does not block the pore.</p><p id="P23">Although the quality of the cryo-EM map is sufficient to place the side chains of amino acid residues as well as protein-associated water molecules, it is still limited and does not allow us to precisely determine the distances between the functional groups of rhodopsin.This hampers the understanding of the molecular mechanisms of <italic>Er</italic>NaR. For instance, while the cryo-EM data clearly show a direct interaction between the D105 residue of the characteristic NDQ motif with the newly identified E64 residue of <italic>Er</italic>NaR at both pH 4.3 and 8.0, the map regions corresponding to these residues merge together and individual positions cannot be resolved (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4E,F</xref>). Nevertheless, this might be indicative that there is a rather short H-bond between these two residues.</p></sec><sec id="S5"><title>The internal organization of the <italic>Er</italic>NaR protomer</title><p id="P24">In order to resolve details of the internal organization of <italic>Er</italic>NaR, we crystallized the protein using <italic>in meso</italic> approach and determined its structures at pH 4.6 and 8.8 at 1.7 Å resolution using X-ray crystallography. The crystals originally appeared at pH 4.6 and contained a monomer of <italic>Er</italic>NaR in the asymmetric unit. To obtain high-resolution structure of <italic>Er</italic>NaR at high pH, we soaked the crystals in the buffer solution with pH 8.8 (see Methods for details). The structures of the rhodopsin at pH 4.6 and 8.8 appeared nearly identical (RMSD of 0.06 Å). The structure of the <italic>Er</italic>NaR protomer obtained using X-ray crystallography is also very similar to that in the pentameric cryo-EM structure (RMSD of overall structures of 0.5 Å). Since the crystal structure is similar to that obtained with cryo-EM but reveals more details on the internal organization of <italic>Er</italic>NaR, we used it for the further analysis.</p><p id="P25">The overall protomer organization of <italic>Er</italic>NaR is similar to that of KR2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5A</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S8C,D</xref>) with a large cavity at the cytoplasmic part of both <italic>Er</italic>NaR and KR2, likely acting as an ion uptake cavity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5A,B</xref>). In the central region, D105 (D116 in KR2) is directly H-bonded to the RSB (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5C</xref>). The retinal cofactor is in the all-<italic>trans</italic> configuration in the resting state of <italic>Er</italic>NaR (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5A</xref>). The internal extracellular region of <italic>Er</italic>NaR is separated from the RSB region with R98 (analog of R109 in KR2) and comprises numerous polar residues including the E5-E149-R234 triad, organized almost identically to the E11-E160-R243 triad of KR2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5A</xref>).</p><p id="P26">Despite some similarities, the protomer structure of <italic>Er</italic>NaR differs from that of KR2 in several aspects. First, the N-terminus is shorter in <italic>Er</italic>NaR and the N-terminal α-helix has only one turn compared to two turns in KR2 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S8C</xref>). Nevertheless, the N-terminus is capping the inside of <italic>Er</italic>NaR (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5A</xref>, S8C). Also, an additional small C-terminal α-helix was found in <italic>Er</italic>NaR, comprising residues 267-272 of the protein (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S8D</xref>).</p><p id="P27">Second, the cytoplasmic ends of helices D, E, and F are shifted by more than 3 Å in <italic>Er</italic>NaR compared to those of KR2 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S8D</xref>). This might be related to the notable differences in the length and organization of the CD and EF loops of the two rhodopsins (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S8D</xref>). However, these shifts of the helices are not reflected in the internal organization of the cytoplasmic part of <italic>Er</italic>NaR. In particular, the ion uptake cavities of <italic>Er</italic>NaR and KR2 are highly similar.</p><p id="P28">Some differences between KR2 and <italic>Er</italic>NaR were also found in the extracellular side of the proteins. For example, there is a leucine (L68) in <italic>Er</italic>NaR at the position of Q78 in KR2, which was shown to be critical for sodium release from the latter rhodopsin<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref></sup>. However, the Q78L mutation of KR2 has no effect on sodium pumping; therefore, we suggest that this natural substitution found in <italic>Er</italic>NaR is in line with the earlier suggested mechanism of sodium release from the NDQ rhodopsins<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref></sup>.</p><p id="P29">Another noteworthy difference between <italic>Er</italic>NaR and KR2 was found in the RSB region. E64, a unique characteristic residue of <italic>Er</italic>NaR and Subgroup 2 of NDQ rhodopsins, is pointed towards the RSB and interacts directly with D105 (D116 in KR2) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5C</xref>). As a result, a large Schiff base cavity found in the ground state of KR2 in the pentameric form is absent in <italic>Er</italic>NaR and only one water molecule is found in this region (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5A,C</xref>). It is coordinated by E64, R98, W102, and D242 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5C,D</xref>). At the same time, the N101 side chain (N112 in KR2) is pointed towards the oligomerization interface similar to that found in the ground state of pentameric KR2<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref></sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5C,D</xref>).</p><p id="P30">The interaction between D105 and E64 has not been observed before and is an intriguing feature of <italic>Er</italic>NaR. Significantly higher (1.7 Å vs 2.5 Å for the cryo-EM data) allowed us to accurately position the side chains of E64 and D105 at both pH 4.6 and 8.8 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5C</xref>). The distance between the nearest oxygens of E64 and D105 was only 2.1 and 2.2 Å at pH 4.6 and 8.8, respectively, which was extremely short for a donor-acceptor distance in a normal H-bond and strongly suggests a low-barrier H-bond (LBHB) between the residues (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5D,E</xref>). The E64 side chain was also connected to the second aspartic acid counterion of the RSB, D242, through a water-mediated H-bond chain (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5C-E</xref>).</p><p id="P31">In order to get insights into the protonation states of carboxylic residues in close vicinity to the RSB and to gain more information on the strong interaction between E64 and D105 we performed hybrid quantum mechanics/molecular mechanics (QM/MM) simulations using the crystal structure of <italic>Er</italic>NaR. In particular, the protonation state of the E64 residue is of high interest as this residue is only found in Subgroup 2 of NDQ rhodopsins. Thus, we probed various protonation states of the counterion complex. For each of the three counterions we have considered one of four proton orientations as shown on <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S9</xref>. In 61 protonation patterns were considered (1 with zero-protonation, 12 single-protonation and 48 double-protonation). For all protonation pattern structure optimization was followed up by the calculation of vertical excitation energies (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S9A</xref>).</p><p id="P32">We found that the spectral and structural properties of <italic>Er</italic>NaR can be explained by system 6 with two protonated counterions, namely, E64 and D242 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S9A,B</xref>). This model also shows the lowest ground state energy with respect to all considered protonation models. The models with one protonated counterion appear significantly blue-shifted compared to those with two protonated counterions. The protonation of D105 would cause the red shift of the spectra by more than 60 nm, but its ground state energy is too high. Moreover, it would break the D105-RSB salt bridge, which is clearly observed in the high-resolution structures. Thus, we conclude that in agreement with the spectroscopic and structural data on <italic>Er</italic>NaR, D105 remains deprotonated in a wide range of pH values, while E64 is likely protonated even at a pH as high as 8.8. In the QM/MM-refined structure (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S9D</xref>) the distance between D105 and E64 is 2.5 Å. In order to analyze the nature of the interaction we performed the energy decomposition analysis using Zero-Order Symmetry Adapted Perturbation Theory (SAPT0). The SAPT0 analysis shows a significant repulsion, but it was overcompensated by electrostatics, polarization, and dispersion interactions (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S9B</xref>).</p><p id="P33">As it was proposed from the spectroscopy data, the newly identified E64 residue in the helix B of <italic>Er</italic>NaR likely maintains low pKa of the main RSB counterion D105. Structural data and QM/MM simulations suggest the following mechanism of the E64 influence on the pKa of D105 with at least two components: (1) an unusually short H-bond to the protonated E64 affecting the electrochemical properties of D105; (2) the tight integration of the E64 side chain into the H-bond network of the RSB region additionally stabilizes the overall conformation associated with the deprotonated form of D105. The LBHB between E64 and D105 means that the E64-D105 pair might also share a proton in the ground state of <italic>Er</italic>NaR in a similar way that shown for the proton release group of BR<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36">36</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="S6"><title>Comparison of the two subgroups of NaRs</title><p id="P34">The bioinformatic analysis of the clade of NDQ rhodopsins revealed two major subgroups. Our functional, spectroscopical, and structural data on <italic>Er</italic>NaR from Subgroup 2 presented here and the previously reported data on KR2 as well as other NDQ rhodopsins of Subgroup 1 allowed us to compare the properties and molecular mechanisms of these two subgroups of NaRs.</p><p id="P35">Electrophysiology demonstrated that <italic>Er</italic>NaR is capable of active transport of sodium across the membrane in a wide range of pH values, including acidic pH, which is in contrast to the functional properties of KR2. Indeed, in KR2, as well as in other members of Subgroup 1, the pH decrease leads to the protonation of the main RSB counterion, aspartic acid of the characteristic NDQ motif<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">3</xref></sup>. This protonation results in the altered photocycle and a dramatic decrease in ion-pumping activity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref></sup>. On the contrary, the members of Subgroup 2 lack such pH dependence both on spectra and sodium-pumping efficiency. In addition, proton pumping by <italic>Er</italic>NaR was negligible at all tested pH values and sodium concentrations. This is also in contrast to KR2<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref></sup>. Therefore, we suggest that the presence of an additional carboxylic residue in close proximity to the RSB in the rhodopsins of Subgroup 2 might lead to their higher selectivity to sodium ions over protons and the possible absence of the proton-pumping mode.</p><p id="P36">Our kinetics studies demonstrated both common features and fundamental differences between Subgroup 1 and Subgroup 2 of NDQ rhodopsins. Clearly, the acceleration of the M state decay upon the increase of either sodium or proton concentration shows that both types of ions can be uptaken by <italic>Er</italic>NaR in a competitive manner, similar to what was found for KR2<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33">33</xref></sup>. However, since the proton-pumping activity of <italic>Er</italic>NaR is weak compared to KR2, the further proton transition steps likely proceed differently in Subgroups 1 and 2. Namely, we suggest that in Subgroup 1 the proton is released to the extracellular space at the end of the photocycle, while in <italic>Er</italic>NaR it is likely released back towards the cytoplasm through the ion uptake cavity.</p><p id="P37">While the conformation of the RSB region in the resting state is different in <italic>Er</italic>NaR and KR2, there is a similarity in the orientation of N101 and N112 of the characteristic NDQ motif in <italic>Er</italic>NaR and KR2, respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref>). The asparagine is oriented outside of the protein protomer towards the pentameric interface in the resting state of both rhodopsins. For KR2, this conformation was directly demonstrated in 2019 but was originally proposed back in 2016 and was named “expanded” as it is characterized by a large water-filled cavity near the RSB<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37">37</xref></sup>. The expanded conformation was only found at neutral pH values, when the rhodopsin works as a sodium pump<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref></sup>. Thus, this conformation was assigned to the functional form of the protein. In <italic>Er</italic>NaR, the conformation of the RSB region lacks the large Schiff base cavity but with respect to the N101 orientation is similar to the expanded one of KR2. This allows us to conclude that in the resting state of all NDQ rhodopsins under sodium-pumping conditions, including both Subgroups 1 and 2, the common characteristic feature is the orientation of asparagine of the functional motif outside of the protomer towards the oligomerization interface. We named this common conformation as the “N-out” one (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref>). Consequently, the conformation of NDQ rhodopsin with the asparagine oriented inside the protomer should be named “N-in” (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref>).</p><p id="P38">As shown for KR2, the N-out conformation is provided by the pentameric assembly<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref></sup>. The N112 side chain is H-bonded to the residues of the nearby rhodopsin molecule when flipped outside of the protomer. At low pH values the pentameric assembly of KR2 is disturbed and oligomers partially dissociate into monomers in detergent micelles<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref></sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref>). In pentamers of KR2 at low pH only the N-in conformation was found<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref></sup>. Furthermore, in the monomer, the N-in conformation was always observed and the major reason for that was suggested to be the absence of the N112 stabilization<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref></sup>. In contrast to KR2, the pentameric assembly of <italic>Er</italic>NaR is more stable and pH independent. <italic>Er</italic>NaR also adapts the N-out conformation at both high and low pH values (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref>). Even in the monomeric form of <italic>Er</italic>NaR formed exclusively in crystals the N-out conformation is present at both acidic and alkaline pH. In summary, we suggest that the conformations of the residues comprising the characteristic NDQ motif (N101, D105, Q112 in <italic>Er</italic>NaR and N112, D116, Q123 in KR2) are similar in the ground states of both proteins, which is likely a common feature of the members of both Subgroups 1 and 2. At the same time, this N-out conformation seems to be much more stable in the proteins of Subgroup 2 than of Subgroup 1, and is independent of pH and oligomeric state.</p><p id="P39">Although the pentameric assembly is a common feature of all NDQ rhodopsins, the central areas of the pentamers of the members of Subgroups 1 and 2 are organized differently. The interprotomeric sodium binding site found in KR2 and thought to be present in all proteins belonging to Subgroup 1, is likely absent in <italic>Er</italic>NaR and the rest of Subgroup 2. The environment of the concave aqueous basin in the middle part of the <italic>Er</italic>NaR oligomer is more hydrophobic than that of KR2. The sodium release through this central region and a possible relay mechanism involving the surface-bound interprotomeric sodium ion in KR2 were proposed to lower the energetic barriers for the ion translocation against strong electrochemical gradients<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref></sup>. Thus, we suggest that sodium-release pathways and mechanisms might be different in Subgroups 1 and 2 of the NDQ rhodopsins.</p></sec></sec><sec id="S7" sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="P40">Constantly expanding gene databases allowed us to discover the naturally occurring variations within the NDQ rhodopsin clade of light-driven sodium pumps. Our findings demonstrated a new natural way of fine-tuning the active sodium transporters by the introduction of an additional carboxylic residue in close proximity to the retinal Schiff base. It results in (1) efficient sodium pumping at a wide range of pH values, (2) spectral stability, and (3) high ion selectivity, which could make the members of the newly highlighted subgroup of NDQ rhodopsins more useful for biotechnological applications. While the mechanistic insights on the resting state reported here shed more light on the NaRs organization, further structural investigations of their intermediate states are required to understand their molecular mechanisms. According to the reported results, there might be multiple mechanisms of light-driven sodium pumping by NDQ rhodopsins. Our study may be the basis for the upcoming time-resolved crystallography and/or cryo-EM as well as cryotrapping studies of the newly identified NDQ rhodopsins.</p></sec><sec id="S8" sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec id="S9"><title>Search for and phylogenetic analysis of the NDQ rhodopsins</title><p id="P41">To retrieve the NDQ rhodopsin genes from available sequence databases, jackhmmer search (N iterations = 5) was performed using the sequence of KR2 rhodopsin (UniProt ID: N0DKS8) as a template against the UniProtKB (2023-09-15), UniParc (2023-09-15), Genbank (2023-09-15), and MGnify (2023-09-15) databases. The 6-letter motifs for each protein of the output multiple sequence alignment (MSA) file, corresponding to the amino acid residues at the positions of R109, N112, D116, Q123, D251, and K216 of KR2 were retrieved using a custom Python script using jupyter notebook. The sequences possessing the RNDQDK motif were selected, filtered to contain more than 250 amino acid residues, and re-aligned separately using MUSCLE<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38">38</xref></sup>. Duplicated sequences were removed using a custom Python script. The selected sequences were also manually inspected to contain full seven transmembrane α-helices. The maximum likelihood phylogenetic tree was built using IQ-TREE webserver<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39">39</xref></sup> (Number of bootstrap alignments: 1000) and visualized using iTOL (v6.8)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40">40</xref></sup>. For the building of the phylogenetic tree all sequences with identity higher than 90% were removed using CD-HIT software<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R67">67</xref></sup>. The full MSA file, 90% identity-filtered MSA file, and phylogenetic tree file are provided as Supplementary files. Two subgroups of NDQ rhodopsins were separated by using the presence/absence of the glutamate of the position of L74 in KR2 as a criterion.</p></sec><sec id="S10"><title>Cloning</title><p id="P42"><italic>Er</italic>NaR coding DNA was optimized for <italic>E.coli</italic> or human codons using GeneArt (Thermo Fisher Scientific). Genes were synthesized commercially (Eurofins). For protein expression and purification, the pET15b plasmid with 6xHis-tag at the C-terminal was used. For electrophysiological recordings, a human codon optimized <italic>Er</italic>NaR gene was cloned into the pcDNA3.1(-) vector between <italic>Bam</italic>HI and <italic>Hind</italic>III sites together with an N-terminal part of channelrhodopsin (C2C1), membrane trafficking signal (TS) and ER export signal (ES) from potassium channel Kir2.1 and enhanced yellow fluorescent protein (EYFP). C2C1 and TS-EYFP-ES were amplified from pEYFP-N1-eKR2<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">22</xref></sup>, which was a gift from Peter Hegemann (Addgene plasmid #115337). The final construct (C2C1-<italic>Er</italic>NaR-TS-EYFP-ES) was verified by sequencing. The plasmid is available from Addgene (#209851).</p></sec><sec id="S11"><title>HEK293T cell culture and transfection</title><p id="P43">The HEK293T cells (Thermo Fisher Scientific) were cultured at 37°C with 5% CO<sub>2</sub> in high-glucose Dulbecco’s Modified Eagle Medium (DMEM), containing 1 mM sodium pyruvate and 1X GlutaMAX, supplemented with 10% heat-inactivated fetal bovine serum, 100 U/ml penicillin and 100 µg/ml streptomycin (all Thermo Fisher Scientific). The cells were regularly tested and were free from mycoplasma. For electrophysiological recordings and confocal imaging cells were seeded on poly-l-ornithine-coated 24-well plates at a concentration of 1.5 × 10<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref></sup> cells per well. After 24h, the cells were transiently transfected using 1.5 µg of Polyethylenimine MAX (PEI) (Polysciences) and 1 µg of plasmid per well in Opti-MEM (Thermo Fisher Scientific), supplemented with 1 µM of all-<italic>trans</italic>-retinal (Sigma). The transfection medium was replaced after 4–5 h with full culture medium, supplemented with 1 µM of all-trans-retinal. 16 h post transfection the cells were plated on poly-l-ornithine-coated 12-mm glass coverslips or 8-well µ-Slide (ibidi) at 20% confluence and analyzed by whole cell patch-clamp or confocal imaging 6-8 h later.</p></sec><sec id="S12"><title>Staining and live cell confocal imaging</title><p id="P44">HEK293T cells were stained with 5 µg/ml Hoechst 33342 to visualize nuclei and CellMask Deep Red (1:2000, Thermo Fisher Scientific) to label plasma membranes in Opti-MEM solution (Thermo Fisher Scientific). Imaging was performed at 37°C and 5% CO<sub>2</sub> within 30 min after the staining on a Leica Stellaris 8 confocal microscope at the Microscopy Core Facility of the Medical Faculty at the University of Bonn. EYFP and CellMask Deep Red were excited with a tunable White Light Laser (440 – 790 nm) at wavelengths 514 nm and 653 nm, respectively. Hoechst 33342 was excited with a 405 nm laser. Middle-plane images were acquired using 63×/1.2 NA water immersion objective and additional ×3 zoom at 1024 × 1024 pixels and with line averaging of 8. The resulting images were processed in FIJI. <italic>Er</italic>NaR membrane localization was similar in at least 15 cells from three separate transfections.</p></sec><sec id="S13"><title>Patch-clamp recordings, data processing and statistics</title><p id="P45">Whole-cell patch clamp recordings were performed at room temperature, using a Multiclamp 700B amplifier (Molecular Devices). The signals were filtered at 10 kHz and digitized at sampling rate of 20 kHz with an Axon Digidata 1550B digitizer (Molecular Devices) using Clampex 11 Software (part of pCLAMP 11, Molecular Devices). Patch pipettes (3-6 MΩ) were fabricated from borosilicate glass with filament (GB150F-8P, Science Products GmbH) on a horizontal puller (Model P-1000, Sutter Instruments). Light was provided by a pE-800 system (CoolLED), controlled via TTL input, and connected to the optical path of Olympus SliceScope Pro 6000 upright microscope (Scientifica) via pE-Universal Collimator (CoolLED). LED light with maximum at 550 nm was applied at 34.3 mW/mm<sup>2</sup> irradiance in the focal plane of the 20×/0.5 NA water objective to activate <italic>Er</italic>NaR. To calculate the irradiance the output light power was measured using a bolometer (Coherent OP-2 VIS, Santa Clara) and divided by the illuminated area. The intensity distribution at the illuminated spot was fitted with gaussian and a radius, within which 95% of total power accumulates, was used as a measure of the spot size. The reference electrode was connected to the bath solution via an agar bridge with 150 mM KCl. The series resistance was &lt;20 MΩ. Each cell was recorded three times and averaged directly in Clampex 11 Software to improve the signal-to-noise ratio. The ionic composition of the extracellular solution and all the intracellular solutions is indicated in Supplementary Table S3. Data were corrected for the respective liquid junction potential (LJP) after recording. LJPs for all solutions were measured directly and are stated in Supplementary Table S3. Data were analyzed using custom Wolfram Mathematica scripts and GraphPad Prism software. Photocurrent amplitudes were normalized to respective cell capacitance. Photocurrents at +60 mV were calculated from the linear fit of data points in positive voltages after LJPs correction. Time constant (t<sub>off</sub>) was determined by monoexponential fit of photocurrent decay upon light-off at holding voltage +80 mV. The data are presented as mean ± SEM of N = 6-9 cells for the photocurrent amplitudes or N = 5-8 cells for off-kinetics. The data from individual cells are also shown when appropriate. Photocurrents at +60 mV were tested for normal distribution using Shapiro-Wilk normality test (passed) and analyzed using two-way ANOVA with two Tukey’s multiple comparisons tests – for the effect of pH<sub>i</sub> changes at fixed [Na<sup>+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> and for the effect of [Na<sup>+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> changes at fixed pH<sub>i</sub>. t<sub>off</sub> was analyzed using Kruskal-Wallis test with Dunn’s multiple comparisons test.</p></sec><sec id="S14"><title>Protein expression, solubilization, and purification</title><p id="P46"><italic>E.coli</italic> cells were transformed with pET15b plasmid containing the gene of interest. Transformed cells were grown at 37°C in shaking baffled flasks in an autoinducing medium ZYP-5052<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41">41</xref></sup>, containing 10 mg/L ampicillin. They were induced at an OD<sub>600</sub> of 0.6-0.7 with 1 mM isopropyl-β-D-thiogalactopyranoside (IPTG). Subsequently, 10 μM all-<italic>trans</italic>-retinal was added. Incubation continued for 3 hours. The cells were collected by centrifugation at 5000g for 20 min. Collected cells were disrupted in an M-110P Lab Homogenizer (Microfluidics) at 25,000 p.s.i. in a buffer containing 20 mM Tris-HCl, pH 7.5, 5% glycerol, 0.5% Triton X-100 (Sigma-Aldrich) and 50 mg/L DNase I (Sigma-Aldrich). The membrane fraction of the cell lysate was isolated by ultracentrifugation at 125,000<italic>g</italic> for 1 h at 4°C. The pellet was resuspended in a buffer containing 50 mM NaH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub>/Na<sub>2</sub>HPO<sub>4</sub>, pH 7.5, 0.15 M NaCl and 1% DDM (Anatrace, Affymetrix) and stirred overnight for solubilization. The insoluble fraction was removed by ultracentrifugation at 125,000<italic>g</italic> for 1h at 4°C. The supernatant was loaded on a Ni-NTA column (Qiagen), and the protein was eluted in a buffer containing 50 mM NaH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub>/Na<sub>2</sub>HPO<sub>4</sub>, pH 7.5, 0.15 M NaCl, 0.4 M imidazole, and 0.05% DDM. The eluate was subjected to size-exclusion chromatography on a Superdex 200i 300/10 (GE Healthcare Life Sciences) in a buffer containing 50 mM NaH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub>/Na<sub>2</sub>HPO<sub>4</sub>, pH 8.0, 200 mM NaCl and 0.05% DDM. In the end, protein was concentrated to 70 mg/ml for crystallization and –80°C storage.</p></sec><sec id="S15"><title>Steady-state absorption spectroscopy and pH titration</title><p id="P47">Absorption spectra of <italic>Er</italic>NaR samples were measured with an absorption spectrometer (Specord600, Analytik Jena). Before and after each experiment, absorption spectra were taken to check sample quality. For the pH titration, samples were prepared to have a protein concentration of ˜0.4 mg/mL. The protein was suspended in the titration buffer containing 10 mM potassium citrate, 10 mM MES, 10 mM HEPES, 10 mM Tris, 10 mM CHES, 10 mM CAPS, and 100 mM Arg-HCl. The pH was adjusted with tiny amounts of [5000 mM] HCl or [5000 mM] KOH, respectively.</p></sec><sec id="S16"><title>Ultrafast transient absorption spectroscopy</title><p id="P48">Ultrafast transient absorption measurements were performed with a home-built pump-probe setup. A fs laser system - consisting of an Amplifier (Spitfire Ace-100F-1K, Spectra-Physics), seeded by a Ti:Sapphire oscillator (Mai Tai SP-NSI, Spectra-Physics) and pumped by a Nd:YLF laser (Empower 45, Spectra-Physics) - was used as the source for ultrashort laser pulses (100 fs, 800 nm, 1 kHz repetition rate). A home-built two-stage noncollinear optical parametric amplifier (NOPA) was used to generate the pump pulses at 550 nm. The white light continuum pulses used to probe the absorption changes of the sample were generated by focusing the 800 nm laser fundamental into a CaF<sub>2</sub>-crystal (3 mm). For the detection of the pump-probe signals a spectrometer (AvaSpec-ULS2048CL-EVO-RS, Avantes) was used. The measurements were performed in a 1 mm quartz cuvette and the sample was adjusted to have a protein concentration of ˜3.8 mg/mL protein. The sample was continuously moved in a plane perpendicular to the excitation beam to avoid photo-degradation. The excitation pulses were adjusted to an energy of 90 nJ/pulse.</p></sec><sec id="S17"><title>Transient flash photolysis spectroscopy</title><p id="P49">A Nd:YAG laser (SpitLight 600, Innolas Laser) was used to pump an optical parametric oscillator (preciScan, GWU-Lasertechnik). The OPO was set to generate excitation pulses with a central wavelength of 550 nm and an average pulse energy of ˜2.2 mJ/cm<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">2</xref></sup>. As probe light sources a Xenon or a Mercury-Xenon lamp (LC-8, Hamamatsu) were used. Two identical monochromators (1200 L/mm, 500 nm blaze), one in front and one after the sample, were used to set the chosen probing wavelengths. Absorption changes were detected by a photomultiplier tube (Photosensor H6780-02, Hamamatsu) and converted into an electrical signal afterwards. This signal was recorded by two oscilloscopes (PicoScope 5244B/D, Pico Technology) with overlapping timescales for detergent-solubilized samples and one oscilloscope (DPO5204B, Tektronix) for crystal samples. For each transient 30 acquisitions were measured and averaged to increase the S/N ratio. To obtain data files with a reasonable size for further analysis, raw data files were reduced using forward averaging and a combined linear and logarithmic timescale.</p><p id="P50">Detergent-solubilized samples were measured in a 2 x 10 mm quartz cuvette and prepared to have a concentration of ˜0.8 mg/mL protein. For conditions pH 8.0 0, 100, 1000 mM NaCl, pH 4.3 0, 100, 1000 mM NaCl, pH 4.3 1000 mM KCl and pH 4.3 1000 mM NMG, absorption changes were measured between 330 and 700 nm with a stepsize of 10 nm. Additional steps of the performed Na<sup>+</sup> titration were measured by recording transients at characteristic wavelengths (pH 8.0: 340 nm, 450 nm, 540 nm, 610 nm and 620 nm; pH 4.3: 340 nm, 450 nm, 540 nm, 580 nm, 600 nm and 620 nm).</p></sec><sec id="S18"><title>Analysis of time-resolved spectroscopic data</title><p id="P51">Analysis of time-resolved spectroscopic data was performed using OPTIMUS software.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref></sup> The data of the ultrafast transient absorption and transient flash photolysis measurements were objected to the model-free lifetime distribution analysis (LDA) yielding the lifetime distributions of the individual photointermediate transitions, which are summarized in a lifetime density map (LDM).</p></sec><sec id="S19"><title>Cryo-EM grid preparation and data collection</title><p id="P52">For cryo-EM all samples were originally purified in the Buffer 1 (20 mM Tris pH 8.0, 200 mM NaCl, 0.05% DDM) and concentrated to 60 mg/ml using 100,000MWCO concentrator. For the structure of <italic>Er</italic>NaR at pH 8.0 (pH 8.0 dataset), the sample was diluted later with Buffer 1 (pH 8.0 structure). For the structure of <italic>Er</italic>NaR at pH 4.3 (pH 4.3 dataset), the sample was diluted with Buffer 2 (100 mM sodium acetate pH 4.6, 200 mM NaCl, 0.05% DDM) and run through Superdex200i 300/10 column in Buffer 2 to remove excess of Buffer 1. After that, the sample was again concentrated to 60 mg/ml 100,000MWCO concentrator. For grid preparation, all samples were diluted to 7 mg/ml, and volume of applied onto freshly glow-discharged (30s at 5 mA) Quantifoil grids (Au R1.2/1.3, 300 mesh) at 20°C and 100% humidity and plunged-frozen in liquid ethane. The cryo-EM data were collected using 300 keV Krios microscope (Thermo Fisher), equipped with Gatan K3 detector.</p></sec><sec id="S20"><title>Cryo-EM data processing</title><p id="P53">All steps of data processing were performed using cryoSPARC v.4.0.2<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42">42</xref></sup> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S6</xref>). Motion correction and contrast transfer function (CTF) estimation were performed with default settings for all three datasets. Initial volume for template picking was generated after picking particles from pH 8.0 dataset using Topaz<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43">43</xref></sup> pre-trained model, followed by two rounds of 2D classification and <italic>ab initio</italic> model generation with 1 class, and homogeneous refinement. After that, for all datasets the final set of particles was picked using this volume as a template, with a template picker (150 Å particle radius), followed by duplicate removal with 50 Å distance.</p><p id="P54">For the pH 4.3 dataset, picked particles were extracted with 3x binning (384 px to 128 px). An initial set of particles was cleaned using two rounds of 2D classification (first round: 80 classes, 80 iterations, 5 final iterations, batch size 400, use clamp-solvent: true; second round: 40 classes, 40 iterations, batch size 200, use clamp-solvent: true). After that, particles were cleaned using a "3D classification" (<italic>ab initio</italic> model generation with 5 classes, followed by heterogeneous refinement), producing 555,294 particles for the non-binned refinement. These particles were re-extracted with 320 px box size, followed by homogeneous refinement (C5 symmetry, with per-particle CTF and defocus refinement) and local refinement (C5 symmetry, map generated with "Volume tools" at threshold 0.48), yielding a final resolution of 2.50 Å.</p><p id="P55">For the pH 8.0 dataset, picked particles were extracted with 4x binning (512 px to 128 px). An initial set of particles was cleaned using two rounds of 2D classification (first round: 50 classes, 40 iterations, batch size 200, use clamp-solvent: true; second round: 20 classes, 40 iterations, batch size 200, use clamp-solvent: true). After that, particles were cleaned using a "3D classification" (<italic>ab initio</italic> model generation with 5 classes, followed by heterogeneous refinement), producing 437,017 particles for the non-binned refinement. These particles were re-extracted with 640 px box size, followed by homogeneous refinement (C5 symmetry, with per-particle CTF and defocus refinement) and local refinement (C5 symmetry), yielding a final resolution of 2.63 Å.</p></sec><sec id="S21"><title>Model building and refinement</title><p id="P56">Automatically sharpened maps from cryoSPARC were aligned using UCSF ChimeraX<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R44">44</xref></sup>. The pentameric model of <italic>Er</italic>NaR was generated using Alphafold<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R45">45</xref></sup> and docked as a rigid body into cryo-EM maps manually in ChimeraX. Further refinement was performed using Phenix<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R46">46</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R47">47</xref></sup> and Coot<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R48">48</xref></sup>, producing the final statistics described in Table S1. Visualization and structure interpretation were carried out in UCSF Chimera<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R44">44</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R49">49</xref></sup> and PyMol (Schrödinger, LLC).</p></sec><sec id="S22"><title>Crystallization</title><p id="P57">The crystals of <italic>Er</italic>NaR were grown with an <italic>in meso</italic> approach<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R50">50</xref></sup>, similar to that used in our previous works<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref></sup>. In particular, the solubilized protein (60 mg/ml) in the crystallization buffer was mixed with premelted at 42°C monoolein (MO, Nu-Chek Prep) in a 3:2 ratio (lipid:protein) to form a lipidic mesophase. The mesophase was homogenized in coupled syringes (Hamilton) by transferring the mesophase from one syringe to another until a homogeneous and gel-like material was formed.</p><p id="P58">Then, 150 nl drops of a protein–mesophase mixture were spotted on a 96-well LCP glass sandwich plate (Marienfeld) and overlaid with 400 nL of precipitant solution by means of the NT8 or Mosquito crystallization robots (Formulatrix and SPT Labtech, respectively). The best crystals were obtained with a protein concentration of 20 mg/ml (in the water part of the mesophase). The best crystals were obtained using 0.1M Sodium acetate pH 4.6, 10% PEG550MME (Hampton Research) as a precipitant. The crystals were grown at 22°C and appeared in 1 month.</p><p id="P59">For the determination of the <italic>Er</italic>NaR crystals structure at pH 4.6, once the crystals reached their final size, crystallization wells were opened, and drops containing the protein-mesophase mixture were covered with 100 μl of the precipitant solution. For the data collection, harvested crystals were incubated for 5 min in the precipitant solution. For the determination of the <italic>Er</italic>NaR crystals structure at pH 8.8, the crystals were originally grown at pH 4.6 using the same precipitant as described above. Once the crystals reached their final size, crystallization wells were opened and the crystals were soaked for 48 hours with exchanging the buffer three times. Crystals were harvested using micromounts (Mitegen, USA), flash-cooled, and stored in liquid nitrogen.</p></sec><sec id="S23"><title>Diffraction data collection and treatment</title><p id="P60">X-ray diffraction data of both structures of the ground state of <italic>Er</italic>NaR at pH 4.6 and 8.8 were collected at the P14 beamline of PETRAIII (Hamburg, Germany) using an EIGER X 16M and EIGER2 X 16M CdTe detectors. The data collection was performed using MxCube2 software. Diffraction images were processed using XDS<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R51">51</xref></sup>. The reflection intensities were scaled and merged using the Staraniso server<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R52">52</xref></sup>. There is no possibility of twinning for the crystals. In both cases, diffraction data from a single crystal were used. The data collection and treatment statistics are presented in Table S2.</p></sec><sec id="S24"><title>Crystal structure determination and refinement of <italic>Er</italic>NaR</title><p id="P61">Initial phases for the ground state of monomeric <italic>Er</italic>NaR at pH 4.6 were successfully obtained in the P6122 space group by molecular replacement using MOLREP<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R53">53</xref></sup> from the CCP4 program suite<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R54">54</xref></sup> using the 4XTL structure of monomeric KR2<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref></sup> as a search model. The initial model was iteratively refined using REFMAC5<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R55">55</xref></sup> and Coot<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R56">56</xref></sup>. The phases for the structure of <italic>Er</italic>NaR at pH 8.8 were determined using MOLREP with the phases of the <italic>Er</italic>NaR structure at pH 4.6 as a search model. The structure refinement statistics are presented in Table S2.</p></sec><sec id="S25"><title>Molecular simulation</title><p id="P62">Structures of all protonation models were optimized using electrostatic embedding QM/MM scheme<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R57">57</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R58">58</xref></sup> using L-BFGS<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R59">59</xref></sup> algorithm, implemented in Orca v5.0.3<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R60">60</xref></sup> computational package. The QM part was treated with TD--DFT (B3LYP<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R61">61</xref></sup> functional) level of theory, with Grimme<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R62">62</xref></sup> dispersion correction, adopting the correlation-consistent<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R63">63</xref></sup> cc-pVDZ atomic basis set and Resolution--of--Identity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R64">64</xref></sup> approximation. The MM part (part of protein within 5 Å of the retinal) was treated using the FF14SB AMBER force field<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R65">65</xref></sup>, while the rest of the protein was frozen. The vertical excitation energy was computed using the same QM/MM scheme at the RI second--order Algebraic Diagrammatic Construction (RI-ADC(2)) level of theory (QM part) implemented in the computational package Turbomole<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R66">66</xref></sup>. The point charges (MM part) of the environment were generated using the FF14SB AMBER force field.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="SM"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1"><label>Supplementary Information</label><media xlink:href="EMS189582-supplement-Supplementary_Information.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" id="d202aAdHbB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack id="S26"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>This research was supported by the German Research Foundation (CRC 1507 – Membrane-associated Protein Assemblies, Machineries and Supercomplexes; Project 05 to J.W.). G.H.U.L., A.V.S. and J.W. also thank Dr. Marvin Asido for helpful discussions. E.M., A.S. and A.G. thank NeCEN personnel for the support during data collection. The access to NeCEN facilities was funded by the Netherlands Electron Microscopy Infrastructure (NEMI), project number 184.034.014 of the National Roadmap for Large-Scale Research Infra- structure of the Dutch Research Council (NWO). A.G. was supported by NWO grant OCENW.KLEIN.141. We thank the Microscopy Core Facility of the Medical Faculty at the University of Bonn for providing support and instrumentation funded by the Bundesministerium für Bildung und Forschung (BMBF, Federal Ministry of Education and Research) – ACCENT: Förderung von Advanced Clinician Scientist im Bereich Immunopathogenese und Organdysfunktion, Gehirn und Neurodegeneration – Förderkennzeichen: 01EO2107. V.B. acknowledges support by the Volkswagen Foundation (Freigeist—A110720) and the Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft (EXC-2151-390873048-Cluster of Excellence—ImmunoSensation2 at the University of Bonn). K.K. has been supported by EMBL Interdisciplinary Postdoctoral Fellowship (EIPOD4) under Marie Sklodowska-Curie Actions Cofund (grant agreement number 847543). The work of A.A. was supported by funding from the German Research Foundation to T. Moser via the Multiscale Bioimaging - Cluster of Excellence (EXC 2067/1-390729940).</p></ack><sec id="S27" sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data Availability</title><p id="P63">Atomic models built using X-ray crystallography and cryo-EM data have been deposited in the RCSB Protein Data Bank with PDB codes 8QR0 (for the pentameric form at pH 4.3), 8QQZ (for the pentameric form at pH 8.0), 8QLE (for the monomeric form at pH 4.6), and 8QLF (for the monomeric form at pH 8.8). Publicly available in RCSB Protein Data Bank structures of KR2 (PDB IDs: 4XTL, 6YC3, 6XYT) were used for analysis. The cryo-EM density maps have been deposited in the Electron Microscopy Data Bank under accession numbers EMD-18610 (pH 4.3) and EMD-18609 (pH 8.0).</p></sec><fn-group><fn id="FN2" fn-type="con"><p id="P64"><bold>Author Contributions</bold></p><p id="P65">K.K. performed bioinformatics analysis of the NDQ rhodopsins with the help of A.A. and under the supervision of A.B.; K.K. cloned the <italic>Er</italic>NaR gene for <italic>E.coli</italic> expression; C.B. and K.K. expressed and purified <italic>Er</italic>NaR in <italic>E.coli</italic>; T.B. supervised the expression and purification; E.P. cloned the <italic>Er</italic>NaR gene for electrophysiology studies with the help of N.M.; E.P. did the electrophysiology of <italic>Er</italic>NaR; G.H.U.L. and A.V.S. did the spectroscopy of <italic>Er</italic>NaR under the supervision of J.W.; K.K. crystallized the protein; R.A. helped with initial crystallization trials; V.G. supervised initial crystallization trials; K.K. collected and processed X-ray crystallography data and solved the crystal structures of <italic>Er</italic>NaR; G.B. helped with the X-ray crystallography data analysis; A.S. prepared grids and performed initial characterization and analysis of EM data; E.M. and A.G. processed cryo-EM data and obtained initial pentameric models of <italic>Er</italic>NaR; K.K. refined the cryo-EM structures; A.G. supervised grid preparation, cryo-EM data collection and processing and structure refinement and validation; D.F. performed QM/MM simulation under the supervision of I.S.; V.G. suggested the concept of short strong H-bonds for pKa control of functional residues; K.K., E.P., A.A., G.H.U.L., D.F., E.M. analyzed the data and prepared a manuscript with contributions of V.G., A.G., V.B., T.R.S., and all other authors.</p></fn><fn id="FN3" fn-type="conflict"><p id="P66"><bold>Competing Interest</bold></p><p id="P67">Authors declare no competing interests.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><ref id="R1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Inoue</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A light-driven sodium ion pump in marine bacteria</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2013</year><volume>4</volume><elocation-id>1678</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23575682</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kandori</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Inoue</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsunoda</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Light-Driven Sodium-Pumping Rhodopsin: A New Concept of Active Transport</article-title><source>Chemical Reviews</source><year>2018</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29513519</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Balashov</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Light-driven Na+pump from Gillisia limnaea: A high-affinity Na+binding site is formed transiently in the photocycle</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><year>2014</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4263435</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25375769</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/bi501064n</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bertsova</surname><given-names>YV</given-names></name><name><surname>Bogachev</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name><name><surname>Skulachev</surname><given-names>VP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Proteorhodopsin from Dokdonia sp. PRO95 is a light-driven Na+-pump</article-title><source>Biochem Mosc</source><year>2015</year><volume>80</volume><fpage>449</fpage><lpage>454</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25869362</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yoshizawa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Functional characterization of flavobacteria rhodopsins reveals a unique class of light-driven chloride pump in bacteria</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2014</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4020065</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24706784</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1403051111</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tsunoda</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Functional characterization of sodium-pumping rhodopsins with different pumping properties</article-title><source>PLOS ONE</source><year>2017</year><volume>12</volume><elocation-id>e0179232</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5531490</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28749956</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0179232</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oesterhelt</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Stoeckenius</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rhodopsin-like protein from the purple membrane of Halobacterium halobium</article-title><source>Nature New Biol</source><year>1971</year><volume>233</volume><fpage>149</fpage><lpage>152</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4940442</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>S-G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Discovery of a new light-driven Li+/Na+-pumping rhodopsin with DTG motif</article-title><source>J Photochem Photobiol B</source><year>2021</year><volume>223</volume><elocation-id>112285</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34411952</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gushchin</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Crystal structure of a light-driven sodium pump</article-title><source>Nat Struct Mol Biol</source><year>2015</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>390</fpage><lpage>396</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25849142</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Structural basis for Na+ transport mechanism by a light-driven Na+ pump</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2015</year><volume>521</volume><fpage>48</fpage><lpage>53</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25849775</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shibata</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Oligomeric states of microbial rhodopsins determined by high-speed atomic force microscopy and circular dichroic spectroscopy</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2018</year><volume>8</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5974397</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29844455</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-018-26606-y</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kovalev</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Structure and mechanisms of sodium-pumping KR2 rhodopsin</article-title><source>Sci Adv</source><year>2019</year><volume>5</volume><elocation-id>eaav2671</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6457933</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30989112</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/sciadv.aav2671</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hoque</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A Chimera Na+-Pump Rhodopsin as an Effective Optogenetic Silencer</article-title><source>PLOS ONE</source><year>2016</year><volume>11</volume><elocation-id>e0166820</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5115807</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27861619</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0166820</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Skopintsev</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Femtosecond-to-millisecond structural changes in a light-driven sodium pump</article-title><source>Natured</source><year>2020</year><volume>583</volume><fpage>314</fpage><lpage>318</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32499654</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsukamoto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Demura</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kikukawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Real-time identification of two substrate-binding intermediates for the light-driven sodium pump rhodopsin</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2021</year><volume>296</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8219890</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34019877</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jbc.2021.100792</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tsujimura</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ishikita</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of intermediate conformations in the photocycle of the light-driven sodium-pumping rhodopsin KR2</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2021</year><volume>296</volume><elocation-id>100459</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8039564</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33639164</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jbc.2021.100459</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fujisawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kinoue</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Seike</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Kikukawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Unno</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reisomerization of retinal represents a molecular switch mediating Na+ uptake and release by a bacterial sodium-pumping rhodopsin</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2022</year><volume>298</volume><elocation-id>102366</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9483557</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35963435</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jbc.2022.102366</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="web"><source>Photochemistry of the Light-Driven Sodium Pump Krokinobacter eikastus Rhodopsin 2 and Its Implications on Microbial Rhodopsin Research: Retrospective and Perspective | The Journal of Physical Chemistry B</source><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/10.1021/acs.jpcb.2c08933">https://pubs.acs.org/doi/10.1021/acs.jpcb.2c08933</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kovalev</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Molecular mechanism of light-driven sodium pumping</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2020</year><volume>11</volume><elocation-id>2137</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7195465</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32358514</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-020-16032-y</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abe-Yoshizumi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Inoue</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name><name><surname>Nureki</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Kandori</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Role of Asn112 in a Light-Driven Sodium Ion-Pumping Rhodopsin</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><year>2016</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>5790</fpage><lpage>5797</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27673340</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Inoue</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Konno</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Abe-yoshizumi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Kandori</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Role of the NDQ Motif in Sodium-Pumping Rhodopsins</article-title><source>Angew Chem</source><year>2015</year><volume>127</volume><fpage>11698</fpage><lpage>11701</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4600240</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26215709</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/anie.201504549</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grimm</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Silapetere</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Vogt</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bernal Sierra</surname><given-names>YA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hegemann</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Electrical properties, substrate specificity and optogenetic potential of the engineered light-driven sodium pump eKR2</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2018</year><volume>8</volume><elocation-id>9316</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6006383</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29915394</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-018-27690-w</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huber</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>pH-Dependent Photoisomerization of Retinal in Proteorhodopsin</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><year>2005</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>1800</fpage><lpage>1806</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15697205</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kriebel</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Structural and functional consequences of the H180A mutation of the light-driven sodium pump KR2</article-title><source>Biophys J</source><year>2023</year><volume>122</volume><fpage>1003</fpage><lpage>1017</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10111219</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36528791</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bpj.2022.12.023</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Asido</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wachtveitl</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Photochemistry of the Light-Driven Sodium Pump Krokinobacter eikastus Rhodopsin 2 and Its Implications on Microbial Rhodopsin Research: Retrospective and Perspective</article-title><source>J Phys Chem B</source><year>2023</year><volume>127</volume><fpage>3766</fpage><lpage>3773</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36919947</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tahara</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Ultrafast Photoreaction Dynamics of a Light-Driven Sodium-Ion-Pumping Retinal Protein from Krokinobacter eikastus Revealed by Femtosecond Time-Resolved Absorption Spectroscopy</article-title><source>J Phys Chem Lett</source><year>2015</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>4481</fpage><lpage>4486</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26582475</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sudo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The Early Steps in the Photocycle of a Photosensor Protein Sensory Rhodopsin I from Salinibacter ruber</article-title><source>J Phys Chem B</source><year>2014</year><volume>118</volume><fpage>1510</fpage><lpage>1518</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24447185</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Ultrafast Pump−Probe Study of the Primary Photoreaction Process in pharaonis Halorhodopsin: Halide Ion Dependence and Isomerization Dynamics</article-title><source>J Phys Chem B</source><year>2008</year><volume>112</volume><fpage>12795</fpage><lpage>12800</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18793013</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mathies</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Brito Cruz</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Pollard</surname><given-names>WT</given-names></name><name><surname>Shank</surname><given-names>CV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Direct Observation of the Femtosecond Excited-State cis-trans Isomerization in Bacteriorhodopsin</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1988</year><volume>240</volume><fpage>777</fpage><lpage>779</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3363359</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eberhardt</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Temperature Dependence of the Krokinobacter rhodopsin 2 Kinetics</article-title><source>Biophys J</source><year>2021</year><volume>120</volume><fpage>568</fpage><lpage>575</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7895995</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33347887</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bpj.2020.12.011</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weissbecker</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The Voltage Dependent Sidedness of the Reprotonation of the Retinal Schiff Base Determines the Unique Inward Pumping of Xenorhodopsin</article-title><source>Angew Chem Int Ed</source><year>2021</year><volume>60</volume><fpage>23010</fpage><lpage>23017</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8518763</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34339559</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/anie.202103882</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Asido</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Transient Near-UV Absorption of the Light-Driven Sodium Pump Krokinobacter eikastus Rhodopsin 2: A Spectroscopic Marker for Retinal Configuration</article-title><source>J Phys Chem Lett</source><year>2021</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>6284</fpage><lpage>6291</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34213348</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Inoue</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kandori</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Kinetic Analysis of H+-Na+ Selectivity in a Light-Driven Na+-Pumping Rhodopsin</article-title><source>J Phys Chem Lett</source><year>2015</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26673197</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Henrich</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>From Gene to Function: Cell-Free Electrophysiological and Optical Analysis of Ion Pumps in Nanodiscs</article-title><source>Biophys J</source><year>2017</year><volume>113</volume><fpage>1331</fpage><lpage>1341</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5607034</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28450130</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bpj.2017.03.026</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sineshchekov</surname><given-names>OA</given-names></name><name><surname>Govorunova</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Spudich</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bacteriorhodopsin-like channelrhodopsins: Alternative mechanism for control of cation conductance</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci</source><year>2017</year><volume>114</volume><fpage>E9512</fpage><lpage>E9519</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5692563</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29078348</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1710702114</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Borshchevskiy</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>True-atomic-resolution insights into the structure and functional role of linear chains and low-barrier hydrogen bonds in proteins</article-title><source>Nat Struct Mol Biol</source><year>2022</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>440</fpage><lpage>450</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35484235</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gushchin</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Structure of the light-driven sodium pump KR2 and its implications for optogenetics</article-title><source>FEBS J</source><year>2016</year><volume>283</volume><fpage>1232</fpage><lpage>1238</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26535564</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Edgar</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MUSCLE: multiple sequence alignment with high accuracy and high throughput</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2004</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>1792</fpage><lpage>1797</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC390337</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15034147</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkh340</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Trifinopoulos</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>L-T</given-names></name><name><surname>Haeseler</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Minh</surname><given-names>BQ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>W-IQ-TREE: a fast online phylogenetic tool for maximum likelihood analysis</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2016</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>W232</fpage><lpage>235</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4987875</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27084950</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkw256</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Letunic</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Bork</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Interactive Tree Of Life (iTOL) v5: an online tool for phylogenetic tree display and annotation</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2021</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>W293</fpage><lpage>W296</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8265157</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33885785</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkab301</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R41"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Studier</surname><given-names>FW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Protein production by auto-induction in high-density shaking cultures</article-title><source>Protein Expr Purif</source><year>2005</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>207</fpage><lpage>234</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15915565</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R42"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Punjani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rubinstein</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Fleet</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Brubaker</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>cryoSPARC: algorithms for rapid unsupervised cryo-EM structure determination</article-title><source>Nat Methods</source><year>2017</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>290</fpage><lpage>296</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28165473</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R43"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bepler</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Positive-unlabeled convolutional neural networks for particle picking in cryo-electron micrographs</article-title><source>Nat Methods</source><year>2019</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>1153</fpage><lpage>1160</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6858545</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31591578</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41592-019-0575-8</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R44"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goddard</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>UCSF ChimeraX: Meeting modern challenges in visualization and analysis</article-title><source>Protein Sci</source><year>2018</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>14</fpage><lpage>25</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5734306</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28710774</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/pro.3235</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R45"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jumper</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Highly accurate protein structure prediction with AlphaFold</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2021</year><volume>596</volume><fpage>583</fpage><lpage>589</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8371605</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34265844</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41586-021-03819-2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R46"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Afonine</surname><given-names>PV</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Real-space refinement in PHENIX for cryo-EM and crystallography</article-title><source>Acta Crystallogr Sect Struct Biol</source><year>2018</year><volume>74</volume><fpage>531</fpage><lpage>544</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6096492</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29872004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1107/S2059798318006551</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R47"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Afonine</surname><given-names>PV</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>New tools for the analysis and validation of cryo-EM maps and atomic models</article-title><source>Acta Crystallogr Sect Struct Biol</source><year>2018</year><volume>74</volume><fpage>814</fpage><lpage>840</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6130467</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30198894</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1107/S2059798318009324</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R48"><label>48</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Emsley</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Lohkamp</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>WG</given-names></name><name><surname>Cowtan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Features and development of Coot</article-title><source>Acta Crystallogr D Biol Crystallogr</source><year>2010</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>486</fpage><lpage>501</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2852313</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20383002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1107/S0907444910007493</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R49"><label>49</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pettersen</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>UCSF Chimera—A visualization system for exploratory research and analysis</article-title><source>J Comput Chem</source><year>2004</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>1605</fpage><lpage>1612</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15264254</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R50"><label>50</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Landau</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosenbusch</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lipidic cubic phases: A novel concept for the crystallization of membrane proteins</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci</source><year>1996</year><volume>93</volume><fpage>14532</fpage><lpage>14535</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC26167</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8962086</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.93.25.14532</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R51"><label>51</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kabsch</surname><given-names>WXDS</given-names></name></person-group><source>Acta Crystallogr D Biol Crystallogr</source><year>2010</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>125</fpage><lpage>132</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R52"><label>52</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tickle</surname><given-names>IJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cambridge, United Kingdom: Global Phasing Ltd</article-title><source>Staraniso</source><year>2018</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R53"><label>53</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vagin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Teplyakov</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular replacement with MOLREP</article-title><source>Acta Crystallogr D Biol Crystallogr</source><year>2010</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>22</fpage><lpage>25</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20057045</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R54"><label>54</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Winn</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Overview of the CCP4 suite and current developments</article-title><source>Acta Crystallogr D Biol Crystallogr</source><year>2011</year><volume>67</volume><fpage>235</fpage><lpage>242</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3069738</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21460441</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1107/S0907444910045749</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R55"><label>55</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Murshudov</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>REFMAC5 for the refinement of macromolecular crystal structures</article-title><source>Acta Crystallogr D Biol Crystallogr</source><year>2011</year><volume>67</volume><fpage>355</fpage><lpage>367</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3069751</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21460454</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1107/S0907444911001314</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R56"><label>56</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Emsley</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Cowtan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Coot: model-building tools for molecular graphics</article-title><source>Acta Crystallogr D Biol Crystallogr</source><year>2004</year><volume>60</volume><fpage>2126</fpage><lpage>2132</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15572765</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R57"><label>57</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Warshel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Levitt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Theoretical studies of enzymic reactions: Dielectric, electrostatic and steric stabilization of the carbonium ion in the reaction of lysozyme</article-title><source>J Mol Biol</source><year>1976</year><volume>103</volume><fpage>227</fpage><lpage>249</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">985660</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R58"><label>58</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shurki</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Warshel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Structure, Function Correlations of Proteins using MM Q, MM, and Related Approaches: Methods, Concepts, Pitfalls, and Current Progress</chapter-title><source>Advances in Protein Chemistry</source><year>2003</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>249</fpage><lpage>313</lpage><publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14631821</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R59"><label>59</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nocedal</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Updating quasi-Newton matrices with limited storage</article-title><source>Math Comput</source><year>1980</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>773</fpage><lpage>782</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R60"><label>60</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Neese</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Software update: The ORCA program system—Version 5.0</article-title><source>WIREs Comput Mol Sci</source><year>2022</year><volume>12</volume><elocation-id>e1606</elocation-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R61"><label>61</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Runge</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Gross</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>U Density-Functional Theory for Time-Dependent Systems</article-title><source>Phys Rev Lett</source><year>1984</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>997</fpage><lpage>1000</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R62"><label>62</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grimme</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Semiempirical GGA-type density functional constructed with a long-range dispersion correction</article-title><source>J Comput Chem</source><year>2006</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>1787</fpage><lpage>1799</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16955487</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R63"><label>63</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dunning</surname><given-names>TH</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name></person-group><article-title>Gaussian basis sets for use in correlated molecular calculations I The atoms boron through neon and hydrogen</article-title><source>J Chem Phys</source><year>1989</year><volume>90</volume><fpage>1007</fpage><lpage>1023</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R64"><label>64</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vahtras</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Almlöf</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Feyereisen</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Integral approximations for LCAO-SCF calculations</article-title><source>Chem Phys Lett</source><year>1993</year><volume>213</volume><fpage>514</fpage><lpage>518</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R65"><label>65</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hahn</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Observation of an electric quadrupole transition in the X-ray absorption spectrum of a Cu(II) complex</article-title><source>Chem Phys Lett</source><year>1982</year><volume>88</volume><fpage>595</fpage><lpage>598</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R66"><label>66</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Balasubramani</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>TURBOMOLE: Modular program suite for ab initio quantum-chemical and condensed-matter simulations</article-title><source>J Chem Phys</source><year>2020</year><volume>152</volume><elocation-id>184107</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7228783</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32414256</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1063/5.0004635</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R67"><label>67</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Niu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>CD-HIT: accelerated for clustering the next-generation sequencing data</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2012</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>3150</fpage><lpage>3152</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3516142</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23060610</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/bts565</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><title>Phylogeny of NDQ rhodopsins.</title><p>A. Phylogenetic tree of the NDQ rhodopsins clade. Subgroups 1 and 2 are highlighted in green and blue, respectively. B. Sequence alignment of the key regions of the representative NDQ rhodopsins: internal polar/rechargeable amino acid residues (left), functionally and structurally relevant external amino acid residues (right). The key positions are marked with bold numbers according to the KR2 sequence. Additional RSB counterion (E64 in <italic>Er</italic>NaR) in the Subgroup 2 is highlighted red. Additional positively charged residue near the interprotomeric sodium binding site (R19 in <italic>Er</italic>NaR) is highlighted blue. C. The RSB region of KR2 in the ground (left, yellow) and O (right, blue) states of the photocycle and the role of L74. Distance from L74 to the nearest water molecule in the Schiff base cavity is indicated with a red arrow (left) and is given in bold italic. The flipping motion of the L74 side chain upon sodium binding in the O state is also indicated with a red arrow (right). The sodium ion is shown with the purple sphere. D. Interprotomeric sodium binding site in KR2. Overall view of the KR2 pentamer from the extracellular side (left) and detailed view of the site (right). Two neighboring protomers are colored yellow and green. The BC loop is colored dark blue. The sodium ion (purple sphere) coordination is indicated with black dashed lines.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS189582-f001"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><title>Functional characterization of <italic>Er</italic> NaR in HEK293T cells.</title><p><bold>A</bold>. Representative confocal images of HEK293T cell expressing <italic>Er</italic>NaR. Fluorescence of EYFP, fused to <italic>Er</italic>NaR, is shown in green; the plasma membrane stain CellMask - in magenta; nucleus stain Hoechst 33342 - in grey. The co-localization of EYFP and CellMask appears in white. Scale bars, 10 µm. B. Representative photocurrents of <italic>Er</italic>NaR recorded from HEK293T cells at 130 mM (left), 20 mM (middle) and 0 mM (right) intracellular [Na<sup>+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> and pH<sub>i</sub> 7.5. C. Voltage dependence of the stationary photocurrents of <italic>Er</italic>NaR at intracellular [Na<sup>+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> 130 mM (left), 20 mM (middle) and 0 mM (right) and different pH<sub>i</sub> values (LJP-corrected; normalized to respective cell capacitance; mean ± SEM of n = 6-9 cells). D. Stationary photocurrents of <italic>Er</italic>NaR at +60 mV, normalized to respective cell capacitance (mean ± SEM and individual data points of n = 6-9 cells). Data were extracted from the recordings at different intracellular [Na<sup>+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> and pH<sub>i</sub> described in C.. Normalized currents were analyzed using two-way ANOVA with two Turkey`s multiple comparisons tests – for the effect of pH<sub>i</sub> at fixed [Na<sup>+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> (depicted on the graph, ns is not shown) and for the effect of [Na<sup>+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> at fixed pH<sub>i</sub> (inset table). E. Kinetics of photocurrent decay upon light-off at 130 mM intracellular [Na<sup>+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> and different pH<sub>i</sub> (mean ± SEM and individual data points of n = 5-8 cells). The time constant (t<sub>off</sub>) was determined by monoexponential fit of photocurrent decay at holding voltage +80 mV. Data were analyzed using Kruskal-Wallis test with Dunn`s multiple comparisons test (all ns). B-E. All patch-clamp experiments were conducted at 110 mM extracellular [Na<sup>+</sup>]<sub>e</sub>, pH<sub>e</sub> 7.5; LED light with maximum at 550 nm was applied for 1 s at 34.3 mW/mm<sup>2</sup> irradiance. ns – not significant (<italic>P</italic> &gt; 0.05), *<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05, **<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01, ***<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001 and ****<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.0001.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS189582-f002"/></fig><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><title>Spectroscopic characterization of <italic>Er</italic>NaR.</title><p><bold>A.</bold>n Normalized absorption spectra of <italic>Er</italic>NaR at acidic (pH 4.3) and neutral (pH 8.0) conditions. The spectra have been normalized to the absorbance at 280 nm. B. 2D-contour plot of a fs-TA measurement of <italic>Er</italic>NaR (pH 8.0, 0 mM NaCl). The timescale is linear until 1 ps and logarithmic afterwards. The signal amplitude is color coded as follows: positive (red), no (white) and negative (blue) abs. The mentioned abbreviations represent excited-state absorption (ESA), ground-state bleach (GSB) and stimulated emission (SE). C. 2D-contour plot of a flash photolysis measurement of <italic>Er</italic>NaR (pH 8.0, 1000 mM NaCl). D. Sodium dependence of the transient at 620 nm, indicative of the O<sub>1/2</sub>-intermediate, at pH 8.0. Transients have been normalized to have the same Δabs. at 0.1 ms. The absorption maximum of the O<sub>1/2</sub>-intermediate was plotted against the sodium concentration and the resulting data was fitted with the Hill equation to obtain the sodium dependence of the O<sub>1/2</sub>-intermediate. E. Schematic model of the <italic>Er</italic>NaR photocycle at pH 8.0, 1000 mM NaCl. F. 2D-contour plot of a flash photolysis measurement of <italic>Er</italic>NaR (pH 4.3, 1000 mM NaCl). G. Sodium dependence of the transient at 600 nm, representative for the O<sub>1/2</sub>-intermediates, at pH 4.3. Transients have been normalized to have the same Dabs. at 0.1 ms. H. Schematic model of the <italic>Er</italic>NaR photocycle at pH 4.3, 1000 mM NaCl.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS189582-f003"/></fig><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><title>Cryo-EM structures of <italic>Er</italic> NaR.</title><p>A. Overall view of the <italic>Er</italic>NaR pentamer from the extracellular (top) and along the membrane plane (bottom). B. Comparison of the hydrophobicity of the concave aqueous basic in the center of the <italic>Er</italic>NaR and KR2 pentamers. C. The region of interprotomeric sodium binding site (according to the KR2 structure) absent in <italic>Er</italic>NaR. The cryo-EM map (pH 8.0) is shown with black mesh. D. The DDM molecule in the cryo-EM structures of <italic>Er</italic>NaR. 5 molecules of DDM are located between neighboring protomers at the cytoplasmic side of the protein. The polar head of DDM is located next to the entrance to the ion uptake cavity and interacts with the C-terminal helix found in <italic>Er</italic>NaR. E. The central region of the <italic>Er</italic>NaR protomer at pH 8.0. The cryo-EM map is shown with black mesh and indicates direct interaction between D105 and E64. F. The central region of the <italic>Er</italic>NaR protomer at pH 4.3. The cryo-EM map is shown with black mesh and indicates direct interaction between D105 and E64.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS189582-f004"/></fig><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><title>Crystal structures of <italic>Er</italic> NaR.</title><p><bold>A.</bold> Overall side view of the <italic>Er</italic>NaR monomer. Hydrophobic/hydrophilic membrane core boundaries are shown with gray lines. B. Detailed view of the cytoplasmic internal part of <italic>Er</italic>NaR. Cavities were calculated using HOLLOW and are shown with a pink surface. Red arrow indicates putative sodium uptake pathway. C. The RSB region of <italic>Er</italic>NaR at pH 4.6. 2Fo-Fc electron density maps are contoured at the level of 1.0σ and are shown with black mesh. H-bonds are shown with black dashed lines. Light-red area indicates the region of the Schiff base cavity found in KR2 and absent in <italic>Er</italic>NaR. D. The detailed view of the RSB region of <italic>Er</italic>NaR at pH 4.6. E. The detailed view of the RSB region of <italic>Er</italic>NaR at pH 8.8. H-bonds are shown with black dashed lines. The lengths of the key H-bonds between the RSB and D105 and D105 and E64 are given in Å and shown with bold italic numbers.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS189582-f005"/></fig><fig id="F6" position="float"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><title>N-in and N-out conformations of the NDQ rhodopsins.</title><p>The scheme of the difference in pH dependence of the spectral properties (spectral shift upon acidification in Subgroup 1 is shown with the change of the color from pink to blue), the pentamer stability (the disturbed pentameric assembly at low pH is shown for KR2 schematically by disoriented protomers; partial dissociation of the pentamers into protomers is also indicated by an additional gray arrow), and the conformation between Subgroup 1 and 2 of NDQ rhodopsins (N-in and N-out conformations of the active centers). Green arrows indicate sodium transport across the membrane by NaRs. Red arrow indicates the absence of sodium transport. The detailed view of the RSB regions of KR2 and <italic>Er</italic>NaR in N-in and N-out conformations is given in the bottom panels. Black arrows indicate orientation of Asn residue of the NDQ motif different in N-in and N-out conformations.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS189582-f006"/></fig></floats-group></article>