<!DOCTYPE article
 PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" article-type="preprint"><?all-math-mml yes?><?use-mml?><?origin ukpmcpa?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">bioRxiv</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>bioRxiv : the preprint server for biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub"/></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">EMS190975</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2023.11.10.566569</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="archive">PPR758702</article-id><article-version-alternatives><article-version article-version-type="status">preprint</article-version><article-version article-version-type="number">1</article-version></article-version-alternatives><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The neurocomputational link between defensive cardiac states and approach-avoidance arbitration under threat</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Klaassen</surname><given-names>Felix H.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CR1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>de Voogd</surname><given-names>Lycia D.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hulsman</surname><given-names>Anneloes M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>O’Reilly</surname><given-names>Jill X.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Klumpers</surname><given-names>Floris</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Figner</surname><given-names>Bernd</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Roelofs</surname><given-names>Karin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Radboud University, Donders Institute for Brain, Cognition, and Behaviour, Nijmegen, The Netherlands</aff><aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Radboud University, Behavioural Science Institute (BSI), Nijmegen, The Netherlands</aff><aff id="A3"><label>3</label>Leiden University, Institute of Psychology and Leiden Institute for Brain and Cognition (LIBC), Leiden, The Netherlands</aff><aff id="A4"><label>4</label>Department of Experimental Psychology, University of Oxford, Oxford, United Kingdom</aff><author-notes><corresp id="CR1"><label>*</label>Correspondence: <email>felix.klaassen@donders.ru.nl</email> (F.H.K)</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted"><day>15</day><month>11</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="preprint"><day>13</day><month>11</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><permissions><ali:free_to_read/><license><ali:license_ref>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is licensed under a <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">CC BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p id="P1">Fearful avoidance is a hallmark of anxiety disorders and often comes at a cost. It reduces the probability of threat and of obtaining rewards. Theoretical models predict that threat-induced psychophysiological states, such as freezing-related bradycardia, facilitate arbitration of approach-avoidance decisions. We indeed show that bradycardia states are linked to the neurocomputational underpinnings of approach-avoidance arbitration when facing varying reward and threat magnitudes. Bradycardia was not only linked to <italic>aversive value-related</italic> avoidance decisions but also to <italic>value comparison</italic> (a stronger tendency to approach vs. avoid when expected reward outweighs potential threat). An amygdala-striatal-prefrontal neural circuit supported approach-avoidance arbitration under threat, with specific involvement of the amygdala and dorsal anterior cingulate (dACC) in integrating subjective outcome values and bradycardia states. These findings highlight the role of human freezing states in value-based decision making, relevant for optimal threat coping. They point to a specific role for amygdala/dACC in state-value integration under threat.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec id="S1" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p id="P2">Fearful avoidance often comes at a cost, particularly in approach-avoidance conflict where avoidance may reduce the probability of aversive outcomes but also of obtaining potential rewards. Approach-avoidance conflict situations therefore require weighing of the potential reward and threat outcomes of our decisions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">3</xref></sup>. Effectively arbitrating between approach and avoidance decisions is crucial for generating adaptive behavior across naturalistic environments. This process might go awry in several psychopathological conditions, including anxiety disorders as they are characterized by excessive avoidance behavior<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">4</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref></sup>. While over the past decades the decision sciences and computational psychiatry have made significant progress in modeling those value-based decisions in healthy and patient populations, the role of the threat-induced psychophysiological state of the organism has been largely overlooked<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref></sup>.</p><p id="P3">Freezing is a defensive threat reaction characterized by immobility and heart rate deceleration (bradycardia), resulting from relative dominance of parasympathetic over sympathetic arousal in the autonomic nervous system<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref></sup>. There is ample evidence from postural, cardiac, and neural analyses that humans as well as animals freeze when experiencing threat<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref></sup>. Freezing is facilitated by projections from the central nucleus of the amygdala to the midbrain periaqueductal gray (PAG), which in turn innervates immobility and bradycardia through medullar connections to spinal cord motor neurons and the vagus nerve, respectively<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref></sup>. This freezing state has been shown to facilitate sensory upregulation and risk assessment while minimizing the likelihood of detection under threat<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">20</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">23</xref></sup>. For instance, freezing-related bradycardia has been linked to enhanced perceptual sensitivity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">25</xref></sup>, increased action preparation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27">27</xref></sup>, and value integration during approach-avoidance decision-making<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">28</xref></sup>.</p><p id="P4">Surprisingly little is known about how freezing-related bradycardia states affect computations and neural circuits underlying approach-avoidance arbitration. This knowledge is critical to provide starting points for optimizing interventions aiming at improved decision-making under threat in health and anxiety.</p><p id="P5">We a-priori formulated three potential mechanisms by which freezing states could impact approach-avoidance arbitration under threat<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">29</xref></sup> (see also <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1A</xref>; pre-registration:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.17605/OSF.IO/KYWV8">https://doi.org/10.17605/OSF.IO/KYWV8</ext-link>). First, freezing may be associated with enhanced processing of <italic>aversive value</italic> information from potential threat in the amygdala-PAG circuit. The presence of environmental threat can shift value processing from being driven primarily by fronto-striatal regions (such as the ventromedial prefrontal cortex and (ventral) striatum<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">30</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33">33</xref></sup>), to regions involved in stress coping, salience, and defensive threat reactions such as the amygdala and PAG<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27">27</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34">34</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37">37</xref></sup>, particularly during states of freezing-related bradycardia<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38">38</xref></sup>. Indeed, the amygdala-PAG pathway is not only involved in triggering defensive threat reactions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">22</xref></sup> but has also been implicated in processing aversive value (e.g., predicted pain<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39">39</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40">40</xref></sup>). Accordingly, we predict that stronger bradycardia states are linked to increased salience of aversive value, resulting in increased avoidance.</p><p id="P6">Second, and even more important for adaptive responding under threat, freezing states may be associated with a change in how potential reward and threat are <italic>compared</italic> with each other. If freezing affects approach-avoidance arbitration through assessment of the associated risks<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41">41</xref></sup>, then freezing states may not be linked to the processing of <italic>aversive value</italic> alone, but rather to the value of one outcome in light of the other (e.g., discounting the value of potential reward by the value of the threat). Adapting the relative weight of potential positive vs. negative outcomes might enable more optimal decisions to approach rather than avoid when the potential reward (relative to threat) is deemed sufficiently large<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">28</xref></sup>. Such value integration has previously been suggested to be driven by the dorsal anterior cingulate cortex (dACC)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32">32</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36">36</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42">42</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43">43</xref></sup> and pre-motor areas such as the supplemental motor area (SMA)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R44">44</xref></sup>. We predict that value integration in these regions might be driven by freezing states.</p><p id="P7">Third, freezing may help to prepare the body for action in acutely threatening situations through <italic>action invigoration.</italic> Evidence for this comes from studies linking freezing to increased fear-potentiated startle and faster response times (suggesting action preparation)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R45">45</xref></sup>. Based on previous human work on the switch from freezing into action, we anticipate that action invigoration during freezing is associated with the perigenual region of the ACC (pgACC)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref></sup>.</p><p id="P8">To test these three hypothesed mechanisms of aversive value, value comparison, and action invigoration (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1A</xref>), 58 human participants performed a Passive-active Approach-avoidance Task (PAT)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">28</xref></sup>. In this task people make approach-avoidance decisions in the face of varying reward (1-5 euros) and threat magnitudes (1-5 shocks) in two action contexts (passive or active; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1B</xref>). Simultaneously, we measured heart rate to assess bradycardia (as a freezing state index), and brain responses using blood-oxygen-level-dependent functional magnetic resonance imaging (BOLD fMRI). Using a modeling approach, we tested the link between event-related bradycardia states and each of the hypothesized neurocomputational mechanisms (while accounting for cardiac and respiratory noise<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R46">46</xref></sup>). Specifically, we modelled how approach-avoidance decisions varied as function of bradycardia interactions with the number of shocks (<italic>aversive value</italic>), the money-shock level difference (<italic>value comparison</italic>), and the action context (<italic>action invigoration</italic>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">29</xref></sup>. Neurally, we expected bradycardia interactions with <italic>aversive value</italic> to activate the amygdala and PAG, with <italic>value comparison</italic> to engage the dACC, and with <italic>action invigoration</italic> to involve the pgACC (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1A</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="S3"><title>Bradycardia states are associated with stronger shock-induced avoidance</title><sec id="S4"><title>Approach-avoidance decisions under threat</title><p id="P9">In the PAT, participants were well able to trade off shocks versus money, replicating typical choice and response time patterns<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">28</xref></sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2A</xref>, see Methods equations (1) and (2) for Bayesian mixed-effects model, i.e. BMM, specifications).</p><p id="P10">Regarding choice, higher money and shock levels led to more approach and avoidance, respectively (as pre-registered, statistical effects whose Bayesian 95% and 90% posterior highest density interval ‘HDI’ did not include 0 were interpreted as ‘significant’ and ‘marginally significant’, respectively, see Methods for details; B<sub>money</sub> = 1.54, HDI<sub>95%</sub> = [1.26, 1.83]; B<sub>shocks</sub> = -1.10, HDI<sub>95%</sub> = [-1.35, -0.84]; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2A</xref>). Additionally, shock-induced avoidance was more pronounced for lower money levels, and money-induced approach was less pronounced for lower shock levels (B<sub>money:shocks</sub> = 0.40, HDI<sub>95%</sub> = [0.22, 0.57]). Choice was not affected by the action context (B<sub>actioncontext</sub> = 0.06, HDI<sub>90%</sub> = [-0.04, 0.17]), but the action context did interact with the money and shock levels. Specifically, the approach-effect of money was stronger in active compared to passive action contexts, indicating action invigoration as a function of reward (B<sub>money:actioncontext</sub> = -0.27, HDI<sub>95%</sub> = [-0.40, -0.16]). Conversely, the avoidance-effect of shocks was stronger in passive compared to active action contexts, indicating more passive responses (i.e., action inhibition) as a function of threat (though only marginally so; B<sub>shocks:actioncontext</sub> = 0.09, HDI<sub>90%</sub> = [0.008, 0.17]).</p><p id="P11">Differences between approach vs. avoidance decisions were also reflected in the response times. Participants responded faster for avoid compared to approach choices (B<sub>choice</sub> = -0.04, HDI<sub>95%</sub> = [-0.07, -0.02]; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2C</xref>), and this response time difference depended on the reward and threat magnitudes: Higher money levels led to faster approach compared to avoid responses (B<sub>money:choice</sub> = 0.04, HDI<sub>95%</sub> = [0.02, 0.05), while higher shock levels led to slower approach compared to avoid responses (B<sub>shocks:choice</sub> = -0.04, HDI<sub>95%</sub> = [-0.06, -0.02]).</p><p id="P12">In sum, we observed (as previously<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">28</xref></sup>) a balanced trade-off between reward and threat, and interactions of reward and threat magnitudes with action and response times.</p></sec><sec id="S5"><title>Behavioral interactions with bradycardia states</title><p id="P13">Next, we assessed to what extent our experimental paradigm induced the desired cardiac effects, and whether these heart rate dynamics interacted with participants’ task behavior.</p><p id="P14">A significant reduction in heart rate during the anticipation screen relative to the pre-trial baseline indicated the expected freezing-like bradycardia state (B<sub>intercept</sub> = -1.77, HDI<sub>95%</sub> = [-2.12, -1.42]). This bradycardia response was not affected by varying money levels (B<sub>money</sub> = 0.10, HDI<sub>90%</sub> = [-0.004, 0.20]), shock levels (B<sub>shocks</sub> = -0.02, HDI<sub>90%</sub> = [-0.12, 0.07]), the action context (B<sub>actioncontext</sub> = 0.04, HDI<sub>90%</sub> = [-0.06, 0.15]), nor their interactions (BMM on Δ<italic>hr</italic> <bold>Methods</bold> <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD3">equation (3)</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2B</xref>).</p><p id="P15">Moreover, stronger bradycardia <italic>was</italic> related to an increased effect of shock level on avoidance (B<sub>shocks:heartrate</sub> = 0.08, HDI<sub>95%</sub> = [0.001, 0.17]). Specifically, in trials with more bradycardia, more shocks led to increasingly more avoidance. There were no significant interactions of bradycardia with any other experimental conditions, including money or the money-by-shocks interaction.</p><p id="P16">Finally, stronger bradycardia was associated with faster response times (BMM on RTs, <bold>Methods</bold> <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD5">equation (5)</xref>; B<sub>heartrate</sub> = 0.03, HDI<sub>95%</sub> = [0.007, 0.05]; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2C</xref>).</p><p id="P17">Together, these results show that bradycardia states were related not only to general task involvement, but also approach-avoidance decisions and faster responding.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="S6"><title>Distinct neural networks underlying anticipation of reward and threat magnitudes versus approach-avoidance decisions</title><sec id="S7"><title>Tracking of reward and threat magnitudes during anticipation</title><p id="P18">Before detailing the modeling effects we investigated the task-based neural correlates of reward and threat anticipation, by performing a parametric modulation of the fMRI signal as a function of the money and shock levels (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3A</xref>). For reward, as expected, higher money levels were positively correlated with increased BOLD activity in the ventral striatum (left: p = .003, right: <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001; peak-voxel family-wise error small-volume corrected, i.e., FWE-SVC). We also expected a reward effect in the vmPFC, but we did not observe a significant association (<italic>p</italic> = .059 peak-voxel FWE-SVC within an anatomical vmPFC mask, see <bold>Methods</bold>). Money levels were negatively correlated with BOLD in the right lateral orbitofrontal cortex (<italic>p</italic> = .024 cluster-level FWE-corrected). Regarding threat, shock levels were as expected positively correlated with BOLD activity in regions part of the salience network such as SMA/dACC and anterior insula, and regions part of the executive control network such as the dlPFC and precuneus (all <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001 cluster-level FWE-corrected). This contrast did not show the expected effects of the shock levels in subcortical regions such as the amygdala; this was only the case when contrasting approach vs. avoid trials, i.e. when the probability of receiving a shock is relatively high (see below). Finally, shocks were negatively correlated with BOLD in the vmPFC (<italic>p</italic> &lt; .001 cluster-level FWE-corrected; for all statistics, see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table S1</xref>). Together, these results show that cortico-striatal regions traditionally implicated in reward and threat confrontation (e.g., reception of money vs. shocks) also parametrically track the processing of these potential outcomes during anticipation.</p></sec><sec id="S8"><title>Circuits underlying approach-avoidance decisions</title><p id="P19">Approach (compared to avoid) trials showed increased activation in regions implicated in both appetitive and aversive processing, such as the ventral striatum (left and right: <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001 peak-voxel FWE-SVC) as well as the amygdala (left: <italic>p</italic> = .005, right: <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001; peak-voxel FWE-SVC). Additionally, regions previously implicated in (approach-avoidance) decision-making such as the vmPFC and the right hippocampus showed stronger BOLD responses during approach (both <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001 cluster-level FWE-corrected). The inverse contrast – showing stronger activation for avoid vs. approach trials – revealed activity in regions consistent with the frontal-parietal network: the right precuneus and superior frontal gyrus (precuneus: <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001, sup. front. gyr.: <italic>p</italic> = .007; cluster-level FWE-corrected; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3B</xref>;see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table S2</xref> for all statistics). Finally, neural patterns were similar for active vs. passive approach-avoidance decisions (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Information</xref>).</p><p id="P20">To verify relevance of these neural findings for decision-making, we performed a follow-up hemodynamic response function (HRF)-agnostic time-series analysis of BOLD response patterns (i.e., a finite impulse impulse response analysis). This control analysis indicated that the neural approach-avoidance effects in our main regions (ventral striatum, amygdala, and vmPFC) were only related to the choice and not the subsequent response (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Figure S1</xref>).</p><p id="P21">Collectively, our task-based neural results outline an approach-avoidance circuit consistent with previous work, and show distinct networks underlying approach-avoidance arbitration and anticipatory processing of reward/threat magnitudes, with only partial overlap.</p></sec></sec><sec id="S9"><title>Neural circuits underlying the link between bradycardia states and approach-avoidance decisions</title><sec id="S10"><title>Support for aversive value and value comparison models</title><p id="P22">After having verified the task-based effects, we addressed our main experimental question regarding the link between bradycardia states and the computations underlying approach-avoidance arbitration (i.e., <italic>aversive value, value comparison,</italic> and <italic>action invigoration</italic>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1A</xref>), using computational modeling and model-based fMRI analysis.</p><p id="P23">We created three separate models (further referred to as freezing models) capturing the effects of <italic>aversive value</italic> (AV), <italic>value comparison</italic> (VC) and <italic>action invigoration</italic> (AI) on trial-by-trial approach-avoidance choices, and contrasted them against a base model (following previous work<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R47">47</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R49">49</xref></sup>). The AV model included an interaction term between bradycardia and the number of shocks (i.e., <italic>β<sub>s:hr</sub></italic>). The VC model included an interaction between bradycardia and money-shock difference <italic>Δms,</italic> which we mathematically defined as the difference between the money and shock levels on offer (i.e., <italic>β<sub>ms:hr</sub></italic>, and △<italic>ms</italic> = <italic>money – shocks</italic>). Lastly, the AI model featured an interaction term between bradycardia and the action context, which estimates participants’ probability of giving an active (vs. passive) response (i.e., <italic>β<sub>ac:hr</sub></italic>). Details on the modeling specifications are included in the <bold>Methods</bold> (see also <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>).</p><p id="P24">We assessed whether the freezing models captured the observed patterns in the choice data (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>, upper panels show aggregated raw choice proportions, lower panels show model-predicted choice probabilities which were generated from model-estimated decision values ‘DVs’, where DVs &lt; 0 correspond to <italic>p</italic>(approach) &lt; .5, and DVs &gt; 0 correspond to <italic>p</italic>(approach) &gt; .5; note that low vs. high Δ<italic>hr</italic> values indicate trials with stronger vs. weaker bradycardia, respectively). Note that some of the bradycardia effects in the freezing models (i.e., <italic>β<sub>s:hr</sub></italic> and <italic>β<sub>ac:hr</sub></italic>) were also tested above in a single task-effect BMM (see <italic>behavioral interactions with bradycardia states</italic> section). Here, these interactions are entered in separate models to allow us to isolate their unique contribution to the neural data (see below).</p><p id="P25">First, the <italic>aversive value</italic> model confirmed the relationship between bradycardia and shocks (also tested in the BMM above; <italic>β<sub>s:hr</sub></italic> = 0.07, HDI<sub>90%</sub> = [0.01, 0.14], <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4A</xref>). For the <italic>value comparison</italic> model, we now found a significant interaction between bradycardia and Δ<italic>ms</italic> (<italic>βms:hr</italic> = -0.09, HDI<sub>95%</sub> = [-0.18, -0.01]), revealing a more pronounced effect of money-shock level differences on choice in trials with stronger compared to weaker bradycardia (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4B</xref>). Interestingly, this interaction seems particularly driven by a higher approach rate in trials with high money (relative to shock) levels (i.e., high Δ<italic>ms</italic> values), and strong bradycardia. In all other conditions (i.e., Δ<italic>ms</italic>values below 2), bradycardia was mostly associated with more avoidance (regardless of the Δ<italic>ms</italic> value). On trials where expected reward strongly outweighs the threat magnitude, bradycardia was associated with increased, rather than decreased approach. Whereas on trials with comparable reward-threat magnitudes, or trials where the threat magnitude outweighs the expected reward, stronger bradycardia is associated with more avoidance. Finally, in the <italic>action invigoration</italic> model there was no relationship between bradycardia and the action context (also tested in the BMM above; <italic>β<sub>ac:hr</sub></italic> = 0. 05; HDI<sub>90%</sub> = [-0.01, 0.11], <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4C</xref>). Overall, the freezing models captured the observed behavioral patterns well (quantitative model comparison indicated that all models fit the data roughly equally well, with the <italic>aversive value</italic> model slightly outperforming the other models, including the base model; see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Information, Table S3</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S11"><title>Model-based and task-based fMRI analyses reveal highly similar neural circuits</title><p id="P26">Then, for our model-based fMRI analysis approach, we first investigated to what extent the predicted approach-avoidance choices by the base model generated similar neural circuits of BOLD activation as the observed approach-avoidance choices (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5A</xref>). Here we found indeed a highly similar pattern of regions for the model-based analysis: a positive correlation between higher decision values (i.e., higher predicted probability to approach) and BOLD activity in the ventral striatum (left: <italic>p</italic> = .001, right: <italic>p</italic> = .009 peak-voxel FWE-SVC), right amygdala (<italic>p</italic> = .019 peak-voxel FWE-SVC), and vmPFC (<italic>p</italic> &lt; .001, cluster-level FWE), and a negative correlation (i.e., higher predicted probability to avoid) with BOLD in the right precuneus and superior frontal gyrus (precuneus: <italic>p</italic> = .001, sup. front.: <italic>p</italic> = .008, cluster-level FWE; see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table S4</xref> for all significant clusters). This supports the base model as being a solid foundation to investigate the neural correlates of the subsequent freezing models each incorporating the distinct bradycardia-state mechanisms.</p></sec><sec id="S12"><title>Amygdala and dACC involvement in bradycardia-state interactions with aversive value and value comparison</title><p id="P27">Next, to test our core neural hypotheses, we investigated the unique contribution of the freezing models to the observed BOLD-fMRI signal, as compared to the base model (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>). For each of the three freezing models, we computed a regressor containing <italic>difference scores</italic> that quantify to what extent that model predicts different decision values as compared to the base model (i.e.,<italic>DVdiff<sub>freezemod</sub></italic> = DV<sub>Base</sub> – DV<sub>freezemod</sub>).For a given freezing model, positive difference scores (i.e., <italic>DVdiff<sub>freezemod</sub></italic> &gt; 0) indicate that it predicts a higher probability of avoidance in that trial, and negative difference scores (i.e., <italic>DVdiff<sub>freezemod</sub></italic>&lt; 0) indicate it predicts a higher probability of an approach choice (relative to the base model, see <bold>Methods</bold>). Note that these prediction differences between the freezing models and the base model are driven by the distinct bradycardia-state interaction terms, since all models were otherwise parameterized identically. The <italic>DV<sub>Base</sub></italic> and three <italic>DVdiff</italic> vectors were then together entered as parametric modulators of the BOLD signal during the anticipation screen. All parametric modulators were orthogonalized relative to the unmodulated (i.e., anticipation screen) regressor, such that each regressor captures its unique BOLD-signal variance (i.e., shared variance between two regressors will be attributed to the error term<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R50">50</xref></sup>).</p><p id="P28">For <italic>aversive value</italic> (AV), we observed a negative correlation between its difference scores and BOLD activity in the amygdala (as expected; right: <italic>p</italic> = .022 peak-voxel FWE-SVC), but unexpectedly not in the PAG (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5B</xref>; for whole-brain results see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table S4</xref>). This suggested that as the difference in choice predictions between the AV and base model increased (i.e., as <italic>DVdiff<sub>AV</sub></italic> becomes more positive), BOLD activity in the amygdala decreased. However, it remained unclear whether this was a general relationship (along the whole range of positive and negative trial-wise <italic>DVdiff<sub>AV</sub></italic> values), or whether this relationship was specific to certain trial conditions. To further investigate this, we performed a follow-up analysis in which we split the AV difference regressor in two: one for trials in which the model predicted a higher probability of avoidance compared to the base model (<italic>DVdiff<sub>AV</sub></italic> &gt; 0), and one for trials in which it predicted a higher probability of an approach choice compared to the base model D(<italic>Vdiff<sub>AV</sub></italic>&lt; 0). This revealed that only in the trials in which AV predicted more avoidance compared to the base model (i.e., <italic>DVdiff<sub>AV</sub></italic> &gt; 0), there was a negative relationship (i.e., stronger prediction of avoidance) with BOLD in the amygdala (right: <italic>p</italic> = .014, <italic>p</italic> = .018, <italic>p</italic> = .027, left: <italic>p</italic> = .045; all peak-voxel FWE-SVC; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5B</xref>). This suggests that the relative decrease of amygdala activity is specific to the interaction effect of shocks and bradycardia on avoidance captured by the AV model (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4A</xref>).</p><p id="P29">For <italic>value comparison</italic> (VC), we observed a large positive whole brain significant cluster in the dorsomedial prefrontal cortex (dmPFC) spanning the (pre) supplemental motor area (SMA) and – as we predicted – the dACC (<italic>p</italic> &lt; .001 cluster-level FWE; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5C</xref>). Follow-up analysis revealed that this effect was only significant in conditions in which the VC model predicted a higher probability to approach compared to the base model, which corresponds to trials with <italic>Δms</italic> ≥ 2 (<italic>p</italic> &lt; .001 peak-voxel FWE for dACC ROI, <italic>p</italic> = .004 cluster-level FWE-corrected for whole brain; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5C</xref>, bottom; see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table S4</xref> for all statistics). Together, these results suggest that the bradycardia-related increase in approach choices for highly positive money-shock differences (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4B</xref>) is inversely related to BOLD activity in the dACC/SMA area (note that more <italic>negative DVdiff<sub>VC</sub></italic> values indicate <italic>higher</italic> differential predicted approach probabilities, see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5C</xref>). These findings might point to a reduction in conflict-related processing when the money-shock difference is relatively high, since approach-avoidance conflict is highest when money and shock levels are similar, and lowest when they are maximally dissimilar (e.g., the average approach rate is 48% when Δ<italic>ms</italic> = -1, and 13% / 93% when Δ<italic>ms</italic> = -4 / 4). Finally, for <italic>action invigoration</italic> (AI), we did not observe any significant associations in our region of interest (i.e., pgACC), nor across the rest of the brain.</p></sec></sec><sec id="S13" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p id="P30">This study highlights the role of the psychophysiological state of freezing in approach-avoidance arbitration under threat, establishing a neurocomputational link between bradycardia states and approach-avoidance decisions. Participants made passive and active approach-avoidance decisions in the face of varying reward and threat magnitudes, showing increased approach for higher money levels and increased avoidance for higher shock levels. Moreover, bradycardia states during anticipation indicated that participants were in a psychophysiological state of freezing. Neurally, approach-avoidance arbitration was associated with BOLD-response patterns in the amygdala, ventral striatum, and vmPFC (in line with previous reports<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">30</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32">32</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36">36</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42">42</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R51">51</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R52">52</xref></sup>).</p><p id="P31">Additionally, we found that trial-by-trial bradycardia states were linked to value-based computations underlying approach-avoidance arbitration. First, bradycardia states were associated with a stronger effect of threat of shock (i.e., aversive value) on avoidance decisions, which was negatively associated with BOLD activity in amygdala. Secondly, bradycardia states were linked to a stronger tendency to approach rather than avoid when the expected reward outweighs the threat (i.e., value comparison), an effect associated with the dACC and SMA. Together, we delineate a neural circuit involved in approach-avoidance arbitration under threat, with specific involvement of the amygdala and dACC in integrating subjective outcome values and defensive psychophysiological states during approach-avoidance decisions. These results stress the relevance of the organism’s psychophysiological state in approach-avoidance arbitration under threat, fitting with recent empirical and theoretical work<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">29</xref></sup>. Together, we highlight the role of human freezing states in value-based decision processes relevant for optimal threat coping.</p><p id="P32">Bradycardia states are linked to distinct value-based computations underlying approach-avoidance arbitration, with distinct neural signatures. Specifically, using model-based fMRI analysis, we found that the relation of bradycardia states with <italic>aversive value</italic> involves the amygdala, and that the link with <italic>value comparison</italic> (i.e., reward-threat magnitude differences) involves the dACC/SMA.</p><p id="P33">First, the finding that bradycardia was linked to increased shock-induced avoidance, indicates that on trials with stronger bradycardia higher shock levels led to more avoidance compared to trials with less bradycardia. This finding points to increased sensitivity for <italic>aversive value</italic> during bradycardia states, resulting in a stronger tendency to avoid. Although the relation with BOLD activity in the amygdala was expected, the direction of the correlation was negative, rather than positive. Perhaps amygdala deactivation during bradycardia states might signal an increase in attentional processing under threat, which is then accompanied by increased sensitivity to aversive value. Previously, downregulation of the default mode network (DMN) during cognitively-demanding tasks has been shown to be accompanied by amygdala inhibition<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R53">53</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R54">54</xref></sup>. Such amygdala deactivation has also been observed in conditions under threat<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R55">55</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R56">56</xref></sup>. Similarly, such an increase in attentional processing under threat might explain why sensory upregulation occurs during bradycardia states<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38">38</xref></sup>. Alternatively, the negative relationship with amygdala activity might reflect a decrease in outcome-related risk anticipation, a safety signal, or sense of relief after choosing to avoid<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R57">57</xref></sup>. Indeed, a potential role of the amygdala in value-based decision-making might be to process the potential negative consequences of the decision, such as anticipation of risk and potential negative outcomes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41">41</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R58">58</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R60">60</xref></sup>. As such, the reduction in amygdala activity might reflect a consequence of the decision (to avoid) rather than a mechanism underlying the decision itself. Unfortunately, the temporal specificity of the fMRI signal does not allow us to separate these two possible explanations. However, our FIR time-series analysis of the BOLD response in the amygdala showed that choice effects already occured early during the anticipation window (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Information</xref>), hinting at early involvement of the amygdala in the approach-avoidance decision process. Future studies using neuroimaging methods with higher temporal precision, such as magnetoencephalography (MEG), might provide more insight into the role of the amygdala and associated neural circuits in value-based decision-making under threat <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R61">61</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R63">63</xref></sup>. Overall, these findings provide further support for an important role of the amygdala in approach-avoidance arbitration in rodents and humans<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R64">64</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R65">65</xref></sup>, but also reveal that threat states may underlie this decision-making process.</p><p id="P34">Secondly, bradycardia states were linked to <italic>value comparison</italic> of potential reward and threat, reflected by a more pronounced impact of the reward-threat magnitude difference on choice. Namely, trial-by-trial bradycardia was associated with more avoidance when the expected reward was equal to or less than the threat, while bradycardia was linked to more approach when the expected reward outweighed the threat. This behavioral observation is in support of the notion that bradycardia states are not only related to value processing in the aversive domain (i.e., defensive responses) but also the appetitive domain (i.e., approach behavior<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R66">66</xref></sup>). Whereas previously such association between computations of subjective outcome value and bradycardia states was found across participants<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">28</xref></sup>, we now show this on a trial-by-trial level. This finding provides empirical support for recent theoretical work on the presumed role of the psychophysiological state of freezing in optimizing decision-making under threat<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref></sup>,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">29</xref></sup>, namely to approach when the expected reward outweighs threat, so as not to miss out on potential opportunities.</p><p id="P35">The relationship between bradycardia states and value comparison was associated with BOLD-activity changes in the dACC/SMA. Specifically, trials with stronger bradycardia and with high reward (relative to threat) magnitudes were associated with less dACC/SMA BOLD activity. This might reflect a change in conflict-related processing. This interpretation would be in line with other evidence indicating a role for the dACC in conflict resolution<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">30</xref></sup>,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32">32</xref></sup>,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42">42</xref></sup>,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R67">67</xref></sup>. Indeed, in our paradigm conflict is relatively high when the reward and threat magnitudes are similar, while conflict is relatively low when the expected reward outweighs threat. Additionally, recent work has demonstrated a central role of the dmPFC (specifically the dACC and preSMA) in encoding value-based decision variables, such as the expected value<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43">43</xref></sup>,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R44">44</xref></sup>. The fact that we find that similar regions are involved in the interaction between value comparison and bradycardia states, suggests that threat states are linked to the neurocomputational basis of value-based decisions in general, and not just approach-avoidance decisions specifically. Finally, while previous work has linked parasympathetic activity to the vmPFC and sympathetic activity to the dACC<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R68">68</xref></sup>, we now show that parasympathetic effects (i.e., bradycardia) might also affect processes in other more dorsal prefrontal areas, such as the dACC/SMA. Together, these findings illustrate the frontal cortical circuitry supporting bradycardia-state interactions with the value computations underlying approach-avoidance arbitration.</p><p id="P36">Finally, we found no evidence for a relation between bradycardia states and <italic>action invigoration</italic> in terms of active versus passive decision-making. There was no behavioral interaction between bradycardia and action context, and accordingly there were no significant correlates at the neural level. This means that, within our paradigm, bradycardia states might not play a role in the decision to take an action. However, we did find a trial-by-trial relationship between bradycardia and faster response times<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">26</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R69">69</xref></sup>. This might suggest that bradycardia states only play a role in actions through increased speed of action once the organism has decided to act.</p><p id="P37">One open question pertains to the causal chain of effects regarding the link between freezing states and value-based computations underlying approach-avoidance. For example, freezing states might not causally contribute to these changes in value computations but rather be an epiphenomenon of task engagement. If that were the case, one would expect bradycardia to be correlated with general task effects, such as arousal and effort. However, while threat and reward typically both induce arousal (e.g., through increased skin conductance responses), bradycardia is particularly observed as a function of threat and not reward magnitudes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R70">70</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R71">71</xref></sup>, ruling out a general effect of arousal. Additionally, bradycardia states are commonly associated with faster response times, which is typically indicative of easier rather than more effortful decisions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R72">72</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R73">73</xref></sup>. How should we then interpret the relation between bradycardia states and value computations? We speculate that freezing states may be more than an epiphenomenon, and that they serve a role in integrating the value of external stimuli. This interpretation would be in line with findings that heart rate reductions and slow breathing rates during freezing serve sensory processing, for example through increased neural signal-to-noise<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R74">74</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R75">75</xref></sup>. This sensory upregulation might subsequentially facilitate neural processing in downstream brain circuits involved in value assignment. Nevertheless, causal manipulations, such as deep brain stimulation of regions critically involved in freezing states (like the periaqueductal gray<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R76">76</xref></sup>), are needed to directly test this hypothesis.</p><p id="P38">Our findings may have implications for people suffering from internalizing symptoms, including anxiety and depression, who display excessive and costly avoidance<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R51">51</xref></sup>. Indeed, altered freezing has been associated with psychopathology<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R77">77</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R79">79</xref></sup>. For example, infants who displayed little to no freezing at all early in life were at high risk to develop internalizing symptoms up until late adolescence<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R80">80</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R81">81</xref></sup>. We provide a formal framework that could be used to test transdiagnostically what might drive maladaptive avoidance patterns<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R82">82</xref></sup>. For example, it would be important to test whether avoidance in anxiety and depression are related to altered freezing patterns and if this is driven by changes in the computation of threat value, and reward-threat comparison.</p><p id="P39">In conclusion, this work illustrates how the psychophysiological state of bradycardia is linked to the neurocomputational underpinnings of approach-avoidance arbitration under threat. Our findings suggest that during bradycardia states the amygdala is involved in increased sensitivity to aversive value (reflected by increased shock-induced avoidance), while the dACC/SMA is involved in the comparison of appetitive vs. aversive value. The results thus demonstrate a potential role for psychophysiological states in shaping value-based decision-making under threat. Altogether, our findings support recent theorizing on an active role of human freezing states in optimizing decision-making under threat<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref></sup>, and may contribute to a better understanding of how defensive threat reactions may affect cognitive and affective processes.</p></sec><sec id="S14" sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><p id="P40">This study was preregistered before data analysis on the Open Science Framework (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.17605/OSF.IO/KYWV8">https://doi.org/10.17605/OSF.IO/KYWV8</ext-link>). All research activities were carried out in accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki, approved by the local ethics committee (Ethical Reviewing Board CMO/METC [Institutional Research Review Board] Arnhem-Nijmegen, CMO 2014/288), and conducted according to these guidelines and regulations.</p><sec id="S15" sec-type="subjects"><title>Participants</title><p id="P41">Sixty-seven healthy volunteers completed the study. After data collection, 9 participants were excluded from data analysis due to an imaging artifact (n=3), too little variance in choice behavior (n=3), unusable heart rate data (n=2), or falling asleep during the experiment (n=1), leading to a sample size of 58 participants (aged 18 - 34, [M±SD = 24.17±3.43], 41 females). Inclusion criteria were age (between 16 and 35 years), Dutch or English speaking, and right-handedness; exclusion criteria were MR incompatibility, self-reported current pregnancy, current or lifetime history of psychiatric, neurological, or cardiovascular disorder, endocrine illness or treatment, claustrophobia, epilepsy, and self-reported high or low blood pressure. All participants gave written informed consent before participation, and were paid for participation (€24) plus bonus money contingent on their task choices (max €15, see <italic>PAT</italic> section below).</p></sec><sec id="S16"><title>Experimental design and procedure</title><p id="P42">Participants came to the lab for a single session of 150 minutes. Upon arrival, they read and signed the screening and informed consent forms. Participants then read through onscreen task instructions and performed 8 practice trials of the Passive-active Approach-avoidance Task (PAT; see below) in a behavioral cubicle. All participants performed the same set of practice trials. Afterwards, the researcher made sure participants fully understood the task, specifically regarding how to approach/avoid, and the relation between approach-avoidance and the probability of receiving one of the outcomes. Next, participants were escorted to the MRI lab, attached to the measurement and stimulation electrodes, given the shock-workup procedure (see <italic>Peripheral measurements and stimulation),</italic> and put inside the scanner. In the scanner, we acquired BOLD fMRI images while participants performed the PAT in three runs of 62 trials each (186 in total). Each run consisted of one repetition of all money (5), shock (5), and action context (2) combinations with long anticipation screen durations (i.e., ≥ 6 s; 50 trials in total), and 12 trials with short anticipation screen durations (pseudorandomized money/shock/action context parameters). See <italic>PAT</italic> section below for details. A field map was acquired between run 1 and 2, and an anatomical image was acquired after the 3<sup>rd</sup> run. After the last scan, participants had to subjectively rate the intensity of one final electrical shock (ranging 1 [not painful at all] to 5 [very painful]), after which they filled in three questionnaires on a computer outside of the scanner: the Beck Depression Inventory (<italic>M±SD</italic> = 6.08±5.98; <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R83">83</xref></sup>) and the Trait questionnaire of the STAI (<italic>M±SD</italic> = 37.27±10.17; <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R84">84</xref></sup>) to characterize our sample, as well as a short debriefing form.</p></sec><sec id="S17"><title>Passive-active Approach-avoidance Task (PAT)</title><p id="P43">Participants performed the PAT<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">28</xref></sup>. In this computer task, participants were instructed to make approach–avoidance decisions in response to a moving target that was associated with receiving varying amounts of monetary rewards (1-5 euro) and numbers of shocks (1-5 stimulations). Additionally, depending on the action context, they could approach or avoid either actively or passively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1B</xref>).</p><p id="P44">In each trial, after an intertrial interval of 9-11 s, the participant was first shown the anticipation screen detailing the money and shock levels (ranging 1-5 each, with 5*5 = 25 possible combinations), the target (a gray circle in the center), and the player icon (a white square in the bottom). This information remained onscreen for a variable anticipation-to-movement screen interval (AMI) of 500-7000 ms. Because of the slow temporal development of the heart rate signal, we only included trials with long (i.e., 6000-7000 ms) AMI’s in our analyses (80% of trials per participant). The short (i.e., 500-5500 ms) AMI trials were in the PAT to ensure continued activation of the participant<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R69">69</xref></sup>. After the AMI, the target started to move either towards (i.e., downwards) or away from the player icon (i.e., left or right, pseudorandomized across trials). During the target movement window (700 ms), the participant could either approach the target by positioning the player icon at the same location as the target, or avoid the target by positioning the player icon at the other location. Specifically, if the target moved downwards (passive action context) the participant could either passively approach (by withholding a response) or actively avoid (by pressing a button). If the target moved left/right (active action context), the participant could either actively approach (by pressing a button) or passively avoid (by withholding). Depending on the approach/avoidance choice, this led probabilistically to either money, shocks, or no outcome. Specifically, if the participant approached, there was a high probability of receiving either the specified money amount (40%) or number of shocks (40%), and a low probability of no outcome (20%). Inversely, if the participant avoided, there was a high probability of receiving no outcome (80%) and a low probability of receiving the money (10%) or shocks (10%). The selected outcome was presented during the outcome screen (1.5 s) by color coding of the target stimulus (i.e., green for money, yellow for shocks, gray for no outcome), and shocks were paid out immediately during that color change. The summed monetary outcome of three randomly selected trials (max. €15) was paid out as a bonus fee. The task was programmed in MATLAB <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R85">85</xref></sup> using the Psychtoolbox extension <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R86">86</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="S18"><title>Psychophysiological measurements</title><p id="P45">To measure heart rate, a pulse oximeter was affixed to the first (i.e., index) finger of the left hand. To measure skin conductance, two standard Ag/AgCl electrodes were applied to the distal phalanges of the third and fourth (i.e., ring and pinky) fingers of the left hand. Respiration was measured using a respiration belt placed around the participant’s abdomen. These were all recorded through a BrainAmp MR amplifier at a sampling rate of 1000 Hz in BrainVision Recorder (Brain Products GmbH). An EyeLink 1000 eye-tracker system (SR Research, Kanata, Ontario, Canada) was used to measure pupil diameter (sampling rate of 1000 Hz). Skin conductance and pupil/eye data were not analyzed for this study.</p></sec><sec id="S19"><title>Electrical stimulation</title><p id="P46">Electrical shocks were delivered through two Ag/AgCl electrodes attached to the distal phalanges of the third and fourth fingers of the right hand using a MAXTENS 2000 (Bio-Protech) machine. Shock durations were 200 ms, and the intensity varied in 10 steps, ranging from 0 – 40 V/0 – 80 mA. During a standardized shock calibration procedure, each participant received and subjectively rated exactly five shocks, allowing the shock intensity to converge to a level that was experienced as uncomfortable, but not painful <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">28</xref></sup>,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R87">87</xref></sup>. The average final shock intensity across shock subjects was 4.48±1.72 steps (range 1-10).</p></sec><sec id="S20"><title>Trial-wise preprocessing and exclusions</title><p id="P47">As pre-registered, we only included trials with long anticipation-to-movement screen intervals in our analyses (i.e., 150 trials per participant). For 8 (out of 58) subjects we only had usable data of 2 out of 3 runs (i.e., 100 trials), due to a lack of observations in our cells of interest for fMRI analysis (i.e., passive and active approach-avoidance choices). For consistency, we used the same data set across all analyses. Additionally, we excluded trials with poor heart rate data, or response times below 200 ms (i.e., excluding a further 304 trials (±3.7%) from the data set). For all analyses involving response times, only trials with active responses (i.e., button-presses) were used (±48.7% of the data set).</p></sec><sec id="S21"><title>Physiological preprocessing</title><p id="P48">Raw pulse and respiratory data were preprocessed using in-house software for removal of radio frequency artifacts and interactive visual artifact correction and peak detection (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/can-lab/brainampconverter">https://github.com/can-lab/brainampconverter</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/can-lab/hera">https://github.com/can-lab/hera</ext-link>). Cardiac inter beat intervals (IBI’s) of the peaks were converted to beats-per-minute (BPM = 60 / IBI) and baseline corrected with respect to the average heart rate (BPM) during the 1 second baseline window prior to the trial onset (i.e., tbaseline = [-1, 0]). As preregistered, the trial-by-trial quantification of bradycardia states (Δ<italic>hr</italic>) was computed by taking the average baseline-corrected heart rate across a 5 – 7 s time window (such that increasingly negative values reflect heart rate deceleration or bradycardia, compared to baseline). Finally, respiratory data were used for physiological noise correction of the BOLD-fMRI signal (see <italic>physiological noise correction</italic> below).</p></sec><sec id="S22"><title>MRI data acquisition</title><p id="P49">MRI scans were acquired using a 3T MAGNETOM PrismaFit MR scanner (Siemens AG, Healthcare Sector, Erlangen, Germany), using a 32 channel head coil. T2*-weighted BOLD-fMRI was acquired using a multiband sequence (68 axial slices, TR = 1500 ms, TE = 28 ms, flip angle = 75°, multiband acceleration factor = 4, interleaved slice acquisition, slice thickness = 2 mm, voxel size = 2 mm isotropic, phase encoding direction = A&gt;&gt;P, bandwith = 2290 Hz/Px, echo spacing = 0.54 ms, phase partial fourier = 7/8, FOV = 210 x 210). Additionally, a field map was acquired to correct for distortions due to structural magnetic field inhomogeneities (68 slices, TR = 435 ms, TE1 = 2.20 ms, TE2 = 4.66 ms, flip angle = 60°). Finally, one anatomical image per participant (1 mm isotropic) was acquired using a single-shot T1-weighted magnetization-prepared rapid gradient-echo sequence (MP-RAGE; acceleration factor of 2 [GRAPPA method], TR = 2300 ms, TE = 3.03 ms, flip angle = 8°, 192 sagittal slices, FOV = 256 x 256 x 192 mm).</p></sec><sec id="S23"><title>MRI data processing</title><p id="P50"><italic>Preprocessing.</italic> All raw MRI images were converted to nifti format and then preprocessed in SPM12 (Statistical Parametric Mapping; Wellcome Trust Centre for Neuroimaging, London, UK). Functional images were realigned and unwarped using the field-map based voxel displacement map, coregistered to the anatomical image using maximization-based rigid-body registration, normalized to MNI152 space (Montreal Neurological Institute), and spatially smoothed with a Gaussian kernel of 5 mm full width at half maximum. Six rigid-body realignment parameters were added to the GLMs analyses as nuisance regressors.</p><p id="P51"><italic>Physiological noise correction.</italic> To correct for cardiac and respiratory noise in the BOLD signal, we applied the same procedure as described by de Voogd et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R87">87</xref></sup>. The preprocessed pulse and respiration measures were used for retrospective image-based correction (RETROICOR) of physiological noise artifacts in BOLD-fMRI data<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R46">46</xref></sup>. Raw pulse and respiratory data were used to specify fifth-order Fourier models of the cardiac and respiratory phase-related modulation of the BOLD signal<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R88">88</xref></sup>, yielding 10 nuisance regressors for cardiac noise and 10 for respiratory noise. Additional regressors were calculated for heart rate frequency, heart rate variability, (raw) abdominal circumference, respiratory frequency, respiratory amplitude, and respiration volume per unit time<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R89">89</xref></sup>, yielding a total of 26 RETROICOR regressors (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/can-lab/RETROICORplus">https://github.com/can-lab/RETROICORplus</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec id="S24"><title>Data analysis</title><p id="P52"><italic>General.</italic> Throughout behavioral and computational analyses, we used Bayesian mixed-effects (also ‘hierarchical’ or ‘multi-level’) models to estimate group-level (i.e., fixed) effects while controlling for participant-level (i.e., random) differences in intercepts and slopes. All models were fitted using the {brms} and {rstan} packages in R (with Rstudio<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R90">90</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R94">94</xref></sup>) using 6000 samples (3000 warmup) across 4 chains, and all converged to a solution without warnings or errors (i.e., all R-hat values between 0.99 and 1.01). All models with binary dependent variables (e.g., approach/avoid choices or passive/active responses) were modelled using Bernoulli distributions (logit link), response time variables with shifted log-normal distributions (identity link), and all others with gaussian distributions. All models followed a ‘maximal’ random-effects structure (i.e., by-participant random intercepts, by-participant random slopes for all within-subjects effects, and all pairwise correlations between random intercepts and slopes)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R95">95</xref></sup>. Finally, for all models we used the default (i.e., weakly regularizing) {brms} priors, which are improper flat priors for group-level effects, weakly informative Student-t priors for participant-level effects (i.e., random intercepts and slopes), and LKJ-Correlation priors for random correlations.</p><p id="P53">To interpret the output of the Bayesian models, we report highest density (credible) intervals (HDIs) of the posterior parameter distributions. These are analogous but not exactly equivalent to frequentist confidence intervals. For example, a 95% HDI indicates the range that includes the 95% most probable parameter estimates (i.e., with the highest probability density), given the evidence provided by the data. All values falling within the interval have a higher probability to reflect the true (unknown) parameter estimate than those falling outside of the interval. Thus, when a large percentage of the posterior distribution is unidirectionally non-zero, this indicates a large probability of the true effect also being non-zero (in that direction). While Bayesian approaches thus allow us to make continuous statements about the probability of an effect (see e.g., Limbachia et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R96">96</xref></sup>), to aid interpretation we report two types of statements pertaining to effects’ significance. Whenever the 95% HDI <italic>does not</italic> include 0 (e.g., it ranges from 0.3 to 1.4), we interpret the effect to be ‘significant’. Whenever the 95% HDI <italic>does,</italic> but the 90% HDI <italic>does not</italic> include 0, we interpret the effect as ‘marginally significant’<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R97">97</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R100">100</xref></sup>. Finally, we also report effects’ posterior estimates; these are simply the medians of the posterior parameter distributions.</p><p id="P54"><italic>Task effects on choices, response times, and heart rate.</italic> We tested effects of the task (i.e., money and shocks levels, and the action context) on decision-making and heart rate (Δ<italic>hr</italic>) using Bayesian mixed-effects models. For the full model specifications of the choice and response time models in {brms} syntax, see <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD1">equations (1)</xref> to <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD3">(3)</xref> below.</p><p id="P55">Choice model: <disp-formula id="FD1"><label>(1)</label><mml:math id="M1"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>choice</mml:mtext><mml:mo>~</mml:mo><mml:mtext>money</mml:mtext><mml:mo>*</mml:mo><mml:mtext>shocks</mml:mtext><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mtext>ac</mml:mtext><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mtext>money</mml:mtext><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mtext>shocks</mml:mtext><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mtext>money</mml:mtext><mml:mo>*</mml:mo><mml:mtext>shocks</mml:mtext><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mtext>money</mml:mtext><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mtext>shocks</mml:mtext><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mo>∣</mml:mo><mml:mo>\</mml:mo><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="P56">Response time model: <disp-formula id="FD2"><label>(2)</label><mml:math id="M2"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>responsetime</mml:mtext><mml:mo>~</mml:mo><mml:mtext>money</mml:mtext><mml:mo>*</mml:mo><mml:mtext>shocks</mml:mtext><mml:mo>*</mml:mo><mml:mtext>choice</mml:mtext><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mtext>money</mml:mtext><mml:mo>*</mml:mo><mml:mtext>shocks</mml:mtext><mml:mo>*</mml:mo><mml:mtext>choicepID</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="P57">Heart rate model: <disp-formula id="FD3"><label>(3)</label><mml:math id="M3"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>heartrate</mml:mtext><mml:mo>~</mml:mo><mml:mtext>money</mml:mtext><mml:mo>*</mml:mo><mml:mtext>shocks</mml:mtext><mml:mo>*</mml:mo><mml:mtext>ac</mml:mtext><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mtext>money</mml:mtext><mml:mo>*</mml:mo><mml:mtext>shocks</mml:mtext><mml:mo>*</mml:mo><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mo>\</mml:mo><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="P58">In this notation, the term left of the tilde (‘~’) denotes the dependent variable and the terms to the right of the tilde denote the predictors, the terms between brackets denote the random effects structure (i.e., ‘1’ reflects the random intercept, and the variables reflect the random slopes, all of which are modelled separately for participants (‘pID’) as the grouping factor), and an asterisk (*) between two variables indicates that both main effects as well as their interaction are modelled, whereas a colon (:) indicates an isolated interaction term between two variables.</p><p id="P59"><italic>Behavioral interactions with bradycardia states.</italic> To statistically test the effect of trial-by-trial bradycardia states on approach-avoidance choices, we ran a Bayesian mixed-effects model with the same effects specification as <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD1">equation (1)</xref>, but with trial-by-trial Δ<italic>hr</italic> as an additional continuous predictor, both as a main effect as well as interacting with all the task effects, as follows: <disp-formula id="FD4"><label>(4)</label><mml:math id="M4"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>choice</mml:mtext><mml:mo>~</mml:mo><mml:mtext>money</mml:mtext><mml:mo>*</mml:mo><mml:mtext>shocks</mml:mtext><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mtext>money</mml:mtext><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mtext>shocks</mml:mtext><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mtext>money</mml:mtext><mml:mi>Δ</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mtext>shocks</mml:mtext><mml:mi>Δ</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:mi>Δ</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mtext>moneyshocks</mml:mtext><mml:mi>Δ</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mtext>money:ac:</mml:mtext><mml:mi>Δ</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mtext>shocksac</mml:mtext><mml:mi>Δ</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mtext>money</mml:mtext><mml:mo>*</mml:mo><mml:mtext>shocks</mml:mtext><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mtext>money</mml:mtext><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mtext>shocks</mml:mtext><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>Δ</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mtext>money</mml:mtext><mml:mi>Δ</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mtext>shocks</mml:mtext><mml:mi>Δ</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:mi>Δ</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mtext>moneyshocks</mml:mtext><mml:mi>Δ</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mtext>moneyac</mml:mtext><mml:mi>Δ</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mtext>shocks:ac</mml:mtext><mml:mi>Δ</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>\</mml:mo><mml:mo>∣</mml:mo><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="P60">We similarly tested the effect of bradycardia states on response times, adding Δ<italic>hr</italic> as the main and interaction effects to the response time model in <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD2">equation (2)</xref>: <disp-formula id="FD5"><label>(5)</label><mml:math id="M5"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>responsetime</mml:mtext><mml:mo>~</mml:mo><mml:mtext>money</mml:mtext><mml:mo>*</mml:mo><mml:mtext>shocks</mml:mtext><mml:mo>*</mml:mo><mml:mtext>choice</mml:mtext><mml:mo>*</mml:mo><mml:mi>Δ</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mtext>money</mml:mtext><mml:mo>*</mml:mo><mml:mtext>shocks</mml:mtext><mml:mo>*</mml:mo><mml:mtext>choice</mml:mtext><mml:mo>*</mml:mo><mml:mi>Δ</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>\</mml:mo><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mtext>ID</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p></sec></sec><sec id="S25"><title>Computational modeling of bradycardia-state interactions</title><p id="P61">Using the same mixed-effects (i.e., hierarchical) Bayesian modeling approach, we performed computational modeling to test our hypotheses regarding the three mechanisms through which freezing may affect computations underlying approach-avoidance choices.</p><sec id="S26"><title>Model specification</title><p id="P62">First, we specified a base model estimating the value of the decision (decision value; DV, ranging [-∞,+∞]) on each trial, accounting for task-induced effects and a main effect of bradycardia on choice. The DV function of this base model consists of 8 free parameters, estimating the average approach rate (β<sub>0</sub>), the effects of money (β<sub>m</sub>), shocks (β<sub>s</sub>), action context (β<sub>ac</sub>), and bradycardia (β<sub>hr</sub>) on choice, and the two-way interaction effects between money and shocks (β<sub>m:s</sub>), money and action context (β<sub>m:ac</sub>), and shocks and action context (β<sub>s:ac</sub>): <disp-formula id="FD6"><label>(6)</label><mml:math id="M6"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Base</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:mi>Δ</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="P63">Where <italic>m</italic> and <italic>s</italic> indicate the potential money amounts and shocks, Δ<italic>hr</italic> reflects the change in heart rate relative to the pre-trial baseline, and <italic>ac</italic> is a sum-to-zero coded dummy variable indicating the action context: <disp-formula id="FD7"><label>(7)</label><mml:math id="M7"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mrow/></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mrow/></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="P64">Specifically, <italic>β<sub>ac</sub></italic> captures the variance in approach-avoidance choices due to the participants’ tendency to respond passively (<italic>ac</italic> &gt; 0) vs. actively (<italic>ac</italic> &lt; 0).</p><p id="P65">Note that this model has the same parameterization as <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD1">equation (1)</xref>, except for the additional inclusion of a main effect of heart rate on choice. This additional term was included to improve the interpretability of the interaction between Δ<italic>hr</italic> and other terms introduced in the freezing models (see below). To fit this model to the choice data, the trial-by-trial DVs were transformed to choice probabilities (ranging [0,1]) through the logistic function: <disp-formula id="FD8"><label>(8)</label><mml:math id="M8"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>approach</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="P66">Next, building from this base-model parameterization, we formalized three new freezing models that each add a single term to the base DV function, corresponding to the three hypothesized mechanisms of bradycardia-state interactions underlying approach-avoidance:</p><p id="P67"><italic>Aversive value</italic> (AV): <disp-formula id="FD9"><label>(9)</label><mml:math id="M9"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>base</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:mi>Δ</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="P68"><italic>Value comparison</italic> (VC): <disp-formula id="FD10"><label>(10)</label><mml:math id="M10"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>base</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:mi>Δ</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:mi>Δ</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="P69">Where the Δ<italic>ms</italic> variable is computed as the difference between the money and shock levels (i.e., △<italic>m:s</italic> = <italic>money</italic> – <italic>shocks</italic>).</p><p id="P70">Action invigoration (AI): <disp-formula id="FD11"><label>(11)</label><mml:math id="M11"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>base</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:mi>Δ</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="P71">The trial-by-trial DVs of the base model and these three additional models were subsequently used in the model-based fMRI analysis.</p><sec id="S27"><title>Model fitting procedure</title><p id="P72">While we initially planned to fit these computational models using MLE (maximum likelihood estimation) and on the subject level (rather than hierarchically), we instead opted for a hierarchical (Bayesian) approach because this tends to estimate group and participant-level parameters more reliably, compared to more traditional ‘flat’ (i.e., non-hierarchical) model-fitting procedures<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R101">101</xref></sup>. For fitting these models we used the same settings for other BMMs as specified in the <italic>Data analysis</italic> – <italic>general’</italic> section (i.e., maximal random-effect structure, default uninformed priors, all continuous predictors mean-centered and scaled across subjects).</p><p id="P73">Computation of trial-by-trial decision values (DV). To compute the trial-by-trial DVs for each of the models (per participant), we multiplied the trial-wise data (i.e., money and shock levels, action context, and heart rate) with the group-level parameter estimates obtained from the fitted Bayesian models described in the Model specification section (see for example also Zorowitz et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R67">67</xref></sup>). We used the group-level parameter estimates for this rather than participant-level estimates, because – following previous reports<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R48">48</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R102">102</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R103">103</xref></sup> – we wanted to investigate the neural correlate of the group-level behavioral effects that the models estimate, not in individual differences that may obscure the common underlying cognitive process. The table below displays an overview of the exact parameter values used to generate the trial-wise DVs per participant for each of the models (obtained from the model fitting procedure). The associated behavioral predictions are drawn in main text <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5B</xref>.</p><table-wrap id="T1" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Group-level parameter estimates used to compute trial-wise decision values (DV) for each model</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top">Model</th><th align="center" valign="top">β0</th><th align="center" valign="top">βm</th><th align="center" valign="top">βs</th><th align="center" valign="top">βm:s</th><th align="center" valign="top">βac</th><th align="center" valign="top">βhr</th><th align="center" valign="top">βm:ac</th><th align="center" valign="top">βs:ac</th><th align="center" valign="top">βs:hr</th><th align="center" valign="top">βms:hr</th><th align="center" valign="top">βac:hr</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top">Base</td><td align="left" valign="top">0.73</td><td align="left" valign="top">1.54</td><td align="left" valign="top">-1.10</td><td align="left" valign="top">0.41</td><td align="left" valign="top">0.07</td><td align="left" valign="top">0.05</td><td align="left" valign="top">-0.28</td><td align="left" valign="top">0.09</td><td align="center" valign="top">-</td><td align="center" valign="top">-</td><td align="center" valign="top">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">AV</td><td align="left" valign="top">0.73</td><td align="left" valign="top">1.54</td><td align="left" valign="top">-1.11</td><td align="left" valign="top">0.40</td><td align="left" valign="top">0.07</td><td align="left" valign="top">0.04</td><td align="left" valign="top">-0.28</td><td align="left" valign="top">0.09</td><td align="left" valign="top">0.07</td><td align="center" valign="top">-</td><td align="center" valign="top">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">VC</td><td align="left" valign="top">0.73</td><td align="left" valign="top">1.55</td><td align="left" valign="top">-1.11</td><td align="left" valign="top">0.40</td><td align="left" valign="top">0.07</td><td align="left" valign="top">0.03</td><td align="left" valign="top">-0.28</td><td align="left" valign="top">0.09</td><td align="center" valign="top">-</td><td align="left" valign="top">-0.09</td><td align="center" valign="top">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">AI</td><td align="left" valign="top">0.73</td><td align="left" valign="top">1.54</td><td align="left" valign="top">-1.10</td><td align="left" valign="top">0.40</td><td align="left" valign="top">0.07</td><td align="left" valign="top">0.05</td><td align="left" valign="top">-0.28</td><td align="left" valign="top">0.09</td><td align="center" valign="top">-</td><td align="center" valign="top">-</td><td align="left" valign="top">0.05</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TFN1"><p id="P74">Note: As described above, the base model did not include any bradycardia interaction term, and the freezing models only included one bradycardia interaction term each (three right-most columns). AV: aversive value; VC: value comparison; AI: action invigoration; m: money; s: shocks; ac: action context; hr: heart rate (Δhr); ms: differential money-shock level; colons (:) depict interaction terms between two variables.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec id="S28"><title>fMRI analysis</title><p id="P75">Since our analyses of interest only included trials with long anticipation-to-movement screen intervals (AMI), the remaining trials with shorter AMI’s (±20% of trials per participant) were modelled in separate regressors of no interest so as to exclude them from the implicit baseline. Unless specified otherwise, all regressors were temporally convolved with the hemodynamic response function (HRF) included in SPM12 (Statistical Parametric Mapping; Wellcome Trust Centre for Neuroimaging, London, UK). Additionally, we included six movement parameter regressors (3 translations, 3 rotations), 26 RETROICOR regressors, high-pass filtering (1/128 Hz cutoff), and AR(1) serial correlation corrections into all models. First-level contrast maps were entered into second-level one-sample t-tests.</p></sec><sec id="S29"><title>Correction for multiple comparisons</title><p id="P76">For analyses within regions of interest (ROI) we use peak-level correction (<italic>p</italic> &lt; .05 FWE-corrected), as preregistered. While for whole-brain level analyses we preregistered the same, we think this would not do justice to the clustered patterns of activation that we observe for our non-ROI contrasts (e.g., approach vs. avoid, passive vs. active, and parametric analyses of money and shock levels). Since the PAT is a new task in the fMRI context, we want to be transparent and report on any significant clusters that appear in any of these contrasts. This will facilitate comparison of our results to data of previous studies using comparable experimental paradigms<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32">32</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33">33</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36">36</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42">42</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R52">52</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R104">104</xref></sup>. Therefore, for whole-brain statistics only, we will report activations that are significant at the cluster level (<italic>p</italic> &lt; .05 FWE-corrected, at an initial cluster-forming threshold of <italic>p</italic> &lt; .001 uncorrected). Note that this will not in any way affect the conclusions of our main hypotheses concerning the bradycardia-state interactions underlying approach-avoidance, since those are tested through ROI analyses (using peak-level correction as planned).</p><p id="P77"><italic>ROI definition.</italic> We preregistered various regions of interest (ROIs) for our fMRI analysis. For the amygdala, vmPFC, and anterior cingulate regions we used the Automated Anatomical Labeling 3 (AAL3)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R105">105</xref></sup> atlas (vmPFC consisting of the frontal medial orbital, rectus, and OFC medial subregions, and ACC consisting of the sup-ACC, pre-ACC, sub-ACC, and Cingulate_Mid subregions). For the ventral striatum we used an independent mask created previously<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R106">106</xref></sup>, because it consists of a combination of different anatomical regions (e.g., nucleus accumbens, part of the caudate nucleus). For the BNST we used a mask provided by Avery et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R107">107</xref></sup>. Finally, for the PAG we used a mask based on manual segmentations from Lojowska et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R108">108</xref></sup> thresholded at a value of .25 (following Neubert et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R109">109</xref></sup>).</p><p id="P78"><italic>Task-based analysis.</italic> To investigate the neural correlates of passive and active approach-avoidance choices, we created a first-level model containing 4 box car regressors during the anticipation screen (passive-approach, active-approach, passive-avoid, active-avoid; 0.5 – 7 s duration), two stick function regressors for the movement screen (passive, active response), and three box car regressors for the outcome screen (money, shocks, neutral; 1.5 s duration).</p><p id="P79">To investigate the neural correlates of reward and threat anticipation, we additionally created a model with a single box car regressor for each anticipation screen, modulated by three parametric regressors: money level, shock level, and their interaction (i.e., multiplying the demeaned money and shock regressors with each other). All parametric regressors were orthogonalized with respect to the unmodulated trial regressor per subject (i.e., demeaned)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R50">50</xref></sup>. This model also contained regressors for the movement and outcome screens as specified for the previous model.</p><sec id="S30"><title>Finite impulse response (FIR) analysis</title><p id="P80">To investigate the time course of the BOLD response during the anticipation screen, we fit a finite impulse response model. In this model, activation during (and shortly after) the anticipation screen was estimated using a model that included 8 time bins (TR = 1.5 s) starting one time bin before the onset of the stimuli (-1.5 s) and ending two time bins after the anticipation screen (10.5 s). This way, bin numbers 2 to 5 (0 – 6 s) always fell within the anticipation screen. This first-level model makes no assumptions regarding the shape of the HRF and yields independent response estimates for each time bin. All additional preprocessing (regarding nuisance regressors, smoothing, etc.) was performed like discussed previously (see above). To analyze the time courses, we extracted the subject-wise β weights from three anatomical ROIs; the bilateral amygdala, ventral striatum, and vmPFC (see <italic>ROI definition).</italic> All responses were baseline corrected relative to the response in bin 1 and analyzed using 3-way repeated measures ANOVAs (per ROI) with within-subjects factors time (bin 2 to 5), choice (approach/avoid), and response (active/passive). Since for all models the assumption of sphericity was violated, we applied Greenhouse-Geisser correction to all degrees of freedom (DFs) and <italic>p</italic>-values, and we report partial <italic>n</italic>-squared <inline-formula><mml:math id="M12"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>η</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> effect-size estimates where appropriate. Significant effects were followed up using two-tailed paired t-tests.</p></sec><sec id="S31"><title>Model-based analysis</title><p id="P81">To test the neural correlates of our three hypothesized mechanisms of bradycardia-state interactions with computations underlying approach-avoidance arbitration, we used model-based fMRI analysis. Specifically, we extracted – per participant – the trial-by-trial DVs of the base computational model (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD6">equation 6</xref>) and the DVs of the three freezing models (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD9">equations 9</xref>, <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD10">10</xref>, and <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD11">11</xref>). We then used these trial-by-trial values as parametric regressors in a single first-level GLM per participant. More specifically, each first-level model had a single box-car regressor for the anticipation screen, and four corresponding parametric regressors (one for the base model, and one for each of the three freezing models).</p><p id="P82">The first parametric regressor contained the raw (standardized) trial-by-trial DVs of the base model. However, to account for high correlations between the base regressor and the regressors of each of the three freezing models (i.e., Spearman correlations for all freezing models with the base model across subjects were approximately M<sub>Rs</sub> = ±.998, SD<sub>Rs</sub>=±.0006), we orthogonalized the regressors of each of the freezing models with respect to the base regressor by computing <italic>difference scores:</italic> For each of the freezing models we computed the difference in trial-wise DV predictions compared to the base model DVs, such that (e.g., for the AV model) <italic>DVdiff<sub>AV</sub></italic> = <italic>DV<sub>Base</sub></italic> – <italic>DV<sub>AV</sub></italic>. This approach has previously been used to deal with correlated model-based parametric regressors <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R47">47</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R49">49</xref></sup> Indeed, after computing difference scores the correlations between regressors were greatly reduced (M<sub>Rs_AV</sub> = -.035, SD<sub>Rs_AV</sub> = 0.165; M<sub>Rs_AV</sub> = -.088, SD<sub>Rs_AV</sub> = 0.249; M<sub>Rs_AI</sub> = .003, SD<sub>Rs_AI</sub> = 0.081).</p><p id="P83">As such, these difference regressors reflect a difference in trial-by-trial predictions of each freezing model with respect to the base model: positive difference scores reflect higher value assigned by the base model than the freezing model (i.e., the freezing model predicts relatively more avoidance), whereas negative difference scores reflect lower value assigned by the base model compared to the freezing model (i.e., the freezing model predicts relatively more approach). Importantly, because each freezing model only deviates from the base model by a single term (e.g., <italic>β<sub>s:hr</sub></italic> for the AV model), any difference in the predicted decision value, as well as its correlate with BOLD-fMRI, is driven by this additional term. Finally, because the difference regressors of all three freezing models were entered together into the same first-level model, the BOLD correlations for each regressor reflect the unique contribution of that regressor, while controlling for the contribution of other regressors. Any shared explained variance between freezing-model regressors will thus be assigned to the error term<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R50">50</xref></sup>.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="SM"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1"><label>Supplementary Information</label><media xlink:href="EMS190975-supplement-Supplementary_Information.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" id="d98aAdHbB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack id="S32"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>This work was supported by a Consolidator Grant from the European Research Council (ERC_CoG – 2017_772337) awarded to Karin Roelofs.</p></ack><sec id="S33" sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data and code availability</title><p id="P84">Data and code will be made available before publication.</p></sec><fn-group><fn id="FN1"><p id="P85"><bold>Materials And Correspondence</bold></p><p id="P86">Correspondence and requests for materials should be addressed to F.H.K. or K.R.</p></fn><fn id="FN2" fn-type="con"><p id="P87"><bold>Author Contributions</bold></p><p id="P88">Conceptualization, F.H.K., L.D.V., A.M.H., J.X.O., F.K., B.F., and K.R.; Methodology. F.H.K., L.D.V., J.X.O., B.F., and K.R.; Software, F.H.K. and L.D.V.; Formal Analysis, F.H.K.; Investigation, F.H.K.; Writing – Original Draft, F.H.K., L.D.V., and K.R.; Writing – Review &amp; Editing; F.H.K., L.D.V., A.M.H., J.X.O., F.K., B.F., and K.R.; Supervision, L.D.V., B.F., and K.R.; Funding Acquisition, K.R.</p></fn><fn id="FN3" fn-type="conflict"><p id="P89"><bold>Competing Interests</bold></p><p id="P90">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><ref id="R1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Corr</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Approach and Avoidance Behaviour: Multiple Systems and their Interactions</article-title><source>Emot Rev</source><year>2013</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>285</fpage><lpage>290</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>McNaughton</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><source>The Neuropsychology of anxiety: an enquiry into the functions of the septo-hippocampal system</source><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name><year>2000</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Experimental studies of conflict</chapter-title><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Hunt</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><source>Personality and the behavior disorders</source><publisher-name>Ronald</publisher-name><year>1944</year><fpage>431</fpage><lpage>465</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bach</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anxiety-Like Behavioural Inhibition Is Normative under Environmental Threat-Reward Correlations</article-title><source>PLoS Comput Biol</source><year>2015</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>20</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4674090</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26650585</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1004646</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krypotos</surname><given-names>A-M</given-names></name><name><surname>Vervliet</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Engelhard</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The validity of human avoidance paradigms</article-title><source>Behav Res Ther</source><year>2018</year><volume>111</volume><fpage>99</fpage><lpage>105</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30396111</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Letkiewicz</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kottler</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><name><surname>Shankman</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Cochran</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quantifying aberrant approach-avoidance conflict in psychopathology: A review of computational approaches</article-title><source>Neurosci Biobehav Rev</source><year>2023</year><volume>147</volume><elocation-id>105103</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10023482</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36804398</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neubiorev.2023.105103</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pittig</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Boschet</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Glück</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></name><name><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Elevated costly avoidance in anxiety disorders: Patients show little downregulation of acquired avoidance in face of competing rewards for approach</article-title><source>Depress Anxiety</source><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33258530</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Paulus</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Driven by Pain, Not Gain: Computational Approaches to Aversion-Related Decision Making in Psychiatry</article-title><source>Biol Psychiatry</source><year>2020</year><volume>87</volume><fpage>359</fpage><lpage>367</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7012695</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31653478</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biopsych.2019.08.025</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rangel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Camerer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Montague</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A framework for studying the neurobiology of value-based decision making</article-title><source>Nat Rev Neurosci</source><year>2008</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>545</fpage><lpage>556</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4332708</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18545266</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrn2357</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kozlowska</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>McLean</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Carrive</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fear and the Defense Cascade: Clinical Implications and Management</article-title><source>Harv Rev Psychiatry</source><year>2015</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>263</fpage><lpage>287</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4495877</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26062169</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/HRP.0000000000000065</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roelofs</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Dayan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Freezing revisited: Coordinated autonomic and central optimization of threat coping</article-title><source>Nat Rev Neurosci</source><year>2022</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35760906</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Azevedo</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A freezing-like posture to pictures of mutilation</article-title><source>Psychophysiology</source><year>2005</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>255</fpage><lpage>260</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15943678</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hashemi</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Neural Dynamics of Shooting Decisions and the Switch from Freeze to Fight</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2019</year><volume>9</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6414631</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30862811</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-019-40917-8</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schipper</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The association between serotonin transporter availability and the neural correlates of fear bradycardia</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2019</year><volume>116</volume><fpage>25941</fpage><lpage>25947</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6925990</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31772023</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1904843116</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nijsen</surname><given-names>MJMA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Endogenous corticotropin-releasing hormone inhibits conditioned-fear-induced vagal activation in the rat</article-title><source>Eur J Pharmacol</source><year>2000</year><volume>389</volume><fpage>89</fpage><lpage>98</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10686300</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tovote</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Midbrain circuits for defensive behaviour</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2016</year><volume>534</volume><fpage>206</fpage><lpage>212</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27279213</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van Der Zee</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Roozendaal</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Bohus</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Koolhaas</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Luiten</surname><given-names>PGM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Muscarinic acetylcholine receptor immunoreactivity in the amygdala-I. Cellular distribution correlated with fear-induced behavior</article-title><source>Neuroscience</source><year>1997</year><volume>76</volume><fpage>63</fpage><lpage>73</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8971759</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Carrive</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Role of ventrolateral periaqueductal gray neurons in the behavioral and cardiovascular responses to contextual conditioned fear and poststress recovery</article-title><source>Neuroscience</source><year>2003</year><volume>116</volume><fpage>897</fpage><lpage>912</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12573728</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fanselow</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Neural organization of the defensive behavior system responsible for fear</article-title><source>Psychon Bull Rev</source><year>1994</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>429</fpage><lpage>438</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24203551</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blanchard</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Griebel</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Pobbe</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Blanchard</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Risk assessment as an evolved threat detection and analysis process</article-title><source>Neurosci Biobehav Rev</source><year>2011</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>991</fpage><lpage>998</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21056591</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bolles</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Species-specific defense reactions and avoidance learning</article-title><source>Psychol Rev</source><year>1970</year><volume>77</volume><fpage>32</fpage><lpage>48</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hermans</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Henckens</surname><given-names>MJAG</given-names></name><name><surname>Roelofs</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Fernández</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fear bradycardia and activation of the human periaqueductal grey</article-title><source>NeuroImage</source><year>2013</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>278</fpage><lpage>287</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23110885</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roelofs</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Freeze for action: Neurobiological mechanisms in animal and human freezing</article-title><source>Philos Trans R Soc B Biol Sci</source><year>2017</year><volume>372</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5332864</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28242739</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rstb.2016.0206</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de Voogd</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name><name><surname>Hagenberg</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name><name><surname>de Lange</surname><given-names>FP</given-names></name><name><surname>Roelofs</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Acute threat enhances perceptual sensitivity without affecting the decision criterion</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2022</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>11</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9156772</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35641536</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-022-11664-0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rösler</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Gamer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Freezing of gaze during action preparation under threat imminence</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2019</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6868270</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31748589</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-019-53683-4</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Löw</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Weymar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamm</surname><given-names>AO</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>When Threat Is Near, Get Out of Here: Dynamics of Defensive Behavior During Freezing and Active Avoidance</article-title><source>Psychol Sci</source><year>2015</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>1706</fpage><lpage>1716</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26408036</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wendt</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Löw</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Weymar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lotze</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamm</surname><given-names>AO</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Active avoidance and attentive freezing in the face of approaching threat</article-title><source>NeuroImage</source><year>2017</year><volume>158</volume><fpage>196</fpage><lpage>204</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28669911</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Klaassen</surname><given-names>FH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Defensive freezing and its relation to approach-avoidance decision-making under threat</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2021</year><volume>11</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8187589</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34103543</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-021-90968-z</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Livermore</surname><given-names>JJA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Approach-Avoidance Decisions Under Threat: The Role of Autonomic Psychophysiological States</article-title><source>Front Neurosci</source><year>2021</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8044748</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33867915</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fnins.2021.621517</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kirlic</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Aupperle</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Animal to human translational paradigms relevant for approach avoidance conflict decision making</article-title><source>Behav Res Ther</source><year>2017</year><volume>96</volume><fpage>14</fpage><lpage>29</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5548639</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28495358</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.brat.2017.04.010</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pedersen</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Computational phenotyping of brain-behavior dynamics underlying approach-avoidance conflict in major depressive disorder</article-title><source>PLoS Comput Biol</source><year>2021</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>21</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8136861</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33970903</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1008955</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schlund</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The tipping point: Value differences and parallel dorsal - ventral frontal circuits gating human approach - avoidance behavior</article-title><source>NeuroImage</source><year>2016</year><volume>136</volume><fpage>94</fpage><lpage>105</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27153979</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Talmi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Dayan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kiebel</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Frith</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Dolan</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>How humans integrate the prospects of pain and reward during choice</article-title><source>J Neurosci</source><year>2009</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>14617</fpage><lpage>14626</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2948535</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19923294</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.2026-09.2009</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Delgado</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Jou</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Phelps</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Neural systems underlying aversive conditioning in humans with primary and secondary reinforcers</article-title><source>Front Neurosci</source><year>2011</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>10</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3101377</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21637321</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fnins.2011.00071</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kolling</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Wittmann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rushworth</surname><given-names>MFS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multiple neural mechanisms of decision making and their competition under changing risk pressure</article-title><source>Neuron</source><year>2014</year><volume>81</volume><fpage>1190</fpage><lpage>1202</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3988955</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24607236</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2014.01.033</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>SQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kahnt</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Rieskamp</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Heekeren</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Neurobiology of Value Integration: When Value Impacts Valuation</article-title><source>J Neurosci</source><year>2011</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>9307</fpage><lpage>9314</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6623498</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21697380</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.4973-10.2011</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reis</surname><given-names>FMCV</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Dorsal periaqueductal gray ensembles represent approach and avoidance states</article-title><source>eLife</source><year>2021</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>22</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8133778</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33955356</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.64934</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lojowska</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ling</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Roelofs</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hermans</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Visuocortical changes during a freezing-like state in humans</article-title><source>NeuroImage</source><year>2018</year><volume>179</volume><fpage>313</fpage><lpage>325</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6553455</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29883732</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2018.06.013</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Representation of aversive prediction errors in the human periaqueductal gray</article-title><source>Nat Neurosci</source><year>2014</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>1607</fpage><lpage>1612</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4213247</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25282614</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nn.3832</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McHugh</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Aversive prediction error signals in the amygdala</article-title><source>J Neurosci</source><year>2014</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>9024</fpage><lpage>9033</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4078079</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24990922</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.4465-13.2014</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R41"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McNaughton</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Corr</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Survival circuits and risk assessment</article-title><source>Curr Opin Behav Sci</source><year>2018</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>14</fpage><lpage>20</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R42"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aupperle</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Melrose</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Francisco</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Paulus</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Stein</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Neural Substrates of Approach-Avoidance Conflict Decision-Making</article-title><source>Hum Brain Mapp</source><year>2015</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>449</fpage><lpage>462</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4300249</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25224633</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/hbm.22639</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R43"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>Y-W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The dorsomedial prefrontal cortex represents subjective value across effort-based and risky decision-making</article-title><source>NeuroImage</source><year>2023</year><volume>279</volume><elocation-id>120326</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37579997</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R44"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aquino</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name><name><surname>Cockburn</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mamelak</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name><name><surname>Rutishauser</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>O’Doherty</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Neurons in human pre-supplementary motor area encode key computations for value-based choice</article-title><source>Nat Hum Behav</source><year>2023</year><elocation-id>2021.10.27.466000</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10330469</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36959327</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41562-023-01548-2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R45"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van Ast</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name><name><surname>Klumpers</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Grasman</surname><given-names>RPPP</given-names></name><name><surname>Krypotos</surname><given-names>A-M</given-names></name><name><surname>Roelofs</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Postural freezing relates to startle potentiation in a human fear-conditioning paradigm</article-title><source>Psychophysiology</source><year>2021</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>20</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9285358</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34954858</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/psyp.13983</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R46"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Glover</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>TQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ress</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Image-based method for retrospective correction of physiological motion effects in fMRI: RETROICOR</article-title><source>Magn Reson Med</source><year>2000</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>162</fpage><lpage>167</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10893535</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R47"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Daw</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name><name><surname>Gershman</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Seymour</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Dayan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Dolan</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Model-based influences on humans’ choices and striatal prediction errors</article-title><source>Neuron</source><year>2011</year><volume>69</volume><fpage>1204</fpage><lpage>1215</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3077926</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21435563</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2011.02.027</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R48"><label>48</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eldar</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Niv</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Interaction between emotional state and learning underlies mood instability</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2015</year><volume>6</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5338993</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25608088</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncomms7149</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R49"><label>49</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wittmann</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><name><surname>Daw</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name><name><surname>Seymour</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Dolan</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Striatal Activity Underlies Novelty-Based Choice in Humans</article-title><source>Neuron</source><year>2008</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>967</fpage><lpage>973</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2535823</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18579085</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2008.04.027</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R50"><label>50</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mumford</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Poline</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Poldrack</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Orthogonalization of regressors in fMRI models</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2015</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>11</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4412813</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25919488</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0126255</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R51"><label>51</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hulsman</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Individual Differences in Costly Fearful Avoidance and the Relation to Psychophysiology</article-title><source>Behav Res Ther</source><year>2021</year><volume>137</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33422745</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R52"><label>52</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bach</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Human hippocampus arbitrates approach-avoidance conflict</article-title><source>Curr Biol</source><year>2014</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>541</fpage><lpage>547</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5628946</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28903053</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2014.05.051</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R53"><label>53</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de Voogd</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name><name><surname>Hermans</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Phelps</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regulating defensive survival circuits through cognitive demand via large-scale network reorganization</article-title><source>Curr Opin Behav Sci</source><year>2018</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>124</fpage><lpage>129</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R54"><label>54</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de Voogd</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name><name><surname>Hermans</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Meta-analytic evidence for downregulation of the amygdala during working memory maintenance</article-title><source>Hum Brain Mapp</source><year>2022</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>2951</fpage><lpage>2971</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9120562</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35349194</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/hbm.25828</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R55"><label>55</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Murty</surname><given-names>DVPS</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Surampudi</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name><surname>Pessoa</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Threat and Reward Imminence Processing in the Human Brain</article-title><source>J Neurosci</source><year>2023</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>2973</fpage><lpage>2987</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10124955</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36927571</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.1778-22.2023</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R56"><label>56</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Visser</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bathelt</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Scholte</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kindt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Robust BOLD Responses to Faces but Not to Conditioned Threat: Challenging the Amygdala’s Reputation in Human Fear and Extinction Learning</article-title><source>J Neurosci</source><year>2021</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>10278</fpage><lpage>10292</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8672698</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34750227</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.0857-21.2021</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R57"><label>57</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Willems</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Oudenhove</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Vervliet</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Omissions of Threat Trigger Subjective Relief and Reward Prediction Error-Like Signaling in the Human Reward System</article-title><year>2023</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2023.08.15.553434</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R58"><label>58</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Piantadosi</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name><name><surname>Halladay</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name><name><surname>Radke</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Advances in understanding meso-cortico-limbic-striatal systems mediating risky reward seeking</article-title><source>J Neurochem</source><year>2021</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>25</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8981567</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33704784</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jnc.15342</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R59"><label>59</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seymour</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Dolan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Emotion, Decision Making, and the Amygdala</article-title><source>Eur J Sci Theol</source><year>2013</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>137</fpage><lpage>146</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18549779</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R60"><label>60</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lerman</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kable</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Amygdala Functional and Structural Connectivity Predicts Individual Risk Tolerance</article-title><source>Neuron</source><year>2018</year><volume>98</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>11</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5910234</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29628186</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2018.03.019</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R61"><label>61</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Castegnetti</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Representation of probabilistic outcomes during risky decision-making</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2020</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>11</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7229012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32415145</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-020-16202-y</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R62"><label>62</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dumas</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>MEG Evidence for Dynamic Amygdala Modulations by Gaze and Facial Emotions</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2013</year><volume>8</volume><elocation-id>e74145</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3769395</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24040190</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0074145</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R63"><label>63</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tzovara</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>High-precision magnetoencephalography for reconstructing amygdalar and hippocampal oscillations during prediction of safety and threat</article-title><source>Hum Brain Mapp</source><year>2019</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>4114</fpage><lpage>4129</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6772181</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31257708</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/hbm.24689</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R64"><label>64</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bach</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoffmann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Finke</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Hurlemann</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Ploner</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Disentangling hippocampal and amygdala contribution to human anxiety-like behavior</article-title><source>J Neurosci</source><year>2019</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>8517</fpage><lpage>8526</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6807285</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31501296</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.0412-19.2019</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R65"><label>65</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Amygdala regulates risk of predation in rats foraging in a dynamic fear environment</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci</source><year>2010</year><volume>107</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3003044</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21115817</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1010079108</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R66"><label>66</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bradley</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Codispoti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Cuthbert</surname><given-names>BN</given-names></name><name><surname>Lang</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Emotion and Motivation I: Defensive and Appetitive Reactions in Picture Processing</article-title><source>Emotion</source><year>2001</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>276</fpage><lpage>298</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12934687</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R67"><label>67</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zorowitz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The neural basis of approach-avoidance conflict: A model based analysis</article-title><source>eNeuro</source><year>2019</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6709212</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31346001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/ENEURO.0115-19.2019</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R68"><label>68</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Critchley</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagai</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mathias</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dissecting axes of autonomic control in humans: Insights from neuroimaging</article-title><source>Auton Neurosci Basic Clin</source><year>2011</year><volume>161</volume><fpage>34</fpage><lpage>42</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20926356</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R69"><label>69</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gladwin</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name><name><surname>Hashemi</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>van Ast</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Roelofs</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ready and waiting: Freezing as active action preparation under threat</article-title><source>Neurosci Lett</source><year>2016</year><volume>619</volume><fpage>182</fpage><lpage>188</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26994781</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R70"><label>70</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lang</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bradley</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Emotion and the motivational brain</article-title><source>Biol Psychol</source><year>2010</year><volume>84</volume><fpage>437</fpage><lpage>450</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3612949</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19879918</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biopsycho.2009.10.007</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R71"><label>71</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Löw</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lang</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Bradley</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Both predator and prey: Emotional arousal in threat and reward</article-title><source>Psychol Sci</source><year>2008</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>865</fpage><lpage>873</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3612950</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18947351</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1467-9280.2008.02170.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R72"><label>72</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de Voogd</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name><name><surname>Phelps</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A cognitively demanding working-memory intervention enhances extinction</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2020</year><volume>10</volume><elocation-id>7020</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7184585</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32341373</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-020-63811-0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R73"><label>73</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krajbich</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Bartling</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Hare</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Fehr</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rethinking fast and slow based on a critique of reaction-time reverse inference</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2015</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4500827</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26135809</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncomms8455</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R74"><label>74</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bagur</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Breathing-driven prefrontal oscillations regulate maintenance of conditioned-fear evoked freezing independently of initiation</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2021</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>15</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8110519</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33972521</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-021-22798-6</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R75"><label>75</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Skora</surname><given-names>LI</given-names></name><name><surname>Livermore</surname><given-names>JJA</given-names></name><name><surname>Roelofs</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The functional role of cardiac activity in perception and action</article-title><source>Neurosci Biobehav Rev</source><year>2022</year><volume>137</volume><elocation-id>104655</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35395334</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R76"><label>76</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Signoret-Genest</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Integrated cardio-behavioral responses to threat define defensive states</article-title><source>Nat Neurosci</source><year>2023</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9991919</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36759559</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41593-022-01252-w</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R77"><label>77</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Adenauer</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Catani</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Keil</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Aichinger</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Neuner</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Is freezing an adaptive reaction to threat? Evidence from heart rate reactivity to emotional pictures in victims of war and torture</article-title><source>Psychophysiology</source><year>2010</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>315</fpage><lpage>322</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20030756</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R78"><label>78</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fragkaki</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Roelofs</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Stins</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Jongedijk</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hagenaars</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reduced Freezing in Posttraumatic Stress Disorder Patients while Watching Affective Pictures</article-title><source>Front Psychiatry</source><year>2017</year><volume>8</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5348645</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28352237</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpsyt.2017.00039</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R79"><label>79</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Niermann</surname><given-names>HCM</given-names></name><name><surname>Figner</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Roelofs</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Individual differences in defensive stress-responses: the potential relevance for psychopathology</article-title><source>Curr Opin Behav Sci</source><year>2017</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>94</fpage><lpage>101</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R80"><label>80</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Niermann</surname><given-names>HCM</given-names></name><name><surname>Figner</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Tyborowska</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Cillessen</surname><given-names>AHN</given-names></name><name><surname>Roelofs</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Investigation of the Stability of Human Freezing-Like Responses to Social Threat From Mid to Late Adolescence</article-title><source>Front Behav Neurosci</source><year>2018</year><volume>12</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5964744</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29867396</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fnbeh.2018.00097</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R81"><label>81</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Held</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The gene environment aetiology of freezing and its relationship with internalizing symptoms during adolescence</article-title><source>eBioMedicine</source><year>2022</year><volume>81</volume><elocation-id>104094</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9194596</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35696830</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ebiom.2022.104094</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R82"><label>82</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Long-term stability of computational parameters during approach-avoidance conflict in a transdiagnostic psychiatric patient sample</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2021</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>13</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8175390</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34083701</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-021-91308-x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R83"><label>83</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beck</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name><surname>Steer</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name></person-group><source>Manual for the Beck Depression Inventory-II</source><publisher-name>Psychological Corporation</publisher-name><year>1996</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R84"><label>84</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Spielberger</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Gorsuch</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Lushene</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Vagg</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacobs</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name></person-group><source>Manual for the State-Trait Anxiety Inventory</source><publisher-name>Consulting Psychologists Press</publisher-name><year>1983</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R85"><label>85</label><element-citation publication-type="other"><collab>The Mathworks</collab><source>MATLAB</source><year>2018</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R86"><label>86</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brainard</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Psychophysics Toolbox</article-title><source>Spat Vis</source><year>1997</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>433</fpage><lpage>436</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9176952</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R87"><label>87</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de Voogd</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Eye-movement intervention enhances extinction via amygdala deactivation</article-title><source>J Neurosci</source><year>2018</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>8694</fpage><lpage>8706</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6596227</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30181134</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.0703-18.2018</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R88"><label>88</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van Buuren</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cardiorespiratory effects on default-mode network activity as measured with fMRI</article-title><source>Hum Brain Mapp</source><year>2009</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>3031</fpage><lpage>3042</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6871216</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19180557</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/hbm.20729</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R89"><label>89</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Birn</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Diamond</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bandettini</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Separating respiratory-variation-related fluctuations from neuronal-activity-related fluctuations in fMRI</article-title><source>NeuroImage</source><year>2006</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>1536</fpage><lpage>1548</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16632379</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R90"><label>90</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bürkner</surname><given-names>P-C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Advanced Bayesian Multilevel Modeling with the R Package brms</article-title><source>R J</source><year>2018</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>395</fpage><lpage>411</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R91"><label>91</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bürkner</surname><given-names>P-C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>brms: An R Package for Bayesian Multilevel Models Using Stan</article-title><source>J Stat Softw</source><year>2017</year><volume>80</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>28</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R92"><label>92</label><element-citation publication-type="other"><collab>Stan Development Team</collab><source>RStan: the R interface to Stan</source><year>2019</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R93"><label>93</label><element-citation publication-type="other"><collab>R Core Team</collab><source>R: A language and environment for statistical computing</source><year>2019</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R94"><label>94</label><element-citation publication-type="other"><collab>RStudio Team</collab><source>RStudio: Integrated Development for R</source><year>2019</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R95"><label>95</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barr</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Levy</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Scheepers</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Tily</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Random effects structure for confirmatory hypothesis testing: Keep it maximal</article-title><source>J Mem Lang</source><year>2013</year><volume>68</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>43</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3881361</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24403724</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jml.2012.11.001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R96"><label>96</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Limbachia</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Controllability over stressor decreases responses in key threat-related brain areas</article-title><source>Commun Biol</source><year>2021</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>11</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7785729</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33402686</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s42003-020-01537-5</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R97"><label>97</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haines</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Anxiety Modulates Preference for Immediate Rewards Among Trait-Impulsive Individuals: A Hierarchical Bayesian Analysis</article-title><source>Clin Psychol Sci</source><year>2020</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>1017</fpage><lpage>1036</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R98"><label>98</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hespanhol</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Vallio</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Saragiotto</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Understanding and interpreting confidence and credible interval around effect estimates</article-title><source>Braz J Phys Ther</source><year>2019</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>290</fpage><lpage>301</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6630113</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30638956</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bjpt.2018.12.006</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R99"><label>99</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Makowski</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Ben-Shachar</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>SHA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lüdecke</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bayesian Indices of Existence and Significance</article-title><source>Front Psychol</source><year>2019</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>14</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6914840</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31920819</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpsyg.2019.02767</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R100"><label>100</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kruschke</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name></person-group><source>Doing Bayesian Data Analysis: A Tutorial with R, JAGS, and Stan</source><publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name><year>2015</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/B978-0-12-405888-0.09999-2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R101"><label>101</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ahn</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Krawitz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Busemeyer</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A Model-Based fMRI Analysis With Hierarchical Bayesian Parameter Estimation</article-title><source>J Neurosci Psychol Econ</source><year>2011</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>95</fpage><lpage>110</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3686299</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23795233</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/a0020684</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R102"><label>102</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Schiller</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Schoenbaum</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Phelps</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Daw</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Differential roles of human striatum and amygdala in associative learning</article-title><source>Nat Neurosci</source><year>2011</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>1250</fpage><lpage>1252</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3268261</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21909088</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nn.2904</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R103"><label>103</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Niv</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Is Model Fitting Necessary for Model-Based fMRI?</article-title><source>PLoS Comput Biol</source><year>2015</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>21</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4472514</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26086934</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1004237</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R104"><label>104</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rolle</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The Role of the Dorsal-Lateral Prefrontal Cortex in Reward Sensitivity During Approach-Avoidance Conflict</article-title><source>Cereb Cortex</source><year>2022</year><fpage>1269</fpage><lpage>1285</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9077265</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34464445</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/cercor/bhab292</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R105"><label>105</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rolls</surname><given-names>ET</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Joliot</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Automated anatomical labelling atlas 3</article-title><source>NeuroImage</source><year>2020</year><volume>206</volume><elocation-id>116189</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31521825</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R106"><label>106</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Piray</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Ouden</surname><given-names>HEMD</given-names></name><name><surname>Schaaf</surname><given-names>MEVD</given-names></name><name><surname>Toni</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Cools</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dopaminergic Modulation of the Functional Ventrodorsal Architecture of the Human Striatum</article-title><source>Cereb Cortex</source><year>2017</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>485</fpage><lpage>495</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26494799</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R107"><label>107</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Avery</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>BNST neurocircuitry in humans</article-title><source>NeuroImage</source><year>2014</year><volume>91</volume><fpage>311</fpage><lpage>323</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4214684</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24444996</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2014.01.017</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R108"><label>108</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lojowska</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gladwin</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name><name><surname>Hermans</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Roelofs</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Freezing promotes perception of coarse visual features</article-title><source>J Exp Psychol Gen</source><year>2015</year><volume>144</volume><fpage>1080</fpage><lpage>1088</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26595839</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R109"><label>109</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Neubert</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Mars</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>Sallet</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Rushworth</surname><given-names>MFS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Connectivity reveals relationship of brain areas for reward-guided learning and decision making in human and monkey frontal cortex</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci</source><year>2015</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>10</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4443352</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25947150</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1410767112</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Theoretical and experimental paradigm – outline of hypothesized mechanisms of freezing-state effects on approach-avoidance, and trial design of the Passive-active Approach-avoidance Task (PAT).</title><p><bold>A)</bold> Visualization of the theoretical framework in which we hypothesize three mechanisms through which freezing states may affect the computations underlying approach-avoidance decisions under threat. We hypothesized interactions with processing of aversive value, value comparison, and action invigoration. See main text for details and rationale. Figure was adapted with permission from Livermore et al., 2021. <bold>B)</bold> To test this model, we developed an experimental task in which participants (white square) have to approach or avoid targets (gray circle) that are associated with varying reward and threat magnitudes (ranging 1-5 euro/shocks and indicated by green coins/lightning bolts respectively). After an initial anticipation screen (duration of 6 – 7 s for 80% of the trials) participants could indicate their choice during the target movement window (700 ms) by positioning themselves (i.e., the white square) on the same location as where the target was moving (approach) or on the other location (avoid). If participants approached, there was a large probability to receive either the indicated number of shocks (40%) or amount of money (40%), and a small probability to receive nothing (20%). If participants avoided, there was a large probability receive to receive nothing (80%), and smaller probabilities to receive shocks (10%) or money (10%). Moreover, the target movement direction during the movement window was manipulated in two action contexts (i.e., movement towards or away from the player, 50% of all trials each), such that participants could always either actively approach/passively avoid, or passively approach/actively avoid. Participants were fully instructed about these task conditions (including the outcome probabilities). Dashed arrows were not present in the actual task.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS190975-f001"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Task effects on choice behavior and heart rate.</title><p><bold>A)</bold> Higher money and shock levels led to more approach vs avoid choices, respectively. <bold>B)</bold> We observed a significant average heart rate deceleration during the anticipation screen relative to the 1 s pre-trial baseline indicative of a freezing-like bradycardia state, which was numerically but not significantly more pronounced in avoid (compared to approach) trials (see main text for statistics). Trial-by-trial bradycardia (Δhr) was quantified as the average baseline-corrected heart rate across a 5-7 s time window relative to the anticipation screen onset, such that lower (relative to higher) Δhr values indicate stronger bradycardia. <bold>C)</bold> Stronger trial-by-trial bradycardia was associated with faster response times (for illustration purposes, individual dots reflect RT and Δhr values aggregated separately for money and shock levels, and approach and avoid choices). Moreover, we observed faster response times for avoid compared to approach decisions. Error bars indicate +/- 1 SEM. Gray-white striped shaded area in <bold>B</bold> reflects partial overlap between anticipation and target movement screens across different trials (i.e., movement window onset was uniformly jittered between 6 – 7 s relative to the anticipation screen onset). BPM: beats per minute; Ap.: approach; Av.: avoid; asterisks (*) indicate ‘significant’ effects.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS190975-f002"/></fig><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Neural correlates of reward-threat and approach-avoidance anticipation.</title><p><bold>A)</bold> We observed positive correlations between BOLD and money levels in the ventral striatum (vStr), and between BOLD and shock levels in the supplemental motor area/dorsal anterior cingulate (SMA/dACC) and anterior insula. <bold>B)</bold> We observed higher BOLD activity in the ventral striatum, amygdala, and ventromedial prefrontal cortex (vmPFC) for approach compared to avoid choices. All labelled areas are significant at p <italic>&lt; .05 FWE-corrected.</italic></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS190975-f003"/></fig><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Comparison of observed and model-predicted bradycardia-state interactions underlying approach-avoidance choices.</title><p>For each hypothesized bradycardia-state mechanism underlying choice, we plot the observed (top) and model-predicted (bottom) relationships with choice, namely the interaction between bradycardia and <bold>A)</bold> the number of shocks, <bold>B)</bold> the money-shock difference Δms, and <bold>C)</bold> the action context. Model-based plots also display the posterior distributions of the interaction coefficients, with the 90% HDI shaded in red, and the 95% HDI in orange. For plotting purposes only, we created conditions with stronger bradycardia (low Δhr) and weaker bradycardia (high Δhr; respectively containing the trials with the 33% lowest vs highest Δhr values). Model predictions are plotted as predicted approach probabilities. Error bars indicate +/-1 SEM; asterisks (*) indicate ‘significant’ effects, hash icons (#) indicate ‘marginally significant’ effects, n.s.: not ‘significant’; m: money; s: shocks.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS190975-f004"/></fig><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>Neural circuits underlying the link between bradycardia states and value-based computations.</title><p><bold>A)</bold> For the base model, we find positive correlations between model-extracted decision values (DVs, indicating the value of approaching vs. avoiding) and BOLD activity in the ventral striatum (vStr) and ventromedial prefrontal cortex (vmPFC), delineating a similar neural circuit as was observed from the task-based analysis (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>). <bold>B)</bold> DVs estimated from the aversive value (AV) model were, relative to the base model, negatively correlated with BOLD activity in the amygdala (top). A follow-up analysis revealed that this negative relationship was specific to conditions in which AV predicted more avoidance, compared to the base model (i.e., <italic>DVdiff<sub>AV</sub></italic> &gt; 0; bottom). <bold>C)</bold> DVs estimated from the value comparison (VC) model were, relative to the base model, positively correlated to BOLD in alarge whole brain-significant cluster in the dorsomedial prefrontal cortex (dmPFC), spanning the SMA and dACC (top). Follow-up analysis revealed that this relationship was specific to conditions in which VC predicted more approach, compared to the base model (i.e., DvdiffVC &lt; 0; bottom). <italic>Dvdiff<sub>AV/VC</sub></italic>: trial-wise difference scores of the DVs of AV/VC models relative to the base model. Positive/negative <italic>Dvdiff<sub>AV/VC</sub></italic> values indicate stronger predicted probability to avoid/approach by AV/VC models compared to the base model. All labelled areas are significant at p &lt; .05 FWE-corrected.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS190975-f005"/></fig></floats-group></article>