<!DOCTYPE article
 PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" article-type="preprint"><?all-math-mml yes?><?use-mml?><?origin ukpmcpa?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">bioRxiv</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>bioRxiv : the preprint server for biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub"/></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">EMS189981</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2023.10.18.562983</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="archive">PPR745911</article-id><article-version-alternatives><article-version article-version-type="status">preprint</article-version><article-version article-version-type="number">1</article-version></article-version-alternatives><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Fine needle aspiration of human lymph nodes reveals cell populations and soluble interactors pivotal to immunological priming</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Provine</surname><given-names>Nicholas M</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CR1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Al-Diwani</surname><given-names>Adam</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Agarwal</surname><given-names>Devika</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Dooley</surname><given-names>Kyla</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Heslington</surname><given-names>Amelia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Murchison</surname><given-names>Andrew G</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A6">6</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN1">#</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Garner</surname><given-names>Lucy C</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sheerin</surname><given-names>Fintan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A6">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Klenerman</surname><given-names>Paul</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">5</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A7">7</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Irani</surname><given-names>Sarosh R</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A8">8</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Pandemic Sciences Institute, Nuffield Department of Medicine, University of Oxford, UK</aff><aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Oxford Autoimmune Neurology Group, Nuffield Department of Clinical Neurosciences, University of Oxford, UK</aff><aff id="A3"><label>3</label>University Department of Psychiatry, University of Oxford, UK</aff><aff id="A4"><label>4</label>Wellcome Centre for Human Genetics, Nuffield Department of Medicine, University of Oxford, UK</aff><aff id="A5"><label>5</label>Translational Gastroenterology Unit, Nuffield Department of Medicine, University of Oxford, UK</aff><aff id="A6"><label>6</label>Department of Radiology, Oxford University Hospitals NHS Foundation Trust, UK</aff><aff id="A7"><label>7</label>Peter Medawar Building for Pathogen Research, Nuffield Department of Medicine, University of Oxford, UK</aff><aff id="A8"><label>8</label>Department of Neurology, John Radcliffe Hospital, Oxford University Hospitals, UK</aff><author-notes><fn id="FN1"><label>#</label><p id="P1">Present address: Department of Radiology, Buckinghamshire Healthcare Trust, UK</p></fn><corresp id="CR1">
<label>*</label>Correspondence to Nicholas Provine (<email>nicholas.provine@ndm.ox.ac.uk</email>)</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted"><day>23</day><month>10</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="preprint"><day>21</day><month>10</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><permissions><ali:free_to_read/><license><ali:license_ref>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is licensed under a <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">CC BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p id="P2">Lymph node (LN) fine needle aspiration (LN FNA) represents a powerful technique for minimally invasive sampling of human lymph nodes <italic>in vivo</italic> and has been used to good effect to directly study aspects of the human germinal center response. However, systematic deep phenotyping of the cellular populations and cell-free proteins recovered by LN FNA has not been performed. Thus, we studied human cervical LN FNAs as a proof-of-concept and used single-cell RNA-sequencing and proteomic analysis to benchmark this compartment, define the purity of LN FNA material, and facilitate future studies into this immunologically pivotal environment. Our data provide evidence that LN FNAs contain <italic>bone fide</italic> LN-resident innate immune populations, with minimal contamination of cells or proteins from blood. Examination of these populations reveals unique biology not predictable from equivalent blood-derived populations. LN FNA supernatants represent a specific source of lymph- and lymph node-derived proteins, and can, in combination with transcriptomic approaches, identify likely receptor-ligand interactions. This study provides the first description of the types and abundance of immune cell populations and cell-free proteins that can be efficiently studied by LN FNA. These findings are of broad utility for understanding LN physiology both in health and disease, including infectious or autoimmune perturbations, and in the case of cervical nodes, neuroscience.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec id="S1" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p id="P3">The first step in the induction of adaptive cellular and humoral immune responses requires the priming of naïve T and B cells. To increase the likelihood of interaction between rare naïve lymphocytes and their cognate antigen, and to localize critical accessory cell populations, this process primarily occurs within highly specialized secondary lymphoid organs (SLOs) – the spleen and peripheral lymph nodes (LNs). Priming often begins with the trafficking of migratory dendritic cells (DCs), carrying tissue antigens, through lymphatics to the LN (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref>). Thereafter, conventional DCs (cDCs) may process and present antigen in complex with HLA molecules to prime naïve T cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">2</xref>). Additionally, specialized LN stromal cells - follicular dendritic cells (FDCs) - capture and retain antigen-rich immune complexes for induction of B cell responses, which supports the development of the germinal center (GC) reaction with consequent B cell affinity maturation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">3</xref>). Local soluble factors, including specific chemokines and cytokines, have a critical role in the priming of both T and B cell responses. Thus, the highly tissue-restricted nature of these processes means direct access to lymphoid tissue is a necessity to study immune priming events.</p><p id="P4">Several practical issues exist around sampling secondary lymphoid tissue in humans. Firstly, due to the anatomy of the lymphatics system, one, or a few, region-specific “draining” LNs may be specifically involved in any single immune priming process. For example, elegant work in recent years has established that cervical LNs of the head and neck drain cerebral lymphatics (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">4</xref>). Yet, it is not known how many of the seven distinct cervical LN basins are relevant to CNS immunology. Secondly, immune priming is a highly temporally regulated response and examination of lymphoid tissue in the steady state may bear little relation to the processes occurring during the early days of an immune response (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref>). Thus, to study disease-relevant events both the precise target LN and the time of sampling must be established.</p><p id="P5">To overcome these issues, in the past five years, ultrasound-guided lymph node fine needle aspiration (LN FNA) has been employed to allow minimally invasive, directly visualized, and time-resolved sampling of specific LNs in volunteers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref>). This is particularly pertinent when mapping the spatial and time-dependent priming processes which occur in the GC response. We have previously applied LN FNA to ask whether cervical LNs are involved in the pathogenesis of autoantibody-mediated brain disease (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref>). Others have utilized LN FNA in healthy volunteers to examine the GC response to HIV (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">8</xref>), influenza (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>), or SARS-CoV-2 virus vaccines (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref>). This approach has permitted studying both B cells and T follicular helper (T<sub>FH</sub>) cells, which support GC formation and maintenance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref>). These studies all obtained robust lymphocyte populations and have focused on the effector phase of lymphocyte function within the LN. Innate immune cell populations, which are pertinent to both GC reactions and T cell priming, were not examined in detail.</p><p id="P6">Thus, it remains to be established if LN FNA is a suitable technique to examine the innate and adaptive immune cell interactions so critical for immune priming. Furthermore, with the exception of our focused investigations of CXCL13 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref>) and autoantibody levels (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref>), in the context of immunology, LN FNA studies have primarily examined cellular fractions. Hence, it remains unclear if the technique is broadly suitable for studying soluble factors within LNs, including cytokines and antigens.</p><p id="P7">To address these questions, we performed single-cell RNA-sequencing (scRNA-seq) with surface protein quantification and high-dimensionality proteomic analysis of cervical LN FNA material and matched blood across four healthy volunteers. We found LN-resident innate immune populations can be efficiently recovered by FNA, and examination of these populations revealed plausible, LN-specific cell-cell interactions. Furthermore, proteomic analysis of cell-free LN FNA material identified proteins not detectable in blood, including candidate lymph-derived material, with utility for neuroimmunology studies. This study demonstrates the utility of LN FNA in addressing these aspects of immune priming directly in vivo using human volunteers and creates an early LN atlas of cells and soluble interactors with significant utility for multiple applications in human autoimmune diseases, cancers, and vaccinations.</p></sec><sec id="S2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="S3"><title>Annotation of immune populations recovered from LN FNA</title><p id="P8">To investigate the feasibility of using LN FNA to study innate immune crosstalk we utilized single-cell RNA-sequencing (scRNA-seq) and high-dimensionality proteomics on cervical LN aspirates and matched peripheral blood from four healthy volunteers (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1A</xref>). Our sorting strategy was devised to enrich for innate immune populations and removed the high proportion of naïve T and B cells present in the LN aspirates of our young, healthy participants. Three populations of cells were separately sorted from each sample: non-T/non-B (live, CD45<sup>+</sup>CD3<sup>−</sup>CD19<sup>−</sup>), non-naïve T cells (live, CD45<sup>+</sup>CD3<sup>+</sup> and NOT CD45RA<sup>+</sup>CD27<sup>+</sup>), and non-naïve B cells (live, CD45<sup>+</sup>CD19<sup>+</sup> and NOT IgD<sup>+</sup>CD27<sup>−</sup>) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplemental Figure 1</xref>). The three sorted populations were recombined at an approximately 1:1:1 ratio and libraries were prepared using the 10x Genomics platform.</p><p id="P9">After data QC and clean-up, we had 19,154 high-quality cells (11,694 from PBMC and 7,460 from LN). Following clustering and batch correction, both tissue sources were found to contribute to all clusters (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1B</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1C</xref>), although to varying degrees (discussed below). To annotate clusters, we utilized the Azimuth algorithm (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref>) to perform automated reference mapping using both a reference PBMC dataset (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref>), and a recently published atlas of human tonsil tissue (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref>). Annotations were refined using expert knowledge to give a total of 28 annotated clusters (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1C</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1D</xref>), with ADT protein data used to assist cluster annotation (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplemental Figure 2A</xref>).</p><p id="P10">Cluster annotation using the reference PBMC dataset L2 annotation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1E</xref>) generated high confidence scores for blood and LN-origin cells (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplemental Figure 2B</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">2C</xref>). Level 1 annotation of the reference tonsil dataset also gave high confidence mapping (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplemental Figure 2B</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">C</xref>), but the annotations revealed limited granularity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1F</xref>). By contrast, reference mapping using the level 2 tonsil annotations identified multiple innate subsets in our samples which specifically associated with lymphoid tissue (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1G</xref>). These were identified within dendritic cells (DCs), innate lymphocytes (ILCs) and natural killer (NK) cells. High resolution of the B cell and T cell compartments was also achieved, including identification of GC-associated B and T cell populations. However, given the 137 unique cluster annotations these mapped with lower confidence (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplemental Figure 2B</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">2C</xref>). Nonetheless, our data indicate an efficient recovery of multiple important innate immune populations within the LN.</p><p id="P11">To avoid over-fitting, we annotated clusters without over-reliance on the level 2 tonsil reference annotations. Consistent with the FACS analysis, no cells classifiable as naïve CD4<sup>+</sup> or CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells were identified, alongside only a small residual naïve B cell cluster (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1C</xref>). We identified a T<sub>FH</sub> cluster that uniquely expressed <italic>PDCD1</italic> (and CD279 protein) and <italic>CXCR5</italic>, and was highest for <italic>ICOS</italic> and <italic>CD40LG</italic> expression (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1C</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1D</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplemental Figure 2A</xref>). We clearly identified multiple innate immune populations: cDC1s (gene: <italic>CST3, XCR1, CLEC9A;</italic> protein: CD141<sup>hi</sup>), cDC2s (gene: <italic>CST3, CD1C, FCER1A</italic>; protein: CD1c<sup>hi</sup>), and plasmacytoid DCs (pDCs; gene: <italic>CST3, CLEC4C, IL3R</italic>; protein: CD303<sup>hi</sup>, CD123<sup>hi</sup>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1C</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1D</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplemental Figure 2A</xref>). Separate ILC (gene: <italic>KLRB1, IL7R;</italic> protein: Lineage<sup>−</sup>CD161<sup>+</sup>CD127<sup>+</sup>) and hematopoietic stem and progenitor cell populations were also observed (HSPCs; gene: <italic>CD34</italic>; protein: Lineage<sup>−</sup>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1C</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1D</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplemental Figure 2A</xref>). Within NK cells, we identified a population that expressed low levels of CD56 and CD16 (at gene and protein level), but still expressed other NK cell markers (e.g., <italic>NKG7</italic>), a phenotype previously associated with lymphoid tissue (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref>). Collectively, these data demonstrate recovery of innate immune cell populations from the LN in addition to other biologically relevant tissue-specific populations.</p></sec><sec id="S4"><title>Relative abundance of cell populations in blood versus lymph node</title><p id="P12">We noted that after more than one needle pass, aspirates could be discolored red, which was associated with a red cell pellet during density centrifugation. Hence, we sought to determine the degree of low-level blood contamination in the cellular and molecular fractions of the LN sample.</p><p id="P13">From the cellular perspective, we specifically examined the abundance of cells across each cluster contributed by blood or LN samples (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>). Encouragingly, the Vδ2<sup>+</sup> γδT cell, MAIT cell, CD14<sup>+</sup> monocyte, and CD16<sup>+</sup> monocyte clusters predominantly consisted of cells from the blood (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2A</xref>), consistent with their reported paucity within SLOs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref>). Further supporting the notion that blood contamination was a minor concern, T<sub>FH</sub> cells, all B cell populations, pDCs, and cDC1s were all over-represented in LN FNA-origin material (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2A</xref>). To analyze this in a formal manner, we performed differential abundance analysis between blood and LN (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="S10">methods</xref>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">20</xref>). Blood origin cells were significantly enriched within the CD14<sup>+</sup> monocyte and CD16<sup>+</sup> monocyte clusters, as well as MAIT cell and Vδ2<sup>+</sup> γδT cell clusters (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2B</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2C</xref>). Conversely, neighborhoods consisting of switched (IgM<sup>−</sup>) and unswitched (IgM<sup>+</sup>) memory B cells, T<sub>FH</sub> cells, and CD16<sup>−</sup>CD56<sup>lo</sup> NK cells were enriched in LN.</p><p id="P14">A particular strength of the <italic>k</italic>-nearest neighbor approach is the ability to examine changes in population abundance at a sub-cluster resolution (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">20</xref>). We utilized neighborhoods identified by this tool to annotate cells which did not form unique clusters but appeared potentially interesting in LN-specific populations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2D</xref>), based on <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1G</xref>. Using the tonsil atlas Level 2 annotations, non-class switched memory B cells (ncsMBC), class switched memory B cells (csMBC), and all identified T<sub>FH</sub> populations (GC-Tfh-OX40, CM PreTfh, non-GC-Tf-regs, Tfh-LZ-GC, and GC-Tfh-SAP) were enriched in LN (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2D</xref>). Furthermore, and consistent with the cluster-level analysis, MAIT cell and monocyte neighborhoods were enriched in blood whereas CD16<sup>−</sup>CD56<sup>−</sup> NK cell-containing neighborhoods were enriched in LN (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2D</xref>). Collectively, these data demonstrate LN FNA can efficiently recover tissue-specific populations including LN-specific innate immune cells.</p></sec><sec id="S5"><title>Differentially expressed genes and proteins between blood and lymph nodes</title><p id="P15">Next, we determined if the same cell clusters identified in blood and LN exhibited different transcriptional programs and expression of surface proteins. Nearly all clusters showed differentially expressed genes in blood or LN (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3A</xref>), with expression changes most pronounced in the T and B cell clusters (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3A</xref>). The high number of differentially expressed genes may reflect the presence of multiple distinct cell subsets with these clusters, based on the Azimuth annotations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1G</xref>) and neighborhood analysis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2D</xref>). The CD16<sup>−</sup>CD56<sup>lo</sup> NK cell subset was the population with the greatest number of upregulated genes in both blood (246 genes up) and LNs (272 genes up; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD5">Supplemental Table 1</xref>). By contrast, the innate-like T cell populations (MAIT cells and Vδ2<sup>+</sup> γδT cells) had relatively few differentially expressed genes, consistent with their highly conserved programs across tissues (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">21</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">22</xref>). Innate immune populations were variable — monocytes, pDCs, and cDC1s differentially expressed few if any genes, while cDC2s (20 genes up in LN and 36 genes up in blood) and ILCs (17 genes up in LN and 14 genes up in blood) had greater differences between the two tissues (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3A</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD5">Supplemental Table 1</xref>). Interestingly, these patterns did not correspond to differentially expressed proteins which showed no bias towards increased variability within the T or B cell clusters (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3B</xref>). However, for nearly all populations, the LN cells showed significantly more upregulated proteins than blood (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3B</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD5">Supplemental Table 2</xref>). There were a few genes (and corresponding proteins) that were enriched in nearly all populations in each tissue (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3C</xref>): <italic>CD69</italic>, CD69 protein, <italic>FOS</italic>, and <italic>JUN</italic> were up in LN; <italic>ITGA4</italic> and CD49d protein in blood.</p><p id="P16">When studying DC populations critical for immune response initiation, we identified <italic>FOS</italic> as the only significantly differentially expressed gene between pDCs in blood and LN (up in LN; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3D</xref>), and the nine significantly differentially proteins displayed gradations of expression between blood and LN (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD3">Supplemental Figure 3A</xref>). In contrast, the 56 differentially expressed genes and 15 proteins in the cDC2 cluster displayed a strong separation between blood and LN (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3D</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD3">Supplemental Figure 3B</xref>). These genes broadly aligned with the differences between DC2 (e.g., <italic>HLA-DQB2, CD1E, ARL4C</italic>) and DC3 (e.g., <italic>S100A8, VAN, S100A9</italic>) subpopulations previously identified in human blood (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">23</xref>), which represent two states of CD1c<sup>+</sup> DCs (“cDC2”) with lower or higher inflammatory signatures, respectively. Using GSEA analysis, the DC2 signature was confirmed to be enriched within LN (NES = 2.35, <italic>P<sub>adj</sub></italic> = 4.4e<sup>−9</sup>), while the DC3 signature was enriched in blood (NES = −2.62, <italic>P<sub>adj</sub></italic> = 9.3e<sup>−11</sup>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3E</xref>). These data suggest cDC2s exhibit a LN-specific profile, in contrast to cDC1 and pDCs that are similar across blood and lymphoid tissue.</p><p id="P17">ILCs consist of multiple transcriptionally distinct subsets with unique functions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref>). We identified distinct ILC subsets between the two anatomic sites (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD3">Supplemental Figure 3B</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD3">3C</xref>), with analysis showing a strong ILC3 signature within LN (NES = 3.38, <italic>P<sub>adj</sub></italic> = 3.8e<sup>−39</sup>) and, conversely, strong signatures of ILC1s (NES = −3.22, <italic>P<sub>adj</sub></italic> = 3.3e<sup>−25</sup>) and ILC2s (NES = −2.07, <italic>P<sub>adj</sub></italic> = 3.4e<sup>−5</sup>) in the blood (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3F</xref>). Thus, LN ILCs appear to be a distinct population from those found in circulation.</p></sec><sec id="S6"><title>LN-derived cells show greater predicted cell-cell interactions</title><p id="P18">One of our underlying hypotheses was that tissue sampling would reveal unique insights not available by studying blood. To test this, we utilized our single-cell sequencing data to examine predicted cell-cell interactions between cells within the blood or LN. CellPhoneDB (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">26</xref>) predicted an overall greater number of cell-cell interactions between cells in the LN compared with blood (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4A</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4B</xref>). In both tissues, most predicted interactions were between monocytes and NK cells. Compared with blood, LN T and B cell clusters had many more predicted interactions.</p><p id="P19">To examine this more systematically, we examined predicted cell-cell interactions for populations with known biologic importance. For example, cDC1 cells have the unique ability to cross-present antigen, and thus play a critical role in the priming of CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27">27</xref>). Accordingly, we examined predicted interactions between cDC1 cells and CD8<sup>+</sup> T<sub>EM</sub> cells and stratified these based on whether they were generated from our data on blood cells, LN cells, or from either source (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4C</xref>). Thirty-five interactions were predicted regardless of which tissue source was used, including the traditional “signal 2” pathway of CD86-CD28 and the interaction of XCL1/XCL2 with XCR1 (the canonical marker of cDC1 cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">28</xref>)). Thirty-five additional interactions were predicted only by examining LN cells: these included IFNγ signaling via its receptor and CXCL9 interactions with CXCR3, a critical chemokine axis for CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">29</xref>). By contrast, only two interactions were uniquely predicted based on data from the blood.</p><p id="P20">Similarly, with regards to key GC-based T<sub>FH</sub>–B cell interactions, we identified a greater number of predicted pathways in the LN relative to blood (29 versus 6, with 26 additional pathways overlapping between tissues; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4D</xref>). The canonical CD40L-CD40 signaling pathway (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">30</xref>), was predicted for the interaction of T<sub>FH</sub> cells with both IgM<sup>+</sup> and switched memory B cells, regardless of tissue origin. In contrast, IFNγ produced by T<sub>FH</sub> cells was a uniquely predicted as a signaling pathway to both IgM<sup>+</sup> and switched memory B cells in the LN and not in the blood. Differential interactions within a tissue were also predicted: IL-6 signaling was uniquely associated with signaling between T<sub>FH</sub> cells and IgM<sup>+</sup> memory B cells. While IL-4 produced by T<sub>FH</sub> cells was uniquely associated with signaling to switched memory B cells, consistent with its established importance in class-switch recombination (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31">31</xref>). Thus, these data validate and extend the importance of directly examining lymphoid tissue when considering pathways of interest for immune cell interactions.</p></sec><sec id="S7"><title>Lymph node aspirate supernatants are a source of unique proteins</title><p id="P21">Having validated the ability of cells collected by LN FNA to provide unique insights into SLO biology, we sought to determine if the aspirate supernatants could contribute orthogonal biologically pertinent information. To this end, we performed highly multiplexed proteomic analysis using the Olink Inflammation I and Neurology I assays using LN supernatants or blood. As two FNA passes (needles) were performed per participant, and each needle was flushed four times with PBS to facilitate cell recovery, we first sought to determine whether this impacted on protein recovery. The highest protein quantities (NPX) were recovered from the first flush of either needle, with particularly good recovery from the first wash of the second needle (LN needle 2; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5A</xref>). Consistent with minimal blood contamination observed at the cellular level (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>) and our previous observation of log-fold lower IgG in LN aspirates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref>), proteomic analysis on capillary blood processed in the same manner as the FNA supernatant consistently recovered less material than LN needle 2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5B</xref>). Additionally, an equivalent volume of serum also resulted in lower protein recovery (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5B</xref>).</p><p id="P22">Between donors, there was a high concordance of the recovered proteins in LN needle 2 and their concentrations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5C</xref>). There was a subset of proteins detected in blood but not in the FNA supernatants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5C</xref>, red text). The proteins differentially detected between participants showed overall lower abundances than the proteins readily detected in both samples of the pairwise comparison (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 3.9e<sup>−5</sup>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5C</xref>). In contrast, the correlation of protein concentration and detection of specific proteins was much more variable for LN needle 1 (first wash of needle 1; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD4">Supplemental Figure 4A</xref>). Inter-sample correlation analysis of capillary blood (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD4">Supplemental Figure 4B</xref>) and diluted serum (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD4">Supplemental Figure 4C</xref>) showed highly concordant abundance patterns. However, there were a much larger number of proteins not detected in either of these samples as compared to the LN aspirates.</p><p id="P23">Next, we asked if lymphatic proteins draining into the node can be detected by FNA by comparing the proteins detected in the LN needle 2 and matched capillary blood. On average there were 300 proteins (of 722 total analytes) specifically detected in the LN aspirates (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5D</xref>). Comparison of LN needle 2 and matched serum showed a slightly greater overlap, but still on average approximately 175 proteins were specifically detected by LN FNA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5E</xref>). LN needle 1 again proved less useful (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD4">Supplemental Figure 4D</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD4">E</xref>). From a comparison of the proteins specifically found in the LN aspirates (needle 2), 152 proteins were found in all 3 samples (31.7%; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5F</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD5">Supplemental Table 3</xref>). A comparison of specifically detected proteins in all three LN aspirates relative to serum also found 31% overlap, consisting of 93 proteins (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD4">Supplemental Figure 4F</xref>).</p><p id="P24">Several of the proteins specifically detected in the LN aspirates of all three participants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5F</xref>) include TREM2, ADAM22, NTF3, and NMNAT1 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD5">Supplemental Table 3</xref>), all of which have well-documented roles in neuronal and microglial function (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32">32</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35">35</xref>). As the cervical LNs sampled are thought to drain the dural sinuses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">4</xref>), we postulated that detection of these proteins in LN aspirates would suggest sampling of lymphatic-associated material. To examine this more formally, ontology analysis was performed on the proteins specifically detected in the LN supernatant. In addition to enrichment for expected terms around immune function (e.g., T cell activation or humoral immune response), several terms associated with neuronal development, differentiation, and survival were enriched (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5G</xref>). Many of the same terms were also enriched relative to serum (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD4">Supplemental Figure 4G</xref>). Thus, examination of the supernatant from LN aspirates is a fruitful means of identifying proteins specifically associated with the LN, whether they are produced locally or traffic from the lymph.</p></sec><sec id="S8"><title>Integration of proteomic and transcriptomic analysis</title><p id="P25">Finally, we sought to integrate proteomic and single-cell transcriptomic analyses towards LN specific receptor-ligand pathways. The list of 152 proteins specifically identified in LN (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5F</xref>) was subset to a list of 96 proteins robustly detected within the transcriptomic data (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6A</xref>). Expression levels of the genes were then visualized per cluster using only cells from the LN. Some genes such as <italic>JUN, RABGAP1L</italic>, and <italic>IL16</italic> had broad expression across the clusters (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6A</xref>). Enrichment of <italic>CLEC4C</italic> was detected only in pDCs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6A</xref>), consistent with its use as a canonical marker of this population (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36">36</xref>). Other interesting protein-producer cell pairings included CD200, which was strongly associated with T<sub>FH</sub> cells and CCL3 which was strongly associated with the CD16<sup>−</sup>CD56<sup>lo</sup> NK cell subset (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6A</xref>).</p><p id="P26">An alternative use for the proteomic data is to have it guide analysis of cell-cell interactions. For example, IL-6 was specifically detected in the LN aspirates (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD5">Supplemental Table 3</xref>), and examination of predicted cell-cell interactions using CellPhoneDB revealed all B cell clusters except switched memory B cells as possible sources of IL-6 with a potential signaling to essentially all CD4<sup>+</sup> T cell clusters as well as CD14<sup>+</sup> monocytes and cDC2s (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6B</xref>). CRTAM was another protein specifically detected in supernatants of LN aspirates (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD5">Supplemental Table 3</xref>), which has a role in activation of CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells and NK cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37">37</xref>). Consistent with this, <italic>CRTAM</italic> was mostly highly expressed by CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells and NK cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6A</xref>). Its ligand (<italic>CADM1</italic>) was expressed by cDC1s, plasmablasts, and cycling cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6C</xref>) – which appear to be cycling GC cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1G</xref>) – and suggest a possible mechanism of NK-mediated regulation of GC function (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38">38</xref>). In sum, merging these modalities can provide insights into specific cellular sources of LN proteins of interest or can inform on signaling pathways of interest through protein-guided validation.</p></sec></sec><sec id="S9" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p id="P27">In this project, we sought to provide proof-of-concept of the utility of LN FNA to examine immune parameters beyond the main prior immunologic area of focus, GC B cell and T<sub>FH</sub> cell biology, and into innate immune cells relevant to priming. We performed unbiased scRNA-seq on recovered cells and high-dimensional proteomics on FNA supernatants. Dendritic cell and other innate immune subsets were detected in sufficient numbers for downstream analysis. Predicted cell-cell interaction analysis highlighted many pathways only predicted by examining LN material, thus reinforcing the importance of studying this tissue. Proteomic analysis also revealed proteins otherwise undetectable by sampling peripheral blood, and these could be further used to cross-validate putative signaling pathways of interest.</p><p id="P28">A technically important question surrounding fine needle aspiration is to what extent blood contamination contributes to the recovered populations, given the vascularized nature of the target tissue alongside the sampling process. In contrast to studies of GC B cells or T<sub>FH</sub> cells, this question is of more concern when examining cell types that have analogs in the circulation. Differential distribution of cell populations between blood and tissues has been the primary validator of the tissue-specific nature of the recovered sample. Prior work examining LN FNA purity has used very low abundance of granulocytes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref>) or monocytes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">8</xref>) as evidence. We confirm these findings through low abundance of monocytes, and also demonstrate low frequencies of MAIT cells and Vδ2<sup>+</sup> γδT cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref>). In addition, we identified an over-abundance of CD16<sup>−</sup>CD56<sup>lo</sup> NK cells, which have been reported in SLOs but are rare in blood (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39">39</xref>). Our detection of specific proteins only within the FNA supernatant further supports the specific nature of this sampling technique. Thus, we are confident that innate immune populations recovered by LN FNA are of genuine LN origin.</p><p id="P29">Differential gene expression analysis of DC subsets revealed few differentially expressed genes and proteins for cDC1 and pDC populations in the LN compared to blood. Prior comparison of human DC phenotype and morphology between blood and LN DCs reported similarities between these tissues (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40">40</xref>). scRNA-seq of blood DCs has revealed greater heterogeneity, especially within cDC2s and pDCs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">23</xref>). At a clustering level, we could not identify populations beyond the historical XCR1<sup>+</sup> cDC1, CD1c<sup>+</sup> cDC2, and BDCA2<sup>+</sup> pDC subsets. However, deeper investigation of the cDC2 cluster revealed distinct transcriptional programs suggesting a more “inflammatory” signature in blood origin cells and a “non-inflammatory” signature in LN origin cells. Thus, CD1c<sup>+</sup> DCs (cDC2 subset by classical naming) in the LN and blood appear to be quite different populations. The relative enrichment of “non-inflammatory” signature CD1c<sup>+</sup> DCs within the LN aligns with data from a recent tonsil atlas (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref>). That these co-clustered in our data may reflect a limitation of our sample size, given the relative scarcity of these cells (discussed below).</p><p id="P30">Despite detecting no differentially expressed genes between blood and LN origin cDC1s, a large number of cell-cell interactions were predicted only when examining LN-derived cells. This was primarily driven by the large number of differentially expressed genes on the second cell population (e.g., CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells) in the interacting pair. These data would suggest that these lymphoid populations change phenotype upon entry into the lymph node. Presumably in the context of an ongoing immune response a very different conclusion would be drawn due to activation of the innate immune cells by PAMPs/DAMPs – future studies will be needed to investigate this hypothesis.</p><p id="P31">One of the goals of the current study was to investigate orthogonal uses for LN FNA beyond cellular analysis to aid in understanding of immune processes within the lymph node. Lymph contains a proteome distinct from peripheral blood (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41">41</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42">42</xref>). Detection of proteins in the LN FNA supernatant that were not detectable from capillary blood or serum supports the conclusion that we are sampling lymph node tissue and/or lymph-associated proteins, as opposed to blood contaminants introduced by the procedure. There has been interest, particularly in cancer, in proteomic analysis of FNA supernatants – from possible malignant tissue or metastases containing LNs – to screen for the presence of cancer cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43">43</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R45">45</xref>). Such studies focus on detecting cellular abundance (i.e., presence of cancer cells). Our detection of CLEC4C and its association with abundance of pDCs supports the use of proteomic analysis in this way for immune cell populations. Another unique way to merge cell- and protein-level data, is the ability to use proteomics to investigate active signaling pathways. We have previously detected CXCL13 within the LN, which was correlated with autoantibody production (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref>). Our ready detection of hundreds of proteins within the LN FNA supernatant suggests this is an approach with wide utility.</p><p id="P32">Detection of proteins in the supernatant more strongly associated with CNS tissue, such as TREM2, ADAM22, NTF3, and NMNAT1, suggests possible detection of lymph-associated proteins. However, some of these proteins are reported as detectable in lymphoid tissue (Human Protein Atlas; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://proteinatlas.org">proteinatlas.org</ext-link>). This highlights a limitation of the current study: there was not sampling of a second lymph node site not associated with CNS drainage. Therefore, future studies with multiple anatomically separated sampling sites will be required to fully address this question. A second limitation of the current study is the relatively small sample size (number of donors and therefore number of cells). During ongoing immune reactions, lymph node cellularity increases substantially (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R46">46</xref>), which increases cell yields by FNA. There are multiple factors around the technique that impact on cell yields (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref>). Our participants did not have acute infection or ongoing neuroimmune disease, we only performed two FNA passes, and aspiration was not performed during the procedure. These factors all likely contributed to the number of cells recovered. Such factors should be carefully considered when designing an experimental plan, especially if studying rare cell populations (e.g., DCs).</p><p id="P33">In summary, we demonstrate the utility of LN FNA combined with omics approaches to study immune processes beyond the GC reaction. Such analysis of innate immune populations, and their interaction with adaptive immune subsets reveals biology not otherwise predicable based on blood sampling. These analyses can be augmented through use of LN FNA supernatants as a source of cell-free material to study pathways of interest. Finally, our dataset provides a useful reference for the cell populations, secreted proteins, and their abundances that can be reliably recovered by LN FNA, which provides a key benchmark when designing future studies using this approach. Detection of proteins associated with neuronal function is potentially compatible with detection of lymphatic drainage. Overall, these data provide a framework for future studies in the context of disease or other immune perturbations.</p></sec><sec id="S10" sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec id="S11"><title>Research ethics</title><p id="P34">Four donors (3 male, 1 female; 24 to 38 years of age) were consented for collection of lymph node material by fine needle aspiration (LN FNA) and matched blood (REC: 16/YH/0013). Informed written consent was received from all participants. All work was performed in accordance with relevant ethical regulation and was performed in compliance with the principles of the Declaration of Helsinki (2008).</p></sec><sec id="S12"><title>Lymph node sample collection and processing</title><p id="P35">Lymph node fine needle aspiration was performed on either level Ia/Ib (Donor 4) or Va (Donors 1-3) lymph nodes under ultrasound guidance as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref>). Two FNA passes were performed on the same lymph node using an identical approach. A sterile 23G 0.60×25 mm blue hypodermic needle (BD Bioscience) was inserted into the lymph node and via a repetitive corkscrew motion material was collected into the needle barrel via capillary action. The needle was withdrawn, and 1 ml of ice-cold, sterile PBS was aspirated through the bevel into a syringe. The needle was removed, and the material was released into a 1.5 ml microtube (Axygen). A total of 4 flushes of the needle were performed into separate collection tubes. The flushing process was repeated a total of four times into separate collection tubes. The process was then repeated for the second FNA pass using a fresh needle. All samples were stored on ice until processing.</p><p id="P36">Samples (8 tubes per participant) were spun down at 400 g for 5 min in a benchtop micro-centrifuge. Supernatant was carefully removed, transferred to a fresh 1.5 ml microtube, and stored at -80 °C for future use. Cell pellets were resuspended in 1 ml of R10 media (RPMI-1640 + 10% FBS + 1% Penicillin/Streptomycin) and combined into a single 15 ml conical. An additional 1 ml of R10 was used to wash and collect residual material. Samples were centrifuged at 931 g for 10 min, 4 °C. Supernatant was discarded and cells were resuspended in 2 ml of R10 and passed through a 30-micron filter into a 5 ml polystyrene FACS tube. An underlay of 2 ml of lymphoprep (STEMCELL technologies) was added. Cells were centrifuged at 931 g for 30 minutes with no brake. The mononuclear cell (MNC) layer was collected and transferred to a fresh 15 ml conical, which was topped up with 13 ml of R10. Cells were centrifuged at 754 g for 8 min and supernatant was discarded. Cells were resuspended in 500 μl of R10 and counted. The appropriate number of cells were used fresh for downstream applications.</p></sec><sec id="S13"><title>Capillary blood sample collection and processing</title><p id="P37">Capillary blood was collected from the index finger using a 1.5 mm safety lancet (Greiner Bio-one). Blood was collected into a 1.5 ml microtube. Blood was then drawn into a 23G 0.60×25 mm blue hypodermic needle (BD Bioscience), same as used for FNA, until the needle was full. The contents of the needle were flushed with 1 ml of ice-cold PBS into a fresh 1.5 ml microtube. This was done to replicate the experimental procedure used to collect LN FNA material. The diluted capillary blood was spun down at 400 g for 5 min in a benchtop micro-centrifuge. Supernatant was carefully removed, transferred to a fresh 1.5 ml microtube, and stored at -80 °C for future use.</p></sec><sec id="S14"><title>Veinous blood sample collection and processing</title><p id="P38">20 ml of peripheral blood was collected by venipuncture into an EDTA tube (BD Bioscience) for plasma and PBMC collection and 5 ml into an SST tube (BD Bioscience) for serum collection. After allowing to stand, SST tubes were spun down at 2000 g for 10 min. Serum was collected and frozen at -80 °C for future use.</p><p id="P39">To isolate peripheral blood mononuclear cells (PBMCs), EDTA blood was layered over 15 ml lymphoprep and centrifuged at 931 g for 30 minutes with no brake. The PBMC-containing layer was collected, transferred to a fresh 50 ml conical and topped up to 40 ml with R10 media. Samples were centrifuged at 754 g for 8 minutes and supernatant was discarded. Cells were washed an additional time with 40 ml of R10 before being counted. The appropriate number of cells were used fresh for downstream applications.</p></sec><sec id="S15"><title>Cell staining and FACS</title><p id="P40">Lymph node MNCs or PBMCs (5×10<sup>5</sup> cells) were added to a 96-well U-bottom plate. Cells were centrifuged at 1,126 g for 2 min and supernatant discarded. Cells were washed once with FACS buffer (PBS + 0.05% bovine serum albumin + 1 mM EDTA) and centrifuged at 1,126 g for 1 min. Supernatant was discarded and cells were stained for 10 min at 4 °C with 2.5 μl Human TruStain FcX block (BioLegend) and 22.5 μl FACS buffer. After staining, cells were centrifuged at 1,126 g for 1 min and supernatant was discarded. Cells were stained with a cocktail containing CD3-PE (clone: UCHT1; 1:100), IgD-PE-Dazzle594 (clone: IA6-2; 1:100), CD19-PE-Cy7 (clone: HIB19; 1:100), CD27-APC (clone: O323; 1:50), CD45-AF700 (clone: HI30; 1:100), CD45RA-BV785 (clone: HI100; 1:200). All antibodies were from BioLegend. Final staining volume was 25 μl and staining was performed for 10 min at 4 °C. TotalSeq-C Human Universal Cocktail V1.0 (BioLegend) was prepared per manufacturer’s instructions and added to the cells without washing. Staining was performed for an additional 30 min at 4 °C. After staining, cells were washed 3 times with FACS buffer, resuspended in 200 μl of FACS buffer and transferred to a 1.5ml microtube. DAPI was added at a final concentration of 3 nM and samples were stored at 4 °C until sorting.</p><p id="P41">Sorting was performed on a BD FACSAria III (BD Bioscience) using an 85-micron nozzle. Three populations were collected: non-T/non-B (live, CD45<sup>+</sup>CD3<sup>−</sup>CD19<sup>−</sup>), non-naïve T cells (live, CD45<sup>+</sup>CD3<sup>+</sup> and NOT CD45RA<sup>+</sup>CD27<sup>+</sup>), and non-naïve B cells (live, CD45<sup>+</sup>CD19<sup>+</sup> and NOT IgD<sup>+</sup>CD27<sup>−</sup>). This sorting scheme resulted in a minor contamination of naïve B cells, confirmed in the scRNA-seq data, but nearly 100% purity of the other populations (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplemental Figure 1</xref>). Cells were sorted into R20 (RPMI-1640 + 20% FBS + 1% Penicillin/Streptomycin) and kept at 4 °C. Flow cytometry data was analyzed using FlowJo (v 10.8.1; Becton Dickinson &amp; Company).</p></sec><sec id="S16"><title>Single-cell RNA-sequencing library preparation</title><p id="P42">The three sorted cell populations were combined into a single tube, with 4,000 cells (or the entire population if &lt; 4,000 sorted cells) from each population. Samples were centrifuged at 400 g for 5 minutes, washed once with loading buffer (PBS + 0.04% bovine serum albumin), and resuspended at an appropriate volume in loading buffer for incorporation into the 10x Genomics Chromium Next GEM Single Cell 5’ v2 (Dual Index) workflow. One sample (∼12,000 cells) was loaded per channel of the Chromium Controller. Gene expression libraries and cell surface protein (“ADT”) libraries were prepared according to manufacturer’s instructions. Sequencing was performed at the Oxford Genomics Centre (University of Oxford) on a Novaseq 6000 per manufacturer’s instructions. Illumina’s bcl2fastq was used to generate FASTQ files.</p></sec><sec id="S17"><title>Proteomic analysis</title><p id="P43">Lymph node FNA supernatant, capillary blood supernatant, and serum (pre-diluted 1:100 in PBS to approximate the volume of blood drawn by aspiration needle) were run using the Olink Explore 384 Inflammation I and Neurology I panels per manufacturer’s instructions (performed at the Oxford Genomics Centre). Proteins that were not detected in any samples were excluded from downstream analysis. Duplicate proteins (TNF, IL6, CXCL8) were removed from the dataset by keeping data only from the Neurology I panel. Proteins with an NPX value &gt; −12 in the first sample and ≤ −12 in the second sample were defined as unique to the first sample. A series of t-tests (per donor pair) was performed to examine differences in NPX levels between proteins concordantly and discordantly detected across samples. The most conservative <italic>P</italic> value is reported. GO term analysis was performed using clusterProfiler (v 4.6.2)(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R47">47</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R48">48</xref>) using the BP (Biological Process) ontogeny. Enriched sets were trimmed to include only those with &gt; 5% of GO term list found in our query data. Particular GO terms of interest were manually selected from this list for visualization.</p></sec><sec id="S18"><title>Data QC and clean-up</title><p id="P44">Sequencing reads were mapped to the GRCh38-2020-A reference genome using CellRanger multi v7.0.1 and a custom marker list was provided for ADT mapping. Median reads per cell was between 36,000 and 262,000 for gene expression data and 3,300 and 20,000 for ADT data. Data was imported into Seurat (v 4.3.0) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref>) and low-quality cells (UMI count &lt; 900, RNA count &lt; 1,300, or percent mitochondrial reads &gt; 6.5%) were removed. Doublets were flagged and removed (except from the cycling cell cluster) using scDblFinder (v 1.12.0) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R49">49</xref>). Immunoglobulin and T cell receptor gene segments, identified from the IMGT database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://imgt.org">imgt.org</ext-link>), were removed from the gene expression object, except for the following genes: <italic>IGHM, IGHG1, IGHG2, IGHG3, IGHG4, IGHD, IGHE, IGHA1, TRAV1-2, TRAV24, TRDV1, TRDV2, TRDV3</italic>. Gene expression data were log normalized, variable features identified, and scaled using default Seurat parameters. The optimal number of PCs (45 dimensions) was determined by a combination of an elbow plot, and manual inspection of PCs. ADT protein data was normalized using the CLR method (margin = 2) and scaled. Clusering was performed using Seurat’s graph-based approach (Louvain algorithm). Harmony (v 0.1.1) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R50">50</xref>) was used to integrate data across donors.</p></sec><sec id="S19"><title>Cluster annotation</title><p id="P45">Cluster annotation was performed using a combination of expert knowledge and the Azimuth web tool (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://azimuth.hubmapconsortium.org">azimuth.hubmapconsortium.org</ext-link>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref>). PBMC (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref>) and human tonsil (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref>) datasets were used as references. An optimal clustering resolution of 1.2 was selected with input from Clustree (v 0.5.0). A multimodal weighted nearest neighbor integration approach (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref>) was investigated, but was not felt to improve cluster annotation, so was not pursued (not shown).</p></sec><sec id="S20"><title>Differential abundance analysis</title><p id="P46">Differential abundance testing was performed using miloR (v 1.7.1) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">20</xref>). Specified parameters were k = 30, d = 30, prop = 0.1. The design was ∼ tissue. plotDAbeeswarm was used without removing mixed populations.</p></sec><sec id="S21"><title>Differential gene expression</title><p id="P47">Differential gene expression and differential protein expression analysis was performed using MAST (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R51">51</xref>) using the Seurat FindMarkers function on a per-cluster basis comparing blood and lymph node as the two conditions, with donor as a latent variable. Significant DEGs were defined as padj &lt; 0.05. Differentially expressed genes and proteins were visualized using FeaturePlot or DoHeatmap.</p></sec><sec id="S22"><title>Gene Set Enrichment Analysis</title><p id="P48">Gene Set Enrichment Analysis (GSEA) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R52">52</xref>) was performed using the fgsea package (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R53">53</xref>). Gene signatures for DC2 and DC3 subsets are from the DEGs listed in (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">23</xref>). The gene signature for ILC subsets was generated by taking the uniquely expressed genes for each subset from (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R54">54</xref>) and selecting only significantly upregulated genes within each cell subset. TCR gene segments, and ribosomal genes were removed, and the list was trimmed to 150 genes for ILC3s (ILC1 and ILC2 signatures already contained &lt; 150 genes). Data were visualized using plotGseaTable.</p></sec><sec id="S23"><title>Cell-cell interactions</title><p id="P49">Predicted cell-cell interactions were defined using CellPhoneDB (v 3.10) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R55">55</xref>) with database version 4.0.0. Blood and lymph node data were separately extracted from the Seurat object and run using cellphonedb method statistical_analysis --counts_data hgnc_symbol --threshold 0.1. Data visualization was performed by adapting the plotting functions included in the CellPhoneDB package (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/ventolab/CellphoneDB">https://github.com/ventolab/CellphoneDB</ext-link>).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="SM"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1"><label>Supplemental Figure 1</label><media xlink:href="EMS189981-supplement-Supplemental_Figure_1.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" id="d187aAdEbB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD2"><label>Supplemental Figure 2</label><media xlink:href="EMS189981-supplement-Supplemental_Figure_2.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" id="d187aAdEcB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD3"><label>Supplemental Figure 3</label><media xlink:href="EMS189981-supplement-Supplemental_Figure_3.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" id="d187aAdEdB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD4"><label>Supplemental Figure 4</label><media xlink:href="EMS189981-supplement-Supplemental_Figure_4.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" id="d187aAdEeB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD5"><label>Supplemental Captions</label><media xlink:href="EMS189981-supplement-Supplemental_Captions.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" id="d187aAdEfB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><sec id="S24" sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>All sequencing data is deposited in the GEO database (accession number XXXX). Analysis pipelines are available upon reasonable request.</p></sec><ack id="S25"><title>Acknowledgments</title><p id="P51">We thank the donors for their participation. We thank Helen Ferry for assistance with cell sorting. Analysis was performed using the MRC WIMM Centre for Computational Biology computing cluster. NMP is supported by a Wellcome Career Development Award [227217/Z/23/Z] and a Goodger &amp; Schorstein Scholarship. AAD is funded by a NIHR Clinical Lectureship and Academy of Medical Sciences Starter Grant for Clinical Lecturers (SGL027\1016). PK is supported by a Wellcome Senior Fellowship [222426/Z/21/Z]. SRI is supported by the Wellcome [104079/Z/14/Z], the Medical Research Council (MR/V007173/1), BMA Research Grants – Vera Down grant (2013), Margaret Temple (2017), Epilepsy Research UK (P1201), the Fulbright UK-US commission (MS Society research award), and by the National Institute for Health Research (NIHR) Oxford Biomedical Research Centre. The views expressed are those of the author(s) and not necessarily those of the NHS, the NIHR or the Department of Health.</p></ack><ref-list><ref id="R1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Steele</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lund</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Afferent Lymphatic Transport and Peripheral Tissue Immunity</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><year>2021</year><volume>206</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>264</fpage><lpage>272</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7789254</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33397740</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4049/jimmunol.2001060</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bevan</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effector and Memory CTL Differentiation</article-title><source>Annual Review of Immunology</source><year>2007</year><volume>25</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>171</fpage><lpage>192</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17129182</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vinuesa</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>T cells and follicular dendritic cells in germinal center B-cell formation and selection</article-title><source>Immunological reviews</source><year>2010</year><volume>237</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>72</fpage><lpage>89</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20727030</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Louveau</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Structural and functional features of central nervous system lymphatic vessels</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2015</year><volume>523</volume><issue>7560</issue><fpage>337</fpage><lpage>341</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4506234</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26030524</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature14432</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Catron</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Visualizing the First 50 Hr of the Primary Immune Response to a Soluble Antigen</article-title><source>Immunity</source><year>2004</year><volume>21</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>341</fpage><lpage>347</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15357945</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Al-Diwani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cervical lymph nodes and ovarian teratomas as germinal centres in NMDA receptor-antibody encephalitis</article-title><source>Brain</source><year>2022</year><volume>145</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>2742</fpage><lpage>2754</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9486890</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35680425</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/brain/awac088</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Damato</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Rituximab abrogates aquaporin-4–specific germinal center activity in patients with neuromyelitis optica spectrum disorders</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci</source><year>2022</year><volume>119</volume><issue>24</issue><elocation-id>e2121804119</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9214492</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35666871</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.2121804119</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Day</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Comparison of blood and lymph node cells after intramuscular injection with HIV envelope immunogens</article-title><source>Front Immunol</source><year>2022</year><volume>13</volume><elocation-id>991509</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9579690</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36275655</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2022.991509</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lederer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Germinal center responses to SARS-CoV-2 mRNA vaccines in healthy and immunocompromised individuals</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2022</year><volume>185</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1008</fpage><lpage>1024</lpage><elocation-id>e15</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8808747</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35202565</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2022.01.027</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Human germinal centres engage memory and naive B cells after influenza vaccination</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2020</year><volume>586</volume><issue>7827</issue><fpage>127</fpage><lpage>132</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7566073</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32866963</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41586-020-2711-0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Havenar-Daughton</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Normal human lymph node T follicular helper cells and germinal center B cells accessed via fine needle aspirations</article-title><source>J Immunol Methods</source><year>2020</year><volume>479</volume><elocation-id>112746</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7200018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31958451</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jim.2020.112746</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>SARS-CoV-2 mRNA vaccines induce persistent human germinal centre responses</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2021</year><volume>596</volume><issue>7870</issue><fpage>109</fpage><lpage>113</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8935394</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34182569</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41586-021-03738-2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Germinal centre-driven maturation of B cell response to mRNA vaccination</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2022</year><volume>604</volume><issue>7904</issue><fpage>141</fpage><lpage>145</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9204750</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35168246</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41586-022-04527-1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mudd</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>SARS-CoV-2 mRNA vaccination elicits a robust and persistent T follicular helper cell response in humans</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2022</year><volume>185</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>603</fpage><lpage>613</lpage><elocation-id>e15</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8695127</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35026152</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2021.12.026</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crotty</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>T Follicular Helper Cell Biology: A Decade of Discovery and Diseases</article-title><source>Immunity</source><year>2019</year><volume>50</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>1132</fpage><lpage>1148</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6532429</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31117010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.immuni.2019.04.011</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Integrated analysis of multimodal single-cell data</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2021</year><volume>184</volume><issue>13</issue><fpage>3573</fpage><lpage>3587</lpage><elocation-id>e29</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8238499</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34062119</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2021.04.048</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Massoni-Badosa</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>An Atlas of Cells in the Human Tonsil</article-title><source>Biorxiv</source><year>2022</year><elocation-id>2022.06.24.497299</elocation-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lepore</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Parallel T-cell cloning and deep sequencing of human MAIT cells reveal stable oligoclonal TCRβ repertoire</article-title><source>Nature Communications</source><year>2014</year><volume>5</volume><elocation-id>3866</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24832684</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eberhard</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>CD161+ MAIT Cells Are Severely Reduced in Peripheral Blood and Lymph Nodes of HIV-Infected Individuals Independently of Disease Progression</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2014</year><volume>9</volume><issue>11</issue><elocation-id>e111323</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4219715</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25369333</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0111323</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dann</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Differential abundance testing on single-cell data using k-nearest neighbor graphs</article-title><source>Nat Biotechnol</source><year>2022</year><volume>40</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>245</fpage><lpage>253</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34594043</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Garner</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Single-cell analysis of human MAIT cell transcriptional, functional and clonal diversity</article-title><source>Nat Immunol</source><year>2023</year><volume>24</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>1565</fpage><lpage>1578</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10457204</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37580605</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41590-023-01575-1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Provine</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Unique and Common Features of Innate-Like Human Vδ2+ γδT Cells and Mucosal-Associated Invariant T Cells</article-title><source>Frontiers in Immunology</source><year>2018</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>756</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5924964</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29740432</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2018.00756</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Villani</surname><given-names>A-C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Single-cell RNA-seq reveals new types of human blood dendritic cells, monocytes, and progenitors</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2017</year><volume>356</volume><issue>6335</issue><elocation-id>eaah4573-14</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5775029</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28428369</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.aah4573</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vivier</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Innate Lymphoid Cells: 10 Years On</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2018</year><volume>174</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>1054</fpage><lpage>1066</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30142344</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Efremova</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>CellPhoneDB: inferring cell–cell communication from combined expression of multi-subunit ligand–receptor complexes</article-title><source>Nat Protoc</source><year>2020</year><volume>15</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1484</fpage><lpage>1506</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32103204</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vento-Tormo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Single-cell reconstruction of the early maternal–fetal interface in humans</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2018</year><volume>563</volume><issue>7731</issue><fpage>347</fpage><lpage>353</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7612850</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30429548</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41586-018-0698-6</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hildner</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Batf3 deficiency reveals a critical role for CD8alpha+ dendritic cells in cytotoxic T cell immunity</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2008</year><volume>322</volume><issue>5904</issue><fpage>1097</fpage><lpage>1100</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2756611</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19008445</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1164206</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dorner</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Selective Expression of the Chemokine Receptor XCR1 on Cross-presenting Dendritic Cells Determines Cooperation with CD8+ T Cells</article-title><source>Immunity</source><year>2009</year><volume>31</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>823</fpage><lpage>833</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19913446</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hickman</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>CXCR3 Chemokine Receptor Enables Local CD8(+) T Cell Migration for the Destruction of Virus-Infected Cells</article-title><source>Immunity</source><year>2015</year><volume>42</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>524</fpage><lpage>537</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4365427</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25769612</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.immuni.2015.02.009</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cellular interaction in germinal centers. Roles of CD40 ligand and B7-2 in established germinal centers</article-title><source>The Journal of Immunology</source><year>1995</year><volume>155</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>556</fpage><lpage>567</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7541819</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kepron</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>IL-4 induces the specific rearrangement of gamma 1 genes on the expressed and unexpressed chromosomes of lipopolysaccharide-activated normal murine B cells</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><year>1989</year><volume>143</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>334</fpage><lpage>339</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2786532</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sokolov</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Nuclear NAD+-biosynthetic enzyme NMNAT1 facilitates development and early survival of retinal neurons</article-title><source>eLife</source><year>2021</year><volume>10</volume><elocation-id>e71185</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8754432</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34878972</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.71185</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sagane</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Ataxia and peripheral nerve hypomyelination in ADAM22-deficient mice</article-title><source>BMC Neurosci</source><year>2005</year><volume>6</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>33</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1142324</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15876356</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2202-6-33</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ernfors</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Lack of neurotrophin-3 leads to deficiencies in the peripheral nervous system and loss of limb proprioceptive afferents</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1994</year><volume>77</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>503</fpage><lpage>512</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7514502</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Paolicelli</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Microglia states and nomenclature: A field at its crossroads</article-title><source>Neuron</source><year>2022</year><volume>110</volume><issue>21</issue><fpage>3458</fpage><lpage>3483</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9999291</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36327895</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2022.10.020</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dzionek</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>BDCA-2, BDCA-3, and BDCA-4: Three Markers for Distinct Subsets of Dendritic Cells in Human Peripheral Blood</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><year>2000</year><volume>165</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>6037</fpage><lpage>6046</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11086035</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boles</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The tumor suppressor TSLC1/NECL-2 triggers NK-cell and CD8+ T-cell responses through the cell-surface receptor CRTAM</article-title><source>Blood</source><year>2005</year><volume>106</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>779</fpage><lpage>786</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15811952</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rydyznski</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Affinity Maturation Is Impaired by Natural Killer Cell Suppression of Germinal Centers</article-title><source>Cell Rep</source><year>2018</year><volume>24</volume><issue>13</issue><fpage>3367</fpage><lpage>3373</lpage><elocation-id>e4</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6192537</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30257198</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.celrep.2018.08.075</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Freud</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Caligiuri</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Human natural killer cell development in secondary lymphoid tissues</article-title><source>Semin Immunol</source><year>2014</year><volume>26</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>132</fpage><lpage>137</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4010312</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24661538</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smim.2014.02.008</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Segura</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Characterization of resident and migratory dendritic cells in human lymph nodes</article-title><source>J Exp Med</source><year>2012</year><volume>209</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>653</fpage><lpage>660</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3328358</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22430490</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1084/jem.20111457</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R41"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dzieciatkowska</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Lymph Is Not a Plasma Ultrafiltrate</article-title><source>Shock</source><year>2014</year><volume>42</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>485</fpage><lpage>498</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4236236</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25243428</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/SHK.0000000000000249</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R42"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clement</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Protein expression profiles of human lymph and plasma mapped by 2D-DIGE and 1D SDS–PAGE coupled with nanoLC–ESI–MS/MS bottom-up proteomics</article-title><source>J Proteomics</source><year>2013</year><volume>78</volume><fpage>172</fpage><lpage>187</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3631612</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23202415</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jprot.2012.11.013</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R43"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Souche</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Detection of soluble biomarkers of pancreatic cancer in endoscopic ultrasound-guided fine-needle aspiration samples</article-title><source>Endoscopy</source><year>2022</year><volume>54</volume><issue>05</issue><fpage>503</fpage><lpage>508</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34448184</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R44"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Franzén</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A fine-needle aspiration-based protein signature discriminates benign from malignant breast lesions</article-title><source>Mol Oncol</source><year>2018</year><volume>12</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>1415</fpage><lpage>1428</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6120227</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30019538</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/1878-0261.12350</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R45"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Deciphering novel biomarkers of lymph node metastasis of thyroid papillary microcarcinoma using proteomic analysis of ultrasound-guided fine-needle aspiration biopsy samples</article-title><source>J Proteom</source><year>2019</year><volume>204</volume><elocation-id>103414</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31195151</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R46"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Burwell</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name><surname>Gowland</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lymph Node Reactivity to Homografts of Cancellous Bone</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1960</year><volume>188</volume><issue>4745</issue><fpage>159</fpage><lpage>160</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13689301</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R47"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>clusterProfiler 4.0: A universal enrichment tool for interpreting omics data</article-title><source>Innov</source><year>2021</year><volume>2</volume><issue>3</issue><elocation-id>100141</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8454663</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34557778</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.xinn.2021.100141</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R48"><label>48</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>clusterProfiler: an R Package for Comparing Biological Themes Among Gene Clusters</article-title><source>OMICS: A J Integr Biol</source><year>2012</year><volume>16</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>284</fpage><lpage>287</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3339379</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22455463</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/omi.2011.0118</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R49"><label>49</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Germain</surname><given-names>P-L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Doublet identification in single-cell sequencing data using scDblFinder</article-title><source>F1000Research</source><year>2021</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>979</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9204188</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35814628</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.12688/f1000research.73600.2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R50"><label>50</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Korsunsky</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Fast, sensitive and accurate integration of single-cell data with Harmony</article-title><source>Nat Methods</source><year>2019</year><volume>16</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>1289</fpage><lpage>1296</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6884693</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31740819</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41592-019-0619-0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R51"><label>51</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Finak</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>MAST: a flexible statistical framework for assessing transcriptional changes and characterizing heterogeneity in single-cell RNA sequencing data</article-title><source>Genome biology</source><year>2015</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>13</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4676162</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26653891</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13059-015-0844-5</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R52"><label>52</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Subramanian</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Gene set enrichment analysis: a knowledge-based approach for interpreting genome-wide expression profiles</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences USA</source><year>2005</year><volume>102</volume><issue>43</issue><fpage>15545</fpage><lpage>15550</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1239896</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16199517</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0506580102</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R53"><label>53</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Korotkevich</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Sukhov</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Sergushichev</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><source>Fast gene set enrichment analysis</source><year>2019</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R54"><label>54</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Björklund</surname><given-names>ÅK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The heterogeneity of human CD127+ innate lymphoid cells revealed by single-cell RNA sequencing</article-title><source>Nat Immunol</source><year>2016</year><volume>17</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>451</fpage><lpage>460</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26878113</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R55"><label>55</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Garcia-Alonso</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Single-cell roadmap of human gonadal development</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2022</year><volume>607</volume><issue>7919</issue><fpage>540</fpage><lpage>547</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9300467</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35794482</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41586-022-04918-4</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Identification of cell populations harvested by lymph node fine needle aspiration.</title><p id="P52"><bold>(A)</bold> Experimental plan. Cervical LN material and matched peripheral blood was collected from <italic>n</italic> = 4 healthy donors. <bold>(B)</bold> UMAP of all cells (<italic>n</italic> = 19,154) separated by tissue of origin. <bold>(C)</bold> UMAP of all cells with cluster annotations. <bold>(D)</bold> Dot plot highlighting key markers used to define each cluster. <bold>(E-G)</bold> UMAP showing the annotation of populations based on the following reference datasets: (E) human PBMCs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref>), (F) broad level 1 annotation of human tonsil, and (G) fine level annotation of human tonsil (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref>). The Azimuth package was used for reference mapping (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="S10">methods</xref>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS189981-f001"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Differentially abundant populations between blood and lymph node.</title><p id="P53"><bold>(A)</bold> Bar plot of the proportion of each cluster derived from LN or peripheral blood. <bold>(B)</bold> KNN weighted-network analysis to identify differentially abundant neighborhoods using the miloR package (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="S10">methods</xref>). <bold>(C, D)</bold> Relative abundance of neighborhoods based on cluster annotations (C) and on level 2 tonsil annotations (D). Neighborhoods enriched in cells from the blood are in red, neighborhoods enriched in cells from the LN are in blue, and no enrichment is in grey.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS189981-f002"/></fig><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Differential expression of genes and surface proteins in lymph node cells.</title><p id="P54"><bold>(A)</bold> Number of differentially expressed genes by cluster. <bold>(B)</bold> Number of differentially expressed surface proteins by cluster. <bold>(C)</bold> Overlay of selected genes (<italic>CD69, FOS, JUN, ITGA4</italic>) and proteins (Hu.CD69, Hu.CD49d) onto the UMAP, which is split by tissue of origin (top, blood; bottom, LN). <bold>(D)</bold> Differentially expressed genes on cDC2s from blood versus LN cells. <bold>(E)</bold> GSEA enrichment results comparing DC2 and DC3 signatures from (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">23</xref>) in lymph node versus blood cDC2s. <bold>(F)</bold> GSEA enrichment results comparing human ILC1, ILC2, and ILC3 signatures from (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R54">54</xref>) in lymph node versus blood ILCs. Positive NES (normalized enrichment score) values indicate enrichment in LN-origin cells and negative NES values indicate enrichment in blood-origin cells.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS189981-f003"/></fig><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Unique predicted cell-cell interactions within the lymph node.</title><p id="P55">CellPhoneDB was used to predict cell-cell interactions (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="S10">methods</xref>). <bold>(A, B)</bold> Total number of predicted significant interactions between each pair of cell types in blood (A) or LNs (B). <bold>(C)</bold> Predicted significant interactions between cDC1s and CD8<sup>+</sup> T<sub>EM</sub> cells based on tissue origin (blood, LN, or both tissues (“shared”)). <bold>(D)</bold> Predicted significant interactions between CD4<sup>+</sup> T<sub>FH</sub> cells and either IgM<sup>+</sup> or Switched memory B cells based on tissue origin (blood, LN, or both tissues (“shared”)). Receptor-ligand pairs (y-axis) are written (receptor)_(ligand) and interacting cells (x-axis) are written (receptor-expressing cell) | (ligand-expressing cell).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS189981-f004"/></fig><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>The FNA supernatant contains lymph node-specific proteins.</title><p id="P56">Supernatant from LN FNA, matched serum, and matched cell-free capillary blood was subjected to proteomic analysis for 722 analytes (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="S10">methods</xref>). <bold>(A)</bold> Relative abundance of each protein after the first or second FNA needle, and each wash of the needle. Needle 2 wash 1 for Donor 4 was not analyzed. <bold>(B)</bold> Comparison of relative protein abundance in matched serum (diluted 1:100), capillary blood, LN FNA needle 1 (wash 1), and LN FNA needle 2 (wash 1). (A,B) Boxes indicate median, 25th percentile, and 75<sup>th</sup> percentile. Whiskers are the IQR and dots represent outliers. <bold>(C)</bold> Correlation of relative protein abundance between LN FNA needle 2 (wash 1) for each donor. Number in black on each axis is the number of proteins not detected in the respective sample. Number in red in the bottom left is number of proteins not detected in either sample. Number in bold and black is Pearson correlation coefficient. <bold>(D, E)</bold> Left: correlation plots between matched LN FNA needle 2 (wash 1) and capillary blood (D) or serum (diluted 1:100) (E). Grey line is a line of identity. Right: number of proteins specifically detected in each matched sample are shown. Each color represents a donor. <bold>(F)</bold> Venn diagram of overlap of proteins specifically detected in each of the LN needle 2 (wash 1) samples compared to matched capillary blood. Number in parentheses indicates fraction of proteins found in all three samples. <bold>(G)</bold> GO pathway analysis of the 152 proteins specifically found in all three LN needle 2 (wash 1) samples compared to matched capillary blood. Selected pathways are shown. Count is number of proteins from the dataset contributing to each pathway.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS189981-f005"/></fig><fig id="F6" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title>Proteomics can inform interpretation of single-cell transcriptomic analysis.</title><p id="P57"><bold>(A)</bold> Dot plot expression of selected genes from LN cells corresponding to LN-specific proteins. Right plot depicts relative abundance of each protein. <bold>(B, C)</bold> CellPhoneDB predicted interactions of LN cells via the IL-6–IL-6 receptor signaling pathway (B) or the CADM1–CRTAM signaling pathway (C). Receptor-ligand pairs (y-axis) are written (receptor)_(ligand) and interacting cells (x-axis_ are written (receptor-expressing cell) | (ligand-expressing cell).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS189981-f006"/></fig></floats-group></article>