<!DOCTYPE article
 PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" article-type="preprint"><?all-math-mml yes?><?use-mml?><?origin ukpmcpa?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">bioRxiv</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>bioRxiv : the preprint server for biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub"/></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">EMS188717</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2023.09.26.558975</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="archive">PPR731751</article-id><article-version-alternatives><article-version article-version-type="status">preprint</article-version><article-version article-version-type="number">1</article-version></article-version-alternatives><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Organizing the coactivity structure of the hippocampus from robust to flexible memory</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Gava</surname><given-names>Giuseppe P.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Lefèvre</surname><given-names>Laura</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Broadbelt</surname><given-names>Tabitha</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>McHugh</surname><given-names>Stephen B.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lopes-dos-Santos</surname><given-names>Vítor</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Brizee</surname><given-names>Demi</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hartwich</surname><given-names>Katja</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sjoberg</surname><given-names>Hanna</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Perestenko</surname><given-names>Pavel V.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Toth</surname><given-names>Robert</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sharott</surname><given-names>Andrew</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Dupret</surname><given-names>David</given-names></name></contrib><aff id="A1">Medical Research Council Brain Network Dynamics Unit, Nuffield Department of Clinical Neurosciences, University of Oxford, Oxford, United Kingdom</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="CR1">Correspondence to: <email>giuseppe.gava@bndu.ox.ac.uk</email> and <email>david.dupret@bndu.ox.ac.uk</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted"><day>29</day><month>09</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="preprint"><day>27</day><month>09</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><permissions><ali:free_to_read/><license><ali:license_ref>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is licensed under a <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0 International license</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p id="P1">New memories are integrated into prior knowledge of the world. But what if consecutive memories exert opposing demands on the host brain network? We report that acquiring a robust (food-context) memory constrains the hippocampus within a population activity space of highly correlated spike trains that prevents subsequent computation of a flexible (object-location) memory. This densely correlated firing structure developed over repeated mnemonic experience, gradually coupling neurons of the superficial CA1 <italic>pyramidale</italic> sublayer to whole population activity. Applying hippocampal theta-driven closed-loop optogenetic suppression to mitigate this neuronal recruitment during (food-context) memory formation relaxed the topological constraint on hippocampal coactivity and restored subsequent flexible (object-location) memory. These findings uncover an organizational principle for the peer-to-peer coactivity structure of the hippocampal cell population to successfully meet memory demands.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><p id="P2">Every day, we use our existing knowledge to guide the actions we make in our environment, integrating new information to gain further knowledge about the world. Therefore, building new memories does not take place in a state of <italic>tabula rasa</italic>, but against a background of prior experiences that have been accumulated across the lifespan and have shaped their host brain networks [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">2</xref>].</p><p id="P3">The hippocampus network uses the collective activity of the population of its neurons to support everyday memory [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">4</xref>]. In principle, the level and structure of the activity coupling between individual neurons could reflect a critical tradeoff between the robustness versus the flexibility of the whole population in processing information. That is, strong peer-to-peer coupling could yield highly correlated spike trains, increasing the consistency of activity patterns within the population for robust memory expression. In contrast, weaker population coupling could release network activity space for new patterns, allowing more diverse mnemonic representations for dynamically adaptable behavior. However, the hippocampus may have to switch between robust versus flexible computations depending on current demands. What are the consequences of placing the hippocampal population into a robust computational mode for subsequent memories that instead require flexible information processing?</p><p id="P4">To address this question, we trained mice to first acquire a strong contextual memory. On every day of our paradigm (16 consecutive days), mice explored two arenas (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1A, B</xref>). During the first 10 days (‘Food-context conditioning’), we paired one arena (context <italic>X</italic>) with two regular-diet (Chow) pellets (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure S1A</xref>). The other arena (context <italic>Y</italic>) contained one chow pellet and one high-fat-diet (Hfd) pellet (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure S1A</xref>), which mice encountered for the first time and did not eat much on day 1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1C</xref>). By repeating these foraging sessions on each subsequent conditioning day, mice showed escalated food intake in context <italic>Y</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1C</xref>; from day 1 to day 10, a fold-change of 17.47 ± 5.34 versus 0.72 ± 0.26 in context <italic>Y</italic> versus <italic>X</italic>; mean ± s.e.m.). To probe discriminative food-context association, we then measured their propensity to express context-biased feeding. By providing both arenas with new food items in post-conditioning days (‘Novel food test’; days 11 and 12; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1B</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure S1B</xref>), we observed higher novel food intake in context <italic>Y</italic> compared to context <italic>X</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1D</xref>; a fold-change of 2.71 ± 1.07 in context <italic>Y</italic> versus <italic>X</italic>; mean ± s.e.m.). Thus, mice in the Hfd-conditioned context readily overcame the rodent natural tendency to express food neophobia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref>]. Mice also exhibited lower Hfd intake when provided in a third arena never paired with any food (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure S1C</xref>). Body weight remained stable across task days (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure S1D</xref>). Thus, mice acquired a discriminative memory that shaped their behavior in a context-dependent manner.</p><p id="P5">Having instantiated this discriminative contextual memory, we next switched task demands to assess novelty detection in these contexts previously paired with food. For this, we used a hippocampus-dependent continuous Novel Object Recognition task (‘cNOR test’; from day 13 to day 16; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1A, B</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure S2A</xref>-D). On each cNOR day, we re-exposed mice to either context <italic>X</italic> or <italic>Y</italic> (‘Re-exposure’; without any food) before they encountered four novel objects there (‘Sampling’; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1A, B</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure S2A, B</xref>). Across four more exploration sessions that day, we iteratively replaced one of the initially sampled objects with a new one (‘Testing’). This procedure thus yielded a set of three familiar (already-seen) objects and one novel (first-time-seen) object in each cNOR test (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1B</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure S2A</xref>). We measured novelty detection in cNOR test <italic>n</italic> using the time spent exploring the novel object over the total time spent on all four objects, thereby probing memory for objects explored in session <italic>n</italic> − 1. Mice showed novel object preference in context <italic>X</italic> but not in context <italic>Y</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1E</xref>). Locomotor speed and distance travelled did not differ across contexts (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure S2E</xref>-G). Thus, the robust (food) memory acquired in context <italic>Y</italic> interfered with a subsequent flexible (object-location) memory in that context.</p><p id="P6">We thus aimed to identify the neuronal correlates of this cross-memory interference. During active behavior, groups of principal cells recruited from the population of hippocampal neurons cooperate within the timeframe of theta-band (5–12Hz) oscillations to support codes and computations for memory [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">3</xref>]. We recorded cell ensembles and local field potentials in the CA1 <italic>stratum pyramidale</italic> of these mice. Using the action potentials discharged by principal cells in theta cycles during exploration of each object in cNOR days (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1F</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure S2H</xref>), a generalized linear model (GLM) trained on session <italic>n</italic> − 1 and applied in test <italic>n</italic> identified each object-location compound with up to 93.5% accuracy (range 9.4 – 93.5 %; mean 55.0 % compared to a chance level of 25.0 %; mean ± s.e.m. number of principal cells = 51.1 ± 3.7 per GLM), consistent with work showing population-level object representation in the hippocampus [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref>]. In context <italic>X</italic>, the mean accuracy of this population-level classification started at 38.6 ± 3.2 % for the novel object-location compound and improved as the object gained familiarity in subsequent tests (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1G</xref>). This across-test gain in object-location representation did not occur in context <italic>Y</italic>. In fact, the mean classification accuracy there started at higher levels for the novel object-location (54.9 ± 3.4 %; P&lt;0.001, permutation test, compared to context <italic>X</italic>), without significant changes in the following tests (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1G</xref>). Compared to context <italic>X</italic>, the contribution of individual cells to each novel object-location classification during test <italic>n</italic> in context <italic>Y</italic> resembled its previous one expressed in session <italic>n</italic> − 1 at that location while having another (familiar) object. This was reported by the higher similarity between the population decoding vector that contained the set of neuron-wise GLM coefficients representing the novel object during test <italic>n</italic> in context <italic>Y</italic> versus that representing the familiar object at the same location during session <italic>n</italic> − 1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1H, I</xref>). In line with this observation, the across-test modulation in single-neuron contributions to population decoding vectors when encountering a novel object (i.e., the changes in the magnitude of individual GLM coefficients) was weaker in context <italic>Y</italic> compared to <italic>X</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1J</xref>). These results suggested a population representational rigidity prevented the hippocampus from updating object-location memory in context <italic>Y</italic>.</p><p id="P7">We hypothesized that this acquired representational rigidity reflects the organization of the population activity into a non-permissive structure. That is, Hfd context-conditioning yielded highly correlated firing patterns that created a dense network activity space for strong contextual (food) memory. But this later conflicted with the switch to a different demand where continually processing familiar versus novel stimuli would instead require sparser, weakly correlated patterns for disentangling discrete (object-location) representations. We indeed found that the correlational structure of the population activity was markedly different in context <italic>Y</italic> compared to <italic>X</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>). We quantified the coactivity association of each cell pair (<italic>i</italic>, <italic>j</italic>) by predicting the theta-nested spike discharge of neuron <italic>j</italic> with the activity of neuron <italic>i</italic> while regressing out the activity of the remaining population (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2A</xref>). This procedure returned a matrix of <italic>β</italic> regression weights (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2B</xref>) that represented the neurons pairwise coactivity structure of the population in each context. With this, for both context <italic>X</italic> and <italic>Y</italic> we constructed weighted neuronal graphs (with no self-connections) where each node is a cell and the edge linking any two nodes represents the coactivity of that cell pair (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2B, C</xref>; <italic>n</italic> = 108 graphs and 210,984 coactivity pairs). We found that neuronal graphs contained more triads of coactive nodes in context <italic>Y</italic> than <italic>X</italic>, as shown by higher clustering coefficients (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2D, E</xref>). Moreover, the population coactivity strength level, calculated for each node as the average weight of all its edges, was also higher in <italic>Y</italic> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure S3A</xref>), despite no difference in the mean neurons’ firing rate across contexts (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure S3B</xref>). Surprisingly, the hippocampal population exhibited this denser coactivity structure in context <italic>Y</italic> without a reduction in the average geodesic path length (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="S1">methods</xref>), calculated as the mean shortest path between any two nodes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2F</xref>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">8</xref>]. This suggested that the hippocampal population structure acquired in context <italic>Y</italic> exhibited the higher node-to-node coherence of a more regular, lattice-like network [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref>]. These topological alterations developed across conditioning days (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure S3C</xref>) to continue altering the level and structure of population coactivity in post-conditioning days (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure S3D</xref>), affecting the baseline re-exposure to context <italic>Y</italic> prior to any testing.</p><p id="P8">To further explore the development of a dense population activity structure in context <italic>Y</italic>, we investigated the one-to-many relationship between individual neurons and the rest of the population. For this, we measured across theta cycles the coupling of each principal cell firing to the summed activity of all other recorded cell members of the population (‘population rate;’ <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2A</xref>). Consistent with the higher topological clustering (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2E</xref>), the average population coupling of individual neurons was stronger in context <italic>Y</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2G</xref>). This increased population coupling reflected a stronger cross-neuron spiking relationship: shuffling the spike times across neurons and theta cycles, while preserving each neuron’s mean rate and the population rate distribution, cancelled the increased population coupling seen in context <italic>Y</italic> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure S4A</xref>). This heightened coupling developed across conditioning days to mark the re-exposure to context <italic>Y</italic> during post-conditioning days even before any test (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure S4B</xref>). Contextual food conditioning thus seemed to increase the recruitment of principal cells as “choristers of a larger hippocampal orchestra” [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref>].</p><p id="P9">We therefore investigated the cellular substrate contributing to the denser correlational structure marking the hippocampal population after contextual food conditioning. We started by quantifying CA1 neuron recruitment in mice exposed to Hfd in context <italic>Y</italic> for 10 days, as indexed by the expression of the activity-dependent immediate-early-gene cFos. In parallel, control mice either ate Hfd in their homecage or explored context <italic>Y</italic> without food. Mice undergoing Hfd-context <italic>Y</italic> conditioning showed higher density of cFos<sup>+</sup> neurons in the CA1 <italic>pyramidale</italic> layer compared to controls (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3A, B</xref>). We further noted that 75.45 ± 3.52 % of these cFos-expressing cells were in the superficial <italic>pyramidale</italic> sublayer (i.e., adjacent to the <italic>radiatum</italic> layer), as revealed by the expression of the marker Calbindin 1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3A</xref>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref>]. This suggested that contextual food conditioning recruited CA1 neurons preferentially in the superficial <italic>pyramidale</italic> sublayer.</p><p id="P10">We leveraged this observation by identifying neurons recorded in the CA1 superficial <italic>pyramidale</italic> sublayer to evaluate their contribution to memory. This identification was achieved using the electrophysiological profile of each tetrode (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure S5</xref>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">8</xref>]. We found that the population representational rigidity that we had observed affecting object-location memory update across cNOR tests in context <italic>Y</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1I, J</xref>) related to unchanged contribution of superficial cells. That is, superficial cells showed significantly reduced modulation of their individual contribution to the population GLM object decoding from cNOR session <italic>n</italic> − 1 to test <italic>n</italic> in context <italic>Y</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3C</xref>). This result suggested that superficial cells did not seemingly distinguish the novel object from the familiar previously encountered at the same location in context <italic>Y</italic>, only effectively representing the location itself. Moreover, superficial cells developed stronger population coupling throughout conditioning in context <italic>Y</italic>, which persisted thereafter in test days (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3D</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure S6A</xref>). In line with this, superficial cells formed more triads of coactive neurons (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure S6B, C</xref>). Cells located in the deep <italic>pyramidale</italic> sublayer did not show a similar activity profile (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure S7</xref>). The CA1 representational rigidity preventing flexible processing of object-location information across memory tests in context <italic>Y</italic> was thus mostly explained by aberrant activity of superficial <italic>pyramidale</italic> sublayer cells.</p><p id="P11">We hypothesized that preventing the rise in population coupling during robust contextual conditioning would restore flexible memory. For this, we used an intersectional optogenetic strategy to target and repress cells recruited in the CA1 superficial <italic>pyramidale</italic> sublayer during Hfd-context <italic>Y</italic> conditioning. CA1 superficial <italic>pyramidale</italic> sublayer cells are genetically defined by the molecular marker Calbindin 1 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref>]. They express cFos during contextual Hfd conditioning (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3A, B</xref>). We thus bred double-transgenic Calb1-Cre;cFos-tTA mice and generated a viral construct for the two-term Boolean logic [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref>] expression of the yellow light-driven neural silencer ArchT-EYFP (or its EYFP-only control) dependent on the two recombinases Cre and FlpO (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4A</xref>). We transduced the CA1 of these mice with this construct together with a second construct allowing the tTA-dependent expression of FlpO (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4A</xref>) for lasting optogenetic tagging of CA1 superficial <italic>pyramidale</italic> sublayer cells with either ArchT-EYFP (in CA1<sup>Calb1-cFos</sup>::ArchT mice) or EYFP-only (in CA1<sup>Calb1-cFos</sup>::EYFP mice) from the onset of Hfd conditioning in context <italic>Y</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4B</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure S8A, B</xref>). CA1 superficial principal cells preferentially fire action potentials at the trough of theta cycles (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure S8C</xref>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref>], further exhibiting increased theta modulation across conditioning days (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure S8D</xref>). We thus combined our intersectional strategy with a closed-loop controller for real-time light-actuated suppression of CA1 superficial cells at their preferred theta phase during Hfd-context <italic>Y</italic> conditioning (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4C-E</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure S8A</xref>). We found that despite undergoing 10-day Hfd feeding in context <italic>Y</italic> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure S8E</xref>), this cell-type-defined network-pattern-informed intervention subsequently restored both natural food neophobia (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure S8F</xref>) and successful novel object-location memory (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4F</xref>) in the “optogenetically adjusted” CA1<sup>Calb1-cFos</sup>::ArchT mice. This was not the case for the “non-optogenetically adjusted” CA1<sup>Calb1-cFos</sup>::EYFP mice that overcame rodent food neophobia (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure S8F</xref>) and showed impaired object-location memory (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4F</xref>) in context <italic>Y</italic>, as our original mice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1D, E</xref>). In line with this behavioral outcome, optogenetically adjusted CA1<sup>Calb1-cFos</sup>::ArchT mice recovered functional object-location population decoding (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4G</xref>) along with restored single-neuron representational flexibility (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure S8G</xref>), population coactivity topology (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4H, I</xref>) and coupling (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4J</xref>) in both context <italic>X</italic> and <italic>Y</italic>. These findings showed that adjusting the hippocampal population coactivity structure in this manner supports adaptive transition from robust to flexible memory.</p><p id="P12">In conclusion, we found that a robust (food-context) memory raises the population coupling of CA1 superficial <italic>pyramidale</italic> sublayer neurons, creating a dense network coactivity structure. With respect to subsequent behavior, this acquired hippocampal topology of heightened coactivity relates to strong contextual (feeding) response and impaired novel information processing. Neural networks have been proposed to fall into the broad class of ‘small-world’ networks, a middle ground between regular and random networks where the combination of high clustering of elements (a property of regular networks) with short path lengths between elements (a property of random networks) would allow important properties of complex networks such as increased computational power and effective synchronizability [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">20</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">22</xref>]. Here, our observation that repeated food-context conditioning affects the coactivity structure of the network by increasing neuronal clustering without shortening node-to-node paths suggests that the hippocampal topology is deviating from a small-world toward a more coherent, regular lattice. This way, the joint activity of an increased number of neurons operating as a cohesive population would permit robust information flow to downstream receiver neurons, possibly at the expense of other (e.g., novel) input channels. This heightened hippocampal coactivity could be broadcasted to several recipient circuits and reader neurons. For instance, recent work points to a contribution for the nucleus accumbens in translating hippocampal dynamics of appetitive memory into a behavioral readout [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">23</xref>] or the hypothalamus in driving non-homeostatic contextual feeding [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref>]. Importantly, the instantiation of this highly clustered topology can be prevented: applying cell-type-selective, network-pattern-informed neuronal suppression during contextual learning rebalances hippocampal coactivity and restores flexible memory. Together, these findings suggest that a plastic organization of the hippocampal network topology constraining the collective activity of its neuron constituents shapes the integration of new memories into pre-existing knowledge, from behavioral adaptation to maladaptation and back.</p><sec id="S1" sec-type="materials | methods" specific-use="web-only"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="S2"><title>Animals</title><p id="P13">These experiments used adult (4–6 months old) C57BL/6J wild-type mice (Charles River Laboratories, UK) and double-transgenic mice obtained by crossing transgenic mice heterozygous for the transgene expressing the Cre recombinase under the control of the Calbindin 1 (Calb1) promoter (Jackson Laboratories; obtained from C57BL/6J crossed with Calb1-IRES2-Cre-D B6.129S-Calb1<sup>tm2.1(cre)Hze</sup>/J, stock number 028532, RRID: IMSR_JAX:028532) with c-fos–tTA transgenic male mice heterozygous for the transgene carrying the c-fos promoter–driven tetracycline transactivator (tTA)[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">26</xref>] (c-fos-tTA mouse line generated at The Scripps Research Institute, maintained at Tufts University until shipment to the MRC BNDU at the University of Oxford where they were bred from c-fos-tTA mice crossed with C57Bl6/J mice). Animals were housed with their littermates up until the start of the experiment. All mice held in IVCs, with wooden chew stick and nestlets in a dedicated housing facility with a 12/12 h light/dark cycle (lights on at 07:00), 19–23°C ambient temperature and 40–70% humidity. They had free access to water and food <italic>ad libitum</italic> throughout the experiment. Experimental procedures performed on mice in accordance with the Animals (Scientific Procedures) Act, 1986 (United Kingdom), with final ethical review by the Animals in Science Regulation Unit of the UK Home Office.</p></sec><sec id="S3"><title>Surgical procedure</title><p id="P14">All surgical procedures were performed under deep anesthesia using isoflurane (0.5–2%) and oxygen (2 l/min), with analgesia provided before (0.1 mg/kg vetergesic) and after (5 mg/kg metacam) surgery.</p><p id="P15">To generate expression of either ArchT-EYFP or EYFP-only in principal cells of the CA1 superficial <italic>pyramidale</italic> sublayer, we combined Cre-dependent, FlpO-dependent, and tTA-dependent approaches (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="S1">section</xref> “Viral constructs” below). We mixed in a 1:5 ratio a tTA-inducible AAV carrying a TRE3G-FlpO construct with a Cre-dependent FlpO-dependent AAV carrying either a hSyn-Con/Fon-ArchT-EYFP or the corresponding control hSyn-Con/Fon-EYFP. Viral injections were targeted bilaterally to dorsal CA1 hippocampus of double-transgenic Calb1-Cre;cFos-tTA mice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure S8</xref>) using stereotaxic coordinates (-1.7 and -2.3 mm anteroposterior from bregma, ±1.25 and ±1.7 mm lateral from bregma, and -1.1 mm ventral from the brain surface; 150 nl per site; 2 injection sites per side) at a rate of 100 nl/min using a glass micropipette lowered to the target site and held in place for 5 min after virus delivery before being withdrawn.</p><p id="P16">For electrophysiological tetrode recordings, mice were implanted with a single microdrive containing 14 independently movable tetrodes, targeting the <italic>stratum pyramidale</italic> of the dorsal CA1 hippocampus [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">8</xref>]. Tetrodes were constructed by twisting together four insulated tungsten wires (12 μm diameter, California Fine Wire) which were briefly heated to bind them together into a single bundle. Each tetrode was loaded in one cannula attached to a 6 mm long M1.0 screw to enable its independent manipulation of depth. The drive was implanted under stereotaxic control in reference to bregma using central coordinates -2.0 mm anteroposterior from bregma, +1.7 mm lateral from bregma as a reference to position each individual tetrode contained in the microdrive, initially implanting tetrodes above the pyramidal layer (-1.0 mm ventral from brain surface). The distance between neighboring tetrodes was 350 μm. Following the implantation, the exposed parts of the tetrodes were covered with paraffin wax, after which the drive was secured to the skull using dental cement and stainless-steel anchor screws inserted into the skull. Two of the anchor screws, both above the cerebellum, were attached to a 50 μm tungsten wire (California Fine Wire) and served as ground. For the recordings, each tetrode was lowered along the vertical axis to reach the CA1 pyramidale layer, using the rotations applied to its tetrode cannula-holding screw and the electrophysiological profile of the local field potentials in the hippocampal ripple frequency band, with final depth position subsequently confirmed by histology of anatomical tracks.</p><p id="P17">For optogenetic manipulations, two optic fibers (230 μm diameter, Doric Lenses, Canada) were incorporated into the 14-tetrode microdrive designed to bilaterally deliver light to CA1 and implanted 10 days after viral injections.</p><p id="P18">In one mouse, a single-shank silicon probe (Neuronexus, model A1x32-5mm-25-177-H32_21mm) was implanted following the same surgical procedure to span the somato-dendritic axis of CA1 principal cells and establish the laminar profile of the sharp-wave ripples detected in the local field potentials. These silicon probe recordings allowed estimating the position (depth) of individual tetrode-recorded principal cell soma with respect to the deep versus the superficial sublayers of the dorsal CA1 <italic>stratum pyramidale</italic> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure S5</xref>).</p><p id="P19">For the hippocampal lesion surgery (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure S2C, D</xref>), mice in the lesion group underwent the same anaesthetic induction as above, then scalp incision and craniotomy, followed by N-methy-D-aspartate (NMDA; 10 mg / mL) injections directly into the hippocampus at four sites per hemisphere using a modified Hamilton 36G syringe needle (anterior-posterior: -1.7, -2.3, -2.8, -3.1; mediolateral: ±1.2, ±1.7, ±2.2, ± 2.8; dorsoventral: -1.9, -1.9, -2.0, -4.0, respectively, 100 to 200 nL per site at the infusion / diffusion rates described above), and were then sutured. Midazolam (5 mg / kg, sub-cutaneous) was used to prevent seizures in hippocampal-lesioned mice. Mice receiving sham surgery were incised and then sutured. All mice had at least 2 weeks recovery before behavioural testing.</p></sec><sec id="S4"><title>Viral constructs</title><p id="P20">To optogenetically target cFos-expressing CA1 superficial <italic>pyramidale</italic> sublayer neurons genetically defined to express Calbindin 1, we first produced a TRE3G-FlpO AAV carrying the optimised FlpO recombinase under the control of the third generation of tetracycline responsive element containing promoter (TRE3G, Clontech Laboratories). For this, we exchanged ArchT-GFP open reading frame (ORF) (cut with NcoI and EcoRV) in pAAV-Tre3G-ArchT-GFP vector [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">26</xref>] with the Myc-FLPo ORF (cut with NcoI and Klenow blunted AscI) from pAAV-EF1a-DIO-FLPo-Myc vector [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">23</xref>] (Addgene plasmid # 124641; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://n2t.net/addgene:124641">http://n2t.net/addgene:124641</ext-link>; RRID:Addgene_124641).</p><p id="P21">We next produced a viral vector allowing the Cre-dependent and Flp-dependent expression of ArchT-eYFP. The corresponding pAAV-hSyn-Con/Fon-ArchT-eYFP construct was cloned in two stages. First, pAAV-hSyn-Coff/Fon-ArchT-eYFP has been cloned. Plasmid vectors pAAV-CamKII-ArchT-GFP (a gift from Edward Boyden, Addgene plasmid #37807; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://n2t.net/addgene:37807">http://n2t.net/addgene:37807</ext-link>; RRID: Addgene_37807)[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27">27</xref>], pAAV-hSyn-Coff/Fon-hChR2(H134R)-eYFP (a gift from Karl Deisseroth, Addgene plasmid #55648; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://n2t.net/addgene:55648">http://n2t.net/addgene:55648</ext-link>; RRID: Addgene_55648) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref>] and the combination of the PCR products was used to assemble two inserts that were then subcloned into the pAAV-hSyn Coff/Fon hChR2(H134R)-eYFP vector to substitute the corresponding hChR2-eYFP coding exons with the ArchT-eYFP ones. Primers and the template plasmid DNA for the first insert (exon 1): GTTTCTGCTAGCAACCCCGACACTTACCTTAGCCAGCAGGGCCAG, GTTTCTGAGCTCGCCACCATGGACCCCATC, plasmid#37807. The PCR product was then cloned into the plasmid #55648 using NheI and SacI recognition sites thus forming the intermediate vector. For the following subcloning of the exon 2 the three PCR products were generated with the primers and the corresponding template DNAs: GTTTCTACTAGTCCTCCTGTACTCACC, GTGAGCAAGGGCGAGGAG, plasmid #55648; CTCCTCGCCCTTGCTCACTGCTACTACCGGTCGGGG, GACTCTATTTCTCATGTGTTTAGGTGGACAGGGTGAGCATCG, plasmid #37807; CCTAAACACATGAGAAATAGAGTC, CGAAGTTATGGTACCTGTGCCCCCCC, plasmid #55648. These three products were then combined in the overlapping PCR and inserted into the intermediate vector using SpeI and KpnI cloning sites forming pAAV-hSyn-Coff/Fon-ArchT-eYFP. pAAV-hSyn-Coff/Fon-ArchT-YFP vector then was used to produce pAAV-hSyn-Con/Fon-ArchT-eYFP by inverting the sequence containing part of ArchT-eYFP exon and flanked with the SpeI and KpnI restriction enzymes. The corresponding insert was produced by the PCR with the primers GTTTCTACTAGTTGTGCCCCCCCTTTTTTTTAT and GTTTCTGGTACCCCTCCTGTACTCACCTTGCC using pAAV-hSyn-Coff/Fon-ArchT-eYFP vector as a template.</p><p id="P22">The control vector expressing eYFP in the Cre-dependent and Flp-dependent manner was a gift from Karl Deisseroth (Addgene plasmid # 55650; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://n2t.net/addgene:55650">http://n2t.net/addgene:55650</ext-link>; RRID:Addgene_55650) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref>].</p><p id="P23">We mixed in a 1:5 ratio the AAV carrying TRE3G-FlpO and one of the two Cre-dependent Flp-dependent AAVs in the CA1 of double-transgenic Calb1-Cre;cFos-tTA mice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure S8</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S5"><title>Contextual feeding task</title><p id="P24">Following full recovery from the surgery, each mouse was first handled in a dedicated handling cloth, connected to the recording system, and exposed to an open-field enclosure (neither context <italic>X</italic> not <italic>Y</italic>) to be familiarized with the recording procedure over a period of one week prior to the start of the experiment itself. During this period, tetrodes were gradually lowered to the CA1 <italic>stratum pyramidale</italic> using their estimated depth location, local field potentials, and neuronal spike waveforms. Mice were always fed <italic>ad libitum</italic> throughout the entire experiment. Our contextual feeding task involved three open-field arenas referred to as context <italic>X</italic>, <italic>Y</italic>, and <italic>Z</italic>. These enclosures (outer dimensions: 46 x 46 cm; 38 cm height) differed in their shape (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1A</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure S1C</xref>) and wall-attached cue cards. In the first stage (“Conditioning”) of this task, mice underwent food-context conditioning over 10 consecutive days (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1B</xref>; days 1–10). On each conditioning day, mice explored the arenas in a random order, for 30 minutes each. One arena (context <italic>X</italic>) always contained two food containers in each of which we provided one regular diet pellet (Chow; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure S1A</xref>), identical to those present in the mouse homecage. Another arena (context <italic>Y</italic>) contained two similar food containers that allowed a choice between one chow pellet versus one high-fat diet pellet (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure S1A</xref>; 45% Hfd; Research Diets Inc.; catalog number #D12451). The third arena (context <italic>Z</italic>) was not paired with any food resources during conditioning. On each conditioning day, mice were allowed to rest for 30 minutes between arena explorations.</p><p id="P25">The second stage (“Novel food test”) of this task both assessed changes in baseline population-level activity caused by the 10-day conditioning and probed discriminative food-context association. For these, on each of the two following days (days 11 and 12; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1B</xref>), we first re-exposed mice to either context <italic>X</italic> or <italic>Y</italic> (“Re-exposure”; 30-min; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1B</xref>) before we measured mouse propensity to express context-biased feeding (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure S1B</xref>). In each novel food test, the arena contained two containers that allowed a choice between two food items: one had a regular chow pellet, the other had a never-seen-before resource (e.g., apricot or blackcurrant fruit jams; chocolate or peanut butter food pastes). The kCal value and palatability of novel food resources were matched across test days and contexts. Novel food intake was measured as the novel food kCal intake in context <italic>Y</italic> minus that in context <italic>X</italic> over their sum. A positive score thus indicates increased novel food intake in context <italic>Y</italic> compared to <italic>X</italic>. We further tested mouse propensity to eat Hfd in a context other than <italic>Y</italic> (“Hfd test”; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure S1C</xref>). For this, mice explored for 30 minutes context <italic>Z</italic> that contained two food containers: one with a chow pellet, the other with a Hfd pellet. Hfd food intake was measured as the Hfd intake in context <italic>Z</italic> minus that measured in context <italic>Y</italic> in the previous day, over their sum.</p><p id="P26">We adapted this 12-day contextual feeding paradigm in Calb1-Cre;cFos-tTA mice in order to optogenetically tag the CA1 principal cells that are genetically defined by Calbindin 1 and further expressed cFos when recruited during Hfd conditioning in context <italic>Y</italic>. For this, Calb1-Cre;cFos-tTA mice were fed for 10 days with doxycycline-containing pellets (Envigo Ltd., Catalog number #TD120240) prior to viral construct injections and microdrive implantation (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure S8A</xref>). In this set of experiments, we replaced the Chow pellets with Dox pellets in both context <italic>X</italic> and <italic>Y</italic>, except during the off-Dox tagging days in context <italic>Y</italic>. Before these tagging days, we conducted the first 2 days of conditioning in context <italic>X</italic> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure S8A</xref>; dox versus dox pellets). For optogenetic tagging, the dox-containing pellet homecage feeding was ceased for the first two days of conditioning in context <italic>Y</italic>, after which they received high-doxycycline containing pellets (Envigo Ltd., Catalog number #TD120658) as homecage feeding for 24 hours before returning to normal doxycycline containing pellets for the remaining of the experiment. During the 2 tagging days, mice only explored context <italic>Y</italic> with chow versus Hfd pellets (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure S8A</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S6"><title>continuous Novel Object Recognition task</title><p id="P27">On each cNOR task day (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1B</xref>; days 13 to 16), mice first re-explored context <italic>X</italic> and <italic>Y</italic> (“Re-exposure”; without any food; <italic>X</italic> versus <italic>Y</italic> in random order across cNOR days; 15-min exploration). This re-exposure session evaluated lasting changes in baseline population-level activity. In the second context (<italic>X</italic> or <italic>Y</italic>) explored that day, we next inserted four novel objects (“Sampling”; 15-min exploration) per day). Mice continued to explore this context for four more sessions (“Tests”; 10-min exploration each cNOR test) that day (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure S2A</xref>). Each object (outer dimension: 50 x 50 mm width; 55 mm height; example objects shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure S2B</xref>) was each positioned midway along a given wall. From the sampling session to the first cNOR test, and then for each other cNOR test, we replaced one of the four objects last explored with a novel object. This procedure thus allowed the mouse to explore three familiar (previously seen) and one completely novel object on each cNOR test. On each test, we measured the time spent exploring each object and we calculated the percentage time spent with the novel object versus the (mean) percentage time spent with the familiar objects. The interval between two cNOR test sessions was 5-min, during which the mouse was in a sleep/rest box transiently placed within the recording arena.</p></sec><sec id="S7"><title>Multichannel data acquisition, position tracking and light delivery</title><p id="P28">The extracellular signals from each tetrode channel were amplified, multiplexed, and digitized using a single integrated circuit located on the head of the animal (RHD2164, Intan Technologies; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://intantech.com/products_RHD2000.html">http://intantech.com/products_RHD2000.html</ext-link>; pass band 0.09 Hz to 7.60 kHz). The amplified and filtered electrophysiological signals were digitized at 20 kHz and saved to disk along with the synchronization signals (transistor-transistor logic digital pulses) reporting the animal’s position tracking and laser activations. The location of the animal was tracked using three differently colored LED clusters attached to the electrode casing and captured at 39 frames per second by an overhead color camera (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/kevin-allen/positrack/wiki">https://github.com/kevin-allen/positrack/wiki</ext-link>). The LFPs were down-sampled to 1,250 Hz for all subsequent analyses. For optogenetic intervention, a 561-nm diode pumped solid-state laser (Crystal Laser, model CL561-100; distributer: Laser 2000, Ringstead, UK) was used to deliver light bilaterally to the CA1 via a 2-channel rotary joint (Doric Lenses Inc.). This was performed using a closed-loop system to deliver in real time 561-nm light pulses in CA1<sup>Calb1-cFos</sup>::ArchT mice and CA1<sup>Calb1-cFos</sup>::EYFP mice using dynamic tracking of ongoing theta phase (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4C,D</xref>). The real-time phase estimate was obtained using the OscillTrack algorithm (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://colinmcn.github.io/OscillTrack/">https://colinmcn.github.io/OscillTrack/</ext-link>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">28</xref>] implemented in the field-programmable gate array of the Intan Technologies interface board. Phase detection was obtained by continuously operating on the data stream coming from an input channel containing the CA1 LFPs. This input channel used as the phase reference was high-pass filtered using a 1st order digital infinite impulse response filter with a corner frequency of 0.4 Hz to remove amplifier offset and electrode drift, then down-sampled 125-fold to a rate of 160 Hz for processing. The phase estimation was operated with a loop-gain of 0.0625 at a centre frequency of 7 Hz. Stimulation was triggered with a phase lead, such that the target phase aligned with the middle of the 50-ms light pulse.</p></sec><sec id="S8"><title>Spike detection and unit isolation</title><p id="P29">Spike sorting and unit isolation were performed with an automated clustering pipeline using Kilosort (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/cortex-lab/KiloSort">https://github.com/cortex-lab/KiloSort</ext-link>) via the SpikeForest framework (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/flatironinstitute/spikeforest">https://github.com/flatironinstitute/spikeforest</ext-link>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">30</xref>]. To apply KiloSort to data acquired using tetrodes, the algorithm restricted templates to channels within a given tetrode bundle, while masking all other recording channels. All sessions recorded on a given day were concatenated and cluster cut together to monitor cells throughout the experiment day. The resulting clusters were verified by the operator using cross-channel spike waveforms, auto-correlation histograms, and cross-correlation histograms. Each unit used for analyses showed throughout the entire recording day stable spike waveforms, clear refractory period in their auto-correlation histogram, and absence of refractory period in its cross-correlation histograms with the other units. Principal cells and interneurons were identified by their auto-correlograms, firing rates, and spike waveforms. In total, this study includes n = 4,423 CA1 principal cells: n = 2,506 for the original dataset (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figures 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>, and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>; n = 7 mice); and n = 910 CA1<sup>Calb1-cFos</sup>::ArchT neurons (n = 5 mice) versus n = 1,007 CA1<sup>Calb1-cFos</sup>::EYFP neurons (n = 4 mice) for the optogenetic dataset (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S9"><title>Theta oscillations, sharp-wave ripples detection, and tetrode depth estimation</title><p id="P30">To detect theta oscillations from the LFPs, we applied Ensemble Empirical Mode Decomposition and selected bouts of at least 5 cycles during active exploratory behavior (animal speed &gt; 2 cm/s) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31">31</xref>]. To detect sharp-wave ripples, the LFP signal of each CA1 pyramidal layer channel (for tetrode recordings) or recording site (for linear silicon probe recordings) were subtracted by the mean across all channels/sites (common average reference). These re-referenced signals were then filtered for the ripple band (110 to 250 Hz; 4th order Butterworth filter) and their envelopes (instantaneous amplitudes) were computed by means of the Hilbert transform. The peaks (local maxima) of the ripple band envelope signals above a threshold (5 times the median of the envelope values of that channel) were regarded as candidate events. Further, the onset and offset of each event were determined as the time points at which the ripple envelope decayed below half of the detection threshold. Candidate events passing the following criteria were determined as SWR events: (<italic>i</italic>) ripple band power in the event channel was at least 2 times the ripple band power in the common average reference (to eliminate common high frequency noise); (<italic>ii</italic>) an event had at least four ripple cycles (to eliminate events that were too brief); (<italic>iii</italic>) ripple band power was at least 2 times higher than the supra-ripple band defined as 200-500 Hz (to eliminate high frequency noise, not spectrally compact at the ripple band, such as spike leakage artefacts). In addition to the SWR profile information, we integrated mean theta profile information to estimate the tetrode depth. We classified tetrodes as being in the deep or superficial sublayer of the CA1 <italic>stratum pyramidale</italic> based on the mean profile of detected SWRs and theta cycles (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure S5</xref>). Positive values indicated that the tetrode was in the deep sublayer (i.e. closest to <italic>stratum oriens</italic>) while negative values indicated tetrode was in the superficial sublayer (i.e. closest to <italic>stratum radiatum</italic>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">8</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="S10"><title>Object-location population decoding</title><p id="P31">We trained a General Linear Model (GLM) to classify each object-location compound explored during cNOR tests, from the recorded neural spiking activity nested in theta cycles associated with these visits (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1F</xref>). By training a model in session <italic>n</italic> − 1 and testing it in test <italic>n</italic> we then obtain one novel and three familiar object scores per cNOR session (four session pairs per day; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1G</xref>). A given object-location compound pair <italic>i</italic> was then associated to a decoding vector composed of each neuron’s GLM coefficient (<italic>P<sup>i</sup></italic>), reporting the individual weight contribution of neuron <italic>n</italic> to the population representation of <italic>i</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1H</xref>). By taking the cosine distance metric between pairs of decoding vectors across subsequent sessions representing the same location but different objects (familiar object <italic>i</italic> versus novel object <italic>j</italic>), we quantified the change in population representation <italic>D<sub>pop</sub></italic> = <italic>dist<sub>cos</sub></italic>(<italic>P<sup>i</sup></italic>, <italic>P<sup>j</sup></italic>) (decoding vectors similarity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1I</xref>). The representational change of individual neurons induced by the insertion of novel objects, was instead computed as <inline-formula><mml:math id="M1"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (Δ single-neuron decoding coefficient, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1J</xref>). To build the GLM model, we employed the function <italic>LogisticRegression</italic> from the <italic>sklearn</italic> package (v .0.18…) with L2 regularization (inverse strength <italic>C</italic>=1e-2, selected by maximizing the classification scores across sessions).</p></sec><sec id="S11"><title>Neuronal coactivity graphs</title><p id="P32">We constructed hippocampal population graphs that represent the coactivity relationships between all pairs of principal cell spike trains recorded during a given task session. These coactivity graphs were computed using theta cycles as time windows spanning active exploratory behavior (speed&gt;2 cm.s-1), discarding periods of immobility and further excluding sharp-wave/ripples. To further control for the shared influence of the general network activity on peer-to-peer coactivity, we used for any two neurons (<italic>i</italic>, <italic>j</italic>) the regression coefficient <italic>β</italic> <sub><italic>ij</italic></sub> obtained by fitting the GLM (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2A</xref>): <disp-formula id="FD1"><mml:math id="M2"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>∼</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula> where <italic>x<sub>j</sub></italic>, <italic>x<sub>i</sub></italic> are the z-scored theta-nested spike trains of individual neurons <italic>j</italic> (the target) and <italic>i</italic> (the predictor), and <italic>P</italic> is the summed activity of the other <italic>N</italic> − 2 neurons, <disp-formula id="FD2"><mml:math id="M3"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:munderover><mml:mi>∑</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:munderover><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula> with <italic>a<sub>ij</sub></italic> weighting the influence of the population contribution to the activity of target neuron <italic>j</italic>.</p><p id="P33">The recorded neurons (and their coactivity associations) are therefore the nodes (and their edges) in the coactivity graph of each task session. We described each graph by its adjacency matrix, <italic>A</italic>, as the <italic>N</italic> x <italic>N</italic> square matrix containing the pairwise coactivity relations within the network, yielding a weighted graph with no self-connections: <disp-formula id="FD3"><mml:math id="M4"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mo>⋯</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mo>⋮</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mo>⋱</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mo>⋮</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mo>⋯</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula> with <italic>β<sub>i,i</sub></italic> = 0 ∀<italic>i in N</italic>, and the symmetry in the weights of the network being ensured by setting <inline-formula><mml:math id="M5"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> to form an undirected graph.</p></sec><sec id="S12"><title>Clustering coefficient</title><p id="P34">We computed a clustering coefficient to characterize the local synchronization of network activity by quantifying the number of three-node motifs. In each graph, for any neuron <italic>i</italic>, we obtained its clustering coefficient <italic>C<sub>i</sub></italic> using the formula proposed by Onnela et al. to quantify the strength of each triad [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32">32</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34">34</xref>]: <disp-formula id="FD4"><mml:math id="M6"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:msub><mml:mi>∑</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>q</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">^</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>q</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">^</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>q</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula> where <italic>j</italic> and <italic>q</italic> are neighbors of neuron <italic>i</italic>, all edge weights are normalized by the maximum edge weight in the network <inline-formula><mml:math id="M7"><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>max</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <italic>k<sub>i</sub></italic> is the degree of neuron <italic>i</italic>, which in these weighted graphs with no self-connection is equal to the number of neurons minus one. Note that this formula accounts for negative edges, yielding a negative value when there is an odd number due to the negative edges in the triad; it is positive otherwise. For this reason, this quantity can also be interpreted as a measure of the “structural balance” around a node, in the sense that its neighborhood presents coherent patterns of connectivity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35">35</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="S13"><title>Geodesic path length</title><p id="P35">We measured the geodesic (i.e., shortest) path length to estimate the activity coordination efficacy between any two nodes in the coactivity graph. In a binary graph, this would represent the smallest number of edges connecting two nodes. Here, we define the length between two nodes <italic>i</italic> and <italic>j</italic> as the inverse of their coactivity: <italic>l</italic> = 1/<italic>β<sub>ij</sub></italic>, discarding all negative edges [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref>]. We then computed the geodesic shortest path length between any two nodes in the graph using the Floyd-Warshall algorithm [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36">36</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38">38</xref>]. We then report the average path length for each principal cell in the coactivity graph.</p></sec><sec id="S14"><title>Single-neuron coactivity strength</title><p id="P36">We defined the single-neuron coactivity strength as the average pairwise activity correlation strength of a given node in a weighted graph. As a reference, the strength in a weighted graph can be compared to the degree in a binary graph, which accounts for the number of the node’s neighbors. Here, the strength <italic>S<sub>i</sub></italic>of a node <italic>i</italic> is the average across all the weights <italic>β<sub>ij</sub></italic> of the edges projected from that node: <disp-formula id="FD5"><mml:math id="M8"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>∑</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula> where <italic>N</italic> is the number of neurons <italic>j</italic> that node <italic>i</italic> projects to.</p></sec><sec id="S15"><title>Population coupling</title><p id="P37">We defined the coupling of neuron <italic>i</italic> to the rest of the population of <italic>N</italic> units (population coupling, <italic>PC</italic>) as the Pearson correlation between its theta-binned activity <italic>x<sub>i</sub></italic> and that of all remaining neurons summed together <italic>P</italic><sup><italic>N</italic>−{<italic>i</italic>}</sup>: <disp-formula id="FD6"><mml:math id="M9"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="P38">To assess whether the increase in population coupling in context <italic>Y</italic> was due to the fine temporal structure of the neural population activity, we independently circularly shuffled the neurons’ theta-binned activity by random delays between 10 to 100 theta cycles, therefore preserving each neurons’ rate and autocorrelation. The final value was taken as the average over 100 iterations.</p></sec><sec id="S16"><title>Anatomy</title><p id="P39">Mice were deeply anesthetized with isoflurane/pentobarbital and transcardially perfused with PBS followed by cold 4 % PFA dissolved in PBS. The brains were extracted, kept in 4% PFA for 24 h, and sliced into 50 μm thick coronal sections. For immunostaining, free-floating sections were rinsed extensively in PBS with 0.25 % Triton X-100 (PBS-T) and blocked for 1 h at room temperature in PBS-T with 10 % normal donkey serum (NDS). Sections were then incubated at 4°C for 48 h with primary antibodies (rabbit anti-cFos, 1:500, Synaptic Systems, cat# 226 003; goat anti-calbindin 1, 1:1,000, Nittobo Medical, cat# Af1040) diluted in PBS-T with 3 % NDS blocking solution. Sections were then rinsed three times for 10 min in PBS and incubated for 24 h at 4°C in secondary antibodies (donkey anti-rabbit Alexa Fluor 488, 1:250, Thermo Fisher Scientific, cat# A-21206, RRID:AB_2535792; donkey anti-goat Cy3, 1:1000, Jackson ImmunoResearch, cat# 705-165-147, RRID: AB_2307351) diluted in PBS-T with 1 % NDS. This step was followed by three rinses for 15 min in PBS. Sections were then incubated for 1 min with 4',6-diamidino-2-phenylindole (DAPI; 0.5 μg/ml, Sigma-Aldrich, cat# D8417) diluted in PBS to label cell nuclei, before undergoing three additional rinse steps of 10 min each in PBS. Sections were finally mounted on slides, cover-slipped with Vectashield mounting medium (Vector Laboratories) and stored at 4 °C. Sections were also used for anatomical verification of the tetrode tracks. The CA1 pyramidal layer was imaged in all 3 channels (DAPI-A405, cFos-A488, and Calb1-CY3) as a mosaic stack across the full z-range using a Zeiss confocal microscope (LSM 880 Indimo, Axio Imager 2) with a Plan-Apochromat 20x/0.8 M27 Objective and the ZEN software (Zeiss Black 2.3, step size: 10μm) using 2 sections at the same rostro-caudal position (-2.0mm and -2.5 mm) for each mouse. Automated counting was performed using Fiji and the 3D ImageJ Suite [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39">39</xref>]. A CA1 stratum pyramidale mask was generated using the DAPI channel, subdividing it into the deep versus the superficial pyramidale sublayers using the Calbindin 1 channel. To automatically detect single cFos cells, a 3D iterative thresholding (minimum threshold: RenyEntropy, pixel-volume: 2000-3000) was used on the cFos stack. A cFos positive cell was also positive for Calb1 when the average intensity within the cFos segment was above the automatic threshold (3D intensity measure, threshold: Huang). Cell densities are number of cells divided by the volume of the pyramidale layer. For the hippocampal lesion experiment, mice were perfused transcardially with physiological saline (0.9% NaCl) followed by 10% formol saline (10% formalin in physiological saline). The brains were then removed and placed in 10% formol saline and 72 hours later transferred to 30% sucrose-formalin. Coronal sections (50 μm) were cut on a freezing microtome and stained with cresyl violet to enable visualization of lesion extent.</p></sec><sec id="S17"><title>Data and statistical analyses</title><p id="P40">Data were analysed in Python 3.6 and using the packages DABEST v0.3.0 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40">40</xref>], scikit-learn v0.23.2 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41">41</xref>], NetworkX v2.4 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42">42</xref>], Numpy v1.18.1, Scipy v1.4.1, Matplotlib v3.1.2, Pandas v0.25.3 and Seaborn v0.11.0. All statistical tests related to a symmetric distribution were performed two-sided using Gardner-Altman plots (to compare 2 groups) and Cumming plots (for more groups) from the Data Analysis with Bootstrap-coupled ESTimation (DABEST) framework [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40">40</xref>]. These DABEST plots allow visualizing the effect size by plotting the data as the mean or median difference between one of the groups (the left-most group of each plot, used as group-reference) and the other groups (to the right, along the x-axis of each plot). For each estimation plot: (<italic>i</italic>) the upper panel shows the distribution of raw data points for the entire dataset, superimposed on bar-plots reporting group mean±SEM, unless stated otherwise; and (<italic>ii</italic>) the lower panel displays the difference between a given group and the (left-most) group-reference, computed from 5,000 bootstrapped resamples and with difference-axis origin aligned to the mean or the median of the group-reference distribution. For each estimation plot: <italic>black-dot</italic>, mean (for normal distributions) or median (for skewed distributions) as indicated; <italic>black-ticks</italic>, 95% or 99% confidence interval as indicated; <italic>filled-curve</italic>: bootstrapped sampling-error distribution. Data distributions were assumed to be normal, but this was not formally tested. We also used the t-test to compare two conditions; the Wald test for assessing the significance of regression lines; and the Kolmogorov–Smirnov test for comparing probability distributions. Neural and behavioural data analyses were conducted in an identical way regardless of the identity of the experimental condition from which the data were collected, with the investigator blind to group allocation during data collection and/or analysis.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="SM"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1"><label>Supplementary Figures</label><media xlink:href="EMS188717-supplement-Supplementary_Figures.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" id="d36aAdMbB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack id="S18"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We would like to thank R. Lambiotte and S.R. Schultz for commenting on a previous version of the manuscript; B. Micklem for technical assistance; all members of the Dupret lab for feedback during the project.</p></ack><sec id="S19"><title>Funding</title><p>This work was supported by the Biotechnology and Biological Sciences Research Council UK (awards BB/S007741/1 and BB/N002547/1) and the Medical Research Council UK (programme MC_UU_00003/4 and award MR/W004860/1).</p></sec><fn-group><fn id="FN1" fn-type="con"><p id="P41"><bold>Author contributions:</bold> Conceptualization, GPG, LL, and DD; Investigation, GPG, LL, TB, SBMc, DB, KH, HH; Analysis, GPG, LL, and DD; Methodology, GPG, LL, SBMc, VLdS, and DD; Resources, PVP, RT, AS, and DD; Visualization, GPG and DD; Funding acquisition: DD; Writing – Original Draft, GPG and DD; Writing – Reviewing &amp; Editing, GPG, LL, TB, SBMc, VLdS, DB, KH, HH, PVP, RT, AS and DD; Supervision, DD.</p></fn><fn id="FN2" fn-type="conflict"><p id="P42"><bold>Competing interests:</bold> The authors declare no competing interests.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><ref id="R1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schacter</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Addis</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Buckner</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Remembering the past to imagine the future: the prospective brain</article-title><source>Nat Rev Neurosci</source><year>2007</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>657</fpage><lpage>661</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17700624</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brod</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Werkle-Bergner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Shing</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Influence of Prior Knowledge on Memory: A Developmental Cognitive Neuroscience Perspective</article-title><source>Frontiers in Behavioral Neuroscience</source><year>2013</year><volume>7</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3792618</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24115923</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fnbeh.2013.00139</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Buzsáki</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Neural syntax: cell assemblies, synapsembles, and readers</article-title><source>Neuron</source><year>2010</year><volume>68</volume><fpage>362</fpage><lpage>385</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3005627</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21040841</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2010.09.023</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mau</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Hasselmo</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The brain in motion: How ensemble fluidity drives memory-updating and flexibility</article-title><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Colgin</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name></person-group><source>eLife</source><year>2020</year><volume>9</volume><elocation-id>e63550</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7771967</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33372892</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.63550</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kronenberger</surname><given-names>J-P</given-names></name><name><surname>Médioni</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Food neophobia in wild and laboratory mice (Mus musculus domesticus)</article-title><source>Behavioural Processes</source><year>1985</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>53</fpage><lpage>59</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24924361</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barnett</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Experiments on “neophobia” in wild and laboratory rats</article-title><source>British Journal of Psychology</source><year>1958</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>195</fpage><lpage>201</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13572791</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nagelhus</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Andersson</surname><given-names>SO</given-names></name><name><surname>Cogno</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name><surname>Moser</surname><given-names>EI</given-names></name><name><surname>Moser</surname><given-names>M-B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Object-centered population coding in CA1 of the hippocampus</article-title><source>Neuron</source><year>2023</year><volume>111</volume><fpage>2091</fpage><lpage>2104</lpage><elocation-id>e14</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37148872</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gava</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name><name><surname>McHugh</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Lefèvre</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Lopes-dos-Santos</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Trouche</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>El-Gaby</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Integrating new memories into the hippocampal network activity space</article-title><source>Nature Neuroscience</source><year>2021</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>326</fpage><lpage>330</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7116855</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33603228</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41593-021-00804-w</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Watts</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Strogatz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><source>Collective Dynamics of Small-World Networks</source><year>1998</year><volume>393</volume><fpage>3</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9623998</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Newman</surname><given-names>MEJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Structure and Function of Complex Networks</article-title><source>SIAM Rev</source><year>2003</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>167</fpage><lpage>256</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1137/S003614450342480</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Muldoon</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><name><surname>Bridgeford</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></name><name><surname>Bassett</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Small-World Propensity and Weighted Brain Networks</article-title><source>Scientific Reports</source><year>2016</year><volume>6</volume><elocation-id>22057</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4766852</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26912196</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep22057</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Okun</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Steinmetz</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name><surname>Cossell</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Iacaruso</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Ko</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Barthó</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Diverse coupling of neurons to populations in sensory cortex</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2015</year><volume>521</volume><fpage>511</fpage><lpage>515</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4449271</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25849776</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature14273</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Soltesz</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Losonczy</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>CA1 pyramidal cell diversity enabling parallel information processing in the hippocampus</article-title><source>Nat Neurosci</source><year>2018</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>484</fpage><lpage>493</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5909691</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29593317</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41593-018-0118-0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cembrowski</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Spruston</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Heterogeneity within classical cell types is the rule: lessons from hippocampal pyramidal neurons</article-title><source>Nature Reviews Neuroscience</source><year>2019</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>193</fpage><lpage>204</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30778192</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Valero</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Cid</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Averkin</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name><surname>Aguilar</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanchez-Aguilera</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Viney</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Determinants of different deep and superficial CA1 pyramidal cell dynamics during sharp-wave ripples</article-title><source>Nature Neuroscience</source><year>2015</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>1281</fpage><lpage>1290</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4820637</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26214372</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nn.4074</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cembrowski</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Bachman</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Sugino</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Shields</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><name><surname>Spruston</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Spatial Gene-Expression Gradients Underlie Prominent Heterogeneity of CA1 Pyramidal Neurons</article-title><source>Neuron</source><year>2016</year><volume>89</volume><fpage>351</fpage><lpage>368</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26777276</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fenno</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name><surname>Mattis</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramakrishnan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Hyun</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Targeting cells with single vectors using multiple-feature Boolean logic</article-title><source>Nature Methods</source><year>2014</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>763</fpage><lpage>772</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4085277</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24908100</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.2996</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grosmark</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Buzsáki</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diversity in neural firing dynamics supports both rigid and learned hippocampal sequences</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2016</year><volume>351</volume><fpage>1440</fpage><lpage>1443</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4919122</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27013730</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.aad1935</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Navas-Olive</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Valero</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Jurado-Parras</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>de Salas-Quiroga</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Averkin</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name><surname>Gambino</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Multimodal determinants of phase-locked dynamics across deep-superficial hippocampal sublayers during theta oscillations</article-title><source>Nature Communications</source><year>2020</year><volume>11</volume><elocation-id>2217</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7200700</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32371879</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-020-15840-6</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bullmore</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Sporns</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Complex brain networks: graph theoretical analysis of structural and functional systems</article-title><source>Nat Rev Neurosci</source><year>2009</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>186</fpage><lpage>198</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19190637</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bassett</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Sporns</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Network neuroscience</article-title><source>Nature Neuroscience</source><year>2017</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>353</fpage><lpage>364</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5485642</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28230844</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nn.4502</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barahona</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pecora</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Synchronization in Small-World Systems</article-title><source>Phys Rev Lett</source><year>2002</year><volume>89</volume><elocation-id>054101</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12144443</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Trouche</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Koren</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Doig</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ellender</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>El-Gaby</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lopes-Dos-Santos</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A Hippocampus-Accumbens Tripartite Neuronal Motif Guides Appetitive Memory in Space</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2019</year><volume>176</volume><fpage>1393</fpage><lpage>1406</lpage><elocation-id>e16</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6424821</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30773318</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2018.12.037</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mohammad</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Senol</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Graf</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>C-Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A neural circuit for excessive feeding driven by environmental context in mice</article-title><source>Nat Neurosci</source><year>2021</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>10</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34168339</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Drane</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Ainsley</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mayford</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Reijmers</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A transgenic mouse line for collecting ribosome-bound mRNA using the tetracycline transactivator system</article-title><source>Front Mol Neurosci</source><year>2014</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>82</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4212621</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25400545</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fnmol.2014.00082</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Trouche</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Perestenko</surname><given-names>PV</given-names></name><name><surname>van de Ven</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bratley</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name><name><surname>McNamara</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name><name><surname>Campo-Urriza</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Recoding a cocaine-place memory engram to a neutral engram in the hippocampus</article-title><source>Nat Neurosci</source><year>2016</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>564</fpage><lpage>567</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4817230</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26900924</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nn.4250</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Chow</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Klapoetke</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Chuong</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rajimehr</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A High-Light Sensitivity Optical Neural Silencer: Development and Application to Optogenetic Control of Non-Human Primate Cortex</article-title><source>Frontiers in Systems Neuroscience</source><year>2011</year><volume>5</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3082132</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21811444</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fnsys.2011.00018</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McNamara</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name><name><surname>Rothwell</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharott</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Stable, interactive modulation of neuronal oscillations produced through brain-machine equilibrium</article-title><source>Cell Reports</source><year>2022</year><volume>41</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7614081</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36351413</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.celrep.2022.111616</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Magland</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Jun</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lovero</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Morley</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hurwitz</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Buccino</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>SpikeForest, reproducible web-facing ground-truth validation of automated neural spike sorters</article-title><source>Elife</source><year>2020</year><volume>9</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7237210</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32427564</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.55167</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pachitariu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Steinmetz</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kadir</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><name><surname>Carandini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Fast and accurate spike sorting of high-channel count probes with KiloSort</chapter-title><source>Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems</source><publisher-name>Curran Associates, Inc</publisher-name><year>2016</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lopes-Dos-Santos</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>van de Ven</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Morley</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Trouche</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Campo-Urriza</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Dupret</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Parsing Hippocampal Theta Oscillations by Nested Spectral Components during Spatial Exploration and Memory-Guided Behavior</article-title><source>Neuron</source><year>2018</year><volume>100</volume><fpage>940</fpage><lpage>952</lpage><elocation-id>e7</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6277817</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30344040</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2018.09.031</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Onnela</surname><given-names>J-P</given-names></name><name><surname>Saramäki</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kertész</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaski</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Intensity and coherence of motifs in weighted complex networks</article-title><source>Physical review E, Statistical, nonlinear, and soft matter physics</source><year>2005</year><volume>71</volume><elocation-id>065103</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16089800</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Costantini</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Perugini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Generalization of Clustering Coefficients to Signed Correlation Networks</article-title><source>PLOS ONE</source><year>2014</year><volume>9</volume><elocation-id>e88669</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3931641</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24586367</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0088669</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saramäki</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kivelä</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Onnela</surname><given-names>J-P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaski</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kertész</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Generalizations of the clustering coefficient to weighted complex networks</article-title><source>Phys Rev E</source><year>2007</year><volume>75</volume><elocation-id>027105</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17358454</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Estrada</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rethinking structural balance in signed social networks</article-title><source>Discrete Applied Mathematics</source><year>2019</year><volume>268</volume><fpage>70</fpage><lpage>90</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.dam.2019.04.019</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Floyd</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Algorithm 97: Shortest Path</article-title><source>Commun ACM</source><year>1962</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>345</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1145/367766.368168</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transitivité et connexité</article-title><source>C R Acad Sci Paris</source><year>1959</year><volume>249</volume><fpage>216</fpage><lpage>218</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Warshall</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A Theorem on Boolean Matrices</article-title><source>J ACM</source><year>1962</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>11</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1145/321105.321107</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ollion</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Cochennec</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Loll</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Escudé</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Boudier</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>TANGO: a generic tool for high-throughput 3D image analysis for studying nuclear organization</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2013</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>1840</fpage><lpage>1841</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3702251</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23681123</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btt276</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Tumkaya</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Aryal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Claridge-Chang</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Moving beyond P values: data analysis with estimation graphics</article-title><source>Nature Methods</source><year>2019</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>565</fpage><lpage>566</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31217592</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R41"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pedregosa</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Varoquaux</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Gramfort</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Michel</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Thirion</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Grisel</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Scikit-learn: Machine Learning in Python</article-title><source>Journal of Machine Learning Research</source><year>2011</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>2825</fpage><lpage>2830</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R42"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="confproc"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hagberg</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Schult</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Swart</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group><source>Exploring Network Structure, Dynamics, and Function using NetworkX</source><conf-name>Proceedings of the 7th Python in Science Conference</conf-name><year>2008</year><fpage>11</fpage><lpage>15</lpage></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Robust contextual (food) memory prevents subsequent flexible (object) memory.</title><p><bold>(A, B)</bold> Behavioral tasks with open-field contexts <bold>(A)</bold> and multiday layout <bold>(B)</bold> for a two-memory paradigm. <bold>(C)</bold> Animals’ food intake during contextual conditioning (each data point represents one mouse). (<bold>D)</bold> Estimation plot (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="S1">Methods</xref>) showing the effect size for the difference in novel food intake across context <italic>X</italic> and <italic>Y</italic> after conditioning. (<bold>E</bold>) Likewise, shown is the percentage of exploration time with novel and familiar objects during cNOR tests in context <italic>X</italic> or <italic>Y</italic>. (<bold>F</bold>) Schematic of the GLM employed to predict the identity of each object-location compound from ongoing population vectors of theta-nested principal cell spiking. For clarity, a sample of a few seconds of data for one object visit (blue trace) is shown. (<bold>G</bold>) Estimation plot showing the classification accuracy of object-location compound in test <italic>n</italic> by GLM trained in session <italic>n</italic> − 1 (each data point represents one object). <bold>(H)</bold> Example population decoding vector pairs containing the neuron-wise GLM coefficients for the familiar versus a novel object at the same location in either context <italic>X</italic> or <italic>Y</italic> (each data point represents one neuron). <bold>(I, J)</bold> Estimation plots showing the cosine similarity between familiar and novel object-location GLM vectors <bold>(I)</bold> and the change (update) in single neuron contribution to whole-population novel object-location classification <bold>(J)</bold> across two consecutive cNOR tests in either context. ***P&lt;0.001, *P&lt;0.05</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS188717-f001"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Robust memory increases neuronal coactivity and population coupling.</title><p><bold>(A)</bold> Schematic of population-level analyses (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="S1">methods</xref>). Coactivity between any two (<italic>i</italic>, <italic>j</italic>) neurons measured as the <italic>β</italic> regression weight from the GLM assessing their firing relationship while accounting for network-level modulation using the sum of the remaining cells in the population (to estimate neuron pair (<italic>i</italic>, <italic>j</italic>) coactivity beyond the population rate). Population coupling of each cell measured as the Pearson correlation coefficient between its theta-binned spike train and the cumulative activity of the remaining cells. <bold>(B-D)</bold> Example adjacency matrix of <italic>β</italic> regression weights (B) and corresponding coactivity graph (C) using the procedure depicted in (A) to access the neuron (<italic>i</italic>, <italic>j</italic>) pairwise coactivity structure of the population in each context. For clarity, (D) shows a subset of adjacency matrices representing contexts <italic>X</italic> versus <italic>Y</italic> (top), along with their clustering coefficients and motifs of coactivity (bottom). <bold>(E, F)</bold> Estimation plots showing that the population coactivity structure is tighter in context <italic>Y</italic> than <italic>X</italic>, as reported by the higher clustering coefficient of neuronal graphs containing more triads of coactive neurons (E), without a significant change in geodesic path length (F). <bold>(G)</bold> Population coupling of principal cells is stronger in context <italic>Y</italic> than <italic>X</italic>. ***P&lt;0.001.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS188717-f002"/></fig><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Contextual food memory recruits CA1 superficial <italic>pyramidale</italic> sublayer cells.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) cFos–expressing neurons in the CA1 superficial <italic>pyramidale</italic> (Pyr.; <italic>Oriens,</italic> Or.; <italic>Radiatum,</italic> Rad.) sublayer (Calbindin 1 marker delineated) for a mouse after 10-day context <italic>Y</italic>-Hfd conditioning (right) and a control mouse not submitted to Hfd conditioning (left). Cell nuclei stained with DAPI (gray). Scale bar: 50 μm. (<bold>B</bold>) Corresponding quantification of cFos<sup>+</sup> cell density in the CA1 pyramidal layer (each data point represents one mouse per condition; p=0.001, Kruskal-Wallis test). (<bold>C, D</bold>) Estimation plots showing the reduced change (update) in the GLM decoding contribution of single CA1 superficial <italic>pyramidale</italic> sublayer cells to population object-location classification (C; as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1J</xref>), and their increased coupling to the rest of the population (D) in context <italic>Y</italic> compared to <italic>X</italic>. ***P&lt;0.001, **P&lt;0.01.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS188717-f003"/></fig><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Adjusting hippocampal population coactivity restores flexible memory.</title><p><bold>(A, B)</bold> Intersectional optogenetic strategy (A) to target CA1 Calb1 neurons recruited during Hfd-context <italic>Y</italic> conditioning (B; <italic>green</italic>, EYFP; <italic>magenta</italic>, Calbindin 1; <italic>blue</italic>, DAPI). <bold>(C, D)</bold> Closed-loop CA1 light delivery controller (C) combined with the optogenetic strategy shown in (A) to suppress superficial <italic>pyramidale</italic> sublayer cells at their preferred theta phase (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure S8C</xref>) during Hfd-context <italic>Y</italic> conditioning. (D) shows example spiking activity for a deep (top) versus a superficial (bottom) <italic>pyramidale</italic> sublayer cell with respect to theta phase-driven light delivery. <bold>(E-I)</bold> Estimation plots (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="S1">methods</xref>). For the optogenetically adjusted ArchT mice, but not the non-optogenetically adjusted EYFP-only mice, this cell-type-selective network-pattern-informed intervention restored normal cNOR performance (E) along with population object-location decoding (F), rebalanced coactivity topology (G, H) and population coupling (I) in context <italic>Y</italic>. ***P&lt;0.001, **P&lt;0.01, *P&lt;0.05.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS188717-f004"/></fig></floats-group></article>