<!DOCTYPE article
 PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" article-type="preprint"><?all-math-mml yes?><?use-mml?><?origin ukpmcpa?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">bioRxiv</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>bioRxiv : the preprint server for biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub"/></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">EMS192679</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2023.12.08.570809</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="archive">PPR771662</article-id><article-version-alternatives><article-version article-version-type="status">preprint</article-version><article-version article-version-type="number">1</article-version></article-version-alternatives><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Increasingly efficient chromatin binding of cohesin and CTCF supports chromatin architecture formation during zebrafish embryogenesis</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Coßmann</surname><given-names>Jonas</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kos</surname><given-names>Pavel I.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Varamogianni-Mamatsi</surname><given-names>Vassiliki</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Assenheimer</surname><given-names>Devin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bischof</surname><given-names>Tobias</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kuhn</surname><given-names>Timo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Vomhof</surname><given-names>Thomas</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Papantonis</surname><given-names>Argyris</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Giorgetti</surname><given-names>Luca</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gebhardt</surname><given-names>J. Christof M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CR1">#</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Institute of Biophysics and IQST, Ulm University, Ulm, Germany</aff><aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Friedrich Miescher Institute for Biomedical Research, University of Basel, Basel, Switzerland</aff><aff id="A3"><label>3</label>Institute of Pathology, University Medical Center Göttingen, Göttingen, Germany</aff><author-notes><corresp id="CR1">
<label>#</label>To whom correspondence should be addressed: <email>christof.gebhardt@uni-ulm.de</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted"><day>11</day><month>12</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="preprint"><day>09</day><month>12</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><permissions><ali:free_to_read/><license><ali:license_ref>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is licensed under a <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">CC BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p id="P1">The three-dimensional folding of chromosomes is essential for nuclear functions such as DNA replication and gene regulation. The emergence of chromatin architecture is thus an important process during embryogenesis. To shed light on the molecular and kinetic underpinnings of chromatin architecture formation, we characterized biophysical properties of cohesin and CTCF binding to chromatin and their changes upon cofactor depletion using single-molecule imaging in live developing zebrafish embryos. We found that chromatin-bound fractions of both cohesin and CTCF increased significantly between the 1000-cell and shield stages, which we could explain through changes in both their association and dissociation rates. Moreover, increasing binding of cohesin restricted chromatin motion, potentially via loop extrusion, and showed distinct stage-dependent nuclear distribution. Polymer simulations with experimentally derived parameters recapitulated the experimentally observed gradual emergence of chromatin architecture. Our findings suggest a kinetic framework of chromatin architecture formation during zebrafish embryogenesis.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec id="S1" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p id="P2">The three-dimensional organization of chromatin is important for nuclear functions such as DNA replication and gene regulation. In interphase, the organizational structures span several hierarchical levels, from chromosome territories<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref></sup> to compartments<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">3</xref></sup>, topologically associating domains (TADs)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">4</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref></sup> and DNA loops<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref></sup> to clutched and separated nucleosomes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref></sup>. TADs and loops contribute to gene regulation by bringing together or insulating enhancers and promoters. They are formed by the architectural protein cohesin through loop extrusion and barrier-forming proteins such as the CCCTC-binding factor (CTCF)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref></sup>.</p><p id="P3">Cohesin is a multi-subunit protein complex that forms a ring-like core complex through the ATPases Smc1/3 and Rad21<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref></sup>. Its ATPase activity and, thereby, the loop extrusion function of the core complex depend on Mau2-Nibpl<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref></sup>, while Wapl determines the release of cohesin from DNA<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref></sup>. The mechanism behind cohesin-mediated loop extrusion is still unclear. Evidence points towards loading of the cohesin complex on the DNA, followed by cohesin reeling in DNA symmetrically or by periodically switching between one-sided extrusion<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">20</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">22</xref></sup>. CTCF binds in an orientation-dependent manner to specific DNA motifs often located at the boundary of TADs<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">23</xref></sup>. It guides the formation of regulatory DNA loops by stalling the loop-extrusion process upon direct interaction with cohesin<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">26</xref></sup>.</p><p id="P4">Chromatin architecture in interphase is absent in zygotes of animals as diverse as flies, zebrafish, and humans<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27">27</xref></sup>, but is gradually reestablished during early embryo development<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">28</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33">33</xref></sup>. In Zebrafish embryos, the new formation of chromatin architecture starts around the 1000-cell stage, concurrent to zygotic genome activation (ZGA), when the embryo begins transcribing its own genome and becomes independent of maternal RNA and protein<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32">32</xref></sup>.</p><p id="P5">While important insight on the mechanistic underpinnings of cohesin-mediated loop extrusion and CTCF, including the interaction kinetics with chromatin and the cellular distribution have been obtained <italic>in vitro</italic> and in cells<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34">34</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42">42</xref></sup>, detailed information on the temporal and spatial behavior <italic>in vivo</italic> is missing. In particular, it is unclear how frequent and how long cohesin and CTCF interact with chromatin, how cohesin action affects chromatin motion, and how these parameters support the formation of chromatin architecture during embryo development.</p><p id="P6">Here, we characterized the binding of cohesin and CTCF to chromatin during early embryogenesis using single molecule tracking in live developing zebrafish embryos and polymer simulations. We measured the fraction of cohesin and CTCF molecules associated with chromatin, their association and dissociation kinetics and the motion of cohesin-bound chromatin at multiple developmental stages. Our experiments and simulations revealed mechanistic insight into these architectural proteins that inform the process of chromatin architecture formation in zebrafish embryogenesis.</p></sec><sec id="S2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="S3"><title>The fraction of chromatin-bound cohesin and CTCF increases during development</title><p id="P7">To be able to visualize cohesin and CTCF in zebrafish embryos, we fused the cohesin subunit rad21 and CTCF to a HaloTag (HT) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1a</xref> and <xref ref-type="sec" rid="S10">Methods</xref>). We injected mRNA encoding for either fusion protein together with mRNA encoding for the nuclear membrane marker GFP-Lap2b into 1-cell stage embryos<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43">43</xref></sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1b</xref> and <xref ref-type="sec" rid="S10">Methods</xref>), which resulted in additional protein expression of ca. 10% for HT-rad21 and 25% for CTCF in shield-stage embryos (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 1</xref>). Prior to imaging, we labeled HT-tagged proteins with HT-dye JF549<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R44">44</xref></sup> and transferred them onto glass-bottom imaging dishes. Illumination of embryos with either 488 nm or 561 nm laser light in a reflected light-sheet microscope<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43">43</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R45">45</xref></sup> enabled detecting the nuclear membrane and the signal of individual HT-rad21 or HT-CTCF molecules in the nucleus.</p><p id="P8">We characterized the overall mobility of HT-rad21 and HT-CTCF in the developmental stages between the 64-cell stage and the shield stage comprising the period of ZGA. In every stage, both species showed mobile and immobile molecules (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1c</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Movie 1 and 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="sec" rid="S10">Methods</xref>). To measure the fraction of immobile molecules, we recorded continuous movies of single HT-tagged molecules with 11.7 ms frame rate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1c</xref>). We analyzed movies using TrackIt<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R46">46</xref></sup>, compiled cumulative histograms of jump distances of tracked molecules (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 2 and 3</xref>), and analyzed these using a model comprising slow, intermediate, and fast diffusion (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 4</xref> and <xref ref-type="sec" rid="S10">Methods</xref>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R47">47</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R48">48</xref></sup>. The slow diffusion component with fraction <italic>A<sub>1</sub></italic> represents immobile molecules presumably bound to chromatin, while intermediate and fast diffusion components with fractions <italic>A<sub>2</sub></italic> and <italic>A<sub>3</sub></italic> account for anomalous diffusion in the nucleus<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R49">49</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R51">51</xref></sup>. For HT-rad21, the fraction of immobile, potentially chromatin-bound molecules increased ca. 8.7-fold, and for HT-CTCF 1.5-fold from 64-cell to shield stage embryos. In contrast, the intermediate and fast diffusion fractions, which presumably comprise freely diffusing molecules in the crowded nucleus, remained roughly constant (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1d and e</xref>). Thus, HT-rad21 and HT-CTCF are more and more driven to the chromatin-bound state during early embryo development.</p></sec><sec id="S4"><title>Long, not short binding of cohesin and CTCF is associated with default DNA binding</title><p id="P9">While analysis of continuous movies reveals the overall bound fraction of molecules, we used an interlaced time-lapse microscopy (ITM) approach to further distinguish chromatin-bound molecules within different binding time classes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43">43</xref></sup>. We chose a repetitive ITM illumination pattern comprising 11.7 ms images interlaced with alternating dark times of 0.2 s and 4 s, which enabled us to separate short-bound molecules that survived a 0.2 s dark time from long-bound molecules that survived at least two 4 s dark times while being confined to a small area (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1f</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Movie 3 and 4</xref>). Importantly, due to the Poissonian nature of molecular interactions, this temporal scheme allowed separating binding classes with distinct dissociation kinetics<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43">43</xref></sup>. Our ITM approach revealed that the fraction of short-bound molecules of both HT-rad21 and HT-CTCF increased ca. 1.5-fold from 64-cell stage to shield stage embryos (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1g and h</xref>, right). The fraction of long-bound HT-rad21 molecules increased ca. 21.5-fold during this time period, while the fraction of long-bound HT-CTCF molecules increased only ca. 3.3-fold (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1g and h</xref>, left).</p><p id="P10">To shed further light onto the nature of the short and long binding classes of HT-rad21 and HT-CTCF, we repeated the ITM experiments with an HT-tagged triple mutant of rad21, HT-rad21-3x, which cannot form a DNA-binding cohesin complex anymore<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37">37</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R52">52</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R53">53</xref></sup>. We also imaged an HT-tagged CTCF mutant lacking the intermediate zinc finger domains 4 to 7, HT-CTCF-ΔZF4-7, which impedes binding of CTCF to its core motif<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R54">54</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R55">55</xref></sup>, and an HT-only control. Both HT-rad21-3x and HT-CTCF-ΔZF4-7 still exhibited a fraction of molecules in the short binding class (short-bound fraction) comparable to the wild-type proteins, while their fraction in the long binding class (long-bound fraction) was, on average, reduced by 93% (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1g and h</xref>). For the HT control, short-binding events were up to 4-fold reduced and long-binding events were reduced on average by 98 % of wild-type cohesin or CTCF (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 5a</xref>). Overall, our ITM results indicate that the long-bound fractions of HT-rad21 or HT-CTCF are predominantly associated with their default chromatin-binding function, while the short-bound fractions are not. Notably, the percentage of long-bound molecules is significantly increased in the shield stage compared to the 64-cell stage, demonstrating that chromatin binding of architectural proteins is dynamically modulated during development.</p></sec><sec id="S5"><title>Wapl, CTCF, and RNA Polymerase II influence the long-bound fraction of cohesin</title><p id="P11">Loop-extruding cohesin relies on various cofactors, including Nipbl, which supports the ATPase activity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref></sup>, the cohesin unloader Wapl<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R56">56</xref></sup>, and CTCF, which protects cohesin unloading by Wapl<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R57">57</xref></sup>. We hypothesized that altering the expression levels of Wapl and CTCF should affect the default DNA binding mode, that is the long-bound fraction of rad21, but not its short-bound fraction. We therefore repeated our ITM measurements in the presence of morpholinos (MOs) impeding the expression of either Nipbl, Wapl, or CTCF. Reduction of Nipbl and CTCF expression levels by MOs have been characterized previously<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R58">58</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R60">60</xref></sup>. We confirmed repression of Wapl upon injection of Wapl-MO using Western Blotting (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="sec" rid="S10">Methods</xref>). We compared the effect of the MOs on the long and short-bound fractions of cohesin in the shield stage (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1i</xref>) and compared with control injections (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 5b</xref>). As predicted, only the long-bound fraction of cohesin was significantly reduced upon CTCF repression and significantly increased upon reduction of Wapl expression. Nipbl did not significantly reduce the long-bound cohesin fraction. Together, the influence of cohesin binding by the cofactors Nipbl, Wapl, and CTCF was compatible with their reported effects on loop-extruding cohesin.</p><p id="P12">Since it was proposed that the initial formation of chromatin architecture in <italic>Drosophila</italic> and mice is independent of transcription<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31">31</xref></sup>, we further tested the impact of RNA Polymerase II, in particular RNA polymerase II elongation, on the binding of cohesin. Therefore, we repeated our ITM measurements in the presence of α-Amanitin or Triptolide (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="S10">Methods</xref>), which both prevent RNA Polymerase II elongation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31">31</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R61">61</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R65">65</xref></sup>. Both drugs increased the short- as well as the long-bound fractions of HT-rad21, indicating that elongation of RNA Polymerase II might disturb the binding of cohesin molecules to chromatin.</p></sec><sec id="S6"><title>Cohesin bound long to chromatin shows reduced spatial confinement in presence of Nipbl</title><p id="P13">It has been shown by monitoring histone mobility and by simulations that the overall mobility of chromatin increases if the expression level of cohesin is reduced<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R66">66</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R68">68</xref></sup>. In our experiments, the DNA binding-deficient mutant HT-rad21-3x showed predominantly short binding events (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1h</xref>), suggesting that long-bound cohesin mirrors the motion of chromatin. We hypothesized that the long-bound fraction of cohesin might contribute to restricting chromatin movement, if its ability to extrude loops is undisturbed. To test our hypotheses, we measured the spatial confinement of short- or long-bound HT-rad21 in shield stage. We devised a novel illumination scheme, time-lapse alternated with continuous intervals (TACO), which combined our ITM scheme to filter for short- or long-bound molecules with periods of ten continuously illuminated images. We analyzed the confinement of HT-rad21 molecules in short or long binding classes by quantifying the mean jump distances of tracked molecules (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2a</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Movie 5-8</xref> and <xref ref-type="sec" rid="S10">Methods</xref>). Supporting our hypotheses, we observed that the mean jump distances of (91 ± 47) nm for HT-rad21 bound long to chromatin were significantly shorter than the value of (166 ± 73) nm for short-bound HT-rad21 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2b</xref>). Moreover, at reduced levels of Nipbl in presence of Nipbl-MO, mean jump distances of long-bound HT-rad21 increased significantly to (112 ± 58) nm compared to undisturbed conditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2b</xref>). This indicates that the Nipbl-facilitated ATPase activity of cohesin, and thereby potentially loop extrusion, is required in restricting chromatin motion (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2c</xref>).</p><p id="P14">We next repeated the TACO experiment for two additional phases during early development, where the first phase comprised the 64- to 512-cell stages (pre-ZGA) and the second phase the high to sphere stages (post-ZGA). Mean jump distances of both short-bound and long-bound cohesin molecules decreased from pre-ZGA to shield stage (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2b</xref>). This is compatible with an increase in chromatin architecture during embryo development<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32">32</xref></sup>. Notably, within every developmental phase, chromatin loci bound long by HT-rad21 were less mobile than short-bound HT-rad21 molecules. Thus, our TACO measurements indicate a role of long-bound, presumably loop-extruding cohesin molecules in reducing chromatin mobility. Long-bound cohesin shows distinct nuclear distribution</p><p id="P15">We further characterized the nuclear distribution of long-bound cohesin. Therefore, we devised a measure of radial nuclear position, the center-border distance (CBD), which ranged from the nuclear center (CBD = 0) to the periphery (CBD = 1) in five equidistant radial steps (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="S10">Methods</xref>). We then sorted every long-bound track from both ITM (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1f</xref>) and TACO (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2a</xref>) measurements into CBD bins (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2d</xref>) and normalized to bin area (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2e</xref>). We found that the density of long-bound cohesin was highest at the nuclear center in the pre-ZGA phase but shifted towards a more isotropic distribution in the post-ZGA phase.</p><p id="P16">At shield stage, we observed that long-bound cohesin was sparse at the nuclear periphery.</p></sec><sec id="S7"><title>Changes in the binding kinetics of cohesin and CTCF facilitate chromatin binding during development</title><p id="P17">Our ITM experiments enabled comparing chromatin binding of HT-rad21 and HT-CTCF at multiple experimental conditions. However, they yield relative, not absolute binding times and fractions of binding classes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43">43</xref></sup>. To obtain absolute bound fractions and dissociation rates (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3a</xref>), we employed a classical time-lapse illumination approach in which we imaged HT-rad21 or HT-CTCF molecules either continuously with 502 ms frame time or interspersed with a dark time of 4 s (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3b</xref>). This approach allows correcting for tracking errors and photobleaching of fluorophores and enables covering a broad temporal bandwidth<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R45">45</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R46">46</xref></sup>. Here, we counted fluorescent molecules as bound if they were confined for at least three frames (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3c</xref> and <xref ref-type="sec" rid="S10">Methods</xref>) and collected the fluorescence survival times of such binding events (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3d and e</xref>). We again considered the three developmental phases pre-ZGA, post-ZGA, and shield stage, which revealed a shift of fluorescence survival time distributions to longer times at later stages. We analyzed the fluorescence survival time distributions using the GRID method, which applies a Laplace transformation to infer full dissociation rate spectra of the respective survival time distribution (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3f and g</xref>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R69">69</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R70">70</xref></sup>. Dissociation rates can be converted to residence times by inversion (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="S10">Methods</xref>).</p><p id="P18">For both cohesin and CTCF, residence times increased in value and fraction during early development (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3f and g</xref>), up to comparably long residence times of ~100 s in shield stage (cohesin: (99 ± 6) s; CTCF: (89 ±11) s; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 12 and 13</xref>). In agreement with an increasing residence time, the survival times of long-bound fluorescent molecules in ITM measurements also increased during development (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 7</xref>). Informed by our ITM measurements, we separated the distribution of residence times into short-bound (&lt;10 s) and long-bound (&gt;10 s) regimes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3f and g</xref>, grey inserts). As expected from the ITM measurements, the overall long-bound fraction from time-lapse measurements increased moderately for HT-CTCF between pre-ZGA and shield stage, while it showed a strong increase for HT-rad21 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3h</xref> and <xref ref-type="sec" rid="S10">Methods</xref>).</p><p id="P19">CTCF has been proposed to transiently associate with RNA-containing clusters while searching for a specific target site<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40">40</xref></sup>. This process is formally similar to a search mechanism including free diffusion and one-dimensional sliding on unspecific sites commonly applied to DNA binding proteins<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35">35</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R71">71</xref></sup>. Therefore, we considered such a mechanism to quantify the time one of the HT-CTCF molecules needed to find any of the accessible specific target sequences on chromatin. This target site search time depends on the overall bound fraction, the fraction and residence time of specific binding events, and the residence time of unspecific binding events (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="S10">Methods</xref>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R72">72</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R73">73</xref></sup>. Since the DNA binding mutant HT-CTCF-ΔZF4-7 showed predominantly short binding events (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1g</xref>), we identified the long-bound fraction of HT-CTCF with specific binding. The association times we calculated for one HT-CTCF molecule to any accessible specific site varied between ~150 s (pre-ZGA), ~330 s (post-ZGA), and ~210 s (shield stage) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3i</xref>). For cohesin, the search mechanism is not known. We therefore estimated the association rate from an equilibrium model including two types of binding classes of short and long cohesin binding (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="S10">Methods</xref>) <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R73">73</xref></sup>. Similar to CTCF, the time we obtained for cohesin to find a long-bound site increased from pre-ZGA (~420 s) to post-ZGA (~902 s) and dropped to ~180 s in shield stage (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3i</xref>). These association times can be converted to association rates by inversion.</p><p id="P20">We further estimated the search times of any HT-rad21 or HT-CTCF molecule to chromatin by considering the relative changes in protein concentration during early zebrafish development (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Figure 8</xref> and <xref ref-type="sec" rid="S10">Methods</xref>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R74">74</xref></sup>. For both HT-CTCF and HT-rad21, the relative search time dropped during development (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3j</xref>).</p><p id="P21">The chromatin-bound fraction of proteins is coupled to the association and dissociation kinetics as well as the concentration of accessible binding sites and the nuclear size via the physicochemical law of mass action<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43">43</xref></sup>. We compared the measured fraction of long-bound HT-CTCF and HT-rad21 molecules with the bound fractions calculated from the association and dissociation rates within the physicochemical model, and found good agreement (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3h</xref> and <xref ref-type="sec" rid="S10">Methods</xref>). This indicates that the altered binding kinetics are sufficient to explain the increase in the bound fractions of HT-rad21 and HT-CTCF during zebrafish development(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3k</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S8"><title>Polymer modeling recapitulates emergence of loop extrusion patterns caused by changing cohesin kinetics</title><p id="P22">Our measurements revealed a notable increase in the residence time and a decrease in the effective search time of both cohesin and CTCF during zebrafish embryogenesis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>). To demonstrate the effect of changing binding kinetics on chromosome folding, we simulated cohesin-mediated loop extrusion using a physical model, which enabled comparing interaction features against published Hi-C experimental data<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32">32</xref></sup>. Our model was constructed as a polymer chain, including excluded volume interactions and loop extrusion<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R68">68</xref></sup>. Within this model, we established a direct correspondence between spatial and temporal units (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="S10">Methods</xref>). Spatial units are important for the spatial organization of chromosomes, while time units are crucial to evaluate the processivity rate of extrusion. We calibrated temporal units based on measurements in mouse embryonic stem cells<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R68">68</xref></sup>.</p><p id="P23">To assess the effect of changing cohesin kinetics, we chose a processivity rate of 0.5 kb/sec (an intermediate value between <italic>in vitro</italic> measurements <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref></sup> and <italic>in vivo</italic> estimates<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R75">75</xref></sup>) and performed an extensive sweeping of the parameter space of cohesin binding kinetics, covering one order of magnitude of association rates and residence times in the range of our measured values (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 10a and b</xref>). From this, we identified a subset of relative association rates, 0.6, 3, and 15 [Mb*min]<sup>-1</sup>, for pre-ZGA, post-ZGA, and shield stages, comparable to our experimentally found changes in the effective cohesin association rate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3j</xref>). We focused on the pre-ZGA and shield stages with the two cohesin residence times of 50 s and 100 s, respectively (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 12</xref>).</p><p id="P24">We represented our simulated trajectories as contact maps, which resemble the output of Hi-C experiments that capture contacts between pairs of DNA loci (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4a, d</xref>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32">32</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R76">76</xref></sup>. To reveal the general principles of the spatial chromosome organization, we determined the average contact probability <italic>P(s)</italic> as a function of the genomic distance <italic>s</italic> for each stage (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4b, e</xref>). As expected from theoretical analysis of looped polymers<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R77">77</xref></sup>, increasing the extruder association rate and residence time resulted in increased <italic>P(s)</italic> around the average size of the extruded loops (green arrowhead in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4b</xref>) and depletion of contacts at longer length scales (orange arrowhead). This is reflected in the local slope of <italic>P(s)</italic> being smaller around the average loop size and bigger at long length scales (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4c</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 10e, f</xref>). These results are in qualitative agreement with experimentally observed changes in contact maps of the pre-ZGA and shield stages (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4e, f</xref>).</p><p id="P25">To estimate the influence of increasing CTCF binding, we conducted simulations with a lower spatial resolution of 10 kb. This enabled us to simulate a longer chromosome region of 50 Mb and thus compensate for the sparsity of accessible CTCF sites in the initial phases of development (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 10d</xref>). We included CTCF sites identified in ChIP-seq data for the pre-ZGA and shield stages (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="S10">Methods</xref>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R78">78</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R79">79</xref></sup>. Again, in qualitative agreement with published experimental Hi-C data, we observed progressively increased insulation around CTCF sites, which is indicative of increased stalling of loop-extruding cohesin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4g</xref>).</p><p id="P26">Comparison of polymer simulations with Hi-C data thus supports the notion that increased binding efficiency of cohesin and CTCF molecules during early development is accompanied by increased loop extrusion activity and physical insulation upon stalling of cohesin at CTCF sites (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4h</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="S9" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p id="P27">Here, we characterized the binding properties of the architectural proteins cohesin and CTCF during early development in live zebrafish embryos. We initially set out to understand the nature of single-molecule binding events of CTCF and cohesin. For CTCF, comparison of the wild-type protein with the DNA binding-deficient mutant CTCF-ΔZF4-7 in ITM experiments enabled associating binding events longer than 10 s with binding to specific CTCF target sequences, while shorter events likely arose from unspecific transient interactions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1g</xref>). Similarly, the rad21-3x mutant, which prevents DNA binding of the cohesin complex, significantly reduced binding events of cohesin longer than 10 s in ITM experiments, while shorter events were unaffected (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1h</xref>). This enabled associating long cohesin interactions with DNA binding. For such distinctions, ITM is advantageous over continuous illumination<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">25</xref></sup> since it enables separating binding time classes and thereby distinguishing long binding events of molecules above a transient background.</p><p id="P28">Several of our experiments suggested that long rad21 binding events were at least partially associated with the loop extrusion function of cohesin: i) Reducing the expression level of Wapl significantly increased long but not short rad21-DNA interactions in ITM experiments (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1i</xref>), consistent with Wapl-mediated unloading of loop extruding cohesin<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R56">56</xref></sup>. Importantly, cohesin involved in sister chromatid cohesion is protected by Sororin from Wapl-mediated unloading<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R80">80</xref></sup>. ii) Reducing the expression level of CTCF significantly reduced long but not short rad21-DNA interactions in ITM experiments (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1i</xref>). This could be due to a stabilizing effect of CTCF bound to TAD borders on cohesin through their mutual binding interaction<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">25</xref></sup>. Additionally, CTCF protects cohesin from Wapl-induced unloading<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R57">57</xref></sup>. iii) Reducing the expression level of Nipbl significantly increased the mobility of rad21 bound long to chromatin in TACO experiments (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2b</xref>). This enabled associating long-binding cohesin with loop extruding cohesin, since Nipbl stimulates the ATPase activity of cohesin and is required for the loop extrusion function. A low mobility of rad21-bound chromatin in the presence of loop extrusion is consistent with polymer simulations<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R68">68</xref></sup>. Overall, our experiments enabled discerning CTCF bound to specific target sequences and cohesin molecules potentially involved in loop extrusion.</p><p id="P29">We found that the binding properties of cohesin and CTCF changed during embryo development and affected chromatin architecture in several ways. First, we observed a decrease in mobility of cohesin-bound chromatin during early zebrafish embryogenesis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2b</xref>). This is consistent with higher chromatin mobility in pluripotent embryonic stem cells than in differentiated cells<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R81">81</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R82">82</xref></sup>, and compatible with an increase in chromatin architecture during embryo development<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32">32</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33">33</xref></sup>. For the radial distribution of long-bound, potentially loop-extruding cohesin, we found a transition from a high central density in pre-ZGA to a more isotropic density with a pronounced decrease at the nuclear border in shield-stage embryos (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2e</xref>). In mammals, the chromatin of differentiated cells is enriched in active histone marks at the nuclear center and repressive marks at the nuclear periphery<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R83">83</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R84">84</xref></sup>. Moreover, it was found that CTCF and rad21 levels were decreased in heterochromatin-enriched lamina-associated domains of mouse embryonic stem cells<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R85">85</xref></sup>. Since histone modifications and chromatin accessibility are gradually established over the zygotic genome activation in zebrafish<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R86">86</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R87">87</xref></sup>, our observations might reflect the transition from pluripotent cells to more differentiated cells.</p><p id="P30">Second, we observed an increase in the chromatin-bound fractions of cohesin upon Triptolide or α -Amanitin treatment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1i</xref>). Since both Triptolide and α-Amanitin show distinct inhibitory effects on RNA PolII<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R61">61</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R65">65</xref></sup>, this increase might be due to more efficient loading at sites of stalled PolII<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R88">88</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R89">89</xref></sup> or due to negative interference of elongating RNA PolII with DNA-bound cohesin. The latter case is still compatible with work showing that PolII is able to push cohesin<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R90">90</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R91">91</xref></sup>, if a fraction of cohesin remains bound to DNA, and compatible with counteraction of loop extrusion and formation of new TADs by RNA-PolII<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R88">88</xref></sup>. Our experiments suggest that disturbing transcription should not interfere with cohesin-mediated chromatin organization. This agrees with recent observations where the initial formation of chromatin architecture in <italic>Drosophila</italic> and mice was independent of transcription<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31">31</xref></sup>.</p><p id="P31">Third, we found that the binding kinetics of cohesin and CTCF changed during embryogenesis. For both molecular species, the effective association time decreased during development (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3k</xref>). This can be understood by an increase in the absolute protein numbers<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R74">74</xref></sup>, a decrease in the nuclear size, and, for CTCF, an increase in the number of accessible target sites<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R78">78</xref></sup>. The residence times of both species increased during early embryo development, up to similar values of ~100 s (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3f and g</xref>). For CTCF, the longest residence time is comparable to a previously reported value of ~120 s<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37">37</xref></sup>. For cohesin, our value is considerably shorter than previous estimates of ~20 min from fluorescence recovery after photobleaching experiments in mammalian cells<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37">37</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41">41</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R57">57</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R68">68</xref></sup>. This might be due to species-specific differences. For example, longer cell cycles in mammalian cells compared to zebrafish embryos<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R92">92</xref></sup> might allow longer residence times. The increase in residence time we observed might be due to a mutual stabilization of CTCF and cohesin at TAD borders<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">25</xref></sup>, changes in the relative concentrations of Stag1 and Stag2 that were suggested to give rise to differently stable cohesin binding<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R57">57</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R93">93</xref></sup>, changes in the degree of acetylation of SMC3<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R57">57</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R94">94</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R96">96</xref></sup>, or the level of other interaction partners such as Wapl. It will be interesting to screen for the origin of the increasing residence times in the future.</p><p id="P32">Fourth, for both cohesin and CTCF, the fraction of long-binding events significantly increased during early embryo development. We could recapitulate this increase by inserting our observed changes in the binding kinetics of both species into a physicochemical model of binding considering a decreasing nuclear size and an increasing target site accessibility during early development (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3k</xref>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43">43</xref></sup>. This model previously could explain a comparable increase in the bound fractions of the transcription factors TBP and Sox19b<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43">43</xref></sup>. The monotonous change in binding kinetics and, thus, the increase in the bound fraction of long-bound cohesin and CTCF molecules imply that the absolute number of bound architectural proteins involved in organizing chromatin increases during embryogenesis. This is compatible with a gradual formation of chromatin architecture<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32">32</xref></sup>. We additionally characterized the effect of changing binding kinetics of cohesin and CTCF on the organization of chromatin by considering our measured kinetic parameters in polymer simulations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>). These revealed changes in chromatin architecture between the pre-ZGA and shield stages comparable to Hi-C experiments<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32">32</xref></sup>. Our results indicate that the changes in the residence time and the search time of cohesin and therefore the increase of its chromatin-bound fraction are important to globally establish chromatin organization by DNA looping (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4j</xref>).</p><p id="P33">To conclude, our single-molecule measurements of cohesin and CTCF binding in live developing zebrafish embryos, in particular the different illumination schemes and altered cofactor levels, revealed the molecular basis of gradual chromatin architecture formation and provided a starting point to characterize the function of architectural proteins such as cohesin in the natural environment of a living embryo.</p></sec><sec id="S10" sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec id="S11"><title>Zebrafish husbandry</title><p id="P34">Zebrafish of the Wild Indian Karyotype (WIK) were maintained by the Weidinger lab (Institute of Biochemistry and Molecular Biology, Ulm University, Ulm, Germany) following the guidelines of the EU directive 2010/63/EU, the German Animal Welfare Act and the State of Baden-Württemberg (Germany) in addition to being permitted by the Regierungspräsidium Tübingen. Zebrafish were solely kept for breeding, and all experiments exclusively used zebrafish embryos before 48 hours post-fertilization.</p></sec><sec id="S12"><title>Generation of wild-type HaloTag constructs, RNA synthesis and Western blot validation</title><p id="P35">We generated N-terminally tagged HaloTag (HT) constructs (HT-rad21, HT-CTCF) by overhang PCR with restriction enzyme sites for PacI, AscI, and complementary DNA sequences for rad21a (OTTDART00000061990, ZFIN) or CTCF (NM_001001844.1, NCBI). The DNA template was cDNA isolated from 1-cell stage zebrafish embryos<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43">43</xref></sup>. Primers are listed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 18</xref>.</p><p id="P36">We cloned digested PCR Fragments in a pCS2-2xHA-HALO-3xGS backbone comprising two HA-tags, the HaloTag, a flexible 3xGS-linker upstream, and an SV40 PolyA tail downstream of the insertion site. The cloning products were amplified in DH5-α cells and isolated using the QIAprep Spin Miniprep Kit (Qiagen) according to the manufacturer’s protocol. All cloning products were validated by Sanger sequencing before proceeding with RNA synthesis.</p><p id="P37">We obtained the control constructs (HT-rad21-3x, HT-CTCF-ΔZF4-7) by site-directed mutagenesis of the HT-rad21 and HT-CTCF plasmids using the Q5 Site-Directed Mutagenesis Kit (New England BioLabs) according to the manufacturer’s protocol with primers given in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 18</xref>. The HT-rad21-3x construct contained three point mutations (F609R, L613R, Q625K) that were previously described to prevent proper cohesin complex formation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37">37</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R52">52</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R53">53</xref></sup>. The HT-CTCF-ΔZF4-7 construct was depleted of its zinc finger domains 4-7 (annotation from Q6JAA4, Uniprot), responsible for CTCF’s primary DNA binding to the core CTCF motif<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R54">54</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R55">55</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R97">97</xref></sup>. Successful mutagenesis was validated by Sanger sequencing before proceeding with RNA synthesis.</p><p id="P38">We synthesized RNA using the mMESSAGE mMACHINE SP6 Transcription Kit (Invitrogen) following the manufacturer’s protocol after plasmid linearization with NotI-HF (New England BioLabs). RNA cleanup was performed with the RNeasy Plus Mini Kit (Qiagen) according to the manufacturer’s protocol. α-Bungarotoxin RNA was synthesized as described above using the pmtb-t7-alpha-bungarotoxin plasmid, a gift from Sean Megason (#69542, Addgene)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R98">98</xref></sup>. eGFP-Lap2β mRNA was generated as described previously<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43">43</xref></sup>. Control HaloTag mRNA was produced from the pCS2-2xHA-HALO-3xGS plasmid without any insert.</p><p id="P39">Ectopic protein expression levels were determined by Western blotting. We isolated protein from 20 shield stage wild-type embryos and embryos injected with 6.7 pg of mRNA encoding for HT-rad21 or 10 pg of mRNA encoding for HT-CTCF based on a standard Western Blot protocol. We chose 10-fold larger injection amounts compared to our single-molecule measurements to observe the HT-protein band. The primary anti-Rad21 antibody (ab992, Abcam) was diluted 1:500, and the anti-CTCF antibody (ab128873, Abcam) 1:3000. Quantification was performed with Image Lab 6.0 by dividing the background subtracted HT-protein band intensity with the endogenous protein band intensity. To obtain the overexpression level of our single-molecule measurements, we divided the value by our over-injection factor of 10.</p></sec><sec id="S13"><title>Sample preparation for single-molecule imaging</title><p id="P40">After spawning, we dechorionated zebrafish embryos in a 1 mg/ml pronase (10165921001, Sigma-Aldrich) Danieau’s medium solution for three minutes, followed by washing in Danieau’s medium. Still in the 1-cell stage, embryos were injected with 5 pg of Lap2β mRNA together with either 1pg Halo-CTCF, 1pg Halo-CTCF-ΔZF4-7, 0.67 pg Halo-rad21, 0.67pg Halo-rad21-3x mRNA (33.5pg for 24 hpf measurements), or 1 pg Halo mRNA (control). Measurements at 24 hpf required an additional 50 pg of α-Bungarotoxin mRNA to prevent embryos from twitching<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R98">98</xref></sup>. To set the injection volume of 1 nl on the pneumatic PicoPump (World Precision Instruments), we adjusted the injection duration to yield droplets of 124 μm, determined by a stereo microscope (Olympus SZX2-ZB10) and a camera (CAM-SC50).</p><p id="P41">HaloTag proteins were labeled by transferring zebrafish embryos to glass tubes followed by incubation in 10 nM HaloTag-JF549 dye solution (50 nM for 24 hpf measurements). After 15 and 30 min past labeling, embryos were washed twice and further bred in Danieau’s medium at room temperature (22 °C) or at 28 °C for shield-stage and 24 hpf measurements. We visually monitored the development of room-temperature embryos until they synchronously reached the 32-cell stage. Then, 4-6 embryos were transferred to a 170 μm thick glass bottom imaging dish (Delta T, Bioptechs) on the reflected light-sheet microscope. Embryos were measured at room temperature in Danieau’s buffer while progressing in development. During measurement, we identified cell divisions and developmental stages using the eGFP-labeled nuclear membrane marker Lap2β. Movies were recorded after fusion of karyomeres and at the largest nuclear cross-section. Measurements were concluded after sphere-stage. The shield-stage and 24 hpf embryos were taken out from the incubator 30 min before measurement, placed on the imaging dish as aforementioned, and measured for a maximum duration of 1 h.</p><p id="P42">To inhibit RNA Polymerase II, we used α-Amanitin (A2263, Sigma-Aldrich), which was dissolved in water and included in the RNA injection mix at a final 0.4 mg/ml concentration. As described above, the injection mix was injected into zebrafish embryos with HT-rad21 and Lap2β RNA. The concentration was similar to previous reports<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R99">99</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R103">103</xref></sup>. Moreover, we used Triptolide (645900, Sigma-Aldrich) dissolved in DMSO and diluted to a 5 μM solution in Danieau’s medium on the day of usage. After dye incubation, embryos were washed and kept in a Triptolide solution for further development and imaging. Triptolide concentration and handling are comparable to previous reports<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R104">104</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R105">105</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="S14"><title>Morpholino (MO) handling and Western blot validation</title><p id="P43">All MOs targeting RNA translation were obtained from Gene Tools LLC (Philomath, USA) and coinjected with 0.67 pg HT-rad21 and 5 pg eGFP-Lap2β mRNA as described above. We used 4 ng of the single CTCF-morpholino (ctcf-MO) or 1 ng of each nipbl-morpholino (nipbla and nipblb, in short nipbl-MO) per injection. Both the CTCF<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R106">106</xref></sup> and the nipbl-MOs<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R107">107</xref></sup> were previously validated with comparable injection amounts. Negative control measurements were performed by coinjection of 4.5 ng standard control morpholino mRNA obtained from Gene Tools LLC (Philomath, USA). In order to target the two wapl paralogs wapla (XM_021473179.1, NCBI) and waplb (XM_021472510.1, NCBI), we designed two translation blocking morpholinos (in short wapl-MO, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 19</xref>) with 2 ng of each morpholino for injection.</p><p id="P44">We validated the wapl-MOs by Western blotting (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 1</xref>). Therefore, we isolated protein from 20 shield-stage wild-type or 2 ng wapla-MO and 2 ng waplb-MO injected embryos based on a standard Western Blot protocol. The primary anti-WAPL antibody (JE51-75, Invitrogen) was diluted 1:500, and the anti-γ-Tubulin antibody was diluted 1:100000 (ab11316, Abcam). We quantified Western blots of three biological replicates with Image Lab 6.0 by first normalizing the background subtracted Wapl-band to the γ-Tubulin band, followed by dividing the morpholino-injected value with the wild-type value.</p></sec><sec id="S15"><title>Reflected light-sheet microscopy</title><p id="P45">Single-molecule movies of live developing zebrafish embryos were recorded on a custom-built reflected light-sheet microscope, allowing lateral excitation of the ~700 μm large zebrafish embryos<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43">43</xref></sup>. A commercial Nikon TI microscope body laid the foundation together with a 1.2 NA water-immersion objective (60× 1.20 NA Plan Apo VC W, NIKON), dichroic mirror (F73–866/F58–533, AHF), emission filter (F72–866/ F57–532, AHF), notch filter (F40–072/F40–513, AHF) and an EM-CCD camera (iXon Ultra DU 897U, Andor). An additional 1.5x post-magnification in the detection path resulted in an effective pixel size of 166 nm. Peripheral devices were controlled with a NIDAQ data acquisition card (National Instruments) and the NIS Elements software (Version 4.40.00 64-bit, Nikon). Laser illuminations during camera exposures were driven by a custom controller, reacting to camera triggers and following predefined patterns (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 20</xref>).</p><p id="P46">The excitation path used 488 nm (iBEAM-SMART-488-S-HP, 200mW, Toptica) and 561 nm (Jive 300, 300mW, Cobolt) lasers, combined and then controlled by an AOTF (AOTFnC-400.650-TN, AA Optoelectronics), followed by a single-mode fiber connected into a custom-built tower. The light sheet is created in the tower by a cylindrical lens that is focused in the back-focal plane of a vertically mounted water-dipping objective (40× 0.8 NA HCX Apo L W, Leica). The tower was placed above the imaging dish and reflected the excitation light sheet laterally with a custom-coated cantilever (40 nm Al coating on both sides of HYDRA2R-100N-TL-20, AppNano). The approximately 3 μm thick light sheet was set to 47 mW and 5 mW after the excitation objective for the 561 nm and 488 nm laser, respectively.</p><p id="P47">We recorded continuous, interlaced time-lapse microscopy (ITM) and time-lapse alternated with continuous intervals (TACO) movies with 10 ms of exposure time and 1.7 ms of camera readout time, resulting in a total frame cycle time of 11.7 ms. Movies for time-lapse illumination were recorded with 500 ms exposure and a total frame cycle time of 501.7 ms. All illumination schemes contained combinations of the nuclear membrane marker eGFP-Lap2β (488 nm) to track the nucleus and drift, 561 nm exposure for HaloTag-JF549 excitation, and dark times without laser excitation (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 20</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S16"><title>Analysis of single-molecule microscopy data</title><p id="P48">Single continuous movies were split into single files for the 488 nm and 561 nm channels using the Movie splitter tool of TrackIt<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R46">46</xref></sup>. Movies with considerable drift were discarded to prevent tracking and subsequent analysis errors.</p><p id="P49">We analyzed all single-molecule microscopy data with the nearest neighbor algorithm of TrackIt and tracking parameters shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 21</xref>. Nuclear tracking regions were drawn based on z-projections of the Lap2β signal if not indicated otherwise.</p></sec><sec id="S17"><title>Data analysis of continuous movies: bound fractions and diffusion coefficients</title><p id="P50">First, we recorded continuous movies with a frame cycle time of 11.7 ms and tracked 100 frames with TrackIt (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 21</xref>). Next, we determined diffusion rates and amplitudes by fitting cumulative distributions of the jump distances within detected tracks with a three-component Brownian diffusion model using the data analysis tool of TrackIt<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R46">46</xref></sup>. The bin width was set to 1 nm, resulting in a total of 747 bins. Jumps over gap frames were removed, and the number of jumps to consider per track was set to 10 in order to prevent overrepresentation of bound molecules<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R45">45</xref></sup>. Effects from molecules moving out of the focus plane (overestimation of bound fraction) or tracking of 3D movement in a 2D plane (underestimation of diffusion coefficients) were not corrected. However, these effects are present to a similar extent in all stages, and relative comparisons are not affected. Errors of diffusion coefficients and amplitudes were estimated based on the standard deviation from analyzing 500 subsets of the jump distances, including 80% of randomly selected jump distances. The amplitude of the slowest diffusion component represented the overall bound fraction <italic>f<sub>b</sub></italic> of the tracked molecules. The unbound fraction of tracked molecules is given by <italic>p<sub>f</sub></italic> =<italic>1-f<sub>b</sub></italic>.</p><p id="P51">To evaluate whether a three-component diffusion model was superior to a two-component diffusion model, the reduced chi-squared and Akaike Information Criterion (AIC) were calculated for each model. The AIC provides a measure for the balance between the goodness of a fit and the complexity of a model, where more complex models with a higher number of parameters are punished. The differences between the models were calculated according to equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD1">1</xref>): <disp-formula id="FD1"><label>(1)</label><mml:math id="M1"><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Δ</mml:mtext><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="0.3em"/><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.3em"/></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>ln</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.3em"/></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.3em"/></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>ln</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula> here, the residual sum of squares (RSS) reflects the sum of differences between data and fit from the cumulative jump distance plot, k reflects the number of parameters from the two- or three-component models, and n is the total number of bins. A positive ΔAIC value indicates a preferential three-component model, whereas a negative value indicates a preferential two-component model.</p></sec><sec id="S18"><title>Data analysis of interlaced time-lapse microscopy (ITM): relative fractions in binding time classes</title><p id="P52">We recorded ITM movies to classify molecules into three binding time classes, namely spots (single frame), short bound (0.2s), and long bound (&gt;8.2s), and to calculate the relative fraction of molecules binding in each class. The illumination scheme includes short and long dark times between frames of molecule detection (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 20</xref>).</p><p id="P53">The tracking and analysis parameters for TrackIt are provided in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 21</xref>. Bound fractions of the binding classes were calculated movie-wise with TrackIts data analysis tool using the following equations (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD2">2</xref>) and (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD3">3</xref>): <disp-formula id="FD2"><label>(2)</label><mml:math id="M2"><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.3em"/><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.3em"/><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.3em"/><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.3em"/><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.3em"/></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.3em"/><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.3em"/></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.3em"/></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.3em"/></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.3em"/></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.3em"/></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula> here N<sub>long</sub> represented the number of all tracks surviving two or more long dark times (&gt;8.2 s), and Nshort all tracks with one long or no long dark time. Nspot depicted the number of all single detections.</p><p id="P54"><disp-formula id="FD3"><label>(3)</label><mml:math id="M3"><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.3em"/><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.3em"/><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.3em"/><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.3em"/><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.3em"/></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.3em"/><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.3em"/></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.3em"/></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.3em"/></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.3em"/></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.3em"/></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula> here N<sub>short</sub> was the sum of all tracks that lasted for one short dark time (0.2 s), and N<sub>long</sub> was the sum of tracks that passed at least one long dark time.</p></sec><sec id="S19"><title>Data analysis of time-lapse alternated with continuous intervals (TACO): mobility of molecules in certain binding time classes</title><p id="P55">The TACO scheme can classify tracks in binding time classes similar to ITM, namely short and long; however, the scheme adds fast and continuous tracking periods. Thus, TACO can provide additional diffusion analysis of similarly classified tracks examined with ITM.</p><p id="P56">The illumination scheme consisted of single detection frames followed by dark times (detection periods) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 20</xref>) to track whether a molecule stayed bound while minimizing laser exposure and photobleaching. Tracking and analysis of molecules were facilitated by appending 10 continuous frames of 11.7 ms frame cycle time (analysis periods). We pooled multiple stages: pre-ZGA (64-cell, 128-cell, 256-cell, 512-cell), post-ZGA (high, oblong, sphere), and shield. After tracking of molecules (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 21</xref>), each track was split into the first complete analysis period if, in the case of the long TACO scheme, the track survived at least 2 dark times (= 8.4 s) or in the case of the short TACO scheme, the track only survived a single short dark time (= 0.2 s) without being detected in the following long dark time. To prevent overrepresentation of single detections, only the first analysis region without gap frames was used, and all other analysis regions of this track were discarded.</p></sec><sec id="S20"><title>Data analysis of time-lapse microscopy: residence times and bound fractions</title><p id="P57">We used time-lapse microscopy and our previously published genuine rate identification method (GRID) to determine residence times of the HT-rad21 and HT-CTCF constructs<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R69">69</xref></sup>. GRID is based on solving the inverse Laplace transformation of fluorescence survival time distributions gained from multiple time-lapse conditions.</p><p id="P58">The first time-lapse condition builds on 501.7 ms frame-cycle time movies with continuous excitation of the JF549 labeled HaloTag construct. The second condition consisted of a repeating pattern with a single 501.7 ms excitation frame followed by a dark time of 4013.6 ms without laser illumination (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 20</xref>). We chose 500 ms exposure time to blur out diffusing molecules and focus on tracking bound molecules. We pooled movies of both time-lapse conditions into pre-ZGA (64-cell, 128-cell, 256-cell, 512-cell), post-ZGA (high, oblong, sphere), and shield stage. Tracking radii for each time-lapse condition were determined to yield equal loss probabilities of 0.0025 in TrackIt. The loss probability, accounting for tracking errors and photobleaching, was set equally for time-lapse conditions and stages of each construct. The resulting tracking parameters were the same for all stages and are listed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 21</xref>.</p><p id="P59">We used GRID to simultaneously analyze the fluorescence survival time distributions of both imaging conditions and obtain the event spectrum of dissociation rates ranging from 10<sup>-3</sup> s<sup>-1</sup> to 10<sup>1</sup> s<sup>-1</sup> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 9</xref>). The amplitudes A<sup>e</sup> of the event spectrum of dissociation rates correspond to the relative fraction of molecular binding events occurring with a certain dissociation rate in a period of time. We transferred the event spectrum to the state spectrum of dissociation rates by dividing each amplitude with the corresponding dissociation rate and renormalization<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R69">69</xref></sup>. The amplitudes A<sup>s</sup> of the state spectrum correspond to the relative fraction of molecular binding events that belong to a certain dissociation rate in a snapshot of time. We estimated the error of both event and state spectra by resampling 500 data subsets, each including 80% of randomly selected survival times.</p><p id="P60">To obtain the residence times <italic>τ<sub>s</sub></italic> of long-binding events, we averaged all dissociation rates below 0.1s<sup>-1</sup> (<italic>k<sub>off,s</sub></italic>) based on the binding time classification determined in ITM experiments and inverted the resulting value. The relative fraction <inline-formula><mml:math id="M4"><mml:msubsup><mml:mtext>A</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>s</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>s</mml:mtext></mml:msubsup></mml:math></inline-formula> of long-binding events is given by the corresponding averaged amplitudes of the state spectrum. To obtain the residence times <italic>τ<sub>u</sub></italic> of short-binding events, we performed these operations with dissociation rates above 0.1s<sup>-1</sup> (<italic>k<sub>off,u</sub></italic>). Again, the relative fraction <inline-formula><mml:math id="M5"><mml:msubsup><mml:mtext>A</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>u</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>s</mml:mtext></mml:msubsup></mml:math></inline-formula> of short-binding events is given by the corresponding averaged amplitudes of the state spectrum. We calculated the overall fractions <inline-formula><mml:math id="M6"><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>∗</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> of long-binding events and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M7"><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>u</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>∗</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> of short-binding events by multiplying the relative bound fractions with the overall bound fraction <italic>f<sub>b</sub></italic> obtained from the analysis of continuous movies (see above). We obtained the errors of the residence times and fractions from the standard deviation of the resampled state spectra and Gaussian error propagation, if necessary.</p></sec><sec id="S21"><title>Calculation of search times</title><p id="P61">DNA-binding proteins follow a search mechanism of facilitated diffusion, which includes three-dimensional diffusion in the nucleoplasm and one-dimensional sliding along unspecific DNA, to search for their specific target sites<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R71">71</xref></sup>. To estimate the search time <italic>τ<sub>search</sub></italic>, that is the average time a DNA-binding protein needs to find any of its specific target sites, we considered an equilibrium binding model with two different types of binding sites, unspecific and specific<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R73">73</xref></sup>. In this model, the DNA-binding protein performs the unspecific and specific binding reactions: <disp-formula id="FD4"><label>(4)</label><mml:math id="M8"><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:munder><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mo>⇄</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>u</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>u</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:munder><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula> <disp-formula id="FD5"><label>(5)</label><mml:math id="M9"><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:munder><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mo>⇄</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:munder><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula> Were <italic>[T]</italic> is the concentration of the free protein, <italic>[D<sub>u</sub>]</italic> and <italic>[D<sub>s</sub>]</italic> are the concentrations of free unspecific and specific binding sites, <italic>[TD<sub>u</sub>]</italic> and <italic>[TD<sub>s</sub>]</italic> are the concentrations of protein-bound binding sites, <italic>k<sub>on,u</sub></italic>, and <italic>k<sub>on,s</sub></italic> are the bimolecular association rates and <italic>k<sub>off,u</sub></italic> and <italic>k<sub>off,s</sub></italic> are the dissociation rates (see time-lapse microscopy analysis). If the concentration of binding sites is much larger than that of the DNA-binding protein and the bound fractions are small, both reactions are approximately decoupled.</p><p id="P62">The dissociation constant of either reaction is given by <disp-formula id="FD6"><label>(6)</label><mml:math id="M10"><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></disp-formula> with <italic>i</italic> = <italic>u</italic>,<italic>s</italic>. Thus, there is a relation between the ratio of kinetic rates and the ratio of the free fraction <italic>p<sub>f</sub></italic> (see continuous movie analysis above) to the bound fraction <italic>p<sub>b,i</sub></italic> (see time-lapse microscopy analysis above) of the DNA-binding protein: <disp-formula id="FD7"><label>(7)</label><mml:math id="M11"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="P63">We set <italic>k* <sub>on, i</sub></italic> = <italic>k<sub>on, i</sub> [Di]</italic> in the following.</p><p id="P64">Within this search model, the target site search time <italic>τ<sub>search</sub></italic> of the DNA-binding protein depends on the time spent finding and binding to an unspecific binding site and the number of unspecific encounters before a specific target sequence is found. It can be estimated to<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R72">72</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R73">73</xref></sup> <disp-formula id="FD8"><label>(8)</label><mml:math id="M12"><mml:msub><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.3em"/></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.3em"/></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.3em"/></mml:mrow><mml:mo>∗</mml:mo></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.3em"/></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.3em"/><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>u</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></disp-formula> where <italic>N<sub>trial</sub></italic> is the number of unspecific encounters. It is given by <disp-formula id="FD9"><label>(9)</label><mml:math id="M13"><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.3em"/></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></disp-formula> with <inline-formula><mml:math id="M14"><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:msubsup></mml:math></inline-formula> the amplitude of the long-binding events in the GRID event spectrum of dissociation rates (see time-lapse microscopy analysis).</p><p id="P65">For CTCF, which follows a search mechanism that is formally equivalent to the mechanism of facilitated diffusion<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R108">108</xref></sup>, we also used this formalism. We obtained the search time <italic>τ<sub>search</sub></italic> from equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD8">8</xref>) by calculating <italic>k* <sub>on,u</sub></italic>, and <italic>N<sub>trial</sub></italic> with equations (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD7">7</xref>) and (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD9">9</xref>) and inserting the measured parameters <inline-formula><mml:math id="M15"><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:msubsup></mml:math></inline-formula>, <italic>k<sub>off,u</sub></italic>, <italic>p<sub>f</sub></italic>, and <italic>p<sub>b,u</sub></italic>. All measured parameters are provided in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 15</xref>.</p><p id="P66">For cohesin, a detailed model of the search mechanism is missing. Since we observed distinct short and long binding events for cohesin similar to CTCF, we considered the same equilibrium binding model with two types of binding events. From this model, we obtained the search time <italic>τ<sub>search</sub></italic> of cohesin by calculating <italic>k*<sub>on,s</sub></italic> directly with equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD7">7</xref>), the measured dissociation rate of long binding events <italic>k<sub>off,s</sub></italic> and the fractions <italic>p<sub>f</sub></italic> and <italic>p<sub>b,s</sub></italic>, and taking the inverse <italic>τ<sub>search</sub></italic> = 1/<italic>k*<sub>on,s</sub></italic>. All parameters inserted in this equation can be found in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 16</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="S22"><title>Calculation of the relative effective search time</title><p id="P67">For our polymer simulations, we additionally estimated the effective search time <italic>τ<sub>effective</sub></italic> of any cohesin or CTCF molecule to find any long-binding site by including estimates of the protein concentrations. With the amount of molecules <italic>N<sub>mol</sub></italic> per nuclear volume <italic>V<sub>nuc</sub></italic>, the effective search time is given by: <disp-formula id="FD10"><label>(10)</label><mml:math id="M16"><mml:msub><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.3em"/></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.3em"/></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.3em"/></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.3em"/></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="P68">We obtained the nuclear volumes for pre- and post-ZGA stages from the area of the cross-section given by the eGFP-Lap2b signal in HT-rad21 ITM movies (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 8</xref>) and assuming a spherical nuclear shape<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43">43</xref></sup>.</p><p id="P69">For the more elliptical nuclei in the shield stage, we obtained the nuclear volume from the signal of GFP-H2B in z-scans with a Lattice Light-Sheet microscope (see section below).</p><p id="P70">The amount of molecules <italic>N<sub>mol</sub></italic> at different developmental stages of zebrafish embryos were estimated from published Western blots <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R74">74</xref></sup>. We used the Rad21 and CTCF protein levels of stages closest to our pooled stages, namely 2.5 hpf for pre-ZGA, 3.3 hpf for post-ZGA, and 5.4 hpf for shield stage. We normalized to the effective search time in pre-ZGA to obtain relative effects of the effective search times. Gaussian error propagation was used for error estimations.</p></sec><sec id="S23"><title>Calculation of long-bound fractions from kinetic rates</title><p id="P71">The overall bound fraction of short- and long-bound molecules, <italic>f<sub>b</sub></italic> (see continuous movie analysis), is given by <disp-formula id="FD11"><label>(11)</label><mml:math id="M17"><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></disp-formula> and the relative bound fraction of long-binding events, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M18"><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msubsup></mml:math></inline-formula> (see time-lapse microscopy analysis), by <disp-formula id="FD12"><label>(12)</label><mml:math id="M19"><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="P72">Thus, the overall fraction of long-bound molecules, <italic>p<sub>b,s</sub></italic>, is <disp-formula id="FD13"><label>(13)</label><mml:math id="M20"><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>∗</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="P73">Using equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD7">7</xref>), the expressions for <italic>f<sub>b</sub></italic> (equation 11) and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M21"><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msubsup></mml:math></inline-formula> (equation 12) can be expressed in terms of kinetic rates, and <italic>p<sub>b,s</sub></italic> becomes <disp-formula id="FD14"><label>(14)</label><mml:math id="M22"><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>∗</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>∗</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>u</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>∗</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>u</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="P74">Notably, the on-rates <italic>k*<sub>on,i</sub></italic>, <italic>i</italic> = <italic>u,s</italic>, include the concentration of binding sites, which depend on the number of accessible binding sites and the nuclear volume.</p><p id="P75">We compared <italic>p<sub>b,s</sub></italic> obtained by equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD13">13</xref>) by inserting the measured bound fractions and <italic>p<sub>b,s</sub></italic> obtained by equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD14">14</xref>) by inserting the kinetic rates.</p></sec><sec id="S24"><title>Lattice Light-Sheet microscopy (LLSM): nuclear volume determination</title><p id="P76">We obtained nuclear volumes for pre- and post-ZGA measurements by assuming a spherical nucleus shape and calculating the sphere volume using the nuclear membrane eGFP-Lap2β signal as the cross-sectional area. Shield stage nuclei, however, are primarily elliptical and prevent volume estimations based on the nuclear cross-section alone. Therefore, we switched to lattice light-sheet microscopy to determine the nuclear volume from image stacks of GFP-labeled histone H2B. We injected zebrafish embryos in the 1-cell stage with 18.5 pg of mRNA encoding for GFP-H2B and incubated embryos that passed the 2-cell stage at 28 °C in an incubator until shield stage.</p><p id="P77">To account for the larger size of zebrafish embryos compared to cells, we devised a novel method to mount zebrafish embryos on the lattice light sheet microscope. This was necessary due to its orthogonal geometry of excitation and detection objectives<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R109">109</xref></sup>. We placed zebrafish embryos upright on the sample holder by mounting them in agarose wells without fully covering the embryo, thereby preventing possible aberrations. We glued a 5 mm glass coverslip to the bottom of the sample holder to form a trough. This trough was slightly overfilled with 3% of low-gelling temperature agarose (A9045, Sigma-Aldrich) dissolved in Danieau’s medium. To insert wells into the agarose, we immediately placed the sample holder upside down on a custom 3D print (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 8</xref>). The 3D print contained notches to center the sample holder and 700 μm tall vertical pins, which stamped small wells into the gelling agarose. We filled the agarose wells with Danieau’s buffer and transferred a single embryo to a well with the animal cap pointing up. Ideally, the yolk reached the bottom of the well, and the animal cap protruded out of the well. This approach did not require adjustments to the sample holder setup, since the animal cap is mounted at a similar spatial location as cells.</p><p id="P78">We used a lattice-light sheet microscope custom-built according to a published design<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R109">109</xref></sup>. To image the nuclear histone marker GFP-H2B of shield stage embryos, GFP was excited with a dithered light sheet from a 488 nm laser (Genesis MX488 STM OPSL, Coherent Europe B.V.) that was formed by a square lattice and an annular mask with an outer NA of 0.55 and an inner NA of 0.52. We recorded image stacks scanning multiple nuclear volumes with a step size of 332 nm and 50 ms exposure time. Image stacks were deskewed and deconvolved using the lattice light-sheet post-processing utility LLSpy<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R110">110</xref></sup>. We then performed nuclear volume analysis in FIJI<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R111">111</xref></sup> by cropping image stacks to exclude frames at the start or end of a movie without a stable GFP signal, followed by equalizing irregular H2B signal with a median filter (20 px) and background subtraction (1 px). Leveraging the 3D ImageJ Suite(Ollion et al. 2013), we segmented nuclei in every image stack by thresholding the H2B signal. Interphase nuclei were manually selected, and their volume analysis was done with FIJIs’ integrated 3D objects counter.</p></sec><sec id="S25"><title>Center-Border-Distance (CBD) analysis</title><p id="P79">We determined the relative position of long-bound tracks between the center of a nucleus and its border.</p><p id="P80">We started by pooling ITM and TACO movies in three stages: pre-ZGA (64-cell, 128-cell, 256-cell, 512-cell), post-ZGA (high, oblong, sphere), and shield stage. Next, we manually identified the nuclear outline at the first, middle, and last frame of a movie based on the nuclear lamina signal (eGFP-Lap2β), and interpolated the shape between these outlines for every frame of the movie to account for cell movement. We proceeded with tracks of the long-bound classification (see ITM: <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1f</xref>, TACO: <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2a</xref>). Since nuclei showed different sizes and forms, we normalized the CBD of tracks between the nucleus center (CBD = 0) and border (CBD = 1). The CBD distances were determined for every track based on a vector spanning the center of mass of the current nuclear outline, the initial xy-position of a track, and the border of the current nuclear outline. Finally, we sorted track-CBDs in a histogram with five ring-shaped area bins. To account for the increasing area of bins closer to the border, we divided the track counts of a bin with the bin area and further normalized the values by the largest histogram value. The errors represented the statistical counting error and were calculated as the square root of track counts per bin.</p></sec><sec id="S26"><title>Identification of accessible CTCF sites from ATAC-seq and ChiP-seq data</title><p id="P81">We identified CTCF sites in open chromatin regions to be used in our simulations.</p><p id="P82">For ATAC-seq analysis and peak calling, we used published ATAC-seq pairs end fastq reads from the Gene Expression Omnibus database (GEO) with the GEO accession number GSE130944<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R79">79</xref></sup>. For the analysis, the developmental stages 256-cell (SRR9032650, SRR9032651), oblong (SRR9032665, SRR9032666) and shield stage (SRR9032668, SRR9032669, SRR9032670, SRR9032671, SRR9032672, SRR9032673) were used. All ATAC-seq fastq files were analyzed according to the pipeline described in the original publication. Next, we aligned Fastq files to zebrafish reference genome danRer10 (see NCBI RefSeq assembly GCF_000002035.5) using the bowtie2 tool<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R112">112</xref></sup> with the parameters -X 2000 --no-mixed --no-discordant. Peak calling was performed after filtering out duplicates and low-quality alignments with q&lt;30. Finally, ATAC peaks were called using MACS2<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R113">113</xref></sup> with parameters --no-model --no-lambda, and a cutoff False Discovery Rate (FDR) of 5% was applied using the parameter --q 0.05. As a control (-c), a digestion of genomic DNA was used (SRR9032640). The common peaks of each replicate from each developmental stage were used for further downstream analysis.</p><p id="P83">To extract the ATAC signal, Chromosome 18 was digested in 1kb windows with the command bedtools makewindows<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R114">114</xref></sup>. For each window, the signal from the bigwig of each developmental stage was calculated (256, oblong, and shield from GEO: GSE130944) with bigWigSummary.</p><p id="P84">For CTCF orientation analysis, CTCF peaks and CTCF motifs were obtained from a published data set with the GEO accession number GSE133437<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R78">78</xref></sup>. Each peak center was extended +/- 5kb, and CTCF orientation per extended peak was extracted using homer<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R115">115</xref></sup> and the parameters – find known_zebra_motif and –size given. The CTCF motif used is given in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 22</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="S27"><title>Polymer simulations</title><p id="P85">For the polymer-chain model, we used Langevin molecular dynamics simulations of beads connected with springs implemented in LAMMPS<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R116">116</xref></sup>. To simulate volume interactions between beads, we utilized the Lennard-Jones potential in equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD15">15</xref>) with coefficients representing θ-solvent<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R117">117</xref></sup> <disp-formula id="FD15"><label>(15)</label><mml:math id="M23"><mml:msub><mml:mi>U</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mi>J</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>4</mml:mn><mml:mi>ϵ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>12</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mn>6</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula> Where <italic>ϵ</italic> is the potential well depth, <italic>σ</italic> the distance at which the potential vanishes (cutoff radius), and <italic>r</italic> the distance between beads. The Lennard-Jones potential prevents the chain from self-intersections.</p><p id="P86">Bonds between beads were simulated using the harmonic potential given in equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD16">16</xref>): <disp-formula id="FD16"><label>(16)</label><mml:math id="M24"><mml:msub><mml:mi>U</mml:mi><mml:mi>H</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mfrac><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:math></disp-formula> Where <italic>k</italic> is the spring constant, r the distance between beads and b the distance at which the potential is zero. We used a relatively high <italic>k</italic> = 40 that prevents stretches allowing self-intersections.</p><p id="P87">Loop extrusion was simulated as a process comprised of 4 steps: <list list-type="order" id="L1"><list-item><p id="P88">Extruding molecules are stochastically loaded onto an adjacent pair of polymer beads every 400k simulation steps (~4 sec). We set the constant probability representing loading rate which we varied. Extruders are simulated as additional bonds between beads that can slide along the chain.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P89">Every 400k simulation steps, each extruder makes a step to increase the size of the loop. This step results in an extrusion processivity of 0.5 kb/sec. Starting from the initial loop [i, i+1], the extruder will bind [i-1, i+2] in the next step and so on.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P90">Every 400k simulation steps, each extruder can be unloaded with a constant probability. This probability determines the residence time of the extruder.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P91">When two loops encounter each other during loop extrusion on the chain, for instance loop 1 [i, i+10] and loop 2 [i+11, i+20], they cannot pass one another. The common base of loop 1 [i+10] and loop 2 [i+11] becomes stationary, whereas the loop can continue extruding at the other end of loop 1 [i] and loop 2 [i+20].</p></list-item></list></p><p id="P92">We had to map arbitrary units of space and time to real units. We chose 1 bead to represent 1 kb of chromatin. Considering the size of a nucleosome with linker of ~15 nm and assuming that the chain of nucleosomes is folded in a random walk configuration, we estimated that 1 bead corresponds to 15 * ✓5 nm ≈ 33.5 nm. To map simulation onto experimental time, we used previously acquired data for mouse embryonic stem cells, were we determined the time it takes for a chromosome segment of 8 kb to move about its own size <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R68">68</xref></sup>. We estimated that for the current system and resolution 100k steps correspond to 1 sec. We fixed extrusion processivity at 0.5 kb/sec and we varied loading and unloading rates, as described above. To test the effect of CTCF sites we remapped our system to 10 kb. Accessible and occupied CTCF sites were identified as described above for three developmental stages, namely 2.25, 4, and 5.3 hpf. The time was mapped as for 1 kb simulations, yielding that 40k simulation steps corresponded to ~1 sec.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="SM"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1"><label>Supplementary_Info</label><media xlink:href="EMS192679-supplement-Supplementary_Info.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" id="d189aAdEbB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack id="S28"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank Gilbert Weidinger (Ulm University) for generously granting us access to his zebrafish facility. Moreover, we are thankful to Astrid Bellan-Koch (Ulm University) for cloning the fusion constructs and performing Western blots, Jens Michaelis (Ulm University) for his excellent contributions in developing the lattice light-sheet microscope, and members of the Gebhardt and Michaelis labs for supportive discussions. We further thank Aleksandra Galitsyna (Massachusetts Institute of Technology) for important discussions on Hi-C data. pmtb-t7-alpha-bungarotoxin was a gift from Sean Megason (Harward Medical School).</p><p>The work was funded by the European Research Council (ERC) under the European Union’s Horizon 2020 Research and Innovation Program (no. 637987 ChromArch to J.C.M.G.) and the Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft (DFG, German Research Foundation no. 422780363 SPP 2202 and no. 427512076 to J.C.M.G.). Support by the Collaborative Research Centres no. 316249678 (CRC 1279) and no. 450627322 (CRC 1506) to J.C.M.G. and the DFG Center for Translational Imaging MoMAN of Ulm University is acknowledged. Research of P.I.K. and L.G. was funded by the Novartis Foundation, the European Research Council (ERC grant no. 759366, ‘BioMeTre’), and the Swiss National Science Foundation (grant no. 310030_192642).</p></ack><sec id="S29" sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p id="P93">Upon publication, data will be freely available at Data Dryad. Data supporting the findings of this manuscript will be available from the corresponding author upon reasonable request.</p></sec><sec id="S30" sec-type="data-availability"><title>Code availability</title><p id="P94">The single-molecule tracking software TrackIt is freely available on GitLab (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://gitlab.com/GebhardtLab/TrackIt">https://gitlab.com/GebhardtLab/TrackIt</ext-link>). Upon publication, the code for the polymer simulations will be freely available on GitHub.</p></sec><fn-group><fn id="FN1" fn-type="con"><p id="P95"><bold>Author contributions</bold></p><p id="P96">J.C.M.G. conceived the project; J.C and J.C.M.G. designed the project; J.C. performed the single-molecule measurements; T.B. contributed to the single-molecule measurements; J.C. analyzed data with contributions from D.A. and J.C.M.G.; T.K. and T.V. set up the lattice light-sheet microscope; V.V.M. and A. P. performed bioinformatics analysis; P.I.K. and L.G. performed computational modeling and analysis; J.C., P.I.K., and J.C.M.G wrote the manuscript with comments from all authors.</p></fn><fn id="FN2" fn-type="conflict"><p id="P97"><bold>Competing interest</bold></p><p id="P98">The authors declared no competing interests.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><ref id="R1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cremer</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Cremer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chromosome territories</article-title><source>Cold Spring Harbor perspectives in biology</source><year>2010</year><volume>2</volume><elocation-id>a003889</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2829961</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20300217</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/cshperspect.a003889</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lieberman-Aiden</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Comprehensive mapping of long-range interactions reveals folding principles of the human genome</article-title><source>Science (80-)</source><year>2009</year><volume>326</volume><fpage>289</fpage><lpage>293</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2858594</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19815776</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1181369</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Spatial organization of the mouse genome and its role in recurrent chromosomal translocations</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2012</year><volume>148</volume><fpage>908</fpage><lpage>921</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3320767</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22341456</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2012.02.002</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dixon</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Topological domains in mammalian genomes identified by analysis of chromatin interactions</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2012</year><volume>485</volume><fpage>376</fpage><lpage>380</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3356448</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22495300</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature11082</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nora</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Spatial partitioning of the regulatory landscape of the X-inactivation centre</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2012</year><volume>485</volume><fpage>381</fpage><lpage>385</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3555144</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22495304</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature11049</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>SSP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A 3D map of the human genome at kilobase resolution reveals principles of chromatin looping</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2014</year><volume>159</volume><fpage>1665</fpage><lpage>1680</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5635824</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25497547</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2014.11.021</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sanyal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lajoie</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name><name><surname>Jain</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Dekker</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The long-range interaction landscape of gene promoters</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2012</year><volume>489</volume><fpage>109</fpage><lpage>113</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3555147</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22955621</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature11279</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ricci</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Manzo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>García-Parajo</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Lakadamyali</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Cosma</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chromatin fibers are formed by heterogeneous groups of nucleosomes in vivo</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2015</year><volume>160</volume><fpage>1145</fpage><lpage>1158</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25768910</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ou</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>ChromEMT: Visualizing 3D chromatin structure and compaction in interphase and mitotic cells</article-title><source>Science (80-)</source><year>2017</year><volume>357</volume><fpage>139</fpage><lpage>148</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5646685</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28751582</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.aag0025</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fudenberg</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Formation of Chromosomal Domains by Loop Extrusion</article-title><source>Cell Rep</source><year>2016</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>2038</fpage><lpage>2049</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4889513</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27210764</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.celrep.2016.04.085</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Splinter</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>CTCF mediates long-range chromatin looping and local histone modification in the β-globin locus</article-title><source>Genes Dev</source><year>2006</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>2349</fpage><lpage>2354</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1560409</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16951251</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gad.399506</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>SSP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cohesin Loss Eliminates All Loop Domains</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2017</year><volume>171</volume><fpage>305</fpage><lpage>320</lpage><elocation-id>e24</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5846482</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28985562</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2017.09.026</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sanborn</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Chromatin extrusion explains key features of loop and domain formation in wild-type and engineered genomes</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2015</year><volume>112</volume><fpage>E6456</fpage><lpage>E6465</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4664323</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26499245</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1518552112</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Noh</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ryu</surname><given-names>J-K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structure-function relationships of SMC protein complexes for DNA loop extrusion</article-title><source>Biodesign</source><year>2021</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>13</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Davidson</surname><given-names>IF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>DNA loop extrusion by human cohesin</article-title><source>Science (80-)</source><year>2019</year><volume>366</volume><fpage>1338</fpage><lpage>1345</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31753851</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Finkelstein</surname><given-names>IJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Human cohesin compacts DNA by loop extrusion</article-title><source>Science (80-)</source><year>2019</year><volume>366</volume><fpage>1345</fpage><lpage>1349</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7387118</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31780627</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.aaz4475</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Petela</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Scc2 Is a Potent Activator of Cohesin’s ATPase that Promotes Loading by Binding Scc1 without Pds5</article-title><source>Mol Cell</source><year>2018</year><volume>70</volume><fpage>1134</fpage><lpage>1148</lpage><elocation-id>e7</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6028919</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29932904</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molcel.2018.05.022</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kueng</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Wapl Controls the Dynamic Association of Cohesin with Chromatin</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2006</year><volume>127</volume><fpage>955</fpage><lpage>967</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17113138</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haarhuis</surname><given-names>JHI</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The Cohesin Release Factor WAPL Restricts Chromatin Loop Extension</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2017</year><volume>169</volume><fpage>693</fpage><lpage>707</lpage><elocation-id>e14</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5422210</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28475897</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2017.04.013</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Corsi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Rusch</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Goloborodko</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Loop extrusion rules: the next generation</article-title><source>Curr Opin Genet Dev</source><year>2023</year><volume>81</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37354885</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Davidson</surname><given-names>IF</given-names></name><name><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genome folding through loop extrusion by SMC complexes</article-title><source>Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol</source><year>2021</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>445</fpage><lpage>464</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33767413</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Barth</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Dekker</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Looping the Genome with SMC Complexes</article-title><source>Annu Rev Biochem</source><year>2023</year><volume>92</volume><fpage>15</fpage><lpage>41</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37137166</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vietri Rudan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Comparative Hi-C Reveals that CTCF Underlies Evolution of Chromosomal Domain Architecture</article-title><source>Cell Rep</source><year>2015</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>1297</fpage><lpage>1309</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4542312</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25732821</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.celrep.2015.02.004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pugacheva</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>CTCF mediates chromatin looping via N-terminal domain-dependent cohesin retention</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2020</year><volume>117</volume><fpage>2020</fpage><lpage>2031</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6995019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31937660</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1911708117</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nora</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Molecular basis of CTCF binding polarity in genome folding</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2020</year><volume>11</volume><elocation-id>5612</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7645679</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33154377</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-020-19283-x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The structural basis for cohesin-CTCF-anchored loops</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2020</year><volume>578</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7035113</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31905366</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41586-019-1910-z</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vallot</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Tachibana</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The emergence of genome architecture and zygotic genome activation</article-title><source>Curr Opin Cell Biol</source><year>2020</year><volume>64</volume><fpage>50</fpage><lpage>57</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7374442</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32220807</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ceb.2020.02.002</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Allelic reprogramming of 3D chromatin architecture during early mammalian development</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2017</year><volume>547</volume><fpage>232</fpage><lpage>235</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28703188</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ke</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>3D Chromatin Structures of Mature Gametes and Structural Reprogramming during Mammalian Embryogenesis</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2017</year><volume>170</volume><fpage>367</fpage><lpage>381</lpage><elocation-id>e20</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28709003</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Key role for CTCF in establishing chromatin structure in human embryos</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2019</year><volume>576</volume><fpage>306</fpage><lpage>310</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31801998</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hug</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name><name><surname>Grimaldi</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Kruse</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Vaquerizas</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chromatin Architecture Emerges during Zygotic Genome Activation Independent of Transcription</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2017</year><volume>169</volume><fpage>216</fpage><lpage>228</lpage><elocation-id>e19</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28388407</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wike</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Chromatin architecture transitions from zebrafish sperm through early embryogenesis</article-title><source>Genome Res</source><year>2021</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>981</fpage><lpage>994</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8168589</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34006569</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gr.269860.120</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kaaij</surname><given-names>LJT</given-names></name><name><surname>van der Weide</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Ketting</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><name><surname>de Wit</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Systemic Loss and Gain of Chromatin Architecture throughout Zebrafish Development</article-title><source>Cell Rep</source><year>2018</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>10</lpage><elocation-id>e4</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6047509</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29972771</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.celrep.2018.06.003</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>QP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Superresolution imaging reveals spatiotemporal propagation of human replication foci mediated by CTCF-organized chromatin structures</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2020</year><volume>117</volume><fpage>15036</fpage><lpage>15046</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7334649</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32541019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.2001521117</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Davidson</surname><given-names>IF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>CTCF is a DNA-tension-dependent barrier to cohesin-mediated loop extrusion</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2023</year><volume>616</volume><fpage>822</fpage><lpage>827</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10132984</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37076620</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41586-023-05961-5</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Holzmann</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Absolute quantification of cohesin, CTCF and their regulators in human cells</article-title><source>Elife</source><year>2019</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>31</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6606026</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31204999</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.46269</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Pustova</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Cattoglio</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Tjian</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Darzacq</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>CTCF and cohesin regulate chromatin loop stability with distinct dynamics</article-title><source>Elife</source><year>2017</year><volume>6</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5446243</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28467304</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.25776</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wutz</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Topologically associating domains and chromatin loops depend on cohesin and are regulated by CTCF, WAPL, and PDS5 proteins</article-title><source>EMBO J</source><year>2017</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>3573</fpage><lpage>3599</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5730888</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29217591</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15252/embj.201798004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Agarwal</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Reisser</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wortmann</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Gebhardt</surname><given-names>JCM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Direct Observation of Cell-Cycle-Dependent Interactions between CTCF and Chromatin</article-title><source>Biophys J</source><year>2017</year><volume>112</volume><fpage>2051</fpage><lpage>2055</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5444008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28487148</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bpj.2017.04.018</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Amitai</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Cattoglio</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Tjian</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Darzacq</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Guided nuclear exploration increases CTCF target search efficiency</article-title><source>Nat Chem Biol</source><year>2020</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>257</fpage><lpage>266</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7036004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31792445</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41589-019-0422-3</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R41"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gerlich</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Dupeux</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ellenberg</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Live-Cell Imaging Reveals a Stable Cohesin-Chromatin Interaction after but Not before DNA Replication</article-title><source>Curr Biol</source><year>2006</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>1571</fpage><lpage>1578</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16890534</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R42"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Golfier</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Quail</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kimura</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Brugués</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cohesin and condensin extrude DNA loops in a cell-cycle dependent manner</article-title><source>Elife</source><year>2020</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>34</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7316503</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32396063</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.53885</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R43"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reisser</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Single-molecule imaging correlates decreasing nuclear volume with increasing TF-chromatin associations during zebrafish development</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2018</year><volume>9</volume><elocation-id>5218</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6283880</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30523256</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-018-07731-8</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R44"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grimm</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A general method to improve fluorophores for live-cell and single-molecule microscopy</article-title><source>Nat Methods</source><year>2015</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>244</fpage><lpage>250</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4344395</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25599551</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.3256</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R45"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kuhn</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Single-molecule tracking of Nodal and Lefty in live zebrafish embryos supports hindered diffusion model</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2022</year><volume>13</volume><elocation-id>6101</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9569377</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36243734</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-022-33704-z</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R46"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kuhn</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hettich</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Davtyan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Gebhardt</surname><given-names>JCM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Single molecule tracking and analysis framework including theory-predicted parameter settings</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2021</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8096815</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33947895</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-021-88802-7</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R47"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mazza</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Abernathy</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Golob</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Morisaki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>McNally</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A benchmark for chromatin binding measurements in live cells</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2012</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>13</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3424588</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22844090</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gks701</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R48"><label>48</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Robust model-based analysis of single-particle tracking experiments with spot-on</article-title><source>Elife</source><year>2018</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>33</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5809147</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29300163</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.33125</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R49"><label>49</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gebhardt</surname><given-names>JCM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Single-molecule imaging of transcription factor binding to DNA in live mammalian cells</article-title><source>Nat Methods</source><year>2013</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>421</fpage><lpage>426</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3664538</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23524394</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.2411</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R50"><label>50</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Speil</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Activated STAT1 transcription factors conduct distinct saltatory movements in the cell nucleus</article-title><source>Biophys J</source><year>2011</year><volume>101</volume><fpage>2592</fpage><lpage>2600</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3297778</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22261046</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bpj.2011.10.006</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R51"><label>51</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Izeddin</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Single-molecule tracking in live cells reveals distinct target-search strategies of transcription factors in the nucleus</article-title><source>Elife</source><year>2014</year><volume>2014</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4095940</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24925319</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.02230</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R52"><label>52</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haering</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Structure and stability of cohesin’s Smc1-kleisin interaction</article-title><source>Mol Cell</source><year>2004</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>951</fpage><lpage>964</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15383284</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R53"><label>53</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Rad21 is the core subunit of the cohesin complex involved in directing genome organization</article-title><source>Res Sq</source><year>2022</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10303866</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37381036</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13059-023-02982-1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R54"><label>54</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nakahashi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A Genome-wide Map of CTCF Multivalency Redefines the CTCF Code</article-title><source>Cell Rep</source><year>2013</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>1678</fpage><lpage>1689</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3770538</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23707059</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.celrep.2013.04.024</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R55"><label>55</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hashimoto</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Structural Basis for the Versatile and Methylation-Dependent Binding of CTCF to DNA</article-title><source>Mol Cell</source><year>2017</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>711</fpage><lpage>720</lpage><elocation-id>e3</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5542067</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28529057</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molcel.2017.05.004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R56"><label>56</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gandhi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Gillespie</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirano</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Human Wapl Is a Cohesin-Binding Protein that Promotes Sister-Chromatid Resolution in Mitotic Prophase</article-title><source>Curr Biol</source><year>2006</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>2406</fpage><lpage>2417</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1850625</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17112726</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2006.10.061</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R57"><label>57</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wutz</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>ESCO1 and CTCF enable formation of long chromatin loops by protecting cohesinstag1 from WAPL</article-title><source>Elife</source><year>2020</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>33</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7054000</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32065581</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.52091</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R58"><label>58</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Muto</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Calof</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Lander</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Schilling</surname><given-names>TF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multifactorial origins of heart and gut defects in Nipbl-deficient zebrafish, a model of cornelia de Lange Syndrome</article-title><source>PLoSBiol</source><year>2011</year><volume>9</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3201921</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22039349</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.1001181</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R59"><label>59</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Muto</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Nipbl and Mediator Cooperatively Regulate Gene Expression to Control Limb Development</article-title><source>PLoS Genet</source><year>2014</year><volume>10</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4177752</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25255084</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1004671</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R60"><label>60</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Delgado-Olguín</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>CTCF promotes muscle differentiation by modulating the activity of myogenic regulatory factors</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2011</year><volume>286</volume><fpage>12483</fpage><lpage>12494</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3069451</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21288905</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M110.164574</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R61"><label>61</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brueckner</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Cramer</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structural basis of transcription inhibition by α-amanitin and implications for RNA polymerase II translocation</article-title><source>Nat Struct Mol Biol</source><year>2008</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>811</fpage><lpage>818</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18552824</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R62"><label>62</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Larsson</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kornberg</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The RNA Polymerase II Trigger Loop Functions in Substrate Selection and Is Directly Targeted by α-Amanitin</article-title><source>Mol Cell</source><year>2008</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>547</fpage><lpage>556</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2475549</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18538653</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molcel.2008.04.023</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R63"><label>63</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bensaude</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inhibiting eukaryotic transcription: Which compound to choose? How to evaluate its activity?</article-title><source>Transcription</source><year>2011</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>103</fpage><lpage>108</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3173647</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21922053</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4161/trns.2.3.16172</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R64"><label>64</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Widespread Rearrangement of 3D Chromatin Organization Underlies Polycomb-Mediated Stress-Induced Silencing</article-title><source>Mol Cell</source><year>2015</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>216</fpage><lpage>231</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4402144</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25818644</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molcel.2015.02.023</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R65"><label>65</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shao</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeitlinger</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Paused RNA polymerase II inhibits new transcriptional initiation</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><year>2017</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>1045</fpage><lpage>1051</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28504701</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R66"><label>66</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nozaki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Dynamic Organization of Chromatin Domains Revealed by Super Resolution Live-Cell Imaging</article-title><source>Mol Cell</source><year>2017</year><volume>67</volume><fpage>282</fpage><lpage>293</lpage><elocation-id>e7</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28712725</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R67"><label>67</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ashwin</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Nozaki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Maeshima</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Sasai</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Organization of fast and slow chromatin revealed by single-nucleosome dynamics</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2019</year><volume>116</volume><fpage>19939</fpage><lpage>19944</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6778247</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31527274</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1907342116</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R68"><label>68</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mach</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cohesin and CTCF control the dynamics of chromosome folding</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><year>2022</year><volume>54</volume><fpage>1907</fpage><lpage>1918</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9729113</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36471076</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41588-022-01232-7</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R69"><label>69</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reisser</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Inferring quantity and qualities of superimposed reaction rates from single molecule survival time distributions</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2020</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>13</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7000831</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32019978</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-020-58634-y</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R70"><label>70</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Popp</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Hettich</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gebhardt</surname><given-names>JCM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Altering transcription factor binding reveals comprehensive transcriptional kinetics of a basic gene</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2021</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>6249</fpage><lpage>6266</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8216454</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34060631</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkab443</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R71"><label>71</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Berg</surname><given-names>OG</given-names></name><name><surname>Winter</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>von Hippel</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diffusion-Driven Mechanisms of Protein Translocation on Nucleic Acids. 1. Models and Theory</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><year>1981</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>6929</fpage><lpage>6948</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7317363</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R72"><label>72</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Livhitz</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gursky</surname><given-names>GV</given-names></name><name><surname>Zasedatelev</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Volkenstein</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Equilibrium and kinetic aspects of protein-DNA recognition</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>1979</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>2217</fpage><lpage>2236</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC327847</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">461187</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/6.6.2217</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R73"><label>73</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Loffreda</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Live-cell p53 single-molecule binding is modulated by C-terminal acetylation and correlates with transcriptional activity</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2017</year><volume>8</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5567047</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28827596</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-017-00398-7</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R74"><label>74</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meier</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cohesin facilitates zygotic genome activation in zebrafish</article-title><source>Dev</source><year>2018</year><volume>145</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>13</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29158440</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R75"><label>75</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cattoglio</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Determining cellular CTCF and cohesin abundances to constrain 3D genome models</article-title><source>Elife</source><year>2019</year><volume>8</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6579579</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31205001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.40164</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R76"><label>76</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Galitsyna</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Extrusion fountains are hallmarks of chromosome organization emerging upon zygotic genome activation</article-title><source>bioRxiv Prepr Serv Biol</source><year>2023</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2023.07.15.549120</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R77"><label>77</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Polovnikov</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Belan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Imakaev</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Brandão</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name><name><surname>Mirny</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Crumpled polymer with loops recapitulates key features of chromosome organization</article-title><source>bioRxiv</source><year>2023</year><elocation-id>2022.02.01.478588</elocation-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R78"><label>78</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pérez-Rico</surname><given-names>YA</given-names></name><name><surname>Barillot</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Shkumatava</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Demarcation of Topologically Associating Domains Is Uncoupled from Enriched CTCF Binding in Developing Zebrafish</article-title><source>iScience</source><year>2020</year><volume>23</volume><elocation-id>101046</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7182764</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32334414</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.isci.2020.101046</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R79"><label>79</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pálfy</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Schulze</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Valen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Vastenhouw</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chromatin accessibility established by Pou5f3, Sox19b and Nanog primes genes for activity during zebrafish genome activation</article-title><source>bioRxiv</source><year>2019</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>25</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6986763</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31940339</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1008546</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R80"><label>80</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nishiyama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Sororin mediates sister chromatid cohesion by antagonizing Wapl</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2010</year><volume>143</volume><fpage>737</fpage><lpage>749</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21111234</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R81"><label>81</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eshghi</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Eaton</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Zidovska</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Interphase Chromatin Undergoes a Local Sol-Gel Transition upon Cell Differentiation</article-title><source>Phys Rev Lett</source><year>2021</year><volume>126</volume><elocation-id>228101</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8405102</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34152157</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1103/PhysRevLett.126.228101</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R82"><label>82</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Subramanian</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>H2A.Z Acidic Patch Couples Chromatin Dynamics to Regulation of Gene Expression Programs during ESC Differentiation</article-title><source>PLoS Genet</source><year>2013</year><volume>9</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3749939</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23990805</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1003725</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R83"><label>83</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Girelli</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>GPSeq reveals the radial organization of chromatin in the cell nucleus</article-title><source>Nat Biotechnol</source><year>2020</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>1184</fpage><lpage>1193</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7610410</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32451505</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41587-020-0519-y</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R84"><label>84</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kinrot</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Bintu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhuang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genome-Scale Imaging of the 3D Organization and Transcriptional Activity of Chromatin</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2020</year><volume>182</volume><fpage>1641</fpage><lpage>1659</lpage><elocation-id>e26</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7851072</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32822575</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2020.07.032</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R85"><label>85</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van Schaik</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>CTCF and cohesin promote focal detachment of DNA from the nuclear lamina</article-title><source>Genome Biol</source><year>2022</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>26</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9438259</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36050765</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13059-022-02754-3</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R86"><label>86</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goll</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Akdogan-Ozdilek</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Duval</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chromatin dynamics at the maternal to zygotic transition: Recent advances from the zebrafish model</article-title><source>F1000Research</source><year>2020</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7262572</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32528656</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.12688/f1000research.21809.1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R87"><label>87</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Laue</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Rajshekar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Courtney</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>ZA</given-names></name><name><surname>Goll</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The maternal to zygotic transition regulates genome-wide heterochromatin establishment in the zebrafish embryo</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2019</year><volume>10</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6449393</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30948728</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-019-09582-3</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R88"><label>88</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>RNA polymerase II is required for spatial chromatin reorganization following exit from mitosis</article-title><source>Sci Adv</source><year>2021</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>14</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8535795</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34678064</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/sciadv.abg8205</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R89"><label>89</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Übelmesser</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Barbieri</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Papantonis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Enhancer-promoter contact formation requires RNAPII and antagonizes loop extrusion</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><year>2023</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>832</fpage><lpage>840</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37012454</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R90"><label>90</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Busslinger</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cohesin is positioned in mammalian genomes by transcription, CTCF and Wapl</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2017</year><volume>544</volume><fpage>503</fpage><lpage>507</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6080695</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28424523</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature22063</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R91"><label>91</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Davidson</surname><given-names>IF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Rapid movement and transcriptional re-localization of human cohesin on DNA</article-title><source>EMBO J</source><year>2016</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>2671</fpage><lpage>2685</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5167347</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27799150</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15252/embj.201695402</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R92"><label>92</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schulz</surname><given-names>KN</given-names></name><name><surname>Harrison</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mechanisms regulating zygotic genome activation</article-title><source>Nat Rev Genet</source><year>2019</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>221</fpage><lpage>234</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6558659</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30573849</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41576-018-0087-x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R93"><label>93</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Casa</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Redundant and specific roles of cohesin STAG subunits in chromatin looping and transcriptional control</article-title><source>Genome Res</source><year>2020</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>515</fpage><lpage>527</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7197483</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32253279</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gr.253211.119</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R94"><label>94</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dauban</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Regulation of Cohesin-Mediated Chromosome Folding by Eco1 and Other Partners</article-title><source>Mol Cell</source><year>2020</year><volume>77</volume><fpage>1279</fpage><lpage>1293</lpage><elocation-id>e4</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32032532</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R95"><label>95</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van Ruiten</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The cohesin acetylation cycle controls chromatin loop length through a PDS5A brake mechanism</article-title><source>Nat Struct Mol Biol</source><year>2022</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>586</fpage><lpage>591</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9205776</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35710836</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41594-022-00773-z</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R96"><label>96</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bastié</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Smc3 acetylation, Pds5 and Scc2 control the translocase activity that establishes cohesin-dependent chromatin loops</article-title><source>Nat Struct Mol Biol</source><year>2022</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>575</fpage><lpage>585</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35710835</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R97"><label>97</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Del Moral-Morales</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>CTCF and Its Multi-Partner Network for Chromatin Regulation</article-title><source>Cells</source><year>2023</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>19</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10216408</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37408191</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/cells12101357</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R98"><label>98</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Swinburne</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mosaliganti</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Megason</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Improved long-term imaging of embryos with genetically encoded α-bungarotoxin</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2015</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>15</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4526548</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26244658</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0134005</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R99"><label>99</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kane</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The zebrafish epiboly mutants</article-title><source>Development</source><year>1996</year><volume>123</volume><fpage>47</fpage><lpage>55</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9007228</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R100"><label>100</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Histone H3K27 acetylation precedes active transcription during zebrafish zygotic genome activation as revealed by live-cell analysis</article-title><source>Dev</source><year>2019</year><volume>146</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6803375</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31570370</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/dev.179127</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R101"><label>101</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heyn</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Salmonowicz</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodenfels</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Neugebauer</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Activation of transcription enforces the formation of distinct nuclear bodies in zebrafish embryos</article-title><source>RNA Biol</source><year>2017</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>752</fpage><lpage>760</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5519242</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27858508</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/15476286.2016.1255397</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R102"><label>102</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pancholi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>RNA polymerase II clusters form in line with surface condensation on regulatory chromatin</article-title><source>Mol Syst Biol</source><year>2021</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>26</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8474054</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34569155</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15252/msb.202110272</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R103"><label>103</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hilbert</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Transcription organizes euchromatin via microphase separation</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2021</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7921102</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33649325</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-021-21589-3</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R104"><label>104</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hadzhiev</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The miR-430 locus with extreme promoter density forms a transcription body during the minor wave of zygotic genome activation</article-title><source>Dev Cell</source><year>2023</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>155</fpage><lpage>170</lpage><elocation-id>e8</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9904021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36693321</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.devcel.2022.12.007</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R105"><label>105</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kontur</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeong</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Cifuentes</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Giraldez</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ythdf m6A Readers Function Redundantly during Zebrafish Development</article-title><source>Cell Rep</source><year>2020</year><volume>33</volume><elocation-id>108598</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33378672</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R106"><label>106</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Delgado-Olguín</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>CTCF promotes muscle differentiation by modulating the activity of myogenic regulatory factors</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2011</year><volume>286</volume><fpage>12483</fpage><lpage>12494</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R107"><label>107</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Muto</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Calof</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Lander</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Schilling</surname><given-names>TF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multifactorial origins of heart and gut defects in Nipbl-deficient zebrafish, a model of cornelia de Lange Syndrome</article-title><source>PLoS Biol</source><year>2011</year><volume>9</volume></element-citation></ref><ref id="R108"><label>108</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Distinct Classes of Chromatin Loops Revealed by Deletion of an RNA-Binding Region in CTCF</article-title><source>Mol Cell</source><year>2019</year><volume>76</volume><fpage>395</fpage><lpage>411</lpage><elocation-id>e13</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7251926</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31522987</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molcel.2019.07.039</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R109"><label>109</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Lattice light-sheet microscopy: Imaging molecules to embryos at high spatiotemporal resolution</article-title><source>Science (80-)</source><year>2014</year><volume>346</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4336192</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25342811</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1257998</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R110"><label>110</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lambert</surname><given-names>Talley</given-names></name><name><surname>Shao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Volker</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><source>tlambert03/LLSpy: v048 (048)</source><year>2019</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5281/zenodo.3554482</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R111"><label>111</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schindelin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Fiji: An open-source platform for biological-image analysis</article-title><source>Nat Methods</source><year>2012</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>676</fpage><lpage>682</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3855844</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22743772</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.2019</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R112"><label>112</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Langmead</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Salzberg</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fast gapped-read alignment with Bowtie 2</article-title><source>Nat Methods</source><year>2012</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>357</fpage><lpage>359</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3322381</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22388286</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.1923</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R113"><label>113</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Model-based analysis of ChIP-Seq (MACS)</article-title><source>Genome Biol</source><year>2008</year><volume>9</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2592715</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18798982</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/gb-2008-9-9-r137</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R114"><label>114</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Quinlan</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>BEDTools: A flexible suite of utilities for comparing genomic features</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2010</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>841</fpage><lpage>842</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2832824</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20110278</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btq033</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R115"><label>115</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heinz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Simple Combinations of Lineage-Determining Transcription Factors Prime cis-Regulatory Elements Required for Macrophage and B Cell Identities</article-title><source>Mol Cell</source><year>2010</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>576</fpage><lpage>589</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2898526</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20513432</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molcel.2010.05.004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R116"><label>116</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Plimpton</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fast Parallel Algorithms for Short-Range Molecular Dynamics</article-title><source>J Comput Phys</source><year>1995</year><volume>117</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>19</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R117"><label>117</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>De Gennes</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name></person-group><source>Scaling Concepts in Polymer Physics</source><year>1979</year><publisher-name>Cornell University Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Cohesin and CTCF bind chromatin increasingly more efficient during zebrafish development</title><p><bold>a)</bold> Scheme of subunits and cofactors of the cohesin complex and positions of the HaloTag (HT) labeled with JF-549. <bold>b)</bold> Scheme outlining the workflow for injecting, labeling, and measuring HT constructs in zebrafish. <bold>c)</bold> Top: Scheme of continuous illumination showing 10 ms camera exposure (yellow bars) and 1.7 ms camera readout time (black bars). Bottom: Example single-molecule tracks of the 64-cell stage (bright pink) and shield stage (dark pink). Scale bar: 1 μm. <bold>d), e)</bold> Fractions of a three-component diffusion model fitted to jump distance distributions of (<bold>d</bold>) HT-rad21 and (<bold>e</bold>) HT-CTCF. Colors indicate stages of development (64-, 128-, 256-, 512-, 1k-cell, high, oblong, sphere, shield). Bars represent mean values ± s.d. from 500 resamplings using 80% of randomly selected jump distances. For fits and diffusion coefficients see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 2-4</xref> and statistics in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 1</xref>. <bold>f)</bold> Scheme of interlaced time-lapse microscopy (ITM) showing 10 ms camera exposure (yellow bars) and alternating short (0.2 s) and long (4 s) dark times without laser excitation. Molecules are classified into different binding classes. Long (green): tracks surviving at least two long dark times (8.2 s). Short (red): Tracks surviving one short dark time (0.2 s). Spot (yellow): Molecules only detected in a single frame. <bold>g), h)</bold> Top: Example nuclei of (<bold>g</bold>) HT-rad21 and (<bold>h</bold>) HT-CTCF ITM movies with tracks colored according to the binding classes in panel (<bold>f</bold>). Grey tracks survived only one long dark time. Scale bar: 5 μm. Bottom: Fractions of short and long binding events of (<bold>g</bold>) HT-rad21 (WT) or HT-rad21-3x mutant and (<bold>h</bold>) HT-CTCF (WT) or HT-CTCF-ΔZF4-7 mutant. Data represent mean ± s.d. of movie-wise determined fractions. Insets show zooms into the respective graphs. Lines serve as guides to the eye. Statistics are provided in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 2-7</xref>. <bold>i)</bold> Fractions of short (left) and long (right) binding events of HT-rad21 (WT) in the presence of morpholinos (MO) or RNA-polymerase inhibitors in the shield stage. P-values were calculated using the Kruskal-Wallis-Test (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Tables 8-9</xref>). Source data are provided as a Source Data file for <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1d-e, g-i</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS192679-f001"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Long-bound cohesin confines chromatin motion and shows distinct nuclear localization</title><p><bold>a)</bold> Schemes of time-lapse illumination alternated with continuous intervals (TACO) showing 10 ms camera exposure (yellow bars) and different dark times without laser excitation. Molecules are classified in short and long-bound binding classes comparable to ITM (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1f</xref>) and analyzed during continuous intervals (dark green and dark red bars, see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="S10">Methods</xref>). <bold>b)</bold> Mean jump distances of HT-rad21 molecules classified as short bound (left) and long bound (right) at different developmental phases. pre-ZGA (red): 64-, 128-, 256, 512-cell stages pooled; post-ZGA (green): high, oblong, sphere stages pooled; shield stage (blue) and shield stage with the addition of Nibpl-morpholino (cyan). Insets: example tracks. Data represent mean ± s.d. P-values were calculated using the Kruskal-Wallis-Test (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 10</xref> and statistics in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 11</xref>). Scale bar: 1 μm. <bold>c)</bold> Sketch of cohesin-mediated decrease in chromatin motion. <bold>d)</bold> Left: Example nucleus (bold white circle) subdivided into five bins (dotted lines) with the initial positions of long-bound tracks (pink). Right: Pooled initial positions of long-bound tracks of all ITM- and TACO measurements at pre-ZGA stages shown in a unit circle. For other developmental phases and statistics, see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 6</xref>. <bold>e)</bold> Histogram of track counts per bin (compare panel <bold>(d)</bold>, right) normalized to bin area and the highest bin value. Error bars represent the square root of track counts per bin. Source data are provided as a Source Data file for Fig. 2b, e.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS192679-f002"/></fig><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Binding kinetics of cohesin and CTCF change during zebrafish embryogenesis</title><p><bold>a)</bold> Scheme depicting the rate constants of chromatin association (k<sub>on</sub>) and dissociation (k<sub>off</sub>) of JF-549-labeled HT-rad21 and HT-CTCF. <bold>b)</bold> Schemes of continuous illumination showing 500 ms camera exposure (yellow bars) and 4.5 s time-lapse illumination with 4 s dark time between exposures (black bars). <bold>c)</bold> Left: Kymographs propagating with the spot-center of continuous and 4.5 s time-lapse illumination. Right: Corresponding tracks, color-coded according to time. Scale bar: 1 μm. <bold>d), e)</bold> Survival time distributions of (<bold>d</bold>) HT-rad21 and (<bold>e</bold>) HT-CTCF of different time-lapse conditions indicated on the top and the respective GRID fits (dashed lines). pre-ZGA (red): 64-, 128-, 256, 512-cell stages pooled; post-ZGA (green): high, oblong, sphere stages pooled; shield (blue). <bold>f), g)</bold> GRID state spectra of dissociation rates of (<bold>f</bold>) HT-rad21 and (<bold>g</bold>) HT-CTCF using all data (solid line, colored according to stages) and 500 resampling runs with randomly selected 80% of data (black spots) as an error estimation of the spectra. Grey insets: Average residence times and percentages of dissociation rates larger or smaller than 0.1 s<sup>-1</sup> (dashed line). Detailed residence times and fractions are provided in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Tables 12-13</xref>, with statistics in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 14</xref>. <bold>h</bold>) Measured bound fractions (circle) and bound fractions calculated from kinetic rates (square) of HT-CTCF (left) and HT-rad21 (right). Measured data represent mean ± s.d. of movie-wise determined fractions. Errors of calculated values were determined with Gaussian error propagation (<xref ref-type="sec" rid="S10">Methods</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 15-16</xref>). <bold>i)</bold> Search times (inverse on-rates) for a single HT-CTCF (left) or HT-rad21 (right) molecule to find any binding site (<xref ref-type="sec" rid="S10">Methods</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Tables 15-16</xref>). <bold>j)</bold> Relative effective search times for any HT-CTCF (left) or HT-rad21 (right) molecule to find any specific binding site. Errors are based on Gaussian error propagation. <bold>k)</bold> Scheme depicting the concentration model: During early embryo development, the nuclear volume (outer black circle) decreases, CTCF- (brown) and cohesin (purple) molecule counts, and accessible CTCF binding sites increase. Changes in kinetic rates are depicted as variations in arrow width and color. Source data are provided as a Source Data file for Fig. 3d-j.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS192679-f003"/></fig><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Simulated contact maps including single-molecule data recapitulate experimental contact maps</title><p><bold>a)</bold> Contact maps of a polymer model with 1 kb mapping for pre-ZGA (left) or shield stages (right). Data is averaged across 10 independent runs. <bold>b)</bold> Contact probability <italic>P(s)</italic> derived from the maps shown in (<bold>a)</bold> as function of genomic distance. <bold>c)</bold> Ratio of P(s) slopes between shield and pre-ZGA stages using modelling data. <bold>d)</bold> Contact maps derived from a published Hi-C dataset <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32">32</xref></sup> for 2.25 hpf (hours post fertilization, similar to pre-ZGA) and 5.3 hpf (similar to shield). <bold>e)</bold> Same as panel (<bold>b)</bold> but for Hi-C contacts maps from panel (<bold>d</bold>). <bold>f)</bold> Ratio of P(s) slopes between shield and pre-ZGA stages for slopes of <italic>P(s)</italic> from panel (<bold>e</bold>). <bold>g)</bold> Pile-up plots representing average observed contact probabilities divided by expected (average contact probabilities at the same genomic distance) in +/-100kb windows around accessible CTCF sites for different developmental stages. Top row represents modeling, and bottom row experimental Hi-C data. <bold>h)</bold> Scheme depicting emergence of cohesin-mediated loops and CTCF binding due to altered binding kinetics of both species during early zebrafish development.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS192679-f004"/></fig></floats-group></article>