<!DOCTYPE article
 PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" article-type="preprint"><?all-math-mml yes?><?use-mml?><?origin ukpmcpa?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">bioRxiv</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>bioRxiv : the preprint server for biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub"/></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">EMS190504</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2023.10.27.563754</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="archive">PPR752132</article-id><article-version-alternatives><article-version article-version-type="status">preprint</article-version><article-version article-version-type="number">1</article-version></article-version-alternatives><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Oncogenic RAS-Pathway Activation Drives Oncofetal Reprogramming and Creates Therapeutic Vulnerabilities in Juvenile Myelomonocytic Leukemia</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Hartmann</surname><given-names>Mark</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Schönung</surname><given-names>Maximilian</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rajak</surname><given-names>Jovana</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN2">#</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Maurer</surname><given-names>Valentin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN2">#</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hai</surname><given-names>Ling</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">5</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN2">#</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bauer</surname><given-names>Katharina</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A6">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hakobyan</surname><given-names>Mariam</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A7">7</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Staeble</surname><given-names>Sina</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Langstein</surname><given-names>Jens</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jardine</surname><given-names>Laura</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A8">8</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rölz</surname><given-names>Roland</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A9">9</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bohler</surname><given-names>Sheila</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Khabirova</surname><given-names>Eleonora</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A10">10</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Maag</surname><given-names>Abdul-Habib</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A11">11</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Vonficht</surname><given-names>Dominik</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A12">12</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A7">7</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lebrecht</surname><given-names>Dirk</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bernt</surname><given-names>Katrin M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A13">13</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>Kai</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A14">14</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A15">15</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Changya</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A14">14</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A15">15</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Alikarami</surname><given-names>Fatemeh</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A16">16</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Boch</surname><given-names>Tobias</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A17">17</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Flore</surname><given-names>Viktoria</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lutsik</surname><given-names>Pavlo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A18">18</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A19">19</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Milsom</surname><given-names>Michael D.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A20">20</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Raffel</surname><given-names>Simon</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A21">21</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Buske</surname><given-names>Christian</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A11">11</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Haas</surname><given-names>Simon</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A22">22</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A23">23</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A24">24</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Haniffa</surname><given-names>Muzlifah</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A8">8</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A10">10</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mallm</surname><given-names>Jan-Philipp</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A6">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Behjati</surname><given-names>Sam</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A10">10</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A25">25</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A26">26</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bonder</surname><given-names>Marc-Jan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A27">27</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A28">28</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A29">29</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fröhling</surname><given-names>Stefan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A30">30</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A31">31</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Niemeyer</surname><given-names>Charlotte M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A32">32</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hey</surname><given-names>Joschka</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A18">18</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A33">33</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN3">§</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Flotho</surname><given-names>Christian</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A32">32</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN3">§</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Plass</surname><given-names>Christoph</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A18">18</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN3">§</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Erlacher</surname><given-names>Miriam</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A32">32</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN3">§</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Schlesner</surname><given-names>Matthias</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A34">34</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN3">§</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Lipka</surname><given-names>Daniel B.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A35">35</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN3">§</xref></contrib><aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Section of Translational Cancer Epigenomics, Division of Translational Medical Oncology, German Cancer Research Center (DKFZ) &amp; National Center for Tumor Diseases (NCT) Heidelberg, Heidelberg, Germany</aff><aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Division of Pediatric Hematology and Oncology, Department of Pediatrics and Adolescent Medicine, Medical Center, Faculty of Medicine, University of Freiburg, Freiburg, Germany</aff><aff id="A3"><label>3</label>European Molecular Biology Laboratory Hamburg, Germany; Centre for Structural Systems Biology (CSSB), Hamburg, Germany</aff><aff id="A4"><label>4</label>Bioinformatics and Omics Data Analytics, German Cancer Research Center (DKFZ), Heidelberg, Germany</aff><aff id="A5"><label>5</label>Clinical Cooperation Unit Neurooncology, German Cancer Research Center (DKFZ) and National Center for Tumor Diseases Heidelberg, Heidelberg, Germany</aff><aff id="A6"><label>6</label>scOPEN Lab, German Cancer Research Center (DKFZ), Heidelberg, Germany</aff><aff id="A7"><label>7</label>Faculty of Biosciences, Heidelberg University, Heidelberg, Germany</aff><aff id="A8"><label>8</label>Biosciences Institute, Newcastle University, Newcastle upon Tyne NE2 4HH, UK</aff><aff id="A9"><label>9</label>Department of Neurosurgery, University of Freiburg, Faculty of Medicine, Medical Center, Freiburg, Germany</aff><aff id="A10"><label>10</label>Wellcome Sanger Institute, Hinxton, United Kingdom</aff><aff id="A11"><label>11</label>Institute of Experimental Cancer Research, University Hospital of Ulm, Ulm, Germany</aff><aff id="A12"><label>12</label>Division of Stem Cells and Cancer, German Cancer Research Center (DKFZ) and DKFZ-ZMBH Alliance, Heidelberg, Germany; Heidelberg Institute for Stem Cell Technology and Experimental Medicine (HI-STEM gGmbH), Heidelberg, Germany</aff><aff id="A13"><label>13</label>Division of Pediatric Oncology, Children’s Hospital of Philadelphia, Philadelphia, USA</aff><aff id="A14"><label>14</label>Center for Childhood Cancer Research, The Children’s Hospital of Philadelphia, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania</aff><aff id="A15"><label>15</label>Department of Pediatrics, University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania</aff><aff id="A16"><label>16</label>Division of Oncology and Center for Childhood Cancer Research, Children’s Hospital of Philadelphia, Philadelphia, USA</aff><aff id="A17"><label>17</label>Department of Hematology and Oncology, Heidelberg University, University Hospital Mannheim, Mannheim, Germany</aff><aff id="A18"><label>18</label>Division of Cancer Epigenomics, German Cancer Research Center (DKFZ), Heidelberg, Germany</aff><aff id="A19"><label>19</label>Computational Cancer Biology and Epigenomics, Department of Oncology, KU Leuven, Leuven, Belgium</aff><aff id="A20"><label>20</label>Division of Experimental Hematology, German Cancer Research Center (DKFZ), Heidelberg, Germany; Heidelberg Institute for Stem Cell Technology and Experimental Medicine (HI-STEM gGmbH), Heidelberg, Germany</aff><aff id="A21"><label>21</label>Department of Medicine, Hematology, Oncology and Rheumatology, University Hospital Heidelberg, Germany</aff><aff id="A22"><label>22</label>Heidelberg Institute for Stem Cell Technology and Experimental Medicine (HI-STEM gGmbH), Heidelberg, Germany; Division of Stem Cells and Cancer, German Cancer Research Center (DKFZ), Heidelberg, Germany</aff><aff id="A23"><label>23</label>Berlin Institute of Health (BIH), Charité - Universitätsmedizin Berlin, Berlin, Germany</aff><aff id="A24"><label>24</label>Berlin Institute for Medical Systems Biology (BIMSB), Max Delbrück Center in the Helmholtz Association, Berlin, Germany</aff><aff id="A25"><label>25</label>Cambridge University Hospitals NHS Foundation Trust, Cambridge, United Kingdom</aff><aff id="A26"><label>26</label>Department of Paediatrics, University of Cambridge, Cambridge, United Kingdom</aff><aff id="A27"><label>27</label>Genome Biology Unit, European Molecular Biology Laboratory (EMBL), Heidelberg, Germany</aff><aff id="A28"><label>28</label>Division of Computational Genomics and Systems Genetics, German Cancer Research Center (DKFZ), Heidelberg, Germany</aff><aff id="A29"><label>29</label>European Bioinformatics Institute (EMBL-EBI), Wellcome Genome Campus, European Molecular Biology Laboratory (EMBL), Hinxton, United Kingdom</aff><aff id="A30"><label>30</label>National Center for Tumor Diseases (NCT), Heidelberg, Germany; Division of Translational Medical Oncology, German Cancer Research Center (DKFZ), Heidelberg, Germany</aff><aff id="A31"><label>31</label>German Cancer Consortium (DKTK), DKFZ, core center Heidelberg, Germany</aff><aff id="A32"><label>32</label>German Cancer Consortium (DKTK), partner site Freiburg, a partnership between DKFZ and University Medical Center Freiburg, Germany</aff><aff id="A33"><label>33</label>German-Israeli Helmholtz International Research School in Cancer Biology</aff><aff id="A34"><label>34</label>Faculty of Applied Computer Sciences, Biomedical Informatics, Data Mining and Data Analytics, University of Augsburg, Augsburg, Germany</aff><aff id="A35"><label>35</label>Faculty of Medicine, Otto-von-Guericke-University, Magdeburg, Germany</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="CR1"><bold>Correspondence to Daniel B. Lipka</bold>, Section of Translational Cancer Epigenomics, Division of Translational Medical Oncology, German Cancer Research Center (DKFZ) &amp; National Center for Tumor Diseases, (NCT) Heidelberg, Im Neuenheimer Feld 581, 69120 Heidelberg, Germany, Phone: +49-6221-42-1613, <email>d.lipka@dkfz.de</email>; <bold>Mark Hartmann</bold>, Section of Translational Cancer Epigenomics, Division of Translational Medical Oncology, German Cancer Research Center (DKFZ) &amp; National Center for Tumor Diseases, (NCT) Heidelberg, Im Neuenheimer Feld 581, 69120 Heidelberg, Germany, Phone: +49-6221-42-1603, <email>m.hartmann@dkfz.de</email></corresp><fn id="FN1" fn-type="equal"><label>*</label><p id="P1">These authors contributed equally as first authors</p></fn><fn id="FN2" fn-type="equal"><label>#</label><p id="P2">These authors contributed equally as second authors</p></fn><fn id="FN3"><label>§</label><p id="P3">Co-senior authors</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted"><day>03</day><month>11</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="preprint"><day>01</day><month>11</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><permissions><ali:free_to_read/><license><ali:license_ref>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is licensed under a <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">CC BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p id="P4">Aberrant fetal gene expression facilitates tumor-specific cellular plasticity by hijacking molecular programs of embryogenesis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref></sup>. Persistent fetal gene signatures in childhood malignancies are typically explained by their prenatal origins<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">2</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref></sup>. In contrast, reactivation of fetal gene expression is considered a consequence of oncofetal reprogramming (OFR) in adult malignancies and is associated with aggressive disease<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref></sup>. To date, OFR has not been described in the context of childhood malignancies. Here, we performed a comprehensive multi-layered molecular characterization of juvenile myelomonocytic leukemia (JMML) and identified OFR as a hallmark of aggressive JMML. We observed that hematopoietic stem cells (HSCs) aberrantly express mixed developmental programs in JMML. Expression of fetal gene signatures combined with a postnatal epigenetic landscape suggested OFR, which was validated in a JMML mouse model, demonstrating that postnatal activation of RAS signaling is sufficient to induce fetal gene signatures. Integrative analysis identified the fetal HSC maturation marker CD52 as a novel therapeutic target for aggressive JMML. Anti-CD52 treatment depleted human JMML HSCs and disrupted disease propagation <italic>in vivo</italic>. In summary, this study implicates OFR, defined as postnatal acquisition of fetal transcription signatures, in the pathobiology of a childhood malignancy. We provide evidence for the direct involvement of oncogenic RAS signaling in OFR. Finally, we demonstrate how OFR can be leveraged for the development of novel treatment strategies.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec id="S1" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p id="P5">Fetal signatures in cancer have been described for a number of entities including pediatric and adult malignancies, although the cellular origins and molecular mechanisms are mostly obscure<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref></sup>. For childhood malignancies, the detection of driver mutations at the time of birth revealed that premalignant clones can arise prenatally leading to a maturation block with subsequent malignant transformation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref></sup>. However, genetic evidence for a prenatal event cannot be obtained in all patients affected by childhood malignancies, suggesting that alternative molecular mechanisms may establish fetal signatures. In adult malignancies, the concept of ‘oncofetal reprogramming’ (OFR) describes the reactivation of fetal programs in cancer cells originating from postnatal cells-of-origin. OFR could explain the occurrence of fetal expression programs in childhood malignancies for which evidence of a prenatal origin is lacking. However, to date, OFR has not been described in the context of childhood cancer<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref></sup>.</p><p id="P6">Juvenile myelomonocytic leukemia (JMML) is a myeloproliferative/myelodysplastic neoplasm of early childhood and clinically a highly heterogeneous disease that is defined by the presence of mutations affecting the RAS-signaling pathway<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref></sup>. Epigenetic disease subgroups, known as epitypes, have been identified as the only solitary significant predictor of overall survival in JMML<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref></sup>. In addition to global DNA hypermethylation, the upregulation of fetal hemoglobin and the fetal hematopoietic stem cell (HSC) marker <italic>LIN28B</italic> have been associated with high-risk disease<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref></sup>. Correspondingly, in a subset of JMML patients oncogenic driver mutations have been found in neonatal blood spots, suggesting a prenatal origin of the disease<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">20</xref></sup>. However, JMML driver mutations can only be detected in a minority of high-risk patients at birth, which may indicate a postnatal origin of the disease in these patients<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">21</xref></sup>. Such indications of a postnatal disease origin in some cases together with the simple genetic landscape and the profound epigenetic remodeling qualifies JMML as a suitable model to study cancer ontogeny.</p><p id="P7">In this study, we used multi-omics profiling to identify disease-specific transcriptomic and epigenomic aberrations associated with high-risk JMML. We observed an unanticipated discrepancy between prenatal transcription and postnatal methylation states, suggesting OFR as a possible explanation. Using a JMML mouse model driven by HSC-specific activation of a <italic>Ptpn11<sup>E76K</sup></italic> mutation revealed that oncogenic RAS pathway activation results in OFR. Furthermore, we demonstrate that OFR drives disease-specific expression programs, resulting in aberrantly upregulated markers in HSCs of high-risk JMML patients. Preclinical data testing one of these aberrantly expressed markers in a xenotransplantation model suggested that CD52 may serve as an efficient therapeutic target in high-risk JMML.</p></sec><sec id="S2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="S3"><title>JMML-related aberrations affect the entire hematopoietic system including hematopoietic stem cells</title><p id="P8">The clinical heterogeneity found across JMML patients has mostly been resolved at the molecular level using DNA methylation analysis which led to the identification of so-called JMML epitypes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref></sup>. However, the molecular mechanisms driving the establishment of JMML epitypes remain elusive. To systematically characterize the degree of molecular heterogeneity in JMML, we adopted a multi-modal analysis strategy to integrate epigenomic, transcriptomic, and surface marker expression data obtained from patient samples representing all three JMML epitypes: namely low (LM); intermediate (IM); and high methylation (HM) JMML (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1a</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Extended Data Fig. 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary Table 1</xref>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref></sup>. Using scRNA-seq of mononuclear cells (MNC) isolated from JMML patients and healthy subjects of different age groups (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Extended Data Fig. 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary Table 2</xref>), we confirmed that all hematopoietic lineages and major cell types were present in the hematopoietic systems of JMML patients, although cell type frequencies were heterogenous across patients (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1b-d</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Extended Data Figs. 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">4</xref>).</p><p id="P9">However, pronounced differences were observed between JMML samples and healthy controls regarding the frequency of cells expressing typical age-matched hematopoietic stem and progenitor cell (HSPC) marker genes (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1e,f</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Extended Data Figs. 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">4</xref>). These aberrant expression profiles were also observed in a systematic trajectory analysis and affected all major lineages, including hematopoietic stem cells (HSC; <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1g</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Extended Data Fig. 5</xref>). All trajectories showed enrichment of inflammatory signaling pathways with a peak in HSCs (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1g</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Extended Data Fig. 5d</xref>). Together, this data suggested that the HSC compartment is massively altered in JMML.</p></sec><sec id="S4"><title>Epitypes are conserved in hematopoietic stem cells of JMML patients</title><p id="P10">To systematically characterize early molecular evolution of JMML epitypes, we investigated the molecular landscape of the HSPC compartment of JMML patients by performing a multi-modal analysis comprising immunophenotypes, epigenotypes, and transcriptomes (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2a</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">Extended Data Fig. 6</xref>). Lineage-negative (Lin<sup>-</sup>) cells of JMML patients revealed cell surface expression patterns for CD34 and CD38 that were different in frequencies but comparable in global structure to those observed in healthy references (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2b</xref>, top panel). In contrast, Lin<sup>-</sup>CD34<sup>+</sup>CD38<sup>-/lo</sup> HSPCs exhibited highly heterogeneous immunophenotypes with respect to CD45RA and CD90 expression (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2b</xref>, bottom panel). This included the appearance of a recently described aberrant Lin<sup>-</sup>CD34<sup>+</sup>CD38<sup>-/lo</sup>CD45RA<sup>+</sup>CD90<sup>+</sup> HSPC population<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">23</xref></sup>. The abundance of these immunophenotypically aberrant CD45RA<sup>+</sup>CD90<sup>+</sup> HSPCs was distinct across JMML epitypes, with hypermethylated (HM) JMML showing the highest frequency of CD45RA<sup>+</sup>CD90<sup>+</sup> HSPCs in an independent validation cohort (n=20 pts; <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2c</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary Table 3</xref>). This observation suggested that epitype-related, disease-specific aberrations of gene regulatory programs might already be present in the HSPC compartment of JMML patients. To test this possibility, we generated ultra-low input whole-genome bisulfite sequencing (WGBS) data from different HSPC subpopulations, i.e. the CD45RA/CD90 quadrants of Lin<sup>-</sup>CD34<sup>+</sup>CD38<sup>-/lo</sup> cells (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2b</xref>, bottom panel, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary Table 4</xref>). DNA methylation-based cell type classification<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref></sup> determined all CD45RA/CD90 subpopulations isolated from JMML patients as HSCs, independent of the epitype, the donor, or the immunophenotypic CD45RA/CD90 quadrant, confirming aberrant molecular programs in the JMML HSC compartment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">Extended Data Fig. 7a</xref>). In line with this observation, unsupervised analysis of JMML HSC methylomes precisely recapitulated the corresponding epitypes that had been determined by methylation array analysis of bulk MNCs (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2d</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Extended Data Figs. 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">7b-d</xref>). In conclusion, the conservation of epitypes between HSCs and differentiated MNCs from JMML patients reveals DNA methylation as a differentiation-independent and early disease-specific aberration, which confirms JMML as a disease originating from HSCs.</p><p id="P11">Next, we aimed to identify DNA methylation changes in JMML HSCs that are characteristic of the HM epitype, as this epitype is associated with an aggressive disease course<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref></sup>. Differentially methylated regions (DMRs) detected between HSCs from HM and non-HM (LM &amp; IM) patients confirmed widespread CpG hypermethylation, which particularly affected bivalent enhancers and polycomb-repressed regions associated with developmental processes (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2e</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">Extended Data Fig. 7b and e-l</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary Table 5</xref>).</p><p id="P12">For example, DMRs were annotated to loci of hematopoietic and developmental regulators such as <italic>FLI1, RUNX1</italic>, and several homeobox gene classes (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2f</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">Extended Data Fig. 7m,n</xref>). Furthermore, DMRs were enriched for transcription factor (TF) binding motifs such as PU.1, HOXC9, as well as various GATA and ETS family members, suggesting an impact of epitypes on specific gene regulatory programs involved in hematopoietic maturation and differentiation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">Extended Data Fig. 7o</xref>). In conclusion, our DNA methylome data demonstrated that JMML epitypes are present in HSCs from JMML patients, and that the observed epigenetic aberrations might govern epitype-specific gene regulation, including the engagement of developmental programs.</p></sec><sec id="S5"><title>Hematopoietic stem cells exhibit epitype-specific gene expression programs in JMML patients</title><p id="P13">To investigate whether the epitype-specific DNA methylation patterns translate into distinct gene expression programs in HSCs of JMML patients, we performed scRNA-seq on Lin<sup>-</sup>CD34<sup>+</sup>CD38<sup>-/lo</sup> HSPCs isolated from the same 8 JMML patients (P1 – P8; <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2a</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">Extended Data Fig. 8a</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary Table 2</xref>). Focusing on transcriptionally defined HSCs, we found significant transcriptional priming towards the myeloid lineage (p = 0.0023, LMM and ANOVA) in patients with IM and HM epitypes as compared to the LM epitype, and this increase in transcriptional myeloid priming occurred at the expense of priming towards the megakaryocytic-erythroid lineages (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">Extended Data Fig. 8b</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary Table 6</xref>). These differences were paralleled by an increase in expression of leukemia-associated signatures from LM- to HM-HSCs, suggesting that aberrant DNA methylation might impact on HSC function in JMML in an epitype-specific manner (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">Extended Data Fig. 8c</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary Table 6</xref>). Differential gene expression analysis between HSCs from HM and non-HM patients revealed a number of highly dysregulated genes, which are critical for hematopoiesis, including HSC markers such as <italic>AVP, CRHBP, CD164</italic>, and <italic>CD34</italic>, differentiation and activation markers such as <italic>LGALS1, DNTT, IGLL1, CD96, CD69</italic>, and <italic>CD52</italic>, as well as developmental factors such as <italic>HMGA2</italic> and <italic>HBG2</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">Extended Data Fig. 8d</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary Table 7</xref>). Functional enrichment analyses confirmed immune activation and inflammation programs in JMML HSCs, which has been described as a feature of prenatal development<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">25</xref></sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">Extended Data Fig. 8e,f</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary Table 8-11</xref>). Taken together, the upregulation of developmental genes in HM-JMML HSCs was in line with the altered DNA methylation seen in regions that are epigenetically regulated during development (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">Extended Data Fig. 7h-o</xref>). This indicated an epitype-specific functional role for developmental factors in JMML pathogenesis and raised the question whether developmental origins vary across JMML epitypes.</p></sec><sec id="S6"><title>Transcriptional mosaicism of developmental programs in JMML HSCs</title><p id="P14">A recent report described the detection of JMML driver mutations at birth in 75% (12 out of 16) of individuals who later developed JMML (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">Extended Data Fig. 8g</xref>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">21</xref></sup>. Together with our observation that JMML epitypes are associated with developmental features in HSCs, this suggested a prenatal origin of the disease in at least a subset of patients. To systematically examine developmental phenotypes of JMML HSCs and to compare these to healthy development, we compiled a scRNA-seq reference map of hematopoietic maturation, including 116 different reference cell types from healthy donors spanning four developmental stages: fetal (FET), neonatal (NEO), juvenile (JUV), and adult (ADU; <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3a</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary Table 2</xref>). Next, we applied “cell type similarity inference”<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref></sup> to independently predict the average similarity of JMML HSCs per patient to each of the reference cell types (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">Extended Data Fig. 8h</xref>). While HSCs from all JMML samples showed high similarity to healthy neonatal HSCs, LM-JMML HSCs also exhibited high similarity to healthy postnatal (i.e., juvenile and adult) HSCs. In contrast, the IM- and HM-JMML stem cells showed high transcriptional similarity to healthy fetal HSCs (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3b</xref>). Such subgroup-specific global expression patterns were confirmed by the expression of known marker genes for HSCs from different developmental stages. Postnatal HSC markers (<italic>CRHBP, AVP</italic>) were found to be upregulated in LM-JMML and healthy postnatal HSCs (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3c</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">Extended Data Fig. 8i</xref>). Conversely, fetal HSC markers, such as <italic>HMGA2</italic> and <italic>MECOM</italic>, were upregulated in HM-JMML and healthy fetal HSCs (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3d</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">Extended Data Fig. 8i</xref>), which implied either preservation or reactivation of fetal gene expression programs in HM-JMML. In this context, it is noteworthy that JMML HSCs revealed different levels of similarity (&gt;0.5) but virtually no dissimilarities (&lt;0.5) to any of the reference HSC populations across hematopoietic development (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3b</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">Extended Data Fig. 8h</xref>). This suggested a transcriptional mosaicism of developmental signatures rather than an unambiguous cell type-specific transcriptional profile for any of the stages. To consolidate this observation, we generated a list of the top 50 stage-specific marker genes of normal HSC development and analyzed the expression of these signature genes in JMML HSCs (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3e</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary Table 12-13</xref>). This revealed a high degree of subgroup- and patient-specific heterogeneity, including aberrant regulation of a range of genes relative to normal HSCs from all of the four developmental stages. This further suggested that JMML is characterized by variegated expression of developmental signatures, including components of fetal gene expression programs, most prominently in HM-JMML.</p></sec><sec id="S7"><title>DNA methylome analysis reveals postnatal maturation of hematopoietic stem cells across all JMML epitypes</title><p id="P15">The observed transcriptional mosaicism in JMML HSCs was inconclusive with respect to the developmental origins of JMML. Since it has previously been demonstrated that DNA methylomes retain elements of the tissues and cell types of origin<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">26</xref></sup>, we sought to investigate the DNA methylomes of JMML HSCs in the context of the developing hematopoietic system. We generated a DNA methylome reference map of normal HSC maturation representing the same developmental stages as used for the scRNA-seq analysis, i.e. fetal, neonatal, juvenile, and adult HSCs (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4a</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary Table 4</xref>). Unsupervised analysis of the 10,000 most variable CpGs across normal and JMML HSCs revealed pronounced genome-wide differences between HM-JMML and healthy references from all developmental stages, whereas LM-JMML HSCs clustered with the postnatal references (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F15">Extended Data Fig. 9a</xref>). To more precisely determine patterns associated with HSC maturation, we identified genomic regions with dynamic DNA methylation in healthy references and found 1,179 regions (441 with methylation gain, 738 with methylation loss) that revealed continuous gain or loss of DNA methylation from fetal to adult HSCs (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4b</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary Table 14</xref>). Using these maturation dynamic regions for phylogenetic analysis recapitulated the trajectory from fetal to adult HSCs during normal maturation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F15">Extended Data Fig. 9b</xref>). Projecting the JMML HSC methylomes onto this maturation phylogeny revealed postnatal epigenetic patterns for all JMML HSCs analyzed here, regardless of their epitype, indicating that at the time of diagnosis all JMML HSCs had acquired a postnatal DNA methylome (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4c</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F15">Extended Data Fig. 9c</xref>). This finding was further corroborated when looking at so called ‘epigenetic scars’, which are genomic regions that change their methylation status significantly in one particular developmental window but remain stable thereafter (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4d</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F15">Extended Data Fig. 9d</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary Table 15-16</xref>). These analyses showed that HSCs from all JMML patients clustered together with postnatal HSCs when looking at the transitions from fetal to postnatal or from neonatal to post-neonatal HSCs, respectively, further indicating that HSCs from all patients examined had passed the neonatal stage regardless of their epitype (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4e</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F15">Extended Data Fig. 9e</xref>). In conclusion, our epigenetic data show postnatal epigenomes in HSCs from all 8 JMML patients investigated, which is in contrast to the fetal-like expression signatures observed in non-LM-JMML. These seemingly contradictory findings could theoretically be explained by two different models: (I.) Prenatal acquisition of a RAS-pathway mutation could lead to altered HSC maturation resulting in partial preservation of fetal transcription signatures (fetal origin hypothesis; <xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4f</xref>, left panel). (II.) Alternatively, acquisition of a RAS-pathway mutation in a postnatal HSC may lead to transformation and induction of aberrant transcription programs which result in reprogramming and reactivation of fetal-like molecular signatures (OFR hypothesis; <xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4f</xref>, right panel).</p></sec><sec id="S8"><title>RAS-pathway activation in postnatal HSCs results in oncofetal reprogramming in a JMML mouse model</title><p id="P16">To experimentally test whether postnatal acquisition of a JMML driver mutation is able to instruct the reactivation of fetal-like expression signatures (OFR hypothesis), we established an inducible JMML mouse model which is driven by the activation of a <italic>Ptpn11<sup>E76K</sup></italic> mutation in HSCs upon tamoxifen injection (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5a</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">Extended Data Fig. 10a</xref>). Postnatal induction of the <italic>Ptpn11<sup>E76K</sup></italic> mutation in adolescent mice (6-12 weeks of age) resulted in rapid development of a JMML-like disease, characterized by leukocytosis, thrombocytopenia, reduced hemoglobin levels, pronounced splenomegaly, excess production of myeloid cells, particularly monocytes, and a median survival of 24 weeks (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5b-f</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">Extended Data Fig. 10b-e</xref>). To analyze the molecular mechanisms underlying the JMML-like disease observed in <italic>Ptpn11<sup>E76K/+</sup></italic> mice, we isolated LSK (Lin<sup>-</sup>Sca1<sup>+</sup>cKit<sup>+</sup>), LK (Lin<sup>-</sup>cKit<sup>+</sup>), and total hematopoietic cells from the bone marrow (BM) of <italic>Ptpn11<sup>E76K/+</sup></italic> and <italic>Ptpn11<sup>+/+</sup></italic> mice 6 weeks after tamoxifen induction and performed scRNA-seq (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary Table 17</xref>). Data were integrated across genotypes and annotated based on the expression of established marker genes (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5g</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">Extended Data Fig. 10f</xref>). We found a significant myelomonocytic skewing and loss of immature HSPCs in <italic>Ptpn11<sup>E76K/+</sup></italic> mice (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5h</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">Extended Data Fig. 10g,h</xref>), demonstrating that the postnatal induction of <italic>Ptpn11<sup>E76K/+</sup></italic> in HSCs precisely recapitulated human JMML. The upregulation of monocytic gene expression programs was already observed at the level of HSCs in <italic>Ptpn11<sup>E76K/+</sup></italic> mice, indicating increased transcriptional priming of <italic>Ptpn11<sup>E76K/+</sup></italic> HSCs towards the myeloid lineage (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5i</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">Extended Data Fig. 10i-k</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary Table 6</xref>). In addition, we found a significant enrichment of fetal gene signatures in HSCs from <italic>Ptpn11<sup>E76K/+</sup></italic> mice as compared to wild-type HSCs (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5j,k</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary Table 6</xref>). In line with this observation, <italic>Ptpn11<sup>E76K/+</sup></italic> HSCs showed a significant upregulation of fetal HSC markers such as <italic>Lgals1</italic> and <italic>Plac8</italic> and concurrent downregulation of adult HSC marker genes (<italic>H3f3b, Fos,</italic> and <italic>Procr;</italic> <xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5l</xref>).</p><p id="P17">In summary, our mouse model recapitulated phenotypic and molecular features of human JMML including transcriptional rewiring and myeloid lineage priming of HSCs. We demonstrated that expression of the <italic>Ptpn11<sup>E76K</sup></italic> mutation in adolescent mice was sufficient to re-establish fetal-like gene expression programs in HSCs, hence providing proof-of-principle that postnatal acquisition of a RAS-pathway mutation can lead to oncofetal reprogramming.</p></sec><sec id="S9"><title>Integrative analysis identifies novel prognostic biomarkers and therapeutic targets for high-risk JMML</title><p id="P18">The mouse model demonstrated that HSC-specific activation of <italic>Ptpn11<sup>E76K</sup></italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref></sup><sup>/+</sup> induces a JMML-like disease. This provided further evidence that HSCs are the likely cell-of-origin of JMML and suggested that effective therapies should target aberrant molecular features of JMML HSCs. Following the experimental proof of OFR in JMML, we asked the question whether disease-specific aberrations affect developmental factors that could be exploited for the treatment of JMML. To identify and prioritize such aberrations, we defined the following selection criteria: (a) DNA methylation-associated gene expression in JMML HSCs; (b) aberrant upregulation of gene expression in JMML HSCs relative to healthy reference HSCs across developmental stages; (c) proposed role in HSC development; (d) availability of drugs, which can be used for preclinical testing (<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6a</xref>). To identify DNA methylation-associated genes in HSCs across JMML epitypes, we determined genes for which differential expression could be explained by differential DNA methylation. Comparing HM with non-HM JMML, we identified 346 DMRs that are associated with 155 DEGs (out of 255 HM vs non-HM DEGs overall) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F17">Extended Data Fig. 11a</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary Table 18-19</xref>), which confirmed the central role of DNA methylation in disease-specific gene regulation. For functional validation, we defined high-confidence candidate genes based on high correlation (&gt;0.9) of DNA methylation and gene expression (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F17">Extended Data Fig. 11a</xref>, <xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6b</xref>). Out of 56 high-confidence candidates, 23% (13 genes) encoded for cell surface proteins (<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6b</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F17">Extended Data Fig. 11b</xref>), which is significantly more than the expected proteome-wide frequency<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">28</xref></sup>. Comparison of expression levels revealed that all 13 candidates were consistently upregulated in JMML HSCs relative to almost all healthy reference HSCs. Moreover, these surface proteins showed epitype-specific expression patterns, suggesting that they could act as both disease- and epitype-specific biomarkers (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F17">Extended Data Fig. 11c</xref>).</p><p id="P19">Focusing on HM-JMML as the epitype with the most urgent need for novel therapeutic approaches, we identified <italic>CD52</italic>, which encodes a cell surface protein that is an established drug target in chronic lymphocytic leukemia and multiple sclerosis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">29</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31">31</xref></sup>. <italic>CD52</italic> is associated with epigenetic aberrations in JMML HSCs (<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6b,c</xref>), and shows moderate expression levels in healthy HSCs across normal hematopoietic maturation, with a slight but significant upregulation in fetal HSCs (<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6d</xref>). However, it is strongly upregulated in JMML HSCs with the highest expression levels found in HM-JMML (<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6d</xref>). Epitype-specific CD52 expression was confirmed at the protein level in CD34<sup>+</sup>CD38<sup>-/lo</sup> HSPCs from JMML patients, suggesting CD52 surface protein as an accessible drug target on JMML HSCs (<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6e</xref>). Finally, murine <italic>Cd52</italic> was transcriptionally upregulated in HSCs of <italic>Ptpn11<sup>E76K/+</sup></italic> mice relative to control HSCs, confirming the disease-specific upregulation in JMML HSCs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F17">Extended Data Fig. 11d</xref>). In conclusion, CD52 is aberrantly upregulated preferentially in HM-JMML and is a promising target for further evaluation as a prognostic biomarker and as a therapeutic target in HM-JMML.</p></sec><sec id="S10"><title>Anti-CD52 treatment reduces leukemia burden, depletes leukemic stem cells, and disrupts disease propagation in a JMML PDX model</title><p id="P20">To assess the therapeutic potential of anti-CD52 targeted treatment, we used an established preclinical patient-derived xenograft (PDX) mouse model of JMML and treated PDX mice with the therapeutic monoclonal antibody alemtuzumab for 4 weeks (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F18">Extended Data Fig. 12a</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary Table 20</xref>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32">32</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33">33</xref></sup>. FACS analysis of primary recipients revealed an efficient depletion of human CD52<sup>+</sup> cells following alemtuzumab treatment, resulting in a significantly reduced frequency of human leukemia cells in blood, bone marrow, spleen, liver, and lung (<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6f-h</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F18">Extended Data Fig. 12b,c</xref>). As proposed by our integrative multi-omics analysis, alemtuzumab treatment targeted human HSPCs as evidenced by an efficient depletion of Lin<sup>-</sup> CD34<sup>+</sup>CD38<sup>-</sup> cells (<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6i</xref>). This resulted in the depletion of virtually all human hematopoietic cells in our xenograft model, including CD52<sup>-</sup> cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F18">Extended Data Fig. 12c-h</xref>). Secondary transplantation of total bone marrow from alemtuzumab- or vehicle-treated animals showed that anti-CD52 treatment prevented leukemic engraftment in 2° recipients (<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6j,k</xref>). In conclusion, therapeutic targeting of CD52 leads to efficient depletion of leukemia-propagating stem cells <italic>in vivo</italic>.</p></sec></sec><sec id="S11" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p id="P21">In the present study, we performed a multi-layered molecular analysis in which we systematically compared JMML across disease-specific epitypes to healthy references of HSC development. Single-cell transcriptome and DNA methylome analyses gave opposing results: transcriptomes revealed pronounced fetal HSC signatures for the more aggressive JMML epitypes whereas DNA methylomes indicated a postnatal epigenomic pattern in all patients analyzed. This finding is particularly important as the current consensus assumes that early childhood malignancies arise during fetal development and manifest as maturation blocks in aberrantly developing tissues<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34">34</xref></sup>. This view is supported by a number of studies which provide mostly genetic evidence for fetal origins, which are based on the detection of driver mutations in neonatal blood spots or on mathematical modeling of the originating developmental stage based on cell cycle-related mutation rates<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35">35</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39">39</xref></sup>. However, whether or not the presence of fetal-like transcriptional programs present across a range of childhood malignancies can unambiguously be considered as indicative of their prenatal origin remains a matter of scientific debate<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40">40</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43">43</xref></sup>. In the present study, an in-depth analysis of the transcriptome layer revealed that malignant hematopoietic stem cells (HSC) hijack transcription programs across different developmental stages and that HSCs from high-risk patients reactivate fetal-like gene expression signatures in a patient-specific manner. To complement the transcriptomic layer with epigenetic information, we performed DNA methylome analysis, which presumably provides more robust information on developmental and tissue origins of tumors than transcriptomes, as multiple lines of evidence suggest that DNA methylomes represent the developmental and differentiation states in which the malignant cells have been arrested<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R44">44</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R48">48</xref></sup>. In the context of JMML, DNA methylome analysis unambiguously showed postnatal epigenomes in HSCs of all JMML samples investigated in this study by phylogeny and epigenetic scar analyses. This indicated that fetal-like transcription programs observed in JMML are unlikely to be caused by a developmental maturation block.</p><p id="P22">These apparently conflicting results might be explained by OFR, a phenomenon well-known in the context of adult but not childhood malignancies. OFR describes the re-acquisition of fetal gene expression programs in tumorigenesis, which has been described for adult malignancies such as hepatocellular carcinoma<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref></sup>. In general, the process of oncogenesis requires cellular reprogramming to sustain cells with physiologically contradicting features such as stemness/pluripotency and differentiation bias<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R49">49</xref></sup>. Thus, OFR might reflect a tumor-specific strategy to gain cellular plasticity and to overcome physiological limitations of normal development. In JMML, the OFR hypothesis is supported by the clinical observation that high-risk JMML patients are typically older than 2 years at the time of diagnosis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref></sup>. In addition, a recent publication tested JMML driver mutations in Guthrie cards from individuals later diagnosed with JMML and found that 9/9 patients with low-risk (i.e. LM epitype) JMML had a detectable RAS-pathway mutation at birth, while only 3/7 patients with higher risk (i.e. IM or HM epitype) JMML were tested positive for a JMML driver mutation at birth<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">21</xref></sup>. Of note, whereas the current literature suggests that LM JMML arises prenatally, our data reveals postnatal maturation signatures at both the transcriptomic and epigenomic levels. This underlines that LM JMML, although most likely arising prenatally, does not show fetal signatures indicative of a maturation block. Vice versa, all HM patients analyzed here revealed postnatal epigenomes combined with pronounced enrichment of fetal-like transcription signatures, supporting the OFR hypothesis. It remains to be studied how many patients ultimately acquire their disease-initiating mutation postnatally and are affected by OFR. Furthermore, it is unclear whether OFR is influenced by the type of driver mutation.</p><p id="P23">Since multi-layer molecular analyses from primary patient samples are descriptive and cannot prove causality, we used a JMML mouse model to test whether the expression of a JMML driver mutation in young adult HSCs is sufficient to establish a fetal-like HSC gene expression program. Indeed, we found that induction of a <italic>Ptpn11<sup>E76K</sup></italic> mutation in postnatal HSCs was sufficient to establish an aberrant fetal-like transcription program, hence formally proving that OFR can occur in JMML. In summary, our work highlights how a multi-layered molecular analysis together with experimental validation enable the dissection of the characteristics of distinct disease phenotypes within a uniformly diagnosed and genetically characterized disease entity such as JMML. Our work, demonstrates that OFR is a phenomenon with relevance to childhood malignancies and might motivate the re-evaluation of the assumed pathogenetic mechanisms in relation to embryonic or fetal development across the entire spectrum of childhood malignancies. Nevertheless, there are still open questions that remain to be answered in the future: 1) How are the transcriptional and epigenetic aberrations established? 2) What is the order of acquisition of aberrations, i.e. is the transcriptome or the epigenome altered first? 3) How can the observed phenotypic heterogeneity be explained in the absence of genetic heterogeneity (i.e. presence of the same disease-initiating mutation)? Although answering these questions is beyond the scope of the current manuscript, it is tempting to speculate that transcriptional re-programming might precede the epigenetic alterations seen in the context of JMML. This hypothesis would be supported by the observation that, despite the presence of fetal-like transcription programs, the DNA methylomes lack pronounced signs of fetal reprogramming in the JMML mouse model (data not shown). Along these lines, DNA hypermethylation has been associated with increased proliferation activity and in some cases with methylation age<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R50">50</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R53">53</xref></sup>.</p><p id="P24">The discovery of OFR highlighted that JMML HSCs express a complex mosaic of expression programs across developmental stages. As a consequence, it is important to consider healthy references across developmental stages to identify cancer-specific aberrations. This approach provided the basis for the identification of prognostic biomarkers and novel therapeutic targets for this subset of patients with particularly poor outcome. For example, we could demonstrate that aberrant DNA methylation is accompanied by elevated mRNA expression levels of <italic>CD52</italic> in leukemic HSCs, especially in HSCs of high-risk JMML patients. This elevated <italic>CD52</italic> mRNA expression was not only recapitulated in HSCs of our JMML mouse model but it also translated into elevated surface protein expression levels on patient HSCs. This raises the possibility of performing clinical risk-stratification of JMML patients using a flow cytometry-based assay without the need for specialized and time-consuming epigenetic analyses. Of note, <italic>CD52</italic> has recently been described to play a functional role in both pre- and postnatal HSC development<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27">27</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R49">49</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R54">54</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R55">55</xref></sup>. Moreover, in line with our observation of an early differentiation bias in JMML HSCs, CD52 has been implicated in early myeloid priming<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R56">56</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R57">57</xref></sup>. A therapeutic monoclonal antibody targeting CD52 (alemtuzumab) is approved by the FDA and EMA for the treatment of multiple sclerosis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R58">58</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R59">59</xref></sup> and has been used as part of conditioning regimens for allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell transplantation (HSCT)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R60">60</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R61">61</xref></sup>. This made CD52 an interesting candidate for pre-clinical target validation, as HSCT is the only potentially curative treatment for high-risk JMML, although, more than 50% of patients relapse post-HSCT<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R62">62</xref></sup>. Furthermore, pre-clinical therapeutic activity of an approved drug could potentially be rapidly translated into the clinical setting. Using a patient-derived xenotransplantation model of JMML, we observed an efficient depletion of CD34<sup>+</sup>CD38<sup>-</sup> JMML hematopoietic stem and progenitor cells upon alemtuzumab treatment, which was functionally evidenced by the depletion of virtually all human hematopoietic cells independent of cell type-specific CD52 expression levels. Furthermore, alemtuzumab treatment abrogated the engraftment of human JMML cells in secondary recipient animals. Of note, this therapeutic effect was observed in PDX mice of the high-risk patient P7, who clinically showed a relapse after allogeneic HSCT. Hence, CD52-targeted therapy with alemtuzumab shows promising pre-clinical efficacy in high-risk JMML. This provides a rationale to further assess anti-CD52 treatment in pre-clinical studies as an option for JMML patients with high risk of relapse after allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell transplantation, for example in the context of the conditioning regimen.</p><p id="P25">In conclusion, our work on JMML provides evidence for oncofetal reprogramming as a mechanism for the expression of fetal-like transcriptional programs in a childhood malignancy. Furthermore, we demonstrate how a molecular high-precision approach identifies aberrantly regulated developmental markers and guides the identification of disease biomarkers and novel targeted therapies for a notoriously difficult-to-treat childhood leukemia.</p></sec><sec id="S12" sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec id="S13"><title>Authorization and ethical approval</title><p id="P26">The study was conducted according to the Declaration of Helsinki after written informed consent was obtained from the healthy subjects, the patients or their legal guardians. All experiments were approved by the local institutional review boards. All information is subject to the provisions of the local data protection regulations. JMML samples were obtained from the Hilda Biobank Freiburg, and fetal samples were obtained from the Wellcome Trust-funded Human Developmental Biology Resource (HDBR; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.hdbr.org">http://www.hdbr.org</ext-link>). HDBR is regulated by the UK Human Tissue Authority (HTA; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.hta.gov.uk">www.hta.gov.uk</ext-link>) and operates in accordance with the relevant HTA Codes of Practice. Healthy BM donors at the Heidelberg University Hospital received financial compensation. All mouse experiments were approved by German local authorities (Regierungspräsidium Karlsruhe and Regierungspräsidium Freiburg). All data were stored in accordance with the DKFZ framework for data protection.</p></sec><sec id="S14"><title>Isolation of hematopoietic cells from spleen of JMML patients</title><p id="P27">Splenectomy specimens from patients diagnosed with JMML were used to prepare single cell suspensions followed red blood cell lysis. To obtain mononuclear cell (MNC) fraction, single cell suspensions prepared from spleen tissue were subjected to density gradient centrifugation (Ficoll). Mononuclear cells were viably frozen and used for downstream analysis.</p></sec><sec id="S15"><title>Primary human pediatric bone marrow</title><p id="P28">Healthy juvenile pediatric bone marrow samples for WGBS were obtained from children at the age of 0 to 7 years in the course of neurosurgical interventions (e.g., correction of craniosynostoses, craniotomies performed for epilepsy surgery) after written informed consent was obtained from the patients’ legal guardians. For this purpose, the diploe of the craniotomized bone was cannulated with 27G needles and manually flushed with Ringer’s solution. Downstream procedures for sample preservation were identical as for materials obtained from JMML patients. For scRNA-seq, left-over bone marrow mononuclear cells from pediatric healthy normal sibling donors were isolated by ficoll gradient centrifugation.</p></sec><sec id="S16"><title>Primary human fetal spleen and liver</title><p id="P29">Tissue from healthy prenatal references was obtained from the HDBR. Developmental age, sex, and aneuploidy screens were performed as previously described<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R63">63</xref></sup>. Liver (n = 4; 12-16 post conception weeks (PCW)) and spleen (n = 3; 12-16 PCW) samples were diced and digested with 1.6mg/mL collagenase type IV (Worthington) in RPMI (Sigma-Aldrich) supplemented with 10% (v/v) heat-inactivated fetal bovine serum (Gibco), 100 U/mL penicillin (Sigma-Aldrich), 0.1 mg/mL streptomycin (Sigma-Aldrich), and 2 mM L-Glutamine (Sigma-Aldrich) for 30 min at 37°C with intermittent shaking. Digested tissue was passed through a 100 μm filter, and cells collected by centrifugation (500 g for 5 min at 4°C). Cells were treated with 1X RBC lysis buffer (eBioscience) for 5 min at room temperature and washed once with flow buffer (PBS containing 5% (v/v) FBS and 2 mM EDTA) prior to counting. Cells were cryopreserved in 90% (v/v) FBS with 10% dimethylsulfoxide (DMSO) to permit analysis in batches.</p></sec><sec id="S17"><title>Primary human bone marrow from adults</title><p id="P30">As healthy adult references, human samples from healthy adult individuals at the age of 23 to 25 were collected from bone marrow aspirates of healthy donors via iliac crest. Mononuclear cells were isolated by Ficoll (GE Healthcare) density gradient centrifugation and stored in liquid nitrogen until further use.</p></sec><sec id="S18"><title>Single-cell RNA-seq and WGBS of JMML patients</title><p id="P31">For scRNA-seq and ultra-low input whole-genome bisulfite sequencing (WGBS) of human JMML spleen and pediatric BM samples, cells were thawed in a water bath at 37°C and transferred dropwise into prewarmed IMDM (Gibco) supplemented with 10% FCS and 2 U/ml DNase I. Cells were centrifuged for 5 min at 300 g and washed with PBS (Gibco) supplemented with 4% FCS and DNase I (LIFE Technologies). Cells were resuspended in PBS containing 4% FCS (4 million per 100 µl) and fluorophore-conjugated antibodies for lineage markers, CD34, CD38, CD45RA, and CD90 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary Table 21</xref>), followed by incubation for 30 min at 4 °C in the dark. Cells were washed with PBS containing 4% FCS and resuspended in an appropriate volume for flow cytometry. For live/dead staining, 4,6-diamidino-2-phenylindole (DAPI; 1:1,000) was supplemented to the cell suspension. After 3 min of incubation at room temperature, cells were filtered through a 40 μm cell strainer (Greiner). Cell sorting was performed using BD FACSAria Fusion. For scRNA-seq of JMML HSPCs, 1,700 to 10,000 Lin<sup>-</sup>CD34<sup>+</sup>CD38<sup>dim/-</sup> cells were sorted into IMDM (Gibco) containing 4% FCS and directly subjected to droplet-based scRNA-seq (3’ v2 protocol from 10X Genomics). All scRNA-seq libraries from primary JMML patient material were sequenced on a HiSeq4000 (Illumina) paired-end 26+74 bp at the DKFZ Genomics &amp; Proteomics Core Facility (GPCF) (Heidelberg, Germany). For WGBS of JMML Lin<sup>-</sup>CD34<sup>+</sup>CD38<sup>dim/-</sup> HSPCs, 33 to 250 cells were directly sorted into RLT plus lysis buffer and stored at −80°C for later use.</p></sec><sec id="S19"><title>Single-cell RNA-seq and WGBS of healthy pediatric references</title><p id="P32">For WGBS of healthy juvenile reference bone marrow, cells were isolated from frozen samples as described above for JMML and 500 Lin<sup>-</sup>CD34<sup>+</sup>CD38<sup>-/lo</sup>CD45RA<sup>-</sup>CD90<sup>+</sup> HSCs were directly FACS-sorted into RLT plus lysis buffer. For WGBS of prenatal HSCs from fetal liver and spleen, up to 1 million cells were stained with antibody cocktail (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary Table 22</xref>), incubated for 30 min on ice and washed with flow buffer. Cells were resuspended at 10 million cells per ml and DAPI added immediately before FACS (Sigma-Aldrich; final concentration of 3 μM). Live, single, Lin-, CD34<sup>+</sup>CD38<sup>-/lo</sup>CD45RA<sup>-</sup> CD90<sup>+</sup> cells were sorted into RLT plus lysis buffer. Cells were stored at −80°C for later use. For scRNA-seq of healthy pediatric bone marrow, mononuclear cells were enriched for immature compartments using CD34<sup>+</sup> progenitors and Lin<sup>-</sup>CD34<sup>+</sup>CD38<sup>-</sup> HSPCs using flow cytometry. Viable live gate, progenitor- and stem cell-enriched populations were subjected to chromium 10X processing using v3 chemistry (10X Genomics).</p></sec><sec id="S20"><title>WGBS of healthy adult references</title><p id="P33">For WGBS of adult stem and progenitor cells, cryopreserved adult bone marrow samples were thawed and stained in FACS buffer (FB) (PBS supplemented with 5% FCS and 0.5 mM EDTA) containing the respective antibodies (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary Table 23</xref>) for 30 minutes followed by washing with FB. Subsequently, cells were sorted using an BD Aria Fusion II sorter. HSPC populations were sorted as previously defined<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R64">64</xref></sup>: Lin<sup>-</sup>CD34<sup>+</sup>CD38<sup>-/lo</sup>CD45RA<sup>-</sup>CD90<sup>+</sup> HSCs, Lin-CD34+CD38-CD45RA-CD90-MPPs, Lin-CD34+CD38+CD10-CD45RA-CD135+ CMPs, Lin-CD34+CD38+CD10-CD45RA+CD135+ GMPs, and Lin-CD34+CD38+CD10-CD45RA-CD135-MEPs. WGBS libraries were generated using a published tagmentation-based protocol<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R65">65</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="S21"><title>Flow cytometry analysis of JMML patients</title><p id="P34">For validation experiments of epitype-specific CD45RA/CD90 expression profiles, single cell suspensions prepared from JMML spleen tissue were subjected to density gradient centrifugation (Ficoll) to obtain mononuclear cell fractions (MNCs). An aliquot of the isolated MNCs was stained for flow cytometry (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary Table 24</xref>) and data acquired using BD LSRFortessa.</p><p id="P35">For validation experiments of epitype-specific CD52 expression profiles, JMML samples were thawed as described above (“Single-cell RNA-seq and WGBS of JMML patients”) and stained with fluorescence-coupled antibodies for flow cytometry (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary Table 25</xref>). Cells were analyzed with BD FACSAria Fusion.</p></sec><sec id="S22"><title>Panel-seq for JMML genotyping</title><p id="P36">DNA from bone marrow granulocytes was used for amplicon-based, next-generation deep sequencing to determine the variant allele frequencies (VAFs) of leukemia-specific index mutations. Targets of JMML associated Genes were enriched using a custom in-house panel (AmpliSeq JMML panel v2, IAA11909_192; Thermo Fisher Scientific) and processed with the NEBNext Ultra II DNA library preparation kit (New England Biolabs). Sequencing was performed on MiSeq sequencers (Illumia). Sequence variants were evaluated according to the ACMG classification system.</p></sec><sec id="S23"><title>Processing of scRNA-seq data</title><p id="P37">scRNA-seq data from JMML patients and JUV references were generated in this study, data from FET, NEO, and ADU references were obtained from the Human Cell Atlas project (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary Table 2</xref>). Sequencing data from JMML patient samples for scRNA-seq were aligned against the hg38 human reference genome, and gene-cell matrices were generated using <italic>CellRanger</italic> (v.2.1.1). Subsequent data processing included the sample-wise inclusion of cells that met specific quality criteria: <list list-type="simple" id="L1"><list-item><label>1.)</label><p id="P38">The number of genes exceeded 100.</p></list-item><list-item><label>2.)</label><p id="P39">The number of genes was within three median absolute deviations (MADs) from the median, determined using the “isOutlier” function in <italic>scater</italic> (v.1.10.1).</p></list-item><list-item><label>3.)</label><p id="P40">The number of counts exceeded 200.</p></list-item><list-item><label>4.)</label><p id="P41">The number of counts was within three MADs from the median, determined using the “isOutlier” function in <italic>scater</italic> (v.1.10.1).</p></list-item><list-item><label>5.)</label><p id="P42">Mitochondrial content was required to be below a 5% cutoff.</p></list-item></list></p><p id="P43">The ADU dataset was annotated to 35 cell types according to Hay et al., 2018<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R66">66</xref></sup>. Subsequently, the annotated ADU dataset was down-sampled to a maximum of 2500 cells per cell type and served as a label transfer reference to annotate other datasets, including FET, NEU, JUV, and JMML. Label transfer was performed using the “FindTransferAnchors” and “TransferData” functions (dims = 1:30) in <italic>Seurat</italic> (v.3.1.5)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R67">67</xref></sup>. Each cell was assigned one transferring score for each cell type, and the cell type assignment of cells was based on the highest cell type transferring score.</p><p id="P44">In the FET dataset, cells with annotations of endothelial cells, fibroblasts, hepatocytes, Kupffer cells, and VCAM1+ EI macrophages, based on the original paper<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R68">68</xref></sup>, retained their original annotations.</p><p id="P45">For the healthy reference datasets, each cell type was down-sampled to a maximum of 2500 cells for further analysis.</p></sec><sec id="S24"><title>scRNA-seq data integration</title><p id="P46">We employed the “anchor” integration method to integrate scRNA-seq datasets from JMML patients and healthy references using <italic>Seurat</italic> (v.3.1.5). The following steps were taken with default settings: <list list-type="simple" id="L2"><list-item><label>1.)</label><p id="P47">Dataset-wise data normalization was performed using the “NormalizeData” function.</p></list-item><list-item><label>2.)</label><p id="P48">Dataset-wise feature selection was conducted with the “FindVariableFeatures” function.</p></list-item><list-item><label>3.)</label><p id="P49">Pairwise “anchors” between the datasets were identified using the “FindIntegrationAnchors” function (dims = 1:30).</p></list-item><list-item><label>4.)</label><p id="P50">Data integration based on these “anchors” was achieved through the “IntegrateData” function (dims = 1:30).</p></list-item><list-item><label>5.)</label><p id="P51">The integrated data underwent regression of counts, scaling, and centering using the “ScaleData” function, followed by PCA dimensionality reduction.</p></list-item></list></p><p id="P52">The scRNAseq data of CD34+-enriched HSPCs and MNCs from JMML patients were integrated using the ‘anchor’ integration methods in the Seurat (v.3.1.5). Similar to the integration of JMML with healthy references, patient-wise data normalization and feature selection were performed. Pairwise ‘anchors’ between patients were identified and integrated. The integrated data was scaled and PCA calculated.</p></sec><sec id="S25"><title>Pseudotemporal analysis of hematopoietic lineages</title><p id="P53">PCA was used to estimate a linear latent pseudotime for each cell across distinct hematopoietic lineages using RNA expression data.</p><p id="P54">RNA expression data was normalized by dividing the feature counts of a given cell by the total counts for that cell, then multiplying the quotient by 10.000 and finally log1p transforming the product (default settings for <italic>Seurat</italic> “NormalizeData”).</p><p id="P55">To facilitate PCA in capturing lineage-specific changes, we devised a gene selection procedure consisting of three main steps: <list list-type="simple" id="L3"><list-item><label>1.)</label><p id="P56">The dataset was restricted to non-tumor cells, and genes with no observed transcripts across all cells were excluded.</p></list-item><list-item><label>2.)</label><p id="P57">For each gene, a cumulative link model was constructed to establish a relationship between the position of cells within the lineage and their normalized expression of the respective gene.</p></list-item><list-item><label>3.)</label><p id="P58">Genes satisfying both a Benjamini-Hochberg adjusted model coefficient p-value less than 0.01 and an absolute coefficient value greater than 1.5 were selected.</p></list-item></list> In the case of the dendritic cell lineage, this procedure was executed using 10,949 non-tumor cells, leading to the identification of 2,205 genes. Subsequently, the normalized expression values of each gene were scaled by subtracting the per-cell expression values by the average expression of the gene and dividing the difference by its standard deviation. This scaling process adhered to the default settings for the <italic>Seurat</italic> “ScaleData” function. The scaled expression values were then employed to perform PCA using <italic>Seurat</italic>.</p><p id="P59">Spearman correlation was calculated to evaluate the concurrence of differences in PCA cell embeddings and various metadata features. For categorical metadata, one-hot encoding was utilized to compute correlations. If necessary, for visualization purposes, the principal component with the highest correlation with lineage was flipped so that the lineage commenced on the left-hand side of the plot.</p></sec><sec id="S26"><title>UMAP integration of scRNA-seq data from CD34<sup>+</sup>-enriched JMML HSPCs and JMML MNCs</title><p id="P60">To project the scRNA-seq data of FACS enriched JMML CD34<sup>+</sup>CD38<sup>-/lo</sup> HSPCs onto the existing MNC UMAP space we used the MNC scRNA-seq set as a reference and identified anchors between both datasets by applying the <italic>Seurat</italic> “FindTransferAnchor” function with PCA as a specified reference reduction. We mapped the HSPC query data onto the MNC UMAP space using the “MapQuery” function and visualized the combined UMAP using <italic>ggplot2</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R69">69</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="S27"><title>Transcriptional priming and leukemia-related transcription programs of human HSCs</title><p id="P61">Gene expression signatures were extracted from previous publications <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R57">57</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R70">70</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R71">71</xref></sup>. Transcriptional priming was calculated using the <italic>Seurat</italic> “AddModuleScore” function for 1000 randomly selected HSCs from each epitype. Statistical significance was determined based on two LMMs as implemented in the <italic>lme4</italic> R package followed by ANOVA:</p><p id="P62">LMM1 = signature ∼ Subgroup + (1|Donor)</p><p id="P63">LMM2 = signature ∼ (1|Donor)</p></sec><sec id="S28"><title>Differential gene expression analysis</title><p id="P64">Differentially expressed genes (DEGs) between JMML HM and JMML nonHM CD34+enriched samples were identified using the “FindMarkers” function with default settings in <italic>Seurat</italic> (v.3.1.5). A total of 255 DEGs with an adjusted p-value &lt; 0.05 and an absolute log fold-change &lt; 0.25 were obtained.</p><p id="P65">Developmental stage-specific DEGs were identified in the cells annotated as HSCs in four healthy reference datasets (FET, NEO, JUV, and ADU) using the “FindAllMarkers” function in <italic>Seurat</italic> (v.3.1.5) for one-vs-rest comparisons. In each stage, the top 50 upregulated DEGs with an adjusted p-value &lt; 0.05 and an absolute log fold-change &lt; 0.25 were obtained. Any overlapping DEGs across stages were removed. We identified 44 DEGs for FET HSCs, 41 DEGs for NEO HSCs, 50 DEGs for JUV HSCs, and 47 DEGs for ADU HSCs.</p></sec><sec id="S29"><title>Enrichment of transcription signatures using Metascape</title><p id="P66">For functional gene list analyses, <italic>Metascape</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R72">72</xref></sup> was used applying default settings. As input, up- or downregulated HM vs nonHM DEGs of JMML HSCs were used (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary Table 7</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S30"><title>Logistic regression analysis of scRNA-seq data</title><p id="P67">The logistic regression method was used to measure the transcriptional similarity between JMML HSCs and healthy reference cell types (FET, NEO, JUV, and ADU) across developmental stages, as previously described <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref></sup>. In brief, we first trained a logistic regression model on the scRNA-seq count matrix of healthy references, encompassing cells of all hematopoietic cell types, using the trainModel function with default settings in LogisticRegression.Core.R. This trained model was then applied to predict the likelihood of similarity between cell types in healthy references and JMML patients using the predictSimilarity function with minGeneMatch = 0.5. The resulting average similarity scores of HSCs in JMML patients against all cell types were visualized in a heatmap using the ComplexHeatmap<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R73">73</xref></sup> package.</p></sec><sec id="S31"><title>DNA methylation array analysis</title><p id="P68">For DNA methylation array profiling, gDNA of 200,000 MNCs per sample was extracted and submitted to the DKFZ GPCF (Heidelberg, Germany) for Infinium MethylationEPIC BeadChip (Illumina) analysis. Data processing and epitype prediction were performed as described previously<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="S32"><title>Library preparation for ultra-low input whole-genome bisulfite sequencing (WGBS)</title><p id="P69">For ultra-low input WGBS library preparation, we used max. 500 cells and followed a customized previously published single-cell Bisulfite Sequencing (scBS-seq) protocol <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R74">74</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R75">75</xref></sup>. In brief, we sorted cells using flow cytometry into RLT Plus buffer to a total volume of 10 μL, which was applied to the following changes: single preamplification for 90 minutes at 37°C; 14 cycles of library amplification; two time 0.7x SPRI selection for library purification. Molarities and fragment sizes were measured and libraries were submitted for Illumina sequencing on a HiSeq X with paired-end 150 bp and 10% PhiX to the DKFZ GPCF.</p></sec><sec id="S33"><title>Processing of whole-genome bisulfite sequencing data</title><p id="P70">The Omics IT and Data Management Core Facility (DKFZ, Heidelberg) processed WGBS data as described earlier<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R76">76</xref></sup>. In short, reads were aligned using an updated pipeline published by Wang et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R65">65</xref></sup>, implemented as a Roddy Workflow (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/DKFZ-ODCF/AlignmentAndQCWorkflows">https://github.com/DKFZ-ODCF/AlignmentAndQCWorkflows</ext-link>) in the automated One Touch Pipeline<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R77">77</xref></sup>. In short, adaptor sequences of raw reads were trimmed using <italic>Trimmomatic</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R78">78</xref></sup>. Next, sequencing reads were in silico bisulfite-converted<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R79">79</xref></sup>(C&gt;T for the first read in the pair, G&gt;A for the second). <italic>BWA-MEM</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R79">79</xref></sup> was used with default parameters to align the converted reads to the in silico bisulfite-converted reference genome hg19, extended with the PhiX and lambda phage sequences. Post alignment, reads were converted back to their original state. Reads with a mapping quality ≥25 and nucleotides with a Phred-scaled quality score ≥25 were considered for PCR duplicate removal per sequencing library using the software <italic>Picar</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R80">80</xref></sup>. Methylation calling and M-bias QC was performed using <italic>MethylDackel</italic> <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R81">81</xref></sup> v0.4.0 and the parameters --<italic>OT 6,146,2,144 --OB 7,146,12,150</italic>, according to the M-bias quality control plots. Methylation calls were imported into R<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R82">82</xref></sup> v3.6 using the R package <italic>methrix</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R83">83</xref></sup> v 1.0.05, summarized based on annotated reference indices, and collapsed based on strand information. Furthermore, single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNP) with a minor allele frequency &gt;0.1 were filtered, using the reference provided in the R package <italic>BSgenome.Hsapiens.UCSC.hg19</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R84">84</xref></sup> v 1.4.0, and initial quality control was performed. For downstream analysis, DNA methylation data were imported into the R package <italic>bsseq</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R85">85</xref></sup> v1.20.0 and technical replicates were collapsed. To define average CpG island (CpGi) methylation, CpGi annotation was extracted using the R package <italic>RnBeads</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R86">86</xref></sup> v 2.4.0. For principal component analysis (PCA), methylation levels of the 20,000 most variable methylated CpGs were applied to the R base function <italic>prcomp</italic>.</p></sec><sec id="S34"><title>Methylation-based cell type classifier</title><p id="P71">For DNA methylation-based cell type classification, a previously published algorithm was applied<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref></sup>. As normal references, WGBS data of adult Lin<sup>-</sup>CD34<sup>+</sup>CD38<sup>-/lo</sup>CD45RA<sup>-</sup>CD90<sup>+</sup> HSCs, Lin<sup>-</sup>CD34<sup>+</sup>CD38<sup>-/lo</sup>CD45RA<sup>-</sup>CD90<sup>-</sup> MPPs, Lin<sup>-</sup>CD34<sup>+</sup>CD38<sup>+</sup>CD10<sup>-</sup>CD45RA<sup>-</sup>CD135<sup>+</sup> CMPs, Lin<sup>-</sup>CD34<sup>+</sup>CD38<sup>+</sup>CD10<sup>-</sup>CD45RA<sup>+</sup>CD135<sup>+</sup> GMPs, and Lin<sup>-</sup>CD34<sup>+</sup>CD38<sup>+</sup>CD10<sup>-</sup>CD45RA<sup>-</sup> CD135<sup>-</sup> MEPs was employed, which was generated in course of this study.</p><p id="P72">As input to the classifier, we used WGBS data that was prepared as outlined in the previous section. Briefly, WGBS data was subsetted to regions outlined in Farlik <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref></sup>, using the hg38 to hg19 liftover function from the R package <italic>rtracklayer</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R87">87</xref></sup>. The average methylation within each region was computed and used to execute the “cellTypePredictor.R” script by Farlik <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref></sup>. The classifier itself was trained on normal references and applied to JMML tumor samples.</p></sec><sec id="S35"><title>Differential methylation analysis</title><p id="P73">To define differentially methylated loci, a linear model was applied, considering the epigenotype (HM and non-HM) and sorting quadrant of the respective sample as a covariate. Therefore, the function “DMLfit.multiFactorR” with the parameter, <italic>smoothing = TRUE</italic>, from the R package <italic>DSS</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R88">88</xref></sup> v2.32.0 was applied. The epigenotype HM coefficient was extracted using the function “DMLtest.multiFactor” and differentially methylated regions (DMRs) were defined using the function “callDMR”, based on regions with &gt;3 CpGs, a length of &gt;50 bps, and a Benjamin-Hochberg corrected <italic>P</italic> value &lt;0.05 in at least 50% of all CpGs within that region. Additionally, DMRs were subsetted for an average coverage of ≥5 in at least half of the samples belonging to the HM and non-HM epigenotype respectively and a difference in methylation &gt;0.2. DMRs were annotated using the R package <italic>ChIPseeker</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R89">89</xref></sup> v1.31.3.900 and <italic>TxDb.Hsapiens.UCSC.hg19.knownGene</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R90">90</xref></sup> v3.2.2. Hierarchical cluster analysis of DMRs was performed using the R package <italic>pheatmap</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R91">91</xref></sup> v1.0.12, applying “ward.D2” as the clustering method to “Manhattan” distances.</p></sec><sec id="S36"><title>Transcription factor motif enrichment</title><p id="P74">DNA transcription factor (TF) motif enrichment was performed using the command line tool <italic>Homer</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R92">92</xref></sup> (v4.9.1) and the parameter <italic>-size given</italic>. DMRs were stratified in hypo- and hypermethylated regions, and a set of random regions with equal size, similar CpG frequency (15% tolerance in the deviation of CpG composition were allowed), and a maximum of 20% N’s in the sequence composition, were used as a background. The top 10 most significantly enriched TF motifs in hypo- and hypermethylated DMRs were visualized.</p></sec><sec id="S37"><title>Locus overlap and enrichment analysis of ChromHMM states</title><p id="P75">The R package <italic>LOLA</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R93">93</xref></sup> (v1.16.0) was used to enrich DMRs with ChromHMM states acquired from Encode<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R94">94</xref></sup>. DMRs were stratified in hypo- and hypermethylated regions and enriched to a background containing a set of random regions with equal size, similar CpG frequency (15% tolerance in the deviation of CpG composition was allowed), and a maximum of 20% N’s in the sequence composition.</p></sec><sec id="S38"><title>Locus plots</title><p id="P76">
<italic>IGV</italic> (v2.12.2) was used to visualize locus-specific methylation at single CpG resolution of WGBS and DNA methylation array data (450k). Alternatively, the R package <italic>gviz</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R95">95</xref></sup> v1.30.3 was used to generate locus plots. For the visualization of WGBS data, methylation calls were smoothed with the R package <italic>bsseq</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R85">85</xref></sup> v1.20.0, applying the function “BSmooth” with default parameters.</p></sec><sec id="S39"><title>Homeobox gene classes</title><p id="P77">Homeobox genes were taken from Holland <italic>et al.</italic> <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R96">96</xref></sup>. We annotated DMRs obtained from comparing HM vs non-HM JMML patients using the “annotatePeak” function from the <italic>ChIPseeker</italic> package<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R89">89</xref></sup>, assuming a tssRegion of +/− 3,000 base pairs. Subsequently, we counted how many DMR associated genes were present in either of the previously defined Homeobox gene classes PRD, ANTP and Misc (LIM, POU, HNF, SINCE, TALE, CUT, PROS, ZF, CERS). We divided the size each gene set by 30,000, and the number of DMR associated genes occurring in each gene set by the number of total DMR associated genes. The log2 fold change of those ratios was plotted.</p></sec><sec id="S40"><title>Delineating methylation profiles linked to healthy hematopoietic stem cell development and maturation</title><p id="P78">To analyze JMML within the context of HSC development, we compared the methylomes of JMML HSCs to those of healthy fetal, neonatal, juvenile, and adult HSCs. For this purpose, the entire genome was segmented into contiguous 1kb regions, and the average methylation in regions covered in all samples was computed (n = 1,209,679). Average methylation within each region was subsequently correlated with the developmental order, progressing from fetal to neonatal, juvenile, and adult stages, using spearman correlation.</p><p id="P79">Of all the regions analyzed, 1,608 exhibited an absolute Spearman correlation coefficient of at least 0.9, corresponding approximately to the 0.999 quantile of the absolute Spearman correlation distribution.</p><p id="P80">As the methylomes of fetal and juvenile samples were measured using post-bisulfite adaptor tagging (PBAT) while those of neonatal and adult samples were assessed by TWGBS, there remained a residual risk of confounding by the sequencing method. To address this issue, we computed the Spearman correlation of average methylation and sequencing method, subsequently removing all regions with an absolute correlation coefficient greater than 0.4 to account for the sequencing method covariate. This threshold corresponded approximately to the 0.75 quantile of the absolute Spearman correlation distribution. The remaining 1,179 regions were presumed to capture the epigenetic changes occurring throughout HSC development</p><p id="P81">For the reconstruction of phylogenetic trees representing HSC development, we calculated the Manhattan distance between samples based on the average methylation of the selected 1,179 regions. Tree reconstruction, assuming minimum evolution, was conducted using the “fastme.bal” function from the R package <italic>ape</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R97">97</xref></sup> (version 5.6.2).</p></sec><sec id="S41"><title>Principal component analysis of JMML and healthy reference bulk methylomes</title><p id="P82">To focus on the HSC bulk methylomes, data were subset accordingly, with the exclusion of the FL2_HSC_PBAT_2 sample due to its poor quality. The methylation values of the 10,000 most variable CpGs across all remaining samples were centered around 0 and scaled by their standard deviation. Subsequently, Principal Component Analysis (PCA) was applied to the scaled methylation values.</p><p id="P83">PCA embeddings and variance explained per principal component were computed using the prcomp function in base R, thereby facilitating an unsupervised analysis of genome-wide methylation patterns across hematopoietic stem cells.</p></sec><sec id="S42"><title>Identifying epigenetic scars of development</title><p id="P84">Epigenetic scars, conceptually, are characterized by marked methylation changes between distinct developmental states, while remaining stable during subsequent development (related to Abdel-Hakeem et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R98">98</xref></sup>). To identify epigenetic scars, DMRs were called between a developmental state of interest and all succeeding states. “callDMR” from the R package <italic>DSS</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R99">99</xref></sup> (2.42.0) was used to identify DMRs across two groups. The “callDMR” function was invoked using the following arguments: delta=.1, p.threshold=.05, minlen=50, minCG=3, dis.merge=50, pct.sig=0.5. Identified DMRs were filtered to suffice an average coverage of five in at least 50% of samples in both groups.</p><p id="P85">We identified 3,332 potential scars from comparing prenatal to postnatal states, and, 8,964 from the comparison between neonatal and post-neonatal states. Given the lenient nature of the DMR calling procedure, only a small fraction of all DMRs represent genuine epigenetic scars.</p><p id="P86">To select DMRs consistent with the concept of epigenetic scars, we applied the following filtering approach: <list list-type="simple" id="L4"><list-item><label>1.)</label><p id="P87">Conduct a Fisher’s exact test on a 2×2 contingency table comparing the total number of methylated and unmethylated CpGs within a given DMR and the two groups being compared. DMRs meeting a Benjamini-Hochberg adjusted p-value threshold of 0.01 were considered for further selection.</p></list-item><list-item><label>2.)</label><p id="P88">Exclude regions exhibiting a within-group standard deviation of average DMR methylation greater than 0.1 in any of the compared groups. For the neonatal vs postneonatal comparison, this cutoff was reduced to 0.05 due to the high number of adult HSC replicates.</p></list-item></list> DMRs passing this selection procedure were deemed genuine epigenetic scars. From the comparison between prenatal and postnatal we retained 100 epigenetic scars, from the comparison between neonatal and post-neonatal we retained 157.</p></sec><sec id="S43"><title>Linking transcriptional with epigenetic changes through generalized linear models</title><p id="P89">Generalized linear model with stepwise feature elimination using AIC was applied to identify DEGs associated with DMRs in a region of 200 Mb around each of the transcription start sites (TSS). The goal of this analysis was to identify genes whose alterations in expression could principally be attributed to changes in neighboring CpG methylation.</p><p id="P90">Specifically, our interest lay in genes differentially expressed between HM and non-HM cells derived from 10X data. Differentially expressed genes (DEGs) were identified using <italic>Seurat</italic> “findMarkers”, selecting genes meeting an adjusted p-value cutoff of 0.01. RNA expression data was normalized as outline in section: Pseudotemporal Analysis of Hematopoietic Lineages.</p><p id="P91">Likewise, DMRs were determined by comparing HM and non-HM patients utilizing bulk WGBS data. To minimize the influence of developmental regions, we excluded DMRs that overlapped with DMRs from all pairwise comparisons of non-tumor neonatal, juvenile, and adult patients. Overlap assessment was performed using the <italic>IRanges</italic> “findOverlaps” function (version 2.32.0) with default arguments. Subsequently, we computed the average methylation per patient per DMR.</p><p id="P92">After defining the sets of DEGs and DMRs, we calculated all DMRs that overlapped with a 100 kb region surrounding the gene body of each DEG. Prior to this, <italic>hgLiftOver</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://genome.ucsc.edu/cgi-bin/hgLiftOver">https://genome.ucsc.edu/cgi-bin/hgLiftOver</ext-link>) was employed to convert gene coordinates from hg38 to hg19.</p><p id="P93">Utilizing the “glm” function from the <italic>stats</italic> package in base R, we fitted a generalized linear model with a Gaussian link function to predict the expression of a given DEG through the methylation of associated DMRs. To reduce the number of model parameters (i.e., the number of DMRs predicting the expression of a given DEG), we employed the step function in base R, which optimizes the Akaike information criterion (AIC) in a stepwise manner. Briefly, this approach finds a balance between removing DMRs with minimal predictive power and maintaining acceptable model performance. Each DEG with at least one associated DMR after AIC optimization was considered linked to epigenetic changes.</p><p id="P94">Model performance was evaluated using standard metrics, including root-mean-square error, mean absolute error, Pearson correlation between prediction and ground truth, and ranked mean absolute error, which, unlike mean absolute error, utilizes the difference of ranks. DEGs were categorized based on the cellular location of their gene product using data from the <italic>CellPhoneDB</italic> database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Teichlab/cellphonedb-data/master/data/sources/protein_curated.csv">https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Teichlab/cellphonedb-data/master/data/sources/protein_curated.csv</ext-link>). DEGs exhibiting a Pearson correlation between prediction and ground truth greater than 0.9 were selected as candidates for further analysis.</p><p id="P95">The heatmaps display expression and methylation values for all DMR-DEG associations for all candidate genes per patient and subgroup. Normalized gene expression was scaled to minimum and maximum across patients. Average methylation for each DMR is the average beta-values across all CpGs per region and JMML epitype. ‘Correlation’ depicts the Pearson correlation coefficients as per DMR-DEG association. The expression of 13 genes encoding for cell surface proteins was found to be significantly correlated with DNA methylation changes in up to 7 DMRs.</p></sec><sec id="S44"><title><italic>Ptpn11<sup>E76K/+</sup></italic> JMML mouse model</title><p id="P96"><italic>Ptpn11<sup>E76K/+</sup> Scl</italic>-CreER<sup>T</sup> mice were bred by crossing previously described <italic>Scl</italic>-CreER<sup>T</sup> and <italic>Ptpn11</italic><sup>E76K-neo/+</sup> mice which were both on a B6.SJL-Ptprc<sup>a</sup> Pepc<sup>b</sup>/BoyJ (CD45.1) genetic background<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R100">100</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R101">101</xref></sup>. All mice were kept at the DKFZ in individually ventilated cages under specific pathogen-free (SPF) conditions.</p><p id="P97">For all experiments, <italic>Ptpn11<sup>E76K/+</sup> Scl-</italic>CreER<sup>T</sup> and <italic>Ptpn11<sup>+/+</sup> Scl</italic>-CreER<sup>T</sup> mice at the age of 6 to 12 weeks were injected intraperitoneally (i.p.) on 5 consecutive days each day with 2 mg tamoxifen (dissolved in 200 µl sunflower oil with 10% ethanol). For differential blood count analysis, peripheral blood was collected from the vena facialis and measured using HemaVet950 (Drew Scientific) or scil Vet abc Plus+ (scil) veterinary hematology analyzers. Additionally, 30 µl of peripheral blood were used for flow cytometry as described below.</p></sec><sec id="S45"><title>Flow cytometric analysis of hematopoietic cells</title><p id="P98">Mice were sacrificed 18 weeks post injection by cervical dislocation according to European guidelines. Bone marrow of tibiae, femora, iliae and vertebrae were isolated by crushing the bones in IMDM (Gibco) three times. Additionally, one femur was flushed using 1 ml PBS supplemented with 2% FCS (PBS/FCS) to determine bone marrow cellularity and the cell suspension was afterwards added to the crushed bones. Spleen cells were isolated by passing the organs through a 40 µm cell strainer (Falcon). Subsequently, bone marrow cells, splenocytes and peripheral blood were resuspended in ACK lysis buffer (Lonza) for red blood cell lysis. Cells were washed and stained in PBS/FCS using established cell surface marker combinations for the identification of hematopoietic cell types (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary Table 26</xref>). Flow cytometry analysis was performed using BD LSR II, BD LSR Fortessa and BD FACS Celesta (BD Biosciences).</p></sec><sec id="S46"><title>Bone marrow isolation and lineage depletion</title><p id="P99">Bone marrow cell isolation and lineage depletion have been performed as described before<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R102">102</xref></sup>. In short, bone marrow was isolated by crushing the bones three times in IMDM (Gibco) followed by red blood cell lysis using ACK lysis buffer (Lonza). Cells were washed in PBC/FCS and biotinylated antibodies added for lineage depletion (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary Table 26</xref>). Mouse depletion Dynabeads (Invitrogen) were used for the depletion of lineage-labeled cells using a DynaMag-15 magnet (Invitrogen). Subsequently, lineage-negative cells were stained with antibodies for the isolation of HSPCs followed by FACS using BD FACS Aria II and III cell sorters (BD Biosciences).</p></sec><sec id="S47"><title>Single-cell genotyping</title><p id="P100"><italic>Ptpn11<sup>E76K/+</sup> Scl-</italic>CreER<sup>T</sup> mice were sacrificed three days after the last tamoxifen injection and subsequently lineage-depleted bone marrow cells isolated from tibiae, femora, iliae and vertebrae as described above. Single HSCs (Lin-cKIT+ Sca1+ CD48-CD150+) were FACS-isolated and expanded for 12 days in StemSpan SFEM (Stemcell Technologies) containing 1% Penicillin/Streptomycin (Gibco), 2 mM L-Glutamine (Gibco), 50 ng/ml IL-3 (PeproTech), 50 ng/ml IL-6 (PeproTech), 50 ng/ml TPO (PeproTech), 50 ng/ml mSCF (PeproTech) and 50 ng/ml Flt3L (PeproTech) at 37°C with 5% CO<sub>2</sub> in 96-well U-bottom plates. Wells with colony growth were analyzed for induction of the <italic>Ptpn11<sup>E76K</sup></italic> mutation by genotyping PCR<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R101">101</xref></sup>. In short, lysis buffer containing 0.01% Tween-20 (Sigma-Aldrich) and Proteinase K (Thermo Scientific) was added to the cells followed by incubation at 65°C for 60 min and 95°C for 15 min. Cell lysate was subjected to genotyping using a HotStar Taq polymerase (QIAGEN) and previously established primers<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R101">101</xref></sup>. PCR products were analyzed on a 2% agarose gel.</p></sec><sec id="S48"><title>Analysis of moribund mice</title><p id="P101">Moribund mice were sacrificed by cervical dislocation according to European guidelines. Spleen and live weight were determined and bone marrow cells isolated from tibiae, femora and iliae by flushing these bones with PBS/FCS. Flow cytometry was performed as described above using established cell surface marker combinations (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary Table 26</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S49"><title>Single-cell RNA-sequencing or material from <italic>Ptpn11<sup>E76K</sup></italic> mice</title><p id="P102">Mice were sacrificed 18 weeks post injection by cervical dislocation according to European guidelines. Femur cellularity was determined by flushing femora with PBS/FCS. Additionally, bone marrow cells from vertebrae, femora, tibiae, iliae, humeri and sterna were isolated by crushing these bones three times in IMDM (Gibco). The femur cells were added to the crushed bones followed by red blood cell lysis using ACK lysis buffer (Lonza). Afterwards, 5 x 10<sup>6</sup> cells were used for the staining of differentiated cells and 2.5 x 10<sup>7</sup> cells for flow cytometry measurements (see ‘Flow cytometric analysis of hematopoietic cells’). The remaining cells were subjected to lineage depletion as described above. Lineage-negative and differentiated cells were stained with antibodies for the isolation of hematopoietic cell types and used for FACS (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary Table 26</xref>). In total, 7,000 Lin-cKIT+ Sca1+ (LSK) and 7,000 Lin-cKIT+ (LK) cells were isolated from each mouse from lineage-negative bone marrow and 7,000 live total hematopoietic cells from unfractioned bone marrow. These cells were subjected to scRNA-sequencing using the Single Cell 3’ Reagent Kits v2 (10X Genomics) according to the manufacturer’s instructions. Sequencing was performed on a NovaSeq 6000 (Illumina) in paired-end (PE 26/96 bp) mode at the DKFZ GPCF.</p><p id="P103">Reads were aligned to GRCm38 and feature count matrices generated using Cell Ranger version 4.0.0 (10X Genomics). Feature counts were further processed using <italic>Seurat</italic> (version 4.0)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R103">103</xref></sup> whereby cells with more than 5% of mitochondrial reads or less than 500 and more than 5800 detected genes were removed from the analysis. Moreover, only genes that were expressed in a minimum of 10 cells were retained for further analysis. Doublets were identified and removed using <italic>DoubletFinder</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R104">104</xref></sup>. Cell cycle states were annotated based on the expression of stage specific marker genes (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/hbc/tinyatlas">https://github.com/hbc/tinyatlas</ext-link>). Filtered data was subsequently integrated across genotypes using the “SCTransform” method followed by PCA, UMAP calculation and clustering. Clusters were annotated to hematopoietic cell states based on the expression of previously identified state-specific marker genes <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R105">105</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R106">106</xref></sup>. Differentiation pseudotime was calculated using <italic>slingshot</italic> for the monocytic differentiation lineage and cells were ordered along this pseudotime based on their rank <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R107">107</xref></sup>.</p><p id="P104">Cluster contributions were calculated based on 10,000 randomly selected cells from each genotype. P-values were determined using Fisher’s exact test followed by Benjamini-Hochberg’s false discovery rate (FDR) correction.</p><p id="P105">Transcriptional priming was calculated based on previously published gene sets <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R108">108</xref></sup> using the <italic>Seurat</italic> “AddModuleScore” function. Statistical significance was determined based on two LMMs as implemented in the <italic>lme4</italic> R package followed by ANOVA:</p><p id="P106">LMM1 = signature ∼ genotype + (1|mouse_id)</p><p id="P107">LMM2 = signature ∼ (1|mouse_id)</p><p id="P108">Murine fetal and adult HSC signature genes were previously published <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27">27</xref></sup> and used for GSEA. In short, the <italic>Seurat</italic> “FindMarkers” function (logfc.threshold = -Inf, min.pct = 0.05, max.cells.per.ident = 1000) was used to calculate differential gene expression and subsequently genes not mapping to sex chromosomes were ranked based on fold change followed by GSEA using the <italic>fgsea</italic> package (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/060012v3">https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/060012v3</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec id="S50"><title>Primary xenotransplantation</title><p id="P109">Newborn <italic>Rag2<sup>-/-</sup>gc<sup>-/-</sup></italic> mice were used for xenotransplantation within the first four days of life. Mice were irradiated with 2,5 Gy. Six to eight hours after irradiation JMML (MNCs) were thawed, depleted from CD3<sup>+</sup> T cells using CD3 MicroBeads (Miltenyi Biotec) and 1×10<sup>6</sup> cells were injected intra-hepatically in 30 µl of PBS. Six to seven weeks after xenotransplantation, peripheral blood was obtained to inspect for human cell engraftment using flow cytometry with an antibody specifically detecting human pan-leukocyte antigen (hCD45). Successfully engrafted mice were then treated with alemtuzumab (100 µg/kg) or vehicle 1x/week for 4 weeks.</p></sec><sec id="S51"><title><italic>In vivo</italic> anti-CD52 treatment</title><p id="P110">At eight weeks following xenotransplantation, mice were divided into two groups: the control group received 100 µl of PBS and the experimental group received 100 mg/kg anti-CD52 antibody (alemtuzumab, Genzyme Corporation Cambridge) prepared in 100 µl of PBS. Injections were given via tail vein once per week for four weeks.</p><p id="P111">One week after the end of the treatment, mice were sacrificed and blood, bone marrow, spleen, liver, and lungs were used for the analysis. Single cell suspensions were obtained for blood, bone marrow, and spleen, while liver and lungs were firstly digested with collagenase D (1 mg/ml) and DNase (25 mg/ml) for 30 minutes at 37°C followed by density gradient centrifugation. Cell suspensions were exposed to red blood cell lysis and stained with antibodies (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary Table 27</xref>). All antibodies were used in 1:100 ratio. Cell acquisition and measurement was done using BD Fortessa. Different cell populations were characterized following gating strategy shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F18">Extended Data Figure 12i</xref>.</p><p id="P112">The expression levels are quantified as total number of events of engrafted CD45+ cells or absolute number of living cells calculated out from two femurs. Statistical analyses were performed using the unpaired Mann-Whitney test in GraphPad Prism 10 software. P values less than 0.05 were considered statistically significant. Treatment effect of alemtuzumab was calculated as difference of the percentage of engrafted human CD45 cells in treated vs untreated mice (treatment effect=treated<sub>mean</sub> - untreated<sub>mean</sub>).</p></sec><sec id="S52"><title>Serial transplantations</title><p id="P113">For serial transplantations, 5-weeks old mice were sublethally irradiated with 3 Gy and six to eight hours after irradiation 1×10<sup>7</sup> total bone marrow cells control- or alemtuzumab-treated mice were injected. Six weeks after transplantation, human cell engraftment was assessed in murine peripheral blood by flow cytometry using an antibody specifically detecting human pan-leukocyte antigen (hCD45). Terminally sick mice were eliminated and organs were analyzed as described above.</p></sec><sec id="S53"><title>Statistical analysis and data visualization</title><p id="P114">Statistical tests are specified in the corresponding figure legends and methods sections. If not differently specified, default statistical tests implemented in <italic>Seurat</italic> or <italic>DSS</italic> were used for scRNA-seq or WGBS analyses, respectively. For the analysis of JMML PDX mice, GraphPad Prism was used. Flow cytometry data was analyzed using FlowJo (v.10.6.2, v.10.8.1, BD Biosciences). Flow cytometers and sorters were operated using DIVA v.8 or v.9. Visualizations were generated using <italic>ggplot2</italic> and <italic>pheatmap, Seurat</italic> and <italic>Nebulosa</italic> in R version 4.0.3, 4.0.5, and 4.2.0<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R82">82</xref></sup>. For Kaplan-Meier analysis, the <italic>survminer</italic> R package was used to calculate leukemia-free survival (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/kassambara/survminer">https://github.com/kassambara/survminer</ext-link>).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="extended-data" id="S57"><title>Extended Data</title><fig id="F7" position="anchor"><label>Extended Data Figure 1</label><caption><title>Multi-omics cohort: annotation of patient cohort to JMML DNA methylation subgroups (‘epitypes’).</title><p id="P115">Patient stratification was conducted using our published JMML DNA methylation classifier<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R109">1</xref></sup>. Heatmap shows average methylation values across 124 classifier CpGs. Based on the probability per JMML subgroup, patients were assigned to one of three subgroups, namely LM (low methylation, blue), IM (intermediate methylation, yellow), or HM (high methylation, red). The annotation tracks specify the genetic background of the patients, which was determined by JMML panel sequencing. As boxplots, average methylation of genome-wide CpG island (CGI) methylation values are summarized. Based on those values and in a semi-quantative manner, patients were annotated to a patientspecific color throughout the manuscript.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS190504-f007"/></fig><fig id="F8" position="anchor"><label>Extended Data Figure 2</label><caption><title>UMAP summarizing the scRNA-seq data of total hematopoiesis in JMML, neonatal cord blood, as well as juvenile and adult bone marrow.</title><p id="P116">Single-cells are colored by cell types, which were annotated by automated cell type annotation using Seurat’s ‘label transfer’ function with adult bone marrow as a reference. JMML (n=7) and juvenile bone marrow (n=2) data were generated for this study. Neonatal cord blood and adult bone marrow data were taken from the Human Cell Atlas project<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R110">2</xref></sup>. The same colors are used for the corresponding cell types throughout the manuscript.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS190504-f008"/></fig><fig id="F9" position="anchor"><label>Extended Data Figure 3</label><caption><title>Dot plot summarizing the expression of the top 4 to 5 hematopoietic cell type marker genes as published in the human cell atlas project<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R110">2</xref></sup>.</title><p id="P117">Average expression is scaled per gene. Dot sizes represent the percentage of cells per cell type expressing the corresponding gene. Expression values are separately analyzed for JMML and healthy references (‘REF’), including neonatal cord blood, as well as juvenile and adult bone marrow.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS190504-f009"/></fig><fig id="F10" position="anchor"><label>Extended Data Figure 4</label><caption><title>Density plots depicting the cell type-specific expression of selected marker genes.</title><p id="P118"><bold>a,</bold> Hematopoietic stem and progenitor cells (HSPCs). <bold>b,</bold> Erythrocytes. <bold>c,</bold> Megakaryocytes. <bold>d,</bold> Dendritic cells. <bold>e,</bold> Monocytes and granulocytic neutrophils. <bold>f,</bold> B cells. <bold>g,</bold> Plasma cells. <bold>h,</bold> NK and T cells. <bold>i,</bold> Eosinophils.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS190504-f010"/></fig><fig id="F11" position="anchor"><label>Extended Data Figure 5</label><caption><title>Principal component analyses (scRNA-seq data) of major hematopoietic lineages stratified by healthy references and JMML.</title><p id="P119">All analyses are ordered in columns per lineage as labeled in b. <bold>a,</bold> Dotplot of principal components. Depicted is the summary of the correlation of principal components with technical and biological features. nCount: number of transcripts/cell; nFeature: number of genes/cell; Cell cycle: cell cycle phase score; Patient: donor of primary material; Subgroup: JMML epitype; Genotype: type of RAS-pathway mutation; Disease: disease status, i.e. healthy or JMML; Cell type: annotated hematopoietic cell type. For every lineage, PC 1 was representative for differentiation (colored per lineage). Additionally, at least one PC was representative for disease-specific features (red) among the first six PCs. Those PCs were used for 2-D PCA plot visualizations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figures 1g &amp; ED5c,d</xref>). <bold>b,</bold> Detailed analysis of differentiation-specific PCs per lineage. From top to bottom: stacked bar plot of cell type contributions over the course of PC1; PC loadings and scaled normalized expression of top genes from PC1. <bold>c,</bold> PCA plot colored by cell types. <bold>d,</bold> PCA plot colored by disease state (JMML in red vs. healthy references in grey). Density plots of cell type distribution across PC1 or disease state for the second dimension. PCA plot for neutrophil lineage in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1g</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS190504-f011"/></fig><fig id="F12" position="anchor"><label>Extended Data Figure 6</label><caption><title>Fluorescence activated cell sorting (FACS) strategy for indepth analysis of JMML HSPCs.</title><p id="P120">Lin<sup>-</sup>CD34<sup>+</sup>CD38<sup>lo/-</sup> cells were selected for scRNA-seq analyses. Lin<sup>-</sup>CD34<sup>+</sup>CD38<sup>lo/-</sup>CD45RA/CD90 quadrants were selected for ultra-low input WGBS analyses.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS190504-f012"/></fig><fig id="F13" position="anchor"><label>Extended Data Figure 7</label><caption><title>Ultra-low input whole-genome bisulfite sequencing data analysis of Lin<sup>-</sup>CD34<sup>+</sup>CD38<sup>lo/-</sup> HSPCs from primary JMML patient samples.</title><p id="P121"><bold>a,</bold> DNA methylation-based cell type classifier to determine the cell type-specific DNA methylation profiles across Lin<sup>-</sup>CD34<sup>+</sup>CD38<sup>lo/-</sup>CD45RA/CD90 quadrants<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R111">3</xref></sup>. Normal bone marrow from adult donors was taken as a reference. HSC, Lin<sup>-</sup>CD34<sup>+</sup>CD38<sup>-</sup>CD45RA<sup>-</sup>CD90<sup>+</sup>; MPP, Lin<sup>-</sup> CD34<sup>+</sup>CD38<sup>-</sup>CD45RA<sup>-</sup>CD90<sup>-</sup> CMP Lin<sup>-</sup>CD34<sup>+</sup>CD38<sup>+</sup>CD10<sup>-</sup>CD45RA<sup>-</sup>CD135<sup>+</sup> GMP Lin<sup>-</sup> CD34<sup>+</sup>CD38<sup>+</sup>CD10<sup>-</sup>CD45RA<sup>+</sup>CD135<sup>+</sup>; MEP, Lin<sup>-</sup>CD34<sup>+</sup>CD38<sup>+</sup>CD10<sup>-</sup>CD45RA<sup>-</sup>CD135<sup>-</sup>. <bold>b,</bold> Boxplot of the average genome-wide DNA methylation of CpG islands (CGI) across patients. <bold>c,</bold> Heatmap of the average methylation of the 1,000 most variable promoters. Epitype, JMML DNA methylation subgroup; Genotype, RAS mutation; Celltype, Lin<sup>-</sup>CD34<sup>+</sup>CD38<sup>lo/-</sup> CD45RA/CD90 quadrant. <bold>d,</bold> Reference-free decomposition of DNA methylation data using MeDeCom<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R112">4</xref></sup> with the following settings: k = 3, lambda = 0.01. <bold>e-g,</bold> HM vs non-HM DMR calling. <bold>e,</bold> Piechart stratifying DMRs into hyper- (11,190) and hypo-methylated (2,642). <bold>f,</bold> Histogram summarizing the size distribution of JMML DMRs with a median of 512 bp. <bold>g,</bold> Circos plot with histograms summarizing genomic DMR locations. Red represents hyper- and blue represents hypomethylated regions in HM vs. non-HM DMRs. Genome-wide distribution of JMML DMRs. <bold>h-j,</bold> Locus overlap analysis for enrichment of genomic ranges (LOLA) using the 15-state ChromHMM chromatin feature annotation. <bold>h,</bold> Bubble plot summarizing genome-wide enrichment analysis of DMRs in chromatin features (ChromHMM) using locus overlap analysis (LOLA). <bold>i,</bold> Boxplot of average methylation in polycomb-repressed (ReprPC) domains across JMML epitypes. <bold>j,</bold> Boxplot of average methylation in bivalent enhancers (EnhBiv) across JMML epitypes. <bold>k,l,</bold> Genomic Regions Enrichment of Annotations Tool (GREAT)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R113">5</xref></sup> analysis for gene ontology analysis of (K.) biological processes (GO_bp) and (L.) murine phenotypes. <bold>m,</bold> Locus line plot of DNA methylation at the RUNX1 locus across JMML patients. Smoothed DNA methylation; ‘DMR’ indicates HM vs. non-HM JMML DMRs. <bold>n,</bold> Bar plot depicting the logarithmic fold change of the number of homeobox genes associated to HM vs. non-HM DMRs relative to the genome-wide abundance. Homeobox gene classes were stratified as previously published<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R114">6</xref></sup>: ANTP, <italic>Antennapedia</italic> (incl. HOXL and NKL genes); PRD, <italic>paired</italic> (incl. PAX and PAXL genes); Misc incl. LIM, POU, HNF, SINE, CUT, PROS, ZF, CERS class genes. <bold>o,</bold> Bubble plot of the genome-wide analysis of enriched motifs across DMRs using Hypergeometric Optimization of Motif EnRichment (HOMER) to summarize the enrichment of TF binding motifs across HM vs non-HM DMRs.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS190504-f013"/></fig><fig id="F14" position="anchor"><label>Extended Data Figure 8</label><caption><title>scRNA-seq data analysis of Lin<sup>-</sup>CD34<sup>+</sup>CD38<sup>lo/-</sup> HSPCs from primary JMML patient samples.</title><p id="P122"><bold>a,</bold> Projection of scRNA-seq data of 20,163 Lin<sup>-</sup> CD34<sup>+</sup>CD38<sup>lo/-</sup> enriched HSPCs onto the UMAP from <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1.B</xref> (total hematopoiesis, small light grey dots). Additionally sequenced JMML HSPCs are represented as larger dots (CD34<sup>+</sup> HSC in black and others in grey). <bold>b,c,</bold> Density plots of single-cell transcription scores of transcriptionally defined JMML HSCs (CD34<sup>+</sup> HSC) stratified by JMML epitype. <bold>b,</bold> Megakaryocytic/erythroid (Mk/Ery) vs. lympho/myeloid priming. These gene signatures reflect the first branching point in lineage commitment of human HSCs according to Pellin et al. (2019)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R115">7</xref></sup>. <bold>c,</bold> Transcription scores for clinically aggressive JMML (AML-like JMML) as defined by Bresolin et al. (2010)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R116">8</xref></sup> and leukemia stem cell programs (17-gene LSC) as defined by Ng et al. (2016)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R117">9</xref></sup>. <bold>d,</bold> Heatmap of 255 differentially expressed genes (DEGs) identified between CD34<sup>+</sup> HSCs from HM and non-HM JMML patients. Depicted are normalized average expression levels aggregated across all HSCs within each of the patients. <bold>e,f,</bold> Bubble plots summarizing the top 25 significant terms of functional enrichment analysis of HM vs non-HM DEGs using Metascape<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R118">10</xref></sup>. Data was stratified by upregulated genes in HM or non-HM HSCs, respectively. Bubble size represents percentage of genes in GO and color the enrichment per term. <bold>g,</bold> Re-analysis of neonatal blood spot genotyping by Behnert et al. (2022)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R119">11</xref></sup>. The frequency of RAS driver mutations in neonatal blood spots of individuals that developed JMML later in life is stratified by JMML epitype. Each square represents a single patient, dark dots represent RAS-positive blood spots and unfilled squares RAS-negative cases. <bold>h,</bold> Referencebased cell type similarity analysis (logistic regression) of JMML HSCs to a reference map of 116 hematopoietic reference cell types across developmental stages (rows). Values above 0.5 (pink) and below 0.5 (grey) refer to similarity and dissimilarity, respectively, to the reference cell type; 0.5 represents randomness (white). Left panel shows the entire results. Right panel shows a zoom into the top part or the heatmap which includes the references with positive similarity values. Row labeling refers to the reference stage (Ref: FET, fetal; NEO, neonatal; JUV, juvenile; ADU, adult) and the cell type, respectively. Reference cell types shown in the main <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">figure 3b</xref> are marked by black boxes. <bold>i.</bold> Dot plot of manually curated HSC marker from pre- and postnatal references. The gene list is manually curated based on previously published data<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R110">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R115">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R120">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R121">13</xref></sup>. Average expression is scaled per gene. Dot sizes represent the percentage of cells expressing the corresponding gene.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS190504-f014"/></fig><fig id="F15" position="anchor"><label>Extended Data Figure 9</label><caption><title>Ultra-low input whole-genome bisulfite sequencing data analysis of Lin<sup>-</sup>CD34<sup>+</sup>CD38<sup>lo/-</sup> HSPCs from primary JMML patient samples in the context of normal HSC development.</title><p id="P123">Ultra-low input WGBS analysis of normal and JMML HSCs from primary samples. FET corresponds to both fetal spleen (FES) and fetal liver (FEL) samples. NEO is neonatal blood. JUV and ADU are juvenile and adult bone marrow. <bold>a,</bold> Principal component analysis (PCA) of the 10k most-variable CpGs (mvCpGs) across the entire WGBS dataset including reference and JMML HSCs. Low-risk HSCs cluster with postnatal HSCs. <bold>b,c,</bold> Methylation-based phylogenetic relationships between JMML and healthy reference HSCs across development using WGBS data. <bold>b.</bold> Phylogenetic tree analysis of healthy HSCs based on genomic regions defined in 3.F. Selected methylation dynamics reflect the expected order of normal HSC development. <bold>c,</bold> Heatmap showing the distances of samples in the phylogenetic tree. Manhatten distances were calculated based on the branch length per subgroup. <bold>d,e,</bold> ‘Epigenetic scars’ across normal and malignant HSCs. Epigenetic scars are per definition DNA methylation changes that occur at a single step during development but do not change downstream of this event. ‘Hypo’ and ‘hyper’ correspond to scars whose methylation de- or increase during developmental state transition. <bold>d,</bold> Schematic of epigenetic scars of the transition between fetal and postnatal stages <bold>e,</bold> Heatmap showing methylation beta values of epigenetic scars from the transition of fetal to postnatal HSCs. Hypo: loss of DNA methylation; hyper: gain of DNA methylation.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS190504-f015"/></fig><fig id="F16" position="anchor"><label>Extended Data Figure 10</label><caption><title>HSC-specific <italic>Ptpn11<sup>E76K/+</sup></italic> JMML mouse model recapitulates human disease.</title><p id="P124"><bold>a</bold>, Recombination efficacy of the loxP-flanked PGK-Neo cassette in HSCs. <italic>Ptpn11<sup>E76K/+</sup> Scl</italic>-CreER<sup>T</sup> mice were injected at the age of 6 weeks on 5 consecutive days with tamoxifen and recombination of the loxP-flanked PGK-Neo cassette was analyzed after 72h in HSCs by PCR. <bold>b-c</bold>, Differential blood counts in <italic>Ptpn11<sup>E76K/+</sup> Scl</italic>-CreER<sup>T</sup> mice (E76K, n = 29) and <italic>Ptpn11<sup>+/+</sup> Scl</italic>-CreER<sup>T</sup> controls (Ctrl, n = 23). The results for hemoglobin levels (Hb; <bold>b</bold>) and mean platelet volume (MPV; <bold>c</bold>) are shown over a time course of 9 months. Mean and SEM are depicted. Statistical significances was determined using Student’s t-test. <bold>d</bold>, Disease phenotype in moribund E76K mice (n = 20). <bold>e</bold>, Flow cytometry measurement of bone marrow cells from a control mouse and a E76K mouse with MPN. The percentage of cells in each gate is depicted. Axis labels indicate the respective surface markers and fluorophores. <bold>f</bold>, Expression of hematopoietic marker genes in scRNA-seq. The scaled expression of the top 5 marker genes for each of the 29 clusters identified in the scRNA-seq data is depicted as a heatmap. Each cluster was downsampled to 25 cells for visualization. Cluster-specific marker genes were empirically selected and labeled. <bold>g-h</bold>, Hematopoietic stem and progenitor compartment remodeling in E76K (n = 15) and Ctrl (n = 18) mice 18-weeks after tamoxifen induction. HSPC frequencies were determined using flow cytometry and are plotted as frequencies of LSK cells (<bold>g</bold>) and singlets (<bold>h</bold>). Whiskers are defined as 1.5 times interquartile range. Statistical significance was calculated using Student’s t-test. <bold>i</bold>, UMAP embedding showing cells from the monocytic differentiation lineage and the calculated monocytic pseudotime. <bold>j-k,</bold> Density plots display the distribution of 3000 randomly selected bone marrow cells from E76K and Ctrl mice along the monocytic pseudotime. The distribution is colored by cell type (<bold>j</bold>) or genotype (<bold>k</bold>), respectively. The annotated cell types are visualized as bars below the density curve per genotype (<bold>k</bold>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS190504-f016"/></fig><fig id="F17" position="anchor"><label>Extended Data Figure 11</label><caption><title>Integrative analysis of methylation and transcription changes in JMML HSCs reveals novel prognostic biomarkers and therapeutic targets including CD52.</title><p id="P125"><bold>a-b,</bold> DMR-DEG associations to determine genes which subgroup-specific expression that can be explained by differential methylation. HM vs non-HM DMRs were associated with HM vs non-HM DEGs applying a generalized linear model with stepwise feature elimination using AIC. Per DEG, DMRs in a region 100 kb up- and downstream of the TSS were considered for potential associations. <bold>a,</bold> GLM results including all genes of which expression changes are associated with methylation changes across subgroups. Lower ranked MAE values represent genes that better fit the model. Pearson correlation between prediction and observation was used to calculate the confidence of the DMR-DEG associations. All genes above 0.9 were considered as candidates for further analysis. <bold>b,</bold> Amount of surface markers across gene sets reveals an enrichment of differentially expressed surface markers in JMML stem cells. As a reference, the previously published in silico human surfaceome was used<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R122">14</xref></sup>. ‘DEG’ are all HM vs. nonHM DEGs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2.I</xref>), ‘DMR_DEG’ are genes that were identified in glm analysis. <bold>c,</bold> Dot plot summarizing the scaled normalized expression of all DMR-associated high-confidence candidate surface marker genes in JMML and healthy reference HSCs. Circle size represents the percentage of cells expressing the gene. <bold>d,</bold> Violin plot of normalized singlecell RNA-seq expression of Cd52 in murine HSCs of <italic>Ptpn11<sup>+/+</sup></italic> and <italic>Ptpn11<sup>E76K</sup></italic> mice.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS190504-f017"/></fig><fig id="F18" position="anchor"><label>Extended Data Figure 12</label><caption><title>Anti-CD52 (Alemtuzumab) treatment depletes total hematopoiesis and disrupts disease-propagation in JMML patient-derived xenografts (PDX).</title><p id="P126"><bold>a,</bold> Schematic of anti-CD52 (Alemtuzumab) treatment of JMML PDX. Created with BioRender.com <bold>b,</bold> FACS plots showing CD52 expression in different organs in anti-CD52 treated (alemtuzumab, green) and untreated (Control, black) mice. <bold>c-h,</bold> Logarithmic scale of absolute cell number per pair of femora of human CD45<sup>+</sup> cells in treated vs. untreated mice. <bold>c,</bold> Total human CD45<sup>+</sup> cells stratified by CD52 expression. <bold>d-h,</bold> Different hematopoietic lineages based on classical cell type surface marker expression: <bold>(d)</bold> monocytes and blasts; <bold>(e)</bold> myeloid precursors; <bold>(f)</bold> neutrophils; <bold>(g)</bold> B cells; <bold>(h)</bold> erythrocytes. <bold>i,</bold> Gating scheme for immunophenotypic characterization of PDX mice.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS190504-f018"/></fig></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="SM"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1"><label>Supplementary Figures</label><media xlink:href="EMS190504-supplement-Supplementary_Figures.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" id="d9aAdFbB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD2"><label>Supplementary Tables</label><media xlink:href="EMS190504-supplement-Supplementary_Tables.xlsx" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.spreadsheetml.sheet" id="d9aAdFcB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack id="S54"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank the patients and their families and the EWOG-MDS study group for supporting our research. We also thank the NGS Core Facility, the Omics IT and Data Management Core Facility, the Flow Cytometry Core Facility and the Center for Preclinical Research, German Cancer Research Center (DKFZ), for providing excellent services. Emely Kleinert and Oliver Mücke provided excellent technical support. The Ptpn11 E76K neo/+ mouse was kindly shared by Dr. Cheng-Kui Qu, Department of Pediatrics, Aflac Cancer and Blood Disorders Center, Emory University, Atlanta, GA, USA. We thank all the members of the Division of Translational Medical Oncology, the Division of Applied Functional Genomics, Oliver Stegle, Stephen J. Clark and Wolf Reik for many fruitful discussions. This work was in part funded by Wellcome Trust (personal fellowship to S.B., institutional grant to the Wellcome Sanger Institute; references 220540/Z/20/A and 223135/Z/21/Z), by DFG (Emmy Noether RA 3166/1) to S.R., by the DKFZ International PhD Program and the German-Israeli Helmholtz International Research School “Cancer-TRAX” to M.Hakobyan, by NCT Molecular Precision Oncology Program to S.F., and by grants from the “Deutsche José Carreras Leukämie-Stiftung” (DJCLS 14R/2022) to M.M. and D.B.L. and from the “Wilhelm Sander-Stiftung” (# 2022.010.1) to D.B.L. This submission is part of the 2023 HCA Publication Package (HCA-105).</p></ack><sec id="S55" sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p id="P150">
<table-wrap id="T1" orientation="portrait" position="anchor"><table frame="void" rules="cols"><thead><tr style="background-color:#E7E6E6; border-bottom:solid thin;"><th valign="bottom" align="left">Data</th><th valign="bottom" align="left">Source</th><th style="border-right:hidden;" valign="bottom" align="left">Reference</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="bottom" align="left">JMML_scRNA-seq</td><td valign="bottom" align="left">EGAS00001007357</td><td style="border-right:hidden;" valign="bottom" align="left">this study</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">FET_scRNA-seq</td><td valign="top" align="left">Human Cell Atlas</td><td style="border-right:hidden;" valign="top" align="left">Popescu et al. (2019)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R68">68</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left">NEO_scRNA-seq</td><td valign="middle" align="left">Human Cell Atlas</td><td style="border-right:hidden;" valign="bottom" align="left"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://data.humancellatlas.org/explore/projects/cc95ff89-2e68-4a08-a234-480eca21ce79">https://data.humancellatlas.org/explore/projects/cc95ff89-2e68-4a08-a234-480eca21ce79</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left">JUV_scRNA-seq</td><td valign="bottom" align="left">HTA4_31 &amp; HTA4_32</td><td style="border-right:hidden;" valign="middle" align="left">this study</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">ADU_scRNA-seq</td><td valign="top" align="left">Human Cell Atlas</td><td style="border-right:hidden;" valign="top" align="left">Hay et al. (2018)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R66">66</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" align="left">JMML_EPIC</td><td valign="bottom" align="left">EGAS00001007357</td><td style="border-right:hidden;" valign="bottom" align="left">this study</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" align="left">JMML_WGBS</td><td valign="bottom" align="left">EGAS00001007357</td><td style="border-right:hidden;" valign="bottom" align="left">this study</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" align="left">FET_WGBS</td><td valign="bottom" align="left">EGAS00001007357</td><td style="border-right:hidden;" valign="bottom" align="left">this study</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" align="left">NEO_WGBS</td><td valign="bottom" align="left">EGAS00001007357</td><td style="border-right:hidden;" valign="bottom" align="left">Maag, Toth et al. (in preparation)</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" align="left">JUV_WGBS</td><td valign="bottom" align="left">EGAS00001007357</td><td style="border-right:hidden;" valign="bottom" align="left">this study</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" align="left">ADU_WGBS</td><td valign="bottom" align="left">EGAS00001007357</td><td style="border-right:hidden;" valign="bottom" align="left">this study</td></tr><tr><td valign="bottom" align="left">Ptpn11-E76K_scRNA-seq</td><td valign="middle" align="left">GEO: GSE240460</td><td style="border-right:hidden;" valign="middle" align="left">this study</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
    </p></sec><sec id="S56" sec-type="data-availability"><title>Code availability</title><p id="P127">WGBS and scRNA-seq data were processed and analyzed using publicly available software packages as specified in the corresponding methods sections. R code is available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/maurerv/jmml_oncofetal_reprogramming">https://github.com/maurerv/jmml_oncofetal_reprogramming</ext-link>.</p></sec><fn-group><fn fn-type="con" id="FN4"><p id="P128"><bold>Contributions</bold></p><p id="P129"><list list-type="simple" id="L5"><label>▪</label><list-item><p id="P130">M.H., M.S. and D.B.L. conceived the study, designed experiments and coordinated the project.</p></list-item><list-item><label>▪</label><p id="P131">R.R., K.M.B., T.B., S.R., S.H., C.B., L.J., M.Haniffa., C.M.N., C.F. and M.E. collected patient and/or healthy reference samples.</p></list-item><list-item><label>▪</label><p id="P132">M.S. established the Ptpn11<sup>E76K</sup> mouse model and performed mouse experiments under supervision of D.B.L.</p></list-item><list-item><label>▪</label><p id="P133">M.H., M.S., K.B., J.P.M., J.R., M.Hakobyan, S.S., J.L., K.M.B., F.A., L.J., S.B., D.V., A.H.M., S.H., D.L. performed experiments.</p></list-item><list-item><label>▪</label><p id="P134">M.H., M.S., V.M., L.H., J.H., E.K., K.T., C.C., V.F. performed bioinformatic analyses.</p></list-item><list-item><label>▪</label><p id="P135">M.J.B., J.H., M.Schlesner and D.B.L. supervised bioinformatic analyses.</p></list-item><list-item><label>▪</label><p id="P136">J.R. and M.E. designed and J.R. performed the PDX experiments.</p></list-item><list-item><label>▪</label><p id="P137">M.H., M.S., J.R., V.M., L.H., J.H., P.L., M.D.M., S.H., S.Behjati, M.J.B., S.F., C.M.N., C.F., C.P., M.E., M.Schlesner and D.B.L. interpreted the data.</p></list-item><list-item><label>▪</label><p id="P138">D.B.L. acquired funding and supervised the project.</p></list-item><list-item><label>▪</label><p id="P139">M.H., M.S., and D.B.L. wrote the manuscript.</p></list-item></list></p><p id="P140">All authors read, edited and approved the manuscript.</p></fn><fn id="FN5" fn-type="conflict"><p id="P141"><bold>Ethics declarations – competing interests</bold></p><p id="P142">A patent application has been filed by M.H., M.E. and D.B.L. based on the data described in this study. D.B.L. works as a drug safety physician for Infectopharm. J.H. is working as a consultant for CytoReason.</p><p id="P143">All other authors declare no competing interests.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><ref id="R1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bleriot</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Currenti</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ginhoux</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Oncofetal reprogramming in tumour development and progression</article-title><source>Nat Rev Cancer</source><year>2022</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>593</fpage><lpage>602</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35999292</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gale</surname><given-names>KB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Backtracking leukemia to birth: identification of clonotypic gene fusion sequences in neonatal blood spots</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>1997</year><volume>94</volume><fpage>13950</fpage><lpage>13954</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC28413</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9391133</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.94.25.13950</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coorens</surname><given-names>THH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Embryonal precursors of Wilms tumor</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2019</year><volume>366</volume><fpage>1247</fpage><lpage>1251</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6914378</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31806814</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.aax1323</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khabirova</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Single-cell transcriptomics reveals a distinct developmental state of KMT2A-rearranged infant B-cell acute lymphoblastic leukemia</article-title><source>Nat Med</source><year>2022</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>743</fpage><lpage>751</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9018413</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35288693</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41591-022-01720-7</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Single-cell transcriptomes from human kidneys reveal the cellular identity of renal tumors</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2018</year><volume>361</volume><fpage>594</fpage><lpage>599</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6104812</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30093597</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.aat1699</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jessa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Stalled developmental programs at the root of pediatric brain tumors</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><year>2019</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>1702</fpage><lpage>1713</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6885128</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31768071</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41588-019-0531-7</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bala</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Aberrant cell state plasticity mediated by developmental reprogramming precedes colorectal cancer initiation</article-title><source>Sci Adv</source><year>2023</year><volume>9</volume><elocation-id>eadf0927</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10058311</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36989360</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/sciadv.adf0927</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pomerantz</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Prostate cancer reactivates developmental epigenomic programs during metastatic progression</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><year>2020</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>790</fpage><lpage>799</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10007911</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32690948</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41588-020-0664-8</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Onco-fetal Reprogramming of Endothelial Cells Drives Immunosuppressive Macrophages in Hepatocellular Carcinoma</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2020</year><volume>183</volume><fpage>377</fpage><lpage>394</lpage><elocation-id>e321</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32976798</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sole</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>p53 wild-type colorectal cancer cells that express a fetal gene signature are associated with metastasis and poor prognosis</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2022</year><volume>13</volume><elocation-id>2866</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9126967</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35606354</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-022-30382-9</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Behjati</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gilbertson</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Pfister</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Maturation Block in Childhood Cancer</article-title><source>Cancer Discov</source><year>2021</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>542</fpage><lpage>544</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33589423</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rudelius</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Weinberg</surname><given-names>OK</given-names></name><name><surname>Niemeyer</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Shimamura</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Calvo</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The International Consensus Classification (ICC) of hematologic neoplasms with germline predisposition, pediatric myelodysplastic syndrome, and juvenile myelomonocytic leukemia</article-title><source>Virchows Arch</source><year>2023</year><volume>482</volume><fpage>113</fpage><lpage>130</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36445482</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lipka</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>RAS-pathway mutation patterns define epigenetic subclasses in juvenile myelomonocytic leukemia</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2017</year><volume>8</volume><elocation-id>2126</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5736667</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29259247</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-017-02177-w</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stieglitz</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genome-wide DNA methylation is predictive of outcome in juvenile myelomonocytic leukemia</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2017</year><volume>8</volume><elocation-id>2127</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5736624</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29259179</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-017-02178-9</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Murakami</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Integrated molecular profiling of juvenile myelomonocytic leukemia</article-title><source>Blood</source><year>2018</year><volume>131</volume><fpage>1576</fpage><lpage>1586</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29437595</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schönung</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>International Consensus Definition of DNA Methylation Subgroups in Juvenile Myelomonocytic Leukemia</article-title><source>Clin Cancer Res</source><year>2021</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>158</fpage><lpage>168</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7785676</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33139265</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1158/1078-0432.CCR-20-3184</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Niemeyer</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Flotho</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Juvenile myelomonocytic leukemia: who’s the driver at the wheel?</article-title><source>Blood</source><year>2019</year><volume>133</volume><fpage>1060</fpage><lpage>1070</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30670449</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Helsmoortel</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>LIN28B overexpression defines a novel fetal-like subgroup of juvenile myelomonocytic leukemia</article-title><source>Blood</source><year>2016</year><volume>127</volume><fpage>1163</fpage><lpage>1172</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26712910</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Strullu</surname><given-names>Marion</given-names></name><name><surname>Aurélie Caye-Eude</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Maillard</surname><given-names>Loïc</given-names></name><name><surname>Lainey</surname><given-names>Elodie</given-names></name><name><surname>Piques</surname><given-names>Florian</given-names></name><name><surname>Fenneteau</surname><given-names>Odile</given-names></name><name><surname>Bruno</surname><given-names>Cassinat</given-names></name><name><surname>Fabien</surname><given-names>Guimiot</given-names></name><name><surname>Dalle</surname><given-names>Jean-Hugues</given-names></name><name><surname>Baruchel</surname><given-names>André</given-names></name><name><surname>Chomienne</surname><given-names>Christine</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonnet</surname><given-names>Dominique</given-names></name><name><surname>Souyri</surname><given-names>Michele</given-names></name><name><surname>Cave</surname><given-names>Helene</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Two Distinct Fetal-Type Signatures Caracterise Juvenile Myelomonocytic Leukemia</article-title><source>Research Square</source><year>2022</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21203/rs.3.rs-1416605/v1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Matsuda</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Quantitative assessment of PTPN11 or RAS mutations at the neonatal period and during the clinical course in patients with juvenile myelomonocytic leukaemia</article-title><source>Br J Haematol</source><year>2010</year><volume>148</volume><fpage>593</fpage><lpage>599</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19874312</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Behnert</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Exploring the genetic and epigenetic origins of juvenile myelomonocytic leukemia using newborn screening samples</article-title><source>Leukemia</source><year>2022</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>279</fpage><lpage>282</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8720242</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34183765</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41375-021-01331-0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Louka</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Heterogeneous disease-propagating stem cells in juvenile myelomonocytic leukemia</article-title><source>J Exp Med</source><year>2021</year><volume>218</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7802370</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33416891</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1084/jem.20180853</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Caye</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Despite mutation acquisition in hematopoietic stem cells, JMML-propagating cells are not always restricted to this compartment</article-title><source>Leukemia</source><year>2020</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>1658</fpage><lpage>1668</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7266742</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31776464</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41375-019-0662-y</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Farlik</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>DNA Methylation Dynamics of Human Hematopoietic Stem Cell Differentiation</article-title><source>Cell Stem Cell</source><year>2016</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>808</fpage><lpage>822</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5145815</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27867036</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.stem.2016.10.019</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Espin-Palazon</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Proinflammatory signaling regulates hematopoietic stem cell emergence</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2014</year><volume>159</volume><fpage>1070</fpage><lpage>1085</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4243083</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25416946</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2014.10.031</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Loyfer</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A DNA methylation atlas of normal human cell types</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2023</year><volume>613</volume><fpage>355</fpage><lpage>364</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9811898</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36599988</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41586-022-05580-6</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Single-Cell Analysis of Neonatal HSC Ontogeny Reveals Gradual and Uncoordinated Transcriptional Reprogramming that Begins before Birth</article-title><source>Cell Stem Cell</source><year>2020</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>732</fpage><lpage>747</lpage><elocation-id>e737</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7655695</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32822583</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.stem.2020.08.001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bausch-Fluck</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The in silico human surfaceome</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2018</year><volume>115</volume><fpage>E10988</fpage><lpage>E10997</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6243280</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30373828</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1808790115</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Osterborg</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Humanized CD52 monoclonal antibody Campath-1H as first-line treatment in chronic lymphocytic leukaemia</article-title><source>Br J Haematol</source><year>1996</year><volume>93</volume><fpage>151</fpage><lpage>153</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8611450</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moreau</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Preliminary evidence from magnetic resonance imaging for reduction in disease activity after lymphocyte depletion in multiple sclerosis</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>1994</year><volume>344</volume><fpage>298</fpage><lpage>301</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7914262</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coles</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Alemtuzumab for patients with relapsing multiple sclerosis after disease-modifying therapy: a randomised controlled phase 3 trial</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>2012</year><volume>380</volume><fpage>1829</fpage><lpage>1839</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23122650</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krombholz</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Long-term serial xenotransplantation of juvenile myelomonocytic leukemia recapitulates human disease in Rag2-/-gammac-/- mice</article-title><source>Haematologica</source><year>2016</year><volume>101</volume><fpage>597</fpage><lpage>606</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5004370</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26888021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3324/haematol.2015.138545</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldman</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name><name><surname>Ravetch</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name><name><surname>Waldmann</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effective therapy for a murine model of adult T-cell leukemia with the humanized anti-CD52 monoclonal antibody, Campath-1H</article-title><source>Cancer Res</source><year>2003</year><volume>63</volume><fpage>6453</fpage><lpage>6457</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14559836</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ford</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>In utero rearrangements in the trithorax-related oncogene in infant leukaemias</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1993</year><volume>363</volume><fpage>358</fpage><lpage>360</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8497319</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>GATA1-mutant clones are frequent and often unsuspected in babies with Down syndrome: identification of a population at risk of leukemia</article-title><source>Blood</source><year>2013</year><volume>122</volume><fpage>3908</fpage><lpage>3917</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3995281</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24021668</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1182/blood-2013-07-515148</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Clonal dynamics of haematopoiesis across the human lifespan</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2022</year><volume>606</volume><fpage>343</fpage><lpage>350</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9177428</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35650442</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41586-022-04786-y</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Korber</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Neuroblastoma arises in early fetal development and its evolutionary duration predicts outcome</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><year>2023</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>619</fpage><lpage>630</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10101850</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36973454</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41588-023-01332-y</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Klusmann</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Developmental stage-specific interplay of GATA1 and IGF signaling in fetal megakaryopoiesis and leukemogenesis</article-title><source>Genes Dev</source><year>2010</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>1659</fpage><lpage>1672</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2912563</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20679399</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gad.1903410</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grimm</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Heckl</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Klusmann</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular Mechanisms of the Genetic Predisposition to Acute Megakaryoblastic Leukemia in Infants With Down Syndrome</article-title><source>Front Oncol</source><year>2021</year><volume>11</volume><elocation-id>636633</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7992977</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33777792</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fonc.2021.636633</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jansky</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Single-cell transcriptomic analyses provide insights into the developmental origins of neuroblastoma</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><year>2021</year><volume>53</volume><fpage>683</fpage><lpage>693</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33767450</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R41"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kildisiute</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Tumor to normal single-cell mRNA comparisons reveal a pan-neuroblastoma cancer cell</article-title><source>Sci Adv</source><year>2021</year><volume>7</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7864567</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33547074</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/sciadv.abd3311</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R42"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vladoiu</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Childhood cerebellar tumours mirror conserved fetal transcriptional programs</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2019</year><volume>572</volume><fpage>67</fpage><lpage>73</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6675628</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31043743</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41586-019-1158-7</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R43"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Human fetal cerebellar cell atlas informs medulloblastoma origin and oncogenesis</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2022</year><volume>612</volume><fpage>787</fpage><lpage>794</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36450980</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R44"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Capper</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>DNA methylation-based classification of central nervous system tumours</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2018</year><volume>555</volume><fpage>469</fpage><lpage>474</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6093218</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29539639</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature26000</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R45"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oakes</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>DNA methylation dynamics during B cell maturation underlie a continuum of disease phenotypes in chronic lymphocytic leukemia</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><year>2016</year><volume>48</volume><fpage>253</fpage><lpage>264</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4963005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26780610</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng.3488</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R46"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kulis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Whole-genome fingerprint of the DNA methylome during human B cell differentiation</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><year>2015</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>746</fpage><lpage>756</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5444519</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26053498</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng.3291</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R47"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sill</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Plass</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Pfister</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lipka</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular tumor classification using DNA methylome analysis</article-title><source>Hum Mol Genet</source><year>2020</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>R205</fpage><lpage>R213</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32657331</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R48"><label>48</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hoadley</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cell-of-Origin Patterns Dominate the Molecular Classification of 10,000 Tumors from 33 Types of Cancer</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2018</year><volume>173</volume><fpage>291</fpage><lpage>304</lpage><elocation-id>e296</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5957518</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29625048</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2018.03.022</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R49"><label>49</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Orlando</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Chemical genomics reveals targetable programs of human cancers rooted in pluripotency</article-title><source>Cell Chem Biol</source><year>2023</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>780</fpage><lpage>794</lpage><elocation-id>e788</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37379846</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R50"><label>50</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beerman</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Proliferation-dependent alterations of the DNA methylation landscape underlie hematopoietic stem cell aging</article-title><source>Cell Stem Cell</source><year>2013</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>413</fpage><lpage>425</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23415915</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R51"><label>51</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Correlation of an epigenetic mitotic clock with cancer risk</article-title><source>Genome Biol</source><year>2016</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>205</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5046977</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27716309</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13059-016-1064-3</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R52"><label>52</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roels</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Aging of preleukemic thymocytes drives CpG island hypermethylation in T-cell acute lymphoblastic leukemia</article-title><source>Blood Cancer Discov</source><year>2020</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>274</fpage><lpage>289</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7116343</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33179015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1158/2643-3230.BCD-20-0059</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R53"><label>53</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hazelton</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name><name><surname>Luebeck</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name><name><surname>Grady</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Epigenetic Aging: More Than Just a Clock When It Comes to Cancer</article-title><source>Cancer Res</source><year>2020</year><volume>80</volume><fpage>367</fpage><lpage>374</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7002254</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31694907</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-19-0924</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R54"><label>54</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Calvanese</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Mapping human haematopoietic stem cells from haemogenic endothelium to birth</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2022</year><volume>604</volume><fpage>534</fpage><lpage>540</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9645817</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35418685</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41586-022-04571-x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R55"><label>55</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Transitions in lineage specification and gene regulatory networks in hematopoietic stem/progenitor cells over human development</article-title><source>Cell Rep</source><year>2021</year><volume>36</volume><elocation-id>109698</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8456780</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34525349</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.celrep.2021.109698</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R56"><label>56</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Temporal molecular program of human hematopoietic stem and progenitor cells after birth</article-title><source>Dev Cell</source><year>2022</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>2745</fpage><lpage>2760</lpage><elocation-id>e2746</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36493772</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R57"><label>57</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pellin</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A comprehensive single cell transcriptional landscape of human hematopoietic progenitors</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2019</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>2395</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6546699</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31160568</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-019-10291-0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R58"><label>58</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dyer</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hale</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayhoe</surname><given-names>FG</given-names></name><name><surname>Waldmann</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of CAMPATH-1 antibodies in vivo in patients with lymphoid malignancies: influence of antibody isotype</article-title><source>Blood</source><year>1989</year><volume>73</volume><fpage>1431</fpage><lpage>1439</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2713487</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R59"><label>59</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coles</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Monoclonal antibody treatment exposes three mechanisms underlying the clinical course of multiple sclerosis</article-title><source>Ann Neurol</source><year>1999</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>296</fpage><lpage>304</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10482259</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R60"><label>60</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kottaridis</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>In vivo CAMPATH-1H prevents graft-versus-host disease following nonmyeloablative stem cell transplantation</article-title><source>Blood</source><year>2000</year><volume>96</volume><fpage>2419</fpage><lpage>2425</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11001893</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R61"><label>61</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Faulkner</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>BEAM-alemtuzumab reduced-intensity allogeneic stem cell transplantation for lymphoproliferative diseases: GVHD, toxicity, and survival in 65 patients</article-title><source>Blood</source><year>2004</year><volume>103</volume><fpage>428</fpage><lpage>434</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12969983</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R62"><label>62</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Locatelli</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Niemeyer</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>How I treat juvenile myelomonocytic leukemia</article-title><source>Blood</source><year>2015</year><volume>125</volume><fpage>1083</fpage><lpage>1090</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25564399</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R63"><label>63</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jardine</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Blood and immune development in human fetal bone marrow and Down syndrome</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2021</year><volume>598</volume><fpage>327</fpage><lpage>331</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7612688</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34588693</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41586-021-03929-x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R64"><label>64</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Velten</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Human haematopoietic stem cell lineage commitment is a continuous process</article-title><source>Nat Cell Biol</source><year>2017</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>271</fpage><lpage>281</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5496982</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28319093</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncb3493</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R65"><label>65</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Tagmentation-based whole-genome bisulfite sequencing</article-title><source>Nat Protoc</source><year>2013</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>2022</fpage><lpage>2032</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24071908</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R66"><label>66</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hay</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferchen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Chetal</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Grimes</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name><name><surname>Salomonis</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Human Cell Atlas bone marrow single-cell interactive web portal</article-title><source>Exp Hematol</source><year>2018</year><volume>68</volume><fpage>51</fpage><lpage>61</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6296228</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30243574</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.exphem.2018.09.004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R67"><label>67</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stuart</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Comprehensive Integration of Single-Cell Data</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2019</year><volume>177</volume><fpage>1888</fpage><lpage>1902</lpage><elocation-id>e1821</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6687398</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31178118</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2019.05.031</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R68"><label>68</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Popescu</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Decoding human fetal liver haematopoiesis</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2019</year><volume>574</volume><fpage>365</fpage><lpage>371</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6861135</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31597962</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41586-019-1652-y</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R69"><label>69</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hadley</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>ggplot2: Elegant Graphics for Data Analysis</article-title><year>2016</year><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://ggplot2.tidyverse.org">https://ggplot2.tidyverse.org</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="R70"><label>70</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bresolin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Gene expression-based classification as an independent predictor of clinical outcome in juvenile myelomonocytic leukemia</article-title><source>J Clin Oncol</source><year>2010</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>1919</fpage><lpage>1927</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20231685</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R71"><label>71</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A 17-gene stemness score for rapid determination of risk in acute leukaemia</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2016</year><volume>540</volume><fpage>433</fpage><lpage>437</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27926740</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R72"><label>72</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Metascape provides a biologist-oriented resource for the analysis of systems-level datasets</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2019</year><volume>10</volume><elocation-id>1523</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6447622</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30944313</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-019-09234-6</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R73"><label>73</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Eils</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Schlesner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Complex heatmaps reveal patterns and correlations in multidimensional genomic data</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2016</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>2847</fpage><lpage>2849</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27207943</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R74"><label>74</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genome-wide base-resolution mapping of DNA methylation in single cells using single-cell bisulfite sequencing (scBS-seq)</article-title><source>Nat Protoc</source><year>2017</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>534</fpage><lpage>547</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28182018</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R75"><label>75</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hey</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>DNA methylation landscape of tumor-associated macrophages reveals pathways, transcription factors and prognostic value relevant to triple-negative breast cancer patients</article-title><source>Int J Cancer</source><year>2023</year><volume>152</volume><fpage>1226</fpage><lpage>1242</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36408934</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R76"><label>76</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Delacher</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genome-wide DNA-methylation landscape defines specialization of regulatory T cells in tissues</article-title><source>Nat Immunol</source><year>2017</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>1160</fpage><lpage>1172</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5912503</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28783152</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ni.3799</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R77"><label>77</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reisinger</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>OTP: An automatized system for managing and processing NGS data</article-title><source>J Biotechnol</source><year>2017</year><volume>261</volume><fpage>53</fpage><lpage>62</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28803971</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R78"><label>78</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bolger</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lohse</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Usadel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Trimmomatic: a flexible trimmer for Illumina sequence data</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2014</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>2114</fpage><lpage>2120</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4103590</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24695404</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btu170</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R79"><label>79</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Aligning sequence reads, clone sequences and assembly contigs with BWA-MEM</article-title><year>2013</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R80"><label>80</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Institute</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Picard Tools</article-title><source>Broad Institute, GitHub repository version 2.18.2</source><year>2018</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R81"><label>81</label><element-citation publication-type="web"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><source>MethylDackel</source><year>2014</year><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/dpryan79/MethylDackel">https://github.com/dpryan79/MethylDackel</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="R82"><label>82</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>R Core Team, R. F. f. S. C. h. w. R.-p. o</collab><source>R: A Language and Environment for Statistical Computing</source><year>2020</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R83"><label>83</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mayakonda</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Methrix: an R/Bioconductor package for systematic aggregation and analysis of bisulfite sequencing data</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2021</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>5524</fpage><lpage>5525</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33346800</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R84"><label>84</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><source>BSgenome.Hsapiens.UCSC.hg19: Full genome sequences for Homo sapiens (UCSC version hg19, based on GRCh37.p13)</source><year>2020</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R85"><label>85</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name><name><surname>Langmead</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Irizarry</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>BSmooth: from whole genome bisulfite sequencing reads to differentially methylated regions</article-title><source>Genome Biol</source><year>2012</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>R83</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3491411</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23034175</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/gb-2012-13-10-r83</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R86"><label>86</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Muller</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>RnBeads 2.0: comprehensive analysis of DNA methylation data</article-title><source>Genome Biol</source><year>2019</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>55</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6419383</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30871603</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13059-019-1664-9</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R87"><label>87</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lawrence</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gentleman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Carey</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>rtracklayer: an R package for interfacing with genome browsers</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2009</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>1841</fpage><lpage>1842</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2705236</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19468054</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btp328</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R88"><label>88</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Differential methylation analysis for BS-seq data under general experimental design</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2016</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>1446</fpage><lpage>1453</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26819470</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R89"><label>89</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>QY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>ChIPseeker: an R/Bioconductor package for ChIP peak annotation, comparison and visualization</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2015</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>2382</fpage><lpage>2383</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25765347</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R90"><label>90</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>Team BC</collab><article-title>TxDb.Mmusculus.UCSC.mm10.knownGene: Annotation package for TxDb object(s)</article-title><source>R package version 3.4.7. bioconductor</source><year>2019</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R91"><label>91</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kolde</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><source>Pheatmap.cran</source><year>2019</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R92"><label>92</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heinz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Simple combinations of lineage-determining transcription factors prime cis-regulatory elements required for macrophage and B cell identities</article-title><source>Mol Cell</source><year>2010</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>576</fpage><lpage>589</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2898526</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20513432</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molcel.2010.05.004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R93"><label>93</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sheffield</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name><name><surname>Bock</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>LOLA: enrichment analysis for genomic region sets and regulatory elements in R and Bioconductor</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2016</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>587</fpage><lpage>589</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4743627</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26508757</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btv612</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R94"><label>94</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roadmap Epigenomics</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Integrative analysis of 111 reference human epigenomes</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2015</year><volume>518</volume><fpage>317</fpage><lpage>330</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4530010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25693563</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature14248</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R95"><label>95</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hahne</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Ivanek</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Visualizing Genomic Data Using Gviz and Bioconductor</article-title><source>Methods Mol Biol</source><year>2016</year><volume>1418</volume><fpage>335</fpage><lpage>351</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27008022</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R96"><label>96</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Holland</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name><name><surname>Booth</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bruford</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Classification and nomenclature of all human homeobox genes</article-title><source>BMC Biol</source><year>2007</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>47</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2211742</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17963489</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1741-7007-5-47</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R97"><label>97</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Paradis</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Schliep</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>ape 5.0: an environment for modern phylogenetics and evolutionary analyses in R</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2019</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>526</fpage><lpage>528</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30016406</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R98"><label>98</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abdel-Hakeem</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Epigenetic scarring of exhausted T cells hinders memory differentiation upon eliminating chronic antigenic stimulation</article-title><source>Nat Immunol</source><year>2021</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>1008</fpage><lpage>1019</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8323971</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34312545</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41590-021-00975-5</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R99"><label>99</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Conneely</surname><given-names>KN</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A Bayesian hierarchical model to detect differentially methylated loci from single nucleotide resolution sequencing data</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2014</year><volume>42</volume><elocation-id>e69</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4005660</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24561809</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gku154</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R100"><label>100</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gothert</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>In vivo fate-tracing studies using the Scl stem cell enhancer: embryonic hematopoietic stem cells significantly contribute to adult hematopoiesis</article-title><source>Blood</source><year>2005</year><volume>105</volume><fpage>2724</fpage><lpage>2732</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15598809</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R101"><label>101</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Non-lineage/stage-restricted effects of a gain-of-function mutation in tyrosine phosphatase Ptpn11 (Shp2) on malignant transformation of hematopoietic cells</article-title><source>J Exp Med</source><year>2011</year><volume>208</volume><fpage>1977</fpage><lpage>1988</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3182060</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21930766</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1084/jem.20110450</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R102"><label>102</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schönung</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Dynamic DNA methylation reveals novel cis-regulatory elements in mouse hematopoiesis</article-title><source>Exp Hematol</source><year>2023</year><volume>117</volume><fpage>24</fpage><lpage>42</lpage><elocation-id>e27</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36368558</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R103"><label>103</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Integrated analysis of multimodal single-cell data</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2021</year><volume>184</volume><fpage>3573</fpage><lpage>3587</lpage><elocation-id>e3529</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8238499</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34062119</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2021.04.048</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R104"><label>104</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McGinnis</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Murrow</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Gartner</surname><given-names>ZJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>DoubletFinder: Doublet Detection in Single-Cell RNA Sequencing Data Using Artificial Nearest Neighbors</article-title><source>Cell Syst</source><year>2019</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>329</fpage><lpage>337</lpage><elocation-id>e324</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6853612</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30954475</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cels.2019.03.003</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R105"><label>105</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Giladi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Single-cell characterization of haematopoietic progenitors and their trajectories in homeostasis and perturbed haematopoiesis</article-title><source>Nat Cell Biol</source><year>2018</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>836</fpage><lpage>846</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29915358</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R106"><label>106</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Paul</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Transcriptional Heterogeneity and Lineage Commitment in Myeloid Progenitors</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2015</year><volume>163</volume><fpage>1663</fpage><lpage>1677</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26627738</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R107"><label>107</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Street</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Slingshot: cell lineage and pseudotime inference for single-cell transcriptomics</article-title><source>BMC Genomics</source><year>2018</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>477</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6007078</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29914354</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12864-018-4772-0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R108"><label>108</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Izzo</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>DNA methylation disruption reshapes the hematopoietic differentiation landscape</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><year>2020</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>378</fpage><lpage>387</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7216752</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32203468</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41588-020-0595-4</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><ref-list><ref id="R109"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schönung</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>International Consensus Definition of DNA Methylation Subgroups in Juvenile Myelomonocytic Leukemia</article-title>
<source>Clin Cancer Res</source>
<year>2021</year>
<volume>27</volume>
<fpage>158</fpage>
<lpage>168</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1158/1078-0432.CCR-20-3184</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R110"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hay</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferchen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Chetal</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Grimes</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name><name><surname>Salomonis</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The Human Cell Atlas bone marrow single-cell interactive web portal</article-title>
<source>Exp Hematol</source>
<year>2018</year>
<volume>68</volume>
<fpage>51</fpage>
<lpage>61</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.exphem.2018.09.004</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R111"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Farlik</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>DNA Methylation Dynamics of Human Hematopoietic Stem Cell Differentiation</article-title>
<source>Cell Stem Cell</source>
<year>2016</year>
<volume>19</volume>
<fpage>808</fpage>
<lpage>822</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.stem.2016.10.019</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R112"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lutsik</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>MeDeCom: discovery and quantification of latent components of heterogeneous methylomes</article-title>
<source>Genome Biol</source>
<year>2017</year>
<volume>18</volume>
<fpage>55</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5366155</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28340624</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13059-017-1182-6</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R113"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McLean</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>GREAT improves functional interpretation of cis-regulatory regions</article-title>
<source>Nat Biotechnol</source>
<year>2010</year>
<volume>28</volume>
<fpage>495</fpage>
<lpage>501</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4840234</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20436461</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nbt.1630</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R114"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Holland</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name><name><surname>Booth</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bruford</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Classification and nomenclature of all human homeobox genes</article-title>
<source>BMC Biol</source>
<year>2007</year>
<volume>5</volume>
<fpage>47</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1741-7007-5-47</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R115"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pellin</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>A comprehensive single cell transcriptional landscape of human hematopoietic progenitors</article-title>
<source>Nat Commun</source>
<year>2019</year>
<volume>10</volume>
<elocation-id>2395</elocation-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-019-10291-0</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R116"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bresolin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Gene expression-based classification as an independent predictor of clinical outcome in juvenile myelomonocytic leukemia</article-title>
<source>J Clin Oncol</source>
<year>2010</year>
<volume>28</volume>
<fpage>1919</fpage>
<lpage>1927</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1200/JCO.2009.24.4426</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R117"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>A 17-gene stemness score for rapid determination of risk in acute leukaemia</article-title>
<source>Nature</source>
<year>2016</year>
<volume>540</volume>
<fpage>433</fpage>
<lpage>437</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature20598</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R118"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Metascape provides a biologist-oriented resource for the analysis of systems-level datasets</article-title>
<source>Nat Commun</source>
<year>2019</year>
<volume>10</volume>
<elocation-id>1523</elocation-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-019-09234-6</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R119"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Behnert</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Exploring the genetic and epigenetic origins of juvenile myelomonocytic leukemia using newborn screening samples</article-title>
<source>Leukemia</source>
<year>2022</year>
<volume>36</volume>
<fpage>279</fpage>
<lpage>282</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41375-021-01331-0</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R120"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lehnertz</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>HLF expression defines the human hematopoietic stem cell state</article-title>
<source>Blood</source>
<year>2021</year>
<volume>138</volume>
<fpage>2642</fpage>
<lpage>2654</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34499717</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R121"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Calvanese</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Mapping human haematopoietic stem cells from haemogenic endothelium to birth</article-title>
<source>Nature</source>
<year>2022</year>
<volume>604</volume>
<fpage>534</fpage>
<lpage>540</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41586-022-04571-x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R122"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bausch-Fluck</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>The in silico human surfaceome</article-title>
<source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
<year>2018</year>
<volume>115</volume>
<fpage>E10988</fpage>
<lpage>E10997</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1808790115</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><boxed-text id="BX1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Highlights</title></caption><p><list list-type="simple" id="L6"><list-item><label>▪</label><p>Epigenomic and transcriptomic landscape of juvenile myelomonocytic leukemia (JMML) in the context of hematopoietic development.</p></list-item><list-item><label>▪</label><p>The presence of fetal transcription signatures in childhood malignancies is not indicative of a developmental maturation block.</p></list-item><list-item><label>▪</label><p>High-risk JMML is characterized by oncofetal reprogramming of postnatal hematopoietic stem cells (HSCs).</p></list-item><list-item><label>▪</label><p>RAS-pathway mutations induce fetal-like gene expression signatures in murine postnatal HSCs.</p></list-item><list-item><label>▪</label><p>The fetal maturation marker CD52 is a novel therapeutic target in high-risk JMML.</p></list-item></list></p></boxed-text><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><title>JMML-related aberrations affect the entire hematopoietic system including hematopoietic stem cells.</title><p><bold>a</bold>, Conceptual and experimental overview. Cellular and molecular aberrations in JMML are characterized in the context of healthy hematopoietic development using a multi-omics approach to identify disease-specific aberrations that can be used for diagnostic and therapeutic purposes. (FET: fetal; NEO: neonatal; JUV: juvenile; ADU: adult; MNC: mononuclear cells; HSC: hematopoietic stem cells; PDX: patient-derived xenograft). <bold>b-g</bold>, Single-cell RNA-sequencing (scRNA-seq) of mononuclear cells (MNCs) isolated from JMML patient samples and healthy postnatal references. Cell types were annotated using adult human cell atlas data as a reference. <bold>b</bold>, UMAP of scRNA-seq data colored by disease status (grey: healthy references; red: JMML). ‘REF’ includes data from neonatal, juvenile and adult samples. <bold>c</bold>, UMAPs of scRNA-seq data split by dataset and colored by cell type. Major cell types are indicated in the legend, detailed cell type annotation is included in <bold>Extended Data</bold> Fig. 3). Erythrobl.: erythroblast; Foll. B cell: follicular B cell; Plasma: plasma cell. <bold>d</bold>, Stacked bar plot summarizing the cell type frequencies across the scRNA-seq datasets. P1 – P7: JMML samples. <bold>e</bold>, Dot plot summarizing gene expression of characteristic lineage markers across major hematopoietic cell types in healthy references (REF) and JMML samples. <bold>f</bold>, Density UMAPs depicting the expression of the hematopoietic stem and progenitor cell markers <italic>AVP</italic> and <italic>CD34</italic>. <bold>g</bold>, Principal component analysis (PCA) of the neutrophil differentiation trajectory. Correlation analysis identified PC 1 and PC 5 as representative of neutrophil differentiation (grey to orange) and disease-specific features (red), respectively. Cells from healthy references: grey; cells from JMML patients: red. Density plots depict the cell density along the axes stratified by cell type (PC 1) or by disease status (PC 5). Bottom panel describes JAK-STAT signaling pathway activity across neutrophil pseudotime for JMML (red) and references (black).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS190504-f001"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><title>Epitypes are conserved in hematopoietic stem cells of JMML patients.</title><p><bold>a</bold>, Left: FACS contour plots from healthy adult bone marrow (n=1; ADU). Right: schematic representing the sorting strategy of HSPCs for single-cell RNA-sequencing (top; Lin<sup>-</sup>CD34<sup>+</sup>CD38<sup>-/lo</sup>) and ultra-low input whole-genome bisulfite sequencing (Lin<sup>-</sup>CD34<sup>+</sup>CD38<sup>-/lo</sup>CD45RA/CD90 quadrants). scRNA: single-cell RNA-sequencing; WGBS: ultra-low input whole-genome bisulfite sequencing. <bold>b</bold>, FACS contour plots depicting expression of CD38 (y-axis) over CD34 (x-axis) in the Lin<sup>-</sup> (top) and expression of CD90 (y-axis) over CD45RA (x-axis) in the Lin<sup>-</sup>CD34<sup>+</sup>CD38<sup>-/lo</sup> (bottom) compartments of JMML patients (n=8; P1 – P8). Colors refer to the semi-quantitative genome-wide methylation states in each patient (Extended Data Fig. 1). <bold>c</bold>, Quantification of aberrant Lin<sup>-</sup> CD34<sup>+</sup>CD38<sup>-/lo</sup>CD45RA<sup>+</sup>CD90<sup>+</sup> HSCs in a validation cohort (n=29 JMML patients) stratified by JMML epitype. <bold>d-f</bold>, µWGBS of sorted JMML HSPCs. <bold>d</bold>, Principal component analysis (PCA) of the 20,000 most-variable CpGs identified across JMML HSPCs. <bold>e</bold>, Heatmap depicting methylation status of 13,832 DMRs identified between HM and non-HM (i.e., “intermediate methylation” [IM] and “low methylation” [LM]) patients. Hierarchical clustering using Manhattan distance and complete linkage. <bold>f</bold>, Genome browser tracks of WGBS and bulk methylation array data. Tracks P1 – P8 depict WGBS data from JMML HSPCs. LM, IM, and HM refer to bulk methylation array data aggregated from 147 JMML patients representing all epitypes (LM=62, IM=45, HM=40). Depicted is the genomic region (hg19, chr11:128,553,548-128,564,856) containing a DMR overlapping an alternative transcription start site of <italic>FLI1</italic>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS190504-f002"/></fig><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><title>JMML HSCs are characterized by transcriptional mosaicism of developmental programs.</title><p><bold>a</bold>, Schematic displaying the systematic comparison of JMML HSCs to healthy HSCs across different developmental stages including fetal liver (FET), cord blood (NEO), juvenile (JUV), and adult (ADU) bone marrow. <bold>b-e</bold>, Transcriptional profiling using scRNA-seq of JMML HSCs in the context of healthy HSCs representing different developmental stages. HSCs were defined uniformly based using automated cell type annotation (see “Materials and Methods” section). <bold>b</bold>, Cell type similarity inference using logistic regression analysis. JMML HSCs were compared at the single-cell level to healthy HSCs isolated at different developmental stages. Depicted are averaged and probability-converted predicted logits. Values &gt;0.5 (pink) indicate similarity whereas values &lt;0.5 (grey) indicate dissimilarity to the references (rows). <bold>c-d</bold>, Violin plots showing the expression profiles of the HSC marker genes <italic>CRHBP</italic> and <italic>HMGA2</italic> in healthy and malignant HSCs. <italic>CRHBP</italic> is a marker for adult HSCs and <italic>HMGA2</italic> is a marker for fetal HSCs. <bold>e</bold>, Heatmap depicting expression profiles of stage-specific signature genes for healthy HSC development. For each developmental stage, the top 50 DEGs compared to all other stages were identified. Only genes, that were found to be differentially expressed in a single reference were kept. Scaling of normalized expression was done on a per gene basis across healthy HSC references to reflect the physiologic expression range. All values above the maximum or below the minimum are flagged with dark red or dark green, respectively, representing aberrantly up- or downregulated signature genes in JMML.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS190504-f003"/></fig><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><title>DNA methylome analysis reveals a postnatal maturation stage in JMML HSCs across all epitypes.</title><p>DNA methylome analysis of JMML HSCs in the context of healthy hematopoietic development using ultra-low input WGBS. Fetal HSCs (<italic>FET</italic>; fetal spleen HSCs [n=3], fetal liver HSCs [n=3]), cord blood HSCs (<italic>NEO</italic>; n=4), juvenile HSCs (<italic>JUV</italic>; n=2), and adult HSCs (<italic>ADU</italic>; n=3). <bold>a</bold>, Schematic summarizing the normal maturation trajectory of healthy HSCs, which was used to determine maturation-associated methylation changes. <bold>b</bold>, Heatmap showing the hierarchical clustering of all methylation-dynamic regions (n=1,179) identified in HSCs across normal development. Plotted are scaled average DNA methylation values. <bold>c</bold>, Phylogenetic tree analysis based on all methylation-dynamic regions. Methylome data of JMML HSCs are projected onto this phylogenetic tree based on Manhattan distances. Replicates are aggregated per patient or healthy developmental stage. <bold>d-e</bold>, ‘Epigenetic scars’ analysis from the transition between neonatal and postneonatal stages. <bold>d</bold>, Epigenetic scars are defined as DNA methylation changes that occur in a given developmental window but do not change thereafter. <bold>e</bold>, Heatmap showing methylation beta values of epigenetic scars from the transition of neonatal to post-neonatal HSCs. Hypo: loss of DNA methylation; hyper: gain of DNA methylation. <bold>f</bold>, Schematic illustrating the two hypothetical scenarios explaining the expression of fetal-like signatures in JMML HSCs: I. Transformation of a prenatal cell-of-origin reprograms HSCs leading to a partial preservation of fetal HSC programs in JMML patients (left panel). II. Alternatively, transformation of a postnatal HSC partially reactivates fetal gene expression patterns, resulting in oncofetal reprogramming (OFR) (right panel).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS190504-f004"/></fig><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><title>RAS-pathway activation in postnatal HSCs results in oncofetal reprogramming in a JMML mouse model.</title><p><bold>a</bold>, Establishment of a JMML mouse model by induction of a <italic>Ptpn11</italic><sup>E76K</sup> mutation in postnatal HSCs. Conditional <italic>Ptpn11</italic><sup>E76K/+</sup> mice were crossed to SclCreER<sup>T</sup> mice to allow HSPC-specific activation of the mutation. <italic>Ptpn11</italic><sup>E76K/+</sup> Scl-CreER<sup>T</sup> mice (E76K) and Ptpn11<sup>+/+</sup> Scl-CreER<sup>T</sup> controls (Ctrl) were injected (i.p.) with tamoxifen (TAM) at the age of 6-12 weeks. <bold>b</bold>, Leukocyte (WBC) and platelet (PLTs) counts are shown throughout 9 months post induction (p.i.). Mean and SEM are depicted. Statistical significance was calculated using student’s t-test. <bold>c</bold>, Differentiated hematopoietic cells were measured by flow cytometry in bone marrow (BM), spleen (SP) and peripheral blood (PB) of mice 18 weeks p.i. The box plots show the abundance of each cell type as percentage of total CD45<sup>+</sup> cells. Whiskers are defined as 1.5 times interquartile range (IQR). Statistical significance was calculated using Student’s t-test. <bold>d</bold>, Kaplan-Meier plot depicting leukemia-free survival. Numbers of animals at risk are denoted under the respective timepoints. Median survival is indicated and significance of survival differences was calculated using log-rank test. <bold>e-f</bold>, Spleens and livers were isolated 18 weeks p.i. and organ weights were documented. Whiskers are defined as 1.5 times interquartile range (IQR). Statistical significance was calculated using Student’s t-test. <bold>g</bold>, Single-cell RNA-seq of E76K (n=3) and Ctrl (n=3) mice 18 weeks after TAM induction. The UMAP shows a 2D representation of 29 clusters identified and annotated to a hematopoietic cell type based on marker gene expression. <bold>h</bold>, Circular bar plot depicting the relative changes in cluster contribution of E76K compared to Ctrl cells. Significance was determined using Fisher’s exact test followed by Benjamini-Hochberg’s FDR correction. <bold>i</bold>, Density plot displaying transcriptional priming of HSCs towards the monocytic lineage (“Monocyte Score”) compared to expression of a “stemness” signature (“Stemness Score”). Significance was determined based on LMM and subsequent ANOVA. <bold>j</bold>, Enrichment analysis of mouse fetal and adult HSC signatures <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27">27</xref></sup> in E76K and Ctrl HSCs. <bold>k</bold>, Enrichment analysis of human HSC signatures across different developmental stages (signature genes identified in this study, <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3e</xref>) HSCs. <bold>l</bold>, Violin plots showing the expression of marker genes for different developmental stages of the hematopoietic system in HSCs. Significance was determined using Wilcoxon rank sum test.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS190504-f005"/></fig><fig id="F6" position="float"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><title>Integrative analysis identifies novel prognostic biomarkers and therapeutic targets for HM-JMML.</title><p><bold>a</bold>, Strategy for the identification of disease-specific candidate genes in JMML HSCs. <bold>b</bold>, Identification of methylation-associated gene expression changes across JMML epitypes. The heatmaps display expression (right) and methylation (left) values of the DMR-DEG associations for the 56 high-confidence candidate genes identified using a generalized linear model (for details, see Material and Methods). Normalized gene expression was scaled to the minimum and maximum for each gene. For each DMR the average beta values across all CpGs per region are depicted. ‘Correlation’ depicts the Pearson correlation coefficients as per DMR-DEG association. ‘Cell surface’ indicates if a gene is predicted to be expressed on the cell surface. The 13 genes encoding for cell surface proteins are indicated by name. Of note, a single gene can be associated with multiple DMRs. <bold>c</bold>, Locus line plot showing the smoothened methylation beta values of the <italic>CD52</italic> locus in HSCs across JMML patients and healthy references. <bold>d</bold>, Violin plots showing the normalized expression profiles of <italic>CD52</italic> in JMML and healthy reference HSCs. Significance of expression differences across samples was tested using Kruskal-Wallis test. Significance of the expression differences of postnatal (i.e. NEO, JUV, ADU) to prenatal (FET) HSCs was tested using Wilcoxon rank sum test. Boxplot center line corresponds to data median, box height to the inter-quartile range and lines to lower / upper quartile +/− 1.5 times inter-quartile range. <bold>e</bold>, Histograms showing the cell surface expression of CD52 in Lin<sup>-</sup>CD34<sup>+</sup>CD38<sup>-/lo</sup> JMML HSPCs using flow cytometry analysis of patients across epitypes. Significance was calculated per patient with Wilcoxon test against P1. <bold>f-k</bold>, Patient-derived xenograft (PDX) mouse experiments. For experimental details refer to ‘Materials and Methods’ and Extended Data Fig. 12a. <bold>f</bold>, Representative FACS contour plot and histogram showing CD52 expression on engrafted human CD45<sup>+</sup> JMML cells in mice treated with alemtuzumab (green) or with vehicle control (dark grey). Expression levels are depicted on a logarithmic scale. <bold>g</bold>, Quantification of engrafting human CD45<sup>+</sup> cells after 4 weeks of treatment with alemtuzumab (green) or vehicle (dark grey). Depicted are the human cells as a percentage of all hematopoietic cells detected in each organ tested. <bold>h</bold>, Effect of alemtuzumab treatment (‘treatment effect’) depicted as the differences of the mean engraftment in treated vs untreated mice per organ (treatment effect = mean<sub>treated</sub> – mean<sub>untreated</sub>). <bold>i</bold>, <italic>Left:</italic> representative FACS plot showing CD34 and CD38 expression on human CD45<sup>+</sup>Lin<sup>-</sup> JMML cells engrafted in the bone marrow of mice treated with alemtuzumab (green) or with vehicle control (dark grey). <italic>Right:</italic> Quantification of Lin<sup>-</sup>CD34<sup>+</sup>CD38<sup>-</sup> and Lin<sup>-</sup>CD34<sup>+</sup>CD38<sup>+</sup> human HSPCs. Depicted is the logarithm of the absolute number of living human cells per femur. <bold>j</bold>, Schematic depicting the 2° transplantation experiments. Secondary recipient mice received bone marrow cells from alemtuzumab-treated or vehicle-treated primary PDX mice. <bold>k</bold>, Frequency of human CD45<sup>+</sup> cells in 2° recipients of cells from alemtuzumab-treated (green) or vehicle-treated (dark grey) donor mice. Engraftment was evaluated 6 weeks after transplantation.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS190504-f006"/></fig></floats-group></article>