<!DOCTYPE article
 PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" article-type="preprint"><?all-math-mml yes?><?use-mml?><?origin ukpmcpa?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">bioRxiv</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>bioRxiv : the preprint server for biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub"/></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">EMS191778</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2023.11.24.568589</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="archive">PPR764616</article-id><article-version-alternatives><article-version article-version-type="status">preprint</article-version><article-version article-version-type="number">2</article-version></article-version-alternatives><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Quantification of GTPase cycling rates of GTPases and GTPase : effector mixtures using GTPase Glo™ assays</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Tschirpke</surname><given-names>Sophie</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">†</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Daalman</surname><given-names>Werner K-G.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">†</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Laan</surname><given-names>Liedewij</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">†</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CR1">**</xref></contrib><aff id="A1"><label>†</label>Bionanoscience Department, Delft University of Technology, Van der Maasweg 9, 2629 HZ Delft, The Netherlands</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="CR1"><label>**</label>corresponding author: <email>L.Laan@tudelft.nl</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted"><day>26</day><month>11</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="preprint"><day>24</day><month>11</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><permissions><ali:free_to_read/><license><ali:license_ref>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is licensed under a <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/4.0/">CC BY-ND 4.0 International license</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p id="P1">In different cellular activities like signal transduction, cell division, and intracellular transportation, small GTPases take on a vital role. Their functioning involves hydrolysing guanosine triphosphate (GTP) to guanosine diphosphate (GDP). In this article we explain the application of a commercially accessible GTPase assay, known as the GTPase Glo™ assay by Promega, for the quantitative investigation of GTPase - effector interactions and the interplay between effectors.</p><p id="P2"><bold>Basic Protocol:</bold> Conducting GTPase assays with GTPase : effector protein mixtures using the GTPase Glo™ assay (Promega).</p><p id="P3"><bold>Supporting Protocol 1:</bold> Analysing GTPase assays to correlate the assay readout (luminescence) to amount of remaining GTP.</p><p id="P4"><bold>Supporting Protocol 2:</bold> Fitting GTPase assay data to obtain GTPase cycling rates.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Cdc42</kwd><kwd>GTPase activity</kwd><kwd>GTPase assay</kwd><kwd>GTPase effectors</kwd><kwd>GTPase cycling rates</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="S1" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p id="P5">Small Guanosine Triphosphatases (GTPases), are a class of enzymes that play a fundamental role in various cellular processes, including signal transduction, cell division, and intracellular transport. GTPases regulate the hydrolysis of guanosine triphosphate (GTP) to guanosine diphosphate (GDP). Mechanistically, this GTPase activity involves three steps (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>): (1) binding of GTP to the GTPase, (2) hydrolysis of GTP to GDP and free phosphate, and (3) release of GDP from the GT-Pase. GTPase activity is often regulated by effector proteins; GTPase activating proteins (GAPs) boost step 2 and GDP/GTP exchange factors (GEFs) enhance step 3 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">Cherfils and Zeghouf, 2013</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">Bos et al., 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">Vetter and Wittinghofer, 2001</xref>]. Several assays exist that examine single GTPase cycle steps, which help us understand the mechanistic details of these cycle steps and their regulation. At the same time, they do not allow studying the interplay of effectors acting on different GTPase cycle steps. Furthermore, approaches that reconstitute the complex cellular functions of GTPases <italic>in vitro</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">Vendel et al., 2019</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">Loose et al., 2008</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">Bezeljak et al., 2020</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">Kohyama et al., 2022</xref>] are sensitive to variations in protein batch activities and benefit from easy and accessible assays assessing protein purification batches activities.</p><p id="P6">We here describe how a commercially available GTPase assay (GTPase Glo™ assay (Promega), from here on referred to as ‘GTPase assay’) can be used to quantitatively study GTPase effector interactions and effector interplay and to easily activity test GTPase and effector purification batches. In the GTPase assay the proteins of interest are incubated with GTP for a certain amount of time for GTPase cycling to occur. Then the reaction is stopped and the amount of remaining GTP, measured as luminescence signal, is determined. GTPase cycling rates can be obtained from this data through using a coarse-grained exponential fitting model (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). This article describes the workflow for conducting GTPase assays using GTPase : effector protein mixtures, and provides analysis software to obtain GTPase cycling rates. We like to note that we do not advice to use this protocol if single GTPase steps are to be examined in-depth, but if effects of a protein on the entire GTPase cycle are of interest. This method is exemplified for a basic GTpase assay using the human Ras (GTPase) (example 1) and for an elaborate GTpase assay set using <italic>S. cerevisae</italic> Cdc42 (GTPase), Cdc24 (GEF), and Rga2 (GAP) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">Tschirpke et al., 2023a</xref>] (example 2). <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Tab. 1</xref> summarises how these examples are used to illustrated the protocols described herein. It can also be applied to other GTPases and their effectors. In the Basic Protocol we outline the workflow for conducting GTPase assays using the GTPase Glo™ assay (Promega). In Supporting Protocol 1 we describe how the GTPase assays data (luminescence) can be converted to amounts of remaining GTP. In Supporting Protocol 2 we describe how data obtained by Supporting Protocol 1 can be fitted with a GTPase cycling model (and the by us developed, openly available Matlab code) to obtain GTPase cycling rates.</p></sec><sec id="S2"><title>Strategic Planning</title><p id="P7">If the GTPase assay is done for the first time, we advice to first practice pipetting of the required small volumes into the wells using coloured water. We advice to conduct smaller assays using a larger number of replicas per sample (e.g. 8 samples rows per assay with 5 replicas each, as described in the basic protocol) first, before moving on to larger assay sets with more proteins.</p><p id="P8">Once you feel more routined with the assay, larger assay sets can be conducted. For example, assays in which the interaction between a GTPase and one or several effectors is studied. The following section applies predominantly (but not solely!) to such larger assays sets involving multiple GTPase enzymes and/or effector proteins (example 2). We advice to determine before starting which assays with how many proteins will need to be carried out. Specifically, we advice to:</p><sec id="S3"><title>Verify that the proteins and protein buffers do not interfere with the assay signal</title><p id="P9">The GTPase assay measures luminescence, which correlates with the amount of remaining GTP. Proteins that interact with luminescence (e.g. fluorescent tags, see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S3</xref>) and can alter it are therefore not suitable for this assay.</p><p id="P10">Buffers containing ADP, ATP, GDP, GTP, and guanosine phosphate analogues are also not suitable for the GPase assay, as they interfere with other GTPase assay reactions.</p><p id="P11">We advice to consider the buffer components and verify that used effector proteins (proteins that are not GTPase enzymes) show no seemingly GTPase activity.</p></sec><sec id="S4"><title>Verify that the used incubation times lay in the exponential decline regime of remaining GTP</title><p id="P12">In the GTPase assay the proteins of interest are incubated with GTP for a certain amount of time, in which GTPase cycling can occur. Then the reaction is stopped and the amount of remaining GTP, measured as luminescence signal, is determined. GTPase cycling rates can be obtained from this data through using a coarse-grained exponential fitting model (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S8</xref>). The model is based on our observation that the amount of remaining GTP declines exponentially with time (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S4</xref>). It is still advisable to verified that this is also true for the proteins (GTPase enzymes and GTPase:effector mixtures) and incubation times intended to be used.</p><p id="P13">To obtain such data, prepare one batch of serial dilutions of the to-be-used proteins. Use exactly these dilutions to conduct several assays using different incubation times. Check if the amount of remaining GTP of these assays follows an exponential decline. Further, analyse each assay individually using our GTPase cycling model. Verify that different incubation times (= different assays) yield the same rates (e.g. <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S4</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S5"><title>Dialyse all to-be-used proteins into the same buffer</title><p id="P14">All proteins should ideally be in the same buffer. In the assay the protein activity is determined by normalising the assay readout (luminescence) of that protein well to that of ‘buffer only’. Differences between those two (in ion concentrations, detergents, or other additives (such as glycerol)) can lead to differences in luminescence. This is easiest avoided if all proteins used in one assay set are in the same buffer. We advice against using a buffer containing glycerol, as the increased viscosity may affect protein activities (unless protein activities in a denser environment are of interest). Further, buffers should <italic>not</italic> contain DTT, GDP, GTP, and other guoanosine analogues, ADP, ATP, and other nucleotide triphosphates, EDTA or other chelating agents that can complex magnesium. If a GTPase GEF interaction ought to be investigated, the buffer usually requires magnesium salts (e.g. 10 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>).</p><p id="P15">Many proteins require glycerol in the buffer for storage. We advice to keep the protein at a high concentration in a buffer containing glycerol (e.g. 50 mM Tris-HCl (pH=7.5), 100 mM NaCl, 10 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 1 mM 2-mercaptoethanol, 10% glycerol), and then dilute it into a buffer of the same composition <italic>without</italic> glycerol (e.g. 50 mM Tris-HCl (pH=7.5), 100 mM NaCl, 10 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 1 mM 2-mercaptoethanol). GTPase assays usually require small concentrations of proteins (in our experience 0.5-5 μM). If the protein is stored at a high concentration, the amount of glycerol in the final sample in the GTPase reaction will be negligible.</p><p id="P16">If it’s not possible to transfer all proteins into the same buffer, it needs to be verified that the differences in buffer composition do not affect luminescence intensities. A GTPase assay containing only the different buffer mixtures can elucidate this: If all buffer mixtures exhibit the same luminescence values then the difference in buffer composition do not affect luminescence. However, it is still possible that the buffer components affect protein behaviour!</p></sec><sec id="S6"><title>Use the same serial dilution for all assays</title><p id="P17">The assay is sensitive to concentration changes (especially of highly active GPases and of effectors strongly boosting GTPase activity), and thus sensitive to any pipetting errors when preparing the protein dilutions. We advice to prepare serial dilutions of every protein, and use exactly the same serial dilution for the entire assay series. Different serial dilutions of the same protein can exhibit slightly different rates. For example, if the effect of effector protein X on GTPase A and GTPase B ought to be compared, the same serial dilution of effector X ought to be used for both GTPases.</p></sec><sec id="S7"><title>Include a reference sample if data from different assays should be compared</title><p id="P18">GTPase assays can be sensitive to GTPase activity changes, which can be due to small pipetting errors or condition changes (incl. temperature, shaker speed, …). This can lead to slight changes in protein activity between separate assays. It is there-fore best to include all samples that ought to be compared into the same assay.</p><p id="P19">However, this is not always possible. If the strength of several effectors on one GTPase enzyme ought to be compared, we advice to always include one sample containing only the GTPase into each assay (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>). Then the assay-specific activity of the GTPase sample can be used to account for any assay-specific variability (through fitting the correction factor <italic>c</italic><sub><italic>corr</italic></sub>, as will be explained in later sections and in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S8</xref> Eq. 9).</p><p id="P20">(Usually these assay-variations are very small (<italic>c</italic><sub><italic>corr</italic></sub> ≈ 1.0) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">Tschirpke et al., 2023b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">Tschirpke et al., 2023a</xref>]. We advice to exclude assays with a big or very small <italic>c</italic><sub><italic>corr</italic></sub>, as these indicate that the GTPase behaviour/assay conditions are unusual.)</p></sec><sec id="S8"><title>Determine useful concentration ranges before conducting an assay series</title><p id="P21">In our experience a good readout regime is between 5-90% remaining GTP. Higher values (90-100% remaining GTP) have a bigger error (due to the normalisation), and in lower regimes (0-5% remaining GTP) saturation effect due to little remaining GTP might take place. In this regime a saturation of the fitted cycling rates may occur. If an assay with multiple proteins (e.g. a GTPase and two effector proteins) is conducted, it is useful to determine beforehand which concentration ranges of each protein lead to optimal readouts to reduce the time it takes to conduct the entire assay series.</p><p id="P22">It is also advisable to stick to similar incubation times for all assays, as this streamlines the selection of protein concentrations (for assays containing protein mixtures) that yield suitable readout regimes.</p></sec><sec id="S9"><title>Make an assay plan</title><p id="P23">If multiple protein interactions ought to be quantified and compared, the same serial dilutions of these proteins ought to be used. Given that we advice against the use of a glycerol-containing buffer, that many proteins require glycerol when being frozen, and that many proteins are not stable for weeks at room temperature or 4<sup>°</sup>C, all required assays need to be conducted within a rather short time period to obtain reliable and comparable results. We therefore strongly recommend to carefully plan which assays with which proteins need to be conducted, and calculate the required volumes of protein needed.</p><p id="P24">We will explain our recommended procedure on the example of a GTPase assay series that investigates the GTPase cycling of a GTPase, and the effect of both a GEF and a GAP, alone and in combination, on it (example 2, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">Tschirpke et al., 2023a</xref>]:</p><p id="P25">Considerations (as we described earlier): (1) Different serial dilutions of the same protein might exhibit slightly different rates (due to small pipetting errors when making the dilution). Hence, the same dilution should be used for the entire assay set. (2) For larger assays it is advisable to already know which concentration ranges give good signal to reduce the time the proteins need to be stored. (3) Include a reference sample (here: sample of the GTPase enzyme alone in the concentration used in the particular assay). (4) The incubation times used are in the exponential regime. (5) It is advisable to use similar incubation times for all assays, as this will make it easier to choose protein concentrations for assays containing protein mixtures that will result in suitable readout regimes.</p><sec id="S10"><title>Protein dilutions</title><p id="P26">To conduct the assay, several protein solutions need to be made: Protein dilutions of GTPase, GEF, and GAP that will be used to conduct the entire assay set (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref> left column). These starting dilutions will be used to create protein mixtures, that will be used to for one GTPase assay (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref> middle column).</p><p id="P27">Which concentrations should these starting dilutions have? To initiate the GTPase reaction, a 2× GTP solution is mixed in a 1:1 volume ratio with the protein mixtures. Therefore, the protein mixture needs to be 2× of the final concentration in the assay. Further, in the final assay the protein mixture needs to contain the GTPase, GEF, and GAP. It is easiest to make this mixture if all proteins can be mixed at 1:1:1 volume ratios. Hence, the initial starting protein serial dilutions, which will be used for all assays of the set, should be 6× stocks of the final protein concentrations. (Similarly, if an assay set will contain at maximum a mixture of 4 (5) proteins, the initial starting protein serial dilutions need to be 8× (10×) stocks of the final protein concentrations.</p></sec><sec id="S11" sec-type="methods"><title>Procedure</title><p id="P28">In which order should the assays be conducted? First, a GTPase assay with a serial dilution of only the GTPase enzyme is conducted (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref> top row). Pick one or two GTPase concentrations to conduct all following assays with. In this case the following assays will involve a GEF and a GAP, both of which boost the activity of the GTPase. It is therefore wise to choose a GTPase concentration that leads to a high amount of remaining GTP (e.g. 90-80% remaining GTP). Next, a GTPase assay with the GTPase and several GEF concentrations (obtained from serial dilutions) is performed. Use the same GTPase concentration for all samples; samples of GTPase:GEF mixtures, and a sample containing only the GTPase (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref> second row). The same procedure is applied to the GAP: Conduct a GTPase assay with the GTPase and several GAP concentrations (obtained from serial dilutions). Use the same GTPase concentration for all samples; samples of GTPase:GAP mixtures, and a sample containing only the GTPase (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref> third row). Lastly, perform GTPase assays in which all proteins are present (GTPase alone, GTPase:GEF mixtures, GTPase:GAP mixtures, and GTPase:GEF:GAP mixtures, all using the same GTPase concentration). Choose GEF and GAP concentrations that resulted in a medium amount of remaining GTP (e.g. 60-70% remaining GTP), to leave room for even lower values when both proteins are combined (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref> bottom row). Ideally additional assays will be added to control for potential non-canonical effects (see below).</p></sec></sec><sec id="S12"><title>Control for non-canonical effects through adding an inert protein</title><p id="P29">We observed that the non-canonical effects can take place during GTPase cycling in the GTPase assay. These effects are generally small, and can be accounted for: For example, we observed that both Bovine serum albumin (BSA) and Casein slightly boost GTPase activity of both Ras and Cdc42. BSA and Casein are considered inert and have no known interaction with neither Ras or Cdc42. We suspect that they seemingly boost the GTPase’s activity through increasing the effective GT-Pase concentration: A few GTPase molecules might stick to the well wall in each reaction chamber, being rendered inactive. Through adding another protein the chamber wall will be covered with both some GTPase molecules and some molecules of the other protein, thereby increasing the effective GTPase concentration.</p><p id="P30">To ensure that the effect of a protein on GTPase cycling is not only due to these non-canonical effects, we advice to additionally conduct assays with the GTPase and an inert protein (e.g. BSA or Casein). The effect of the to-be-studied protein will need to exceed that of a equimolar concentration of the inert protein to be of non-canonical origin.</p><p id="P31">Both BSA and Casein are considered inert proteins. However, BSA is strongly negatively charged, which could lead to non-specific protein interactions. Therefore Casein, or another supposedly inert protein, might be more suitable as a control.</p><p id="P32">For the previously used example 2 (an assay series including a GTPase, GEF, and GAP, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>), control assays for non-canonical effects include: (1) GTPase:Casein serial dilution, (2) GTPase:GEF:Casein, (3) GTPase:GAP:Casein.</p></sec></sec><sec id="S13"><title>Basic Protocol: Conducing GTPase assays</title><p id="P33">In the GTPase assay the proteins of interest (GTPase enzymes with or without effectors) are incubated with GTP for a certain amount of time for GTPase cycling to occur. Then the reaction is stopped. The remaining GTP is, through two follow up reactions, translated into luminescence signal, which is measured (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>).</p><p id="P34">The following protocol steps are, with only minor modifications, those described in the assay manual. The volumes are for assays conducted in 384-well microplates. Assays using larger volumes can be conduced using different plates (see GTPase Glo™ assay manual). In addition to following the steps described here we advice to carefully read the assay manual [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">Promega Corporation, 2015</xref>].</p><p id="P35">The following protocol describes the steps to conduct a GTPase assay using 6 concentrations of Ras GTPase (example 1) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>). An illustration of required assay planning steps is shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S2</xref>. The assay results in data found in ‘example1.xlsx’ (tab: ‘E1’, ‘E2’).</p><sec id="S14" sec-type="materials"><title>Materials</title><list list-type="bullet" id="L1"><list-item><p id="P36">GTPase Glo™ assay (Promega, cat. no. V7681 (1’000 reactions) or V7682 (10’000 reactions))</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P37">proteins of interest: a GTPase enzyme (and optionally effector proteins). As a test GTPase human Ras (EMD Millipore, cat. no. 553325) can be used.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P38">buffer in which the proteins of interest are stored (‘protein buffer’)</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P39">optional: Casein (Sigma-Aldrich, cat. no. C7078) or Bovine serum albumin (BSA) (Thermo Scientific, cat. no. 23209)</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P40">1.5 mL and 15 mL reaction tubes</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P41">384-well white flat bottom microplates (Corning, cat. no. 3572)</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P42">parafilm (Bemis Company Inc., cat. no. PM996)</p></list-item></list></sec><sec id="S15"><title>Equipment</title><list list-type="bullet" id="L2"><list-item><p id="P43">pipettes: 0.5 μL, 10 μL, 20 μL, 100 or 200 μL, 1 mL</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P44">vortex mixer (e.g. Thermo Scientific, cat. no. 88882011)</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P45">Mini centrifuge (e.g. Thermo Scientific, cat. no.75004061)</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P46">orbital shaker (e.g. Innova 2300 platform shaker (New Brunswick Scientific))</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P47">optional: temperature-controlled incubator</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P48">a plate reader that can measure luminescence (e.g. Synergy HTX plate reader from BioTek)</p></list-item></list></sec><sec id="S16"><title>Preparation of proteins</title><list list-type="order" id="L3"><list-item><p id="P49">Dialyse the GTPase enzyme into a suitable buffer (‘protein buffer’).</p><p id="P50"><italic>E.g. 50</italic> mM <italic>Tris-HCl (pH=7.5), 100</italic> mM <italic>NaCl, 10</italic> mM <italic>MgCl</italic><sub>2</sub>, <italic>1</italic> mM <italic>2-mercaptoethanol. More considerations on the buffer are described in the strategic planning section</italic>.</p><p id="P51"><italic>If the GTPase enzyme is at a high concentration (e.g. 50-100</italic> mM<italic>) and the buffer the protein is stored in does not differ that much from the protein buffer, it can be sufficient to only dilute the protein using protein buffer</italic>.</p></list-item></list></sec><sec id="S17"><title>Before starting the assay</title><p id="P52">2. ‘Mise-en-place’: Decide on the assay scope and prepare all assay materials needed. Templates can be found in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S1</xref>. An example for an assay of Ras GTPase is shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>.
<list list-type="simple" id="L4"><list-item><label>(a)</label><p id="P53">Decide which samples and how many replica wells per sample you want to use.</p><p id="P54">We recommend 3-5 replicas per sample. In the beginning In the beginning we recommend using one GTPase enzyme per assay and 5 replicas. We suggest using 8 samples per assay: 6 concentrations of the GTPase enzyme (here: Ras GTPase) + 2 protein buffer samples (for normalisation) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>).</p></list-item><list-item><label>(b)</label><p id="P55">Calculate which volumes of protein dilutions, 2× GTP solution, Glo solution, and detection reagent are needed to conduct one assay (example calculation are given in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S2</xref>).</p><p id="P56">Vol.(protein dilution) = 5μL × number of replicas</p><p id="P57">Vol.(2× GTP solution) = 5μL × number of replicas per sample × number of samples</p><p id="P58">Vol.(Glo solution) = 2 × Vol.(2× GTP solution)</p><p id="P59">Vol.(detection reagent) = 4 × Vol.(2× GTP solution)</p><p id="P60">We recommend to always prepare a bit more of the solutions that needed.</p><p id="P61"><italic>We recommend preparing 5</italic>μL <italic>more of each protein dilution than calculated, to ensure that there is also sufficient solution for the last well. E.g. for 5 replicas per sample, for each dilution prepare 5</italic>μL × <italic>5 + 5</italic>μL <italic>= 30</italic>μL.</p></list-item><list-item><label>(c)</label><p id="P62">Calculate the dilution series steps for proteins used. Note that the solutions prepared need to be 2× of the final concentration in the assay (example calculation are given in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S2</xref>).</p></list-item><list-item><label>(d)</label><p id="P63">Prepare the plate: seal the assay wells that will not be used with parafilm to prevent contamination with dirt, and label/mark the wells where sample will be added.</p><p id="P64">Leave one empty row between all sample rows to avoid any spill-over of luminescence signal between samples (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S5</xref>).</p></list-item><list-item><label>(e)</label><p id="P65">Cut 4 pieces of parafilm that are sufficiently big to cover the area where samples will be added.</p></list-item></list></p></sec><sec id="S18"><title>Conducting GTPase Glo™ assays</title><list list-type="simple" id="L5"><list-item><label>3.</label><p id="P66">Thaw protein samples and assay solutions on ice.</p></list-item><list-item><label>4.</label><p id="P67">Serial dilute the Ras GTPase enzyme with protein buffer (according to your calculation) to obtain 2× GTPase enzyme dilutions (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3a</xref>).</p><p id="P68">Vortex for proper mixing, then spin down mildly to collect all volume in the bottom of the tube.</p></list-item><list-item><label>5.</label><p id="P69">Prepare a 2× GTP solution. A pipetting scheme is given in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Tab. 2</xref>.</p><p id="P70"><italic>The 2</italic>× <italic>GTP solution should always be freshly prepared immediately before starting the assay. Vortex the GTP and DTT before use. Vortex the 2</italic>× <italic>GTP solution for proper mixing. The 2</italic>× <italic>GTP solution can only be used freshly and should not be stored/frozen (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S6</xref>). We advice to aliquot GTP and DTT to reduce the number of freeze-thaw cycles, in our experience up to 3 freeze-thaw cycles do not impact assay performance</italic>.</p></list-item><list-item><label>6.</label><p id="P71">Add 5μL 2× GTP solution to all wells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3b</xref>).</p></list-item><list-item><label>7.</label><p id="P72">Add 5μL protein buffer and 2× Ras GTPase dilutions to designated wells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3c</xref>).</p><p id="P73">We advice to have one row containing protein buffer on top of the assay and one row in the bottom. In rare cases the luminescence values slightly drift towards lower values throughout the assay. Placement of a buffer row as a first and last sample row ensures that this drift can be (1) detected and (2) accounted for in the analysis.</p></list-item><list-item><label>8.</label><p id="P74">Seal the wells with two sheets of parafilm and incubate for a designated time on an orbital shaker.</p><p id="P75">We recommend to seal the wells through placing one sheet of parafilm on top of the plate (without stretching it) and firmly pressing it into to plate with a rounded surface (such as sissor handles). Then repeat the same process with the second sheet of parafilm. This ensures that the wells are tightly closed. Using only one sheet of parafilm can result insufficient sealing (small holes in the parafilm from the too much pressure).</p><p id="P76">The incubation time and temperature depends on the protein of interest and used concentrations. We recommend choosing a temperature in accordance to the protein’s environment in vivo. We recommend incubation times of 60-90 min.</p></list-item><list-item><label>9.</label><p id="P77">Prepare the Glo solution a few minutes before the incubation time is reached. A pipetting scheme is given in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">Tab. 3</xref>. Then add 10μL Glo solution to all wells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3e</xref>).</p><p id="P78">Preparation of the Glo solution:
<list list-type="simple" id="L6"><list-item><label>(a)</label><p id="P79"><italic>Vortex the Glo buffer and 10</italic> mM <italic>ADP before use. Do NOT vortex the GTPase-Glo reagent. Instead, gently tap it for proper mixing</italic>.</p></list-item><list-item><label>(b)</label><p id="P80"><italic>To use the pipetting scheme provided in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">Tab. 3</xref>, 10</italic> mM <italic>ADP provided in the assay kit needs to be diluted to 1</italic> mM <italic>ADP using ultra pure water!</italic></p></list-item><list-item><label>(c)</label><p id="P81"><italic>We advice to aliquot 10</italic> mM <italic>ADP, Glo buffer, and Glo reagent to reduce the number of freeze-thaw cycles. These aliqouts can be re-used (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S6</xref>)</italic>.</p></list-item><list-item><label>(d)</label><p id="P82"><italic>Both 1</italic> mM <italic>ADP and Glo solution can only be used freshly and should not be stored/frozen. Vortex both for proper mixing</italic>.</p></list-item><list-item><label>(e)</label><p id="P83">The Glo reagent is the reagent that usually runs out first. To increase the number of assay runs per kit, prepare only the volume needed.</p></list-item></list></p></list-item><list-item><label>10.</label><p id="P84">Seal the wells with two sheets of parafilm and incubate for 30 min on an orbital shaker.</p></list-item><list-item><label>11.</label><p id="P85">Add 20μL detection reagent to all wells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3g</xref>).</p><p id="P86">We advice to aliquote the detection reagent to reduce the number of freeze-thaw cycles and decrease the time required for thawing.</p><p id="P87">Calculate how much detection reagent is required per assay run. In some cases we observed that two seperately stored aliquots from the same batch can lead to distinct luminescence values (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S7</xref>). To avoid such a shift within an assay, pull a sufficient volume into one tube (e.g. pull several aliquots) before adding the detection reagent to the wells. Vortex for proper mixing.</p></list-item><list-item><label>12.</label><p id="P88">Measure the luminescence of each well using a plate reader for 20 min.</p><p id="P89">Activate orbital shaking between measurements to ensure proper mixing. If the plate reader does not have a shaking option, incubate the plate for 5 min on an orbital shaker before measuring luminescence. Then measure for 15 min.</p></list-item></list></sec></sec><sec id="S19"><title>Support Protocol 1: Basic analysis of GTPase assay data</title><p id="P90">This protocol describes basic analysis steps to calculate from the GTPase assay readout (luminescence) the amount of remaining GTP. The amount of remaining GTP is a simple measure used to compare the GTPase activity of different GTPases (of the same concentration, incubated with GTP for the same amount of time).</p><p id="P91">The protocol illustrates the steps for GTPase data from example 1: an assay including 6 Ras GTPase serial dilutions and two buffer reference samples, with each 3 replicas per sample (see basic protocol and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S2</xref>). This protocol uses <italic>and</italic> generates data in ‘example1.xlsx’, tab: ‘E1’, ‘E2’.</p><sec id="S20"><title>Necessary resources</title><list list-type="bullet" id="L7"><list-item><p id="P92">A spreadsheet editor or other analysis software (e.g. python script)</p></list-item></list></sec><sec id="S21"><title>Protocol steps</title><list list-type="order" id="L8"><list-item><p id="P93">Calculate the average luminescence for time points 5-20 min per well (= replica) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>)</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P94">Calculate the luminescence average for each sample: Average between wells (=replicas) of the same sample (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5a</xref>).</p><p id="P95">Combine the wells/replicas of the first and last buffer row. Calculate the average using all values. I.e. do not distinguish between the first and last buffer row (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S2</xref>).</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P96">Calculate the standard error of the mean for each sample (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5b</xref>).</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P97">Use the average luminescence values (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5a</xref>) to translate luminescence into amount of remaining GTP using <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD1">Eq. 1</xref> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5c</xref>): The luminescence values of the buffer samples correspond to 100% remaining GTP. The amount of remaining GTP of each protein sample corresponds to the luminescence of this sample divided by the luminescence of the buffer.</p><p id="P98">This step normalises the luminescence values of the protein samples to 100% remaining GTP (luminescence of the buffer). In principle, the protein samples also need to be normalised to 0% GTP. Given that we observed basically no luminescence in the blank samples (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S5</xref>), this step is not necessary. <disp-formula id="FD1"><label>(1)</label><mml:math id="M1"><mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mtext>remaining GTP</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mtext>Luminescence sample</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mtext>Luminescence buffer</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn><mml:mtext>%</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p></list-item><list-item><p id="P99">Calculate the error (‘Δ remaining GTP’) using error propagation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD2">Eq. 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5d</xref>): ‘Lum.’ is the average luminescence and ‘ΔLum.’ refers to the standard error of the mean. <disp-formula id="FD2"><label>(2)</label><mml:math id="M2"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Δ</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mtext>remaining GTP</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msqrt><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Δ Lum. sample</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext> Lum . sample</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Δ Lum. buffer</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext> Lum. buffer</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:msqrt><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mtext>Lum. sample</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mtext>Lum. buffer</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn><mml:mtext>%</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="P100">The following step is only required if the data analysis will be continued using Supporting Protocol 2:</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P101">Re-format the data in a spreadsheet to follow the formatting shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref>. This can be done using the python script provided in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S9</xref>. In short, the data must be organised into the following columns with specific headers: <list list-type="bullet" id="L9"><list-item><p id="P102">‘Run’: state the assay number. The assay number must start with an ‘E’ followed by a number, which can be followed by a letter (and underscore letter). Eg. E1, E2, E100, E1a, E100abc, E1_a, E100_abc, E1a_abc, E100f_abc</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P103">‘Time’: incubation time, stated in hours</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P104">‘GTP_remaining’: amount of remaining GTP, normalised to 1</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P105">‘Error’: error values, normalised to 1</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P106">‘Buffer_error’: error of the buffer, normalised to 1</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P107">‘[GTPase]_conc’: The header must contain the name of the GTPase, followed by ‘_conc’ (e.g. Ras_conc, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref>). The concentration must be stated in μM</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P108">optional: ‘[Effector]_conc’: The header must contain the name of the effector, followed by ‘_conc’. The concentration must be stated in μM. This column should only be there if it contains more than one unique value per assay.</p></list-item></list></p><p id="P109">We advice to group assays of the same type (i.e. containing the same proteins and dilution types) into one speadsheet tab. They must follow the same structure. The header can only be included once. E.g. An assay set examines the GTPase Cdc42 and its GEF Cdc24. Two types of assays were conducted: (A) GTPase assays using only serial dilutions of the GTPase Cdc42. (B) GTPase assays using a constant Cdc42 concentration and serial dilutions of the GEF Cdc24. We advice to group all assay data of (A) into one tab and all assay data of (B) into one tab.</p><p id="P110">More examples are given in Support Protocol 2.</p></list-item></list></sec></sec><sec id="S22"><title>Support Protocol 2: Fitting GTPase cycling rates</title><p id="P111">This protocol describes how the data, pre-processed using the steps described in Support Protocol 1, can be fitted using a GTPase activity model (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S8</xref>) to obtain GTPase cycling rates. It can be used to fit data of GTPases and GTPase - effector <italic>X</italic> mixtures (up to 2 effectors).</p><p id="P112">In short, first data of GTPase serial dilutions are fitted with an exponential to obtain GTPase cycling rates <italic>k</italic><sub>1</sub> and <italic>k</italic><sub>2</sub>: <disp-formula id="FD3"><label>(3)</label><mml:math id="M3"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mtext>GTP</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mtext>GTP</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>exp</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mtext>using</mml:mtext><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mtext>and</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mtext>GTPase</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mtext>GTPase</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:msup><mml:mtext>‌</mml:mtext><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="P113">Here <italic>K</italic> refers to the ‘overall GTP hydrolysis rate’ and depends on the concentration of the GTPase. We call the concentration-independent rates <italic>k</italic> GTPase cycling rates, referring to the fact that they describe GTPase cycling (and not specific GTpase cycle steps). The overall hydrolysis rate <italic>K</italic> is composed of an unaided hydrolysis contribution by an individual GTPase <inline-formula><mml:math id="M4"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, and an cooperative contribution by two GTPase molecules <inline-formula><mml:math id="M5"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p><p id="P114">Then, mixtures of one GTPase and one effector <italic>X</italic><sub>1</sub> are fitted with <disp-formula id="FD4"><label>(4)</label><mml:math id="M6"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mtext>GTPase</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mtext>GTPase</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mtext>GTPase</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="P115">and mixtures of one GTPase and two effectors (<italic>X</italic><sub>1</sub>, <italic>X</italic><sub>2</sub>) are fitted with <disp-formula id="FD5"><label>(5)</label><mml:math id="M7"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mtext>GTPase</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mtext>GTPase</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mtext>GTPase</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mtext>GTPase</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mtext>GTPase</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="P116">using <italic>n</italic> and <italic>m</italic> either 1 or 2. This fits yield correction factors <italic>c</italic><sub><italic>corr</italic></sub> and cycling rates <inline-formula><mml:math id="M8"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M9"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>).</p><p id="P117"><italic>c</italic><sub><italic>corr</italic></sub> is dimensionless and accounts for variability between assays. It ought to be close to 1.0 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S8</xref>).</p><p id="P118"><italic>K</italic><sub>1</sub> and <italic>K</italic><sub>2</sub> represent corrected version of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M10"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M11"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> obtained from the GTPase serial dilutions <inline-formula><mml:math id="M12"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p><p id="P119"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M13"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M14"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> represents the overall hydrolysis rate contribution connected to effectors. They depend linearly on the corrected GTPase concentration, but also on the respective effector concentrations, either linearly or quadratically.</p><p id="P120">Note, in order to analyse GTPase - effector mixtures, <italic>k</italic><sub>1</sub> and <italic>k</italic><sub>2</sub> must be known. It is thus required to fit data of GTPase (serial) dilutions first. The model allows to fit GTPase - effecotr mixtures of up to two effectors present, with each effector showing either a linear or quadratic concentration dependence. If the effectors show neither of these concentration-dependencies (e.g. due to saturation), we advice to either only include the linear/quadratic regimes into the analysis or extend our fitting model to match the specific case. With the provided software it thus is possible to fit the following protein (mixtures):
<list list-type="bullet" id="L10"><list-item><p id="P121">GTPase serial dilution (example 1)</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P122">GTPase + effector serial dilution (linear or quadratic conc. dependence, <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD4">Eq. 4</xref>) (example 2)</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P123">GTPase + effector <italic>X</italic>1 serial dilutions + effector <italic>X</italic>2 serial dilutons (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD5">Eq. 5</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>) (example 2)</p></list-item></list></p><p id="P124">The model is based on our observation that the amount of remaining GTP declines exponentially with time (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S4</xref>). It is still advisable to verified that this is also true for the proteins (GTPase enzymes and GTPase:effector mixtures) and incubation times intended to be used.</p><p id="P125">The model code analyses data of each GTPase assay individually and then generates pooled rate values (details on weighting of <italic>k</italic> for pooling and error propagation are given in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S11</xref>) The analysis code allows to exclude GTPase assays from pooling if <italic>c</italic><sub><italic>corr</italic></sub> values or standard errors of <italic>k</italic> are out of range. Decision criteria are set in the code using two parameters (see steps below):
<list list-type="order" id="L11"><list-item><p id="P126"><monospace>conc_corr_bounds</monospace> states which range of <italic>c</italic><sub><italic>corr</italic></sub> allows assays to be included in the pooling.</p><p id="P127">As c<sub>corr</sub> is expected to be close to 1.0, it is generally advisable to set in particular the lower bound not too close to 0, as such low values are indicative that the inferred activity of the GTPase is unusually low in this assay.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P128"><monospace>k_low_err_filt.’GTPase-name’</monospace> states if assays containing this particular GTPase that have low standard errors (1e-10 or lower) on the <italic>k</italic> values are excluded from pooling. This parameter must be declared for each GTPase individually.</p><p id="P129">In general it is advisable to set this parameter to ‘true’, i.e. assays with low standard errors will be excluded.</p><p id="P130">If, however, a GTPase is domineered by k<sub>2</sub> (and has k<sub>1</sub> ≈ 0 and thus std.err(k<sub>1</sub>)≈0), this parameter needs to be set to ‘false’ to still allow for pooling of k. In many cases this can not be known before an initial analysis. If chosen inappropriately, the parameter simply needs to be changed and the code needs to be re-run.</p></list-item></list></p><p id="P131">In the following we first describe the general protocol steps, which we will specify for both data of example 1 and example 2 thereafter.</p><sec id="S23"><title>Necessary resources</title><list list-type="bullet" id="L12"><list-item><p id="P132">spreadsheet editor</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P133">Matlab software license</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P134">Matlab analysis scripts and example data files encompassing this protocol</p></list-item></list></sec><sec id="S24"><title>General protocol steps</title><list list-type="order" id="L13"><list-item><p id="P135">Set up the matlab environment. To run the code, ensure that all required files are present:</p><p id="P136"><fig id="F14" position="anchor"><graphic xlink:href="EMS191778-f014"/></fig>
</p><p id="P137"><italic>Assay data (‘assaydata.xlsx’) must follow the formatting described at the end of Support Protocol 1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref>). Core of the fitting of the model occurs in the function</italic> <monospace>Crocodile_model.m.</monospace> <italic>This function determines which model scenario of effectors applies, and then generates fit results. To plot these</italic>, <monospace>plot_rate_data.m</monospace> <italic>is required, which uses colormaps from</italic> <monospace>useful_colormaps.m</monospace> <italic>(containing a colourmap from [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">Smith et al., 2015</xref>]). When needed, an unequal variance t-test</italic> <monospace>(Unequal_var_t_test.m)</monospace> <italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">Ruxton, 2006</xref>], to test for non-zero interactions between effectors. From the main function</italic> <monospace>Process_assay.m</monospace> <italic>a predefined spreadsheet list is read using</italic> <monospace>Read_assay_list.m,</monospace> <italic>to determine which data sets to use and how these are built up. The data is then read using</italic> <monospace>extract_activity_data.m</monospace> <italic>and passed to</italic> <monospace>Crocodile_model.m.</monospace></p></list-item><list-item><p id="P138">Define the processing of the data in the ‘assaylist.xlsx’ speadsheet. Follow the formatting provided in the example files (discussed in the next sections). The following sections are required:
<list list-type="bullet" id="L14"><list-item><p id="P139">Assay name: Gives an internal assay name. This name will be used in the output to refer to this data.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P140">Proteins: These are the names of proteins whose concentration varies within the assay. State each protein in a separate column. At maximum 2 proteins can be varied per assay. GTPase ref.: State the assay name where the GTPae protein used in this assay was varied. Ensure that this assay is processed already (i.e. earlier in the list).</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P141">Data file location: State the relevant file location.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P142">Relevant tab names: State which tab of the data file should be used.</p></list-item></list></p></list-item><list-item><p id="P143">Open Process_assays.m. Define the input parameters and processing options:</p><p id="P144"><preformat>
%% Input parameters
AssayListName = ‘. xlsx ‘ ;
% State the assaylist file name
GTPases = { ‘ ‘ } ;
% state proteins (that are stated in the assaylist file) that are GTPases
LinFitEffector = { ‘ ‘ } ;
% state proteins X (that are stated in the assaylist file) that should be
% fitted with a linear fit : k_3, X [ GTPase ] [X]
Quad Fit Effector = { ‘ ‘ } ;
% state proteins X (that are stated in the assaylist file) that should be
% fittd with a quadratic fit : k_3, X [ GTPase ] [ X]^2
act_corr = true (1) ;
% Logical to determine whether terms in the rate equation that depend on
% [ GTPase ] are corrected for run− specific GTPase activity / concentration
% differences
num_draws = 1e5 ;
% Number of random draws from distribution of rate parameters k
plot_fits = true (1) ;
% Logical indicating whether fits should be outputted in. pdf and. tiff
% (false is faster)
print_fits = true (1) ;
% Logical indicating whether fit results should be printed in the command window
GTP_filt = true (1) ;
% Logical indicating whether data points 0.00 − 0.05 % GTP remaining
% should be disregarded for the fits
conc_corr_bounds = [ 0. 5 1. 5 ] ;
% Two−element vector that states a c_corr lower and upper bound. Assays that
% have c_corr values within this range will be included in pooling of
% estimates. [0 Inf ] means assays with any c_corr value will be included.
% We recommend [ 0. 5 1. 5 ] : assays with c_corr values from 0. 5 to 1. 5 will be
% included.
k_l o w_err_filt. ‘ GTPase−name ‘ = fa l s e ;
% Logical that states per GTPase whether to discard runs from pooling that
% have very low standard errors (1 e−10 or lower) on the k values.
% If nothing is provided for a GTPase, default is true (i e. runs with low
% standard errors will be excluded).</preformat></p></list-item><list-item><p id="P145">Run <monospace>Process_assays.m</monospace>.</p><p id="P146">Using processing options shown above, the script will generate a folder ‘Figures’ (where all plots are saved), a spead-sheet ‘Data_summary.xlsx’ (summarising all fitting parameters) and a ‘Data_assays.mat’ file (saved in the ‘Data’ folder). ‘Data_assays.mat’ and plotting functions discussed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S10</xref> can be used generate plots based on the fits conducted here.</p></list-item></list></sec><sec id="S25"><title>Protocol steps: Simple assay (example 1: Ras GTPase)</title><p id="P147">We here show the specific protocol steps to run data of example 1: For this example a GTPase assay containing only serial dilutions Ras GTPase was conducted twice. Assay steps were described in the basic protocol and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S2</xref>. Basic analysis of the assay data was described in Support Protocol 1 (and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S9</xref>), resulting in data shown in ‘example1.xlsx’ tab: ‘matlab’. The data of each individual assay will be fitted with the model: <disp-formula id="FD6"><mml:math id="M15"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mtext>GTP</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mtext>GTP</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>exp</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mtext>using</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mtext>GTP</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mtext>and</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mtext>Ras</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mtext>Ras</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="P148">resulting one <italic>k</italic><sub>1</sub> and <italic>k</italic>2 each. A pooled estimate of <italic>k</italic><sub>1</sub> and <italic>k</italic>2 will be generated.</p><sec id="S26"><title>Steps</title><list list-type="order" id="L15"><list-item><p id="P149">Set up the matlab environment. To run the code, ensure that all required files are present:</p><p id="P150"><fig id="F15" position="anchor"><graphic xlink:href="EMS191778-f015"/></fig></p></list-item><list-item><p id="P151">Define the processing of the data in the ‘assaylist-example1.xlsx’ speadsheet.</p><p id="P152"><table-wrap id="T5" orientation="portrait" position="anchor"><table frame="box" rules="all"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" style="background-color: #E6E6E6;">Assay name</th><th valign="top" align="left" style="background-color: #E6E6E6;">Proteins</th><th valign="top" align="left" style="background-color: #E6E6E6;">GTPase ref.</th><th valign="top" align="left" style="background-color: #E6E6E6;">Datafile location</th><th valign="top" align="left" style="background-color: #E6E6E6;">Relevant tab names</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left">Ras</td><td valign="top" align="left">Ras</td><td valign="top" align="left"/><td valign="top" align="left">./Data/examplel.xlsx</td><td valign="top" align="left">matlab</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="P153">Example 1 entails two assays of Ras serial dilutions, which are stored in ‘example1.xlsx’ in tab ‘matlab’. Because the concentration of Ras is varied in each assay, ‘Proteins’ states ‘Ras’.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P154">Open <monospace>Process_assays.m</monospace>. Define the input parameters:</p><p id="P155"><preformat>AssayListName = ‘ Assaylist −example1. xlsx ‘ ;
GTPases = { ‘ Ras ‘ } ;
LinFitEffector = { ‘ ‘ } ;
Quad Fit Effector = { ‘ ‘ } ;
act_corr = true (1) ;
num_draws = 1e5 ;
plot_fits = true (1) ;
print_fits = true (1) ;
GTP_filt = true (1) ;
conc_corr_bounds = [ 0. 5 1. 5 ] ;
k_low_err_filt. Ras = false ;</preformat></p></list-item><list-item><p id="P156">Run <monospace>Process_assays.m.</monospace></p><p id="P157">Using processing options shown above, the script will generate a folder ‘Figures’ (where all plots are saved), a spead-sheet ‘Data_summary.xlsx’ (summarising all fitting parameters) and a ‘Data_assays.mat’ file (saved in the ‘Data’ folder). ‘Data_assays.mat’ and plotting functions discussed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S10</xref> can be used generate plots based on the fits conducted here. The data this script ought to generate can be found in the folder ‘example1 matlab output’.</p></list-item></list></sec></sec><sec id="S27"><title>Protocol steps: Elaborate assay set (example 2: GTPase effector mixtures)</title><p id="P158">We here show the specific protocol steps to run data of example 2: Example 2 entails GTPase assay data (‘example2.xlsx’) of several protein mixtures (also see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>):
<list list-type="simple" id="L16"><list-item><label>(A)</label><p id="P159">GTPase assays in which the GTPase Cdc42 is varied (all in tab: ‘dCdc42’).</p></list-item><list-item><label>(B)</label><p id="P160">GTPase assays using a constant Cdc42 concentration and serial dilutions of the GEF Cdc24 (all in tab: ‘Cdc42-dCdc24’).</p></list-item><list-item><label>(C)</label><p id="P161">GTPase assays using a constant Cdc42 concentration and serial dilutions of the GAP Rga2 (all in tab: ‘Cdc42-dRga2’). (D) GTPase assays using a constant Cdc42 concentration and serial dilutions of both GEF Cdc24 and GAP Rga2 (all in tab: ‘Cdc42-dCdc24-dRga2’).</p></list-item></list></p><p id="P162">The data of each individual assay will be fitted with the model: <disp-formula id="FD7"><mml:math id="M16"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mtext>GTP</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mtext>GTP</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>exp</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mtext>using</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mtext>GTP</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mtext>and</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mn>24</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mn>24</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mtext>Cdc</mml:mtext><mml:mn>42</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mtext>Cdc</mml:mtext><mml:mn>42</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mn>24</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mtext>Cdc</mml:mtext><mml:mn>24</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mtext>Cdc</mml:mtext><mml:mn>42</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mtext>Rga</mml:mtext><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mtext>Cdc</mml:mtext><mml:mn>42</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mn>24</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mtext>Cdc</mml:mtext><mml:mn>24</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mtext>Rga</mml:mtext><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mtext>Cdc</mml:mtext><mml:mn>42</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="P163">resulting for each assay one set of fitting parameters. Assays of group (A) yield <italic>k</italic><sub>1</sub>, <italic>k</italic><sub>2</sub>. Assays of group (B) yield <italic>k</italic><sub>3,<italic>Cdc</italic>24</sub>, <italic>c</italic><sub><italic>corr</italic></sub>. Assays of group (C) yield <italic>k</italic><sub>3,<italic>Rga</italic>2</sub>, <italic>c</italic><sub><italic>corr</italic></sub>. And assays of group (C) yield <italic>k</italic><sub>3,<italic>Cdc</italic>24</sub>, <italic>k</italic><sub>3,<italic>Rga</italic>2</sub>, <italic>k</italic><sub>3,<italic>Cdc</italic>24,<italic>Rga</italic>2</sub>, <italic>c</italic><sub><italic>corr</italic></sub>. A pooled estimate of all cycling rates <italic>k</italic> will be generated.</p><sec id="S28"><title>Steps</title><list list-type="order" id="L17"><list-item><p id="P164">Set up the matlab environment. To run the code, ensure that all required files are present:</p><p id="P165"><fig id="F16" position="anchor"><graphic xlink:href="EMS191778-f016"/></fig></p></list-item><list-item><p id="P166">Define the processing of the data in the ‘assaylist-example2.xlsx’ speadsheet.</p><p id="P167"><table-wrap id="T6" orientation="portrait" position="anchor"><table frame="box" rules="all"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" style="background-color: #E6E6E6">Assay name</th><th valign="top" align="left" colspan="2" style="background-color: #E6E6E6">Proteins</th><th valign="top" align="left" style="background-color: #E6E6E6">GTPase ref.</th><th valign="top" align="left" style="background-color: #E6E6E6">Datafile location</th><th valign="top" align="left" style="background-color: #E6E6E6">Relevant tab names</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-left: 1px solid">C42</td><td valign="top" align="left">Cdc42</td><td valign="top" align="left"/><td valign="top" align="left"/><td valign="top" align="left">./Data/example2-matlab.xlsx</td><td valign="top" align="left">dCdc42</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-left: 1px solid">C42-C24</td><td valign="top" align="left">Cdc24</td><td valign="top" align="left"/><td valign="top" align="left">C42</td><td valign="top" align="left">./Data/example2-matlab.xlsx</td><td valign="top" align="left">Cdc42-dCdc24</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-left: 1px solid">C42-R2</td><td valign="top" align="left">Rga2</td><td valign="top" align="left"/><td valign="top" align="left" style="color: #1B1B1B">C42</td><td valign="top" align="left">./Data/example2-matlab.xlsx</td><td valign="top" align="left">Cdc42-dRga2</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-left: 1px solid">C42-C24-R2</td><td valign="top" align="left">Cdc24</td><td valign="top" align="left">Rga2</td><td valign="top" align="left">C42</td><td valign="top" align="left">./Data/example2-matlab.xlsx</td><td valign="top" align="left">Cdc42-dCdc24-dRga2</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="P168">To analyse this assay set, first all data with varied Cdc42 needs to be fitted. We give these assays the name ‘C42’. Because Cdc42 is varied, ‘Proteins’ states ‘Cdc42’.</p><p id="P169">Then, Cdc42-effector mixtures can be analysed. We call assays with Cdc42-Cdc24 mixtures ‘C42-C24’. They include a constant concentration of Cdc42 and varied concentrations of Cdc24. Hence, ‘Proteins’ states ‘Cdc24’ (it does not state ‘Cdc42’ as well because the Cdc42 concentration is constant in these assays). To fit these assay data we want to use the rates of Cdc42 obtained in the line above, so we need to refer to ‘C42’ in ‘GTPase ref.’ (also see <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD3">Eq. 3</xref>,<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD4">4</xref>).</p><p id="P170">We apply the same logic to Cdc42-Rga2 assay data, which we call ‘C42-R2’.</p><p id="P171">We call assays in which both Cdc24 and Rga2 is varied ‘C42-C24-R2’. Here ‘Proteins’ states ‘Cdc24’ and ‘Rga2’ (because both proteins are varied), and ‘GTPase ref.’ states ‘C42’ to refer to the Cdc42 assay analysis in the first line.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P172">Open <monospace>Process_assays.m</monospace>. Define the input parameters:</p><p id="P173"><preformat>AssayListName = ‘ Assaylist −example2. xlsx ‘ ;
GTPases = { ‘ Cdc42 ‘ } ;
LinFitEffector = { ‘ Rga2 ‘ } ;
Quad Fit Effector = { ‘ Cdc24 ‘ } ;
act_corr = true (1) ;
num_draws = 1e5 ;
plot_fits = true (1) ;
print_fits = true (1) ;
GTP_filt = true (1) ;
conc_corr_bounds = [ 0. 5 1. 5 ] ;
k_low_err_filt. Cdc42 = true ;</preformat></p></list-item><list-item><p id="P174">Run <monospace>Process_assays.m.</monospace></p><p id="P175">Using processing options shown above, the script will generate a folder ‘Figures’ (where all plots are saved), a spead-sheet ‘Data_summary.xlsx’ (summarising all fitting parameters) and a ‘Data_assays.mat’ file (saved in the ‘Data’ folder). ‘Data_assays.mat’ and plotting functions discussed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S10</xref> can be used generate plots based on the fits conducted here. The data this script ought to generate can be found in the folder ‘example2 matlab output’.</p></list-item></list></sec></sec><sec id="S29"><title>Protocol steps: Combined analysis of several assays</title><p id="P176">It is also possible to analyse assay data of example 1 and example 2 in one go. In order to do so, simply combine the inputs of the two previous examples.
<list list-type="order" id="L18"><list-item><p id="P177">Set up the matlab environment. To run the code, ensure that all required files are present:</p><p id="P178"><fig id="F17" position="anchor"><graphic xlink:href="EMS191778-f017"/></fig></p></list-item><list-item><p id="P179">Define the processing of the data in the ‘assaylist-example1and2.xlsx’ speadsheet.</p><p id="P180"><table-wrap id="T7" orientation="portrait" position="anchor"><table frame="box" rules="all"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" style="background-color: #E6E6E6">Assay name</th><th valign="top" align="left" style="background-color: #E6E6E6">Proteins</th><th valign="top" align="left" style="background-color: #E6E6E6;"/><th valign="top" align="left" style="background-color: #E6E6E6">GTPase ref.</th><th valign="top" align="left" style="background-color: #E6E6E6">Datafile location</th><th valign="top" align="left" style="background-color: #E6E6E6">Relevant tab names</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-left: 1px solid">Ras</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="color: #1B1B1B">Ras</td><td valign="top" align="left"/><td valign="top" align="left"/><td valign="top" align="left" style="color: #1B1B1B">./Data/examplel.xlsx</td><td valign="top" align="left">matlab</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-left: 1px solid #000000;">C42</td><td valign="top" align="left">Cdc42</td><td valign="top" align="left"/><td valign="top" align="left"/><td valign="top" align="left">./Data/example2-matlab.xlsx</td><td valign="top" align="left">dCdc42</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-left: 1px solid #000000;">C42-C24</td><td valign="top" align="left">Cdc24</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="color: #1B1B1B;"/><td valign="top" align="left" style="color: #1B1B1B">C42</td><td valign="top" align="left">./Data/example2-matlab.xlsx</td><td valign="top" align="left">Cdc42-dCdc24</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-left: 1px solid #000000;">C42-R2</td><td valign="top" align="left">Rga2</td><td valign="top" align="left"/><td valign="top" align="left">C42</td><td valign="top" align="left">./Data/example2-matlab.xlsx</td><td valign="top" align="left">Cdc42-dRga2</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-left: 1px solid">C42-C24-R2</td><td valign="top" align="left">Cdc24</td><td valign="top" align="left">Rga2</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="color: #1B1B1B">C42</td><td valign="top" align="left">./Data/example2-matlab.xlsx</td><td valign="top" align="left">Cdc42-dCdc24-dRga2</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></list-item><list-item><p id="P181">Open <monospace>Process_assays.m.</monospace> Define the input parameters:</p><p id="P182"><preformat>AssayListName = ‘ Assaylist −example1and2. xlsx ‘ ;
GTPases = { ‘ Ras ‘, ‘ Cdc42 ‘ } ;
LinFitEffector = { ‘ Rga2 ‘ } ;
Quad Fit Effector = { ‘ Cdc24 ‘ } ;
act_corr = true (1) ;
num_draws = 1e5 ;
plot_fits = true (1) ;
print_fits = true (1) ;
GTP_filt = true (1) ;
conc_corr_bounds = [ 0. 5 1. 5 ] ;
k_low_err_filt. Ras = false ;
k_low_err_filt. Cdc42 = true ;</preformat></p></list-item><list-item><p id="P183">Run <monospace>Process_assays.m.</monospace></p><p id="P184">Using processing options shown above, the script will generate a folder ‘Figures’ (where all plots are saved), a spead-sheet ‘Data_summary.xlsx’ (summarising all fitting parameters) and a ‘Data_assays.mat’ file (saved in the ‘Data’ folder). ‘Data_assays.mat’ and plotting functions discussed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S10</xref> can be used generate plots based on the fits conducted here. The data this script ought to generate can be found in the folder ‘example1and2 matlab output’.</p></list-item></list></p></sec></sec><sec id="S30"><title>Reagents and solutions</title><sec id="S31"><title>Commentary</title><sec id="S32"><title>Background Information</title><p id="P185">In the GTPase assay the proteins of interest (GTPase enzymes with or without effectors) are incubated with GTP for a certain amount of time for GTPase cycling to occur, hydrolysing GTP to GDP and free phoshate. Then the reaction is stopped through addition of Glo solution, which contains a nucleoside-diphosphate kinase and ADP. The kinase converts the remaining GTP to ATP. Addition of the detection reagent, containing a luciferase/luciferin mixture, makes the ATP luminescent, which is measured using a plate reader in luminescence mode (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">Promega Corporation, 2015</xref>]. The luminescence signal correlates with the amount of remaining GTP (in inversly correlates with the activity of the GTPase): the higher the luminescence values, the more GTP remainded in soluion (and thus the less active the GTPase is). Low or no luminescence corresponds to very little or no remaining GTP and a higher GTPase activity.</p><p id="P186">The GTPase Glo™ assay examines the entire GTPase cycle of the respective GTPase. An assay that examines all steps of the GTPase cycle can be advantageous: For one, it allows investigation of GTPase activities and GTPase effector interactions. The obtained rates might be more comparable to those observed <italic>in vivo</italic> (in contrast to other <italic>in vitro</italic> assays that only examine one specific step of the GTPase cycle), as GTPase cycling constantly occurs <italic>in vivo</italic>. Further, it enables comparison of the strength of effectors that act on different steps of the GTPase cycle, such as GEFs and GAPs. Also, effector interplay can be studied. The origin of these advantages is also at the centre of the assay’s disadvantage: Because GTPase cycling (multiple completions of the entire GTPase cycle) is studied, the origin of observed effects remain elusive. It is less suitable if detailed mechanistic features of a GTPase cycle step ought to be investigated. For this, other GTPase assasy, such as the MESG/phosphorylase system [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">Zhang et al., 1997</xref>] or N-methylanthraniloyl-GTP/GDP [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">Rapali et al., 2017</xref>] system, which examine only the GTP hydrolysis or GDP release step.</p></sec><sec id="S33"><title>Critical Parameters</title><p id="P187">The GTPase assay is sensitive to small pipetting errors, changes in buffer and assay components. We <italic>strongly</italic> recommend a mise-en-place procedure, in which each assay is carefully planned (e.g. use one of the templates provided in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S1</xref>) and the materials are prepared before the assay is stared. This greatly reduce the likelihood of errors due to inattentiveness, hurry/time stress, and chaos. Accurate pipetting is essential for this assay!</p><p id="P188">Further, we advice to
<list list-type="bullet" id="L19"><list-item><p id="P189">aliquot and vortex all components before use (except the Glo reagent)</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P190">dialyse all proteins into the same buffer</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P191">include control samples such as a buffer row in the beginning and end of the plate, a positive control (Ras GTPase enzyme), and potentially inert proteins to account for non-canonical effects</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P192">always prepare the 2× GTP solution, 1mM ADP, and Glo solution freshly and to never re-use/store it</p></list-item></list></p><p id="P193">If executed properly, the assay leads to reliable and reproducible results (e.g. see [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">Tschirpke et al., 2023b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">Tschirpke et al., 2023a</xref>]).</p></sec><sec id="S34"><title>Troubleshooting</title><p id="P194">For a detailed troubleshooting on basic problems such as
<list list-type="bullet" id="L20"><list-item><p id="P195">no change in luminescence with increasing or decreasing concentration of GTPase, GAP or GEF</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P196">low signal-to-background ratio</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P197">high luminescent signal</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P198">low luminescent signal</p></list-item></list></p><p id="P199">please consult the user manual of GTPase Glo™ assay kits [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">Promega Corporation, 2015</xref>], we here (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T4">Tab. 4</xref>) only discuss these issues briefly.</p></sec><sec id="S35"><title>Understanding Results</title><p id="P200">The GTPase assay yields luminescence values, which are translated into amount of remaining GTP. These values can be fitted with GTPase cycling rates <italic>k</italic>. Using example 1 luminescence and cycling rates <italic>k</italic><sub>1</sub>, <italic>k</italic><sub>2</sub> and their pooling will be discussed. Example 2 discusses assay correction factors <italic>c</italic><sub><italic>corr</italic></sub> and cycling rates <italic>k</italic><sub>3,<italic>X</italic></sub>.</p><p id="P201">Example 1</p><p id="P202">In example 1 GTPase assay data for 5 serial dilutions of Ras GTPase were collected. The basic assay steps are described in the Basic Protocol (and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S2</xref>), and their subsequent analysis is outlined in Support Protocol 1 and Support Protocol 2.</p></sec><sec id="S36"><title>Luminescence</title><p id="P203">Basic protocol yields luminescence values, from which the amount of remaining GTP is calculated (Support Protocol 1). The luminescence values of the buffer rows should always be quite similar, although a small shift can be observed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7</xref> (top)). If this shifts gets big, the error bars of the entire assay will increase (because the buffer wells are used for normalisation). Dilutions of Ras need to show lower luminescence values than the buffer (because Ras is a GT-Pase and hydrolyses GTP, which correlates with luminescence (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>)). With increasing Ras concentration, the luminescence should drop. Replicas/wells containing the same Ras concentration should have the same luminescence (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7</xref> (bottom)). The bigger their spread, the bigger the error will be. In some cases we observe a small decrease of the luminescence over time (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7</xref>). As long as this decrease is not drastic and occurs in all wells to roughly the same extend, it will not impact the analysis. Assays in which the luminescence decreases drastically within 20 min should be discarded from further analysis, as well as wells that behave differently than the majority.</p><p id="P204">According to the assay manual, the luminescence should be measured after 5 min. We average the luminescence values from 5-20 min for every assay, to smoothen out possible small deviations in the luminescence curve. The exact time window (as long as it begins after 5 min) is less important than choosing exactly the same time window for every assay.</p><p id="P205">The luminescence values are used to calculate the amount of remaining GTP (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref>). It is possible to use these values to compare the activity of different GTPases, the activity of two different effectors on a GTPase, or the activity of one effector on different GTPases, as long as all samples are part of the same assay (to avoid small variability between assays) and are used in the same concentration.</p></sec><sec id="S37"><title>GTPase cycling rates<italic>k</italic><sub>1</sub>, <italic>k</italic><sub>2</sub></title><p id="P206">To increase comparability of GTPase and effector activities, we developed a GTPase cycling model (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S8</xref>). Support Protocol 2 describes how the model can be used to fit data of Ras. In short, we fit an exponential to the amount of remaining GTP (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S8</xref>): <disp-formula id="FD8"><mml:math id="M17"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mtext>GTP</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mtext>GTP</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>exp</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mtext>using</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mtext>GTP</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mtext>and</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mtext>Ras</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mtext>Ras</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="P207">Here <italic>K</italic> refers to the ‘overall GTP hydrolysis rate’ and depends on the concentration of the GTPase Ras. GTPase cycling rates <italic>k</italic> describe the rate of the <italic>entire</italic> GTPase cycle of Ras.</p><p id="P208">The model fits two cycling rates (<italic>k</italic><sub>1</sub> and <italic>k</italic><sub>2</sub>) for every GTPase (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD3">Eq. 3</xref>). <italic>K</italic><sub>1</sub> accounts for the linear contribution of the GTPase (<italic>K</italic><sub>1</sub> = <italic>k</italic><sub>1</sub> [GTPase]). <italic>K</italic><sub>2</sub> accounts for the quadratic contribution (<italic>K</italic><sub>2</sub> = <italic>k</italic><sub>2</sub> [GTPase]<sup>2</sup>) which can be due to dimerisation or other cooperative effects increasing the activity of the enzyme (for examples, see [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">Zhang et al., 1999</xref>]). The bigger the <italic>K</italic><sub>2</sub>/<italic>K</italic><sub>1</sub> ratio, the bigger the contribution of the non-linear term. This can suggest that the GTPase forms a dimer that is more active than the monomer. However, additional studies examining GTPase di-/oligomerisation are required before making such a deduction. The data indicates that some effect leads to a non-linear concentration dependence of the rate <italic>K</italic>. It does not reveal its origin. Ras does not show a linear concentration dependence (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8</xref>) and is domineered by <italic>k</italic><sub>2</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 9</xref>: <italic>k</italic><sub>2</sub> &gt;&gt;&gt; <italic>k</italic><sub>1</sub>). In this case this is likely due to dimerisation - Ras GTPases are known to dimerise.</p></sec><sec id="S38"><title>Output file structure and pooling of rates <italic>k</italic></title><p id="P209">Estimates of Ras GTPase cycling rates <italic>k</italic><sub>1</sub> and <italic>k</italic><sub>2</sub> are summarised in ‘Data_summay.xlsx’ (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 9</xref>). The file is structured in the following way: The column ‘Run’ shows the assay number, followed by two ‘varied protein’ colmuns stating which protein(s) were varied in the assay (i.e. for which proteins several dilutions were used). If the assay contains only one varied protein, the second column is empty (as it is the case for example 1: here only Ras was used). Then Parameter 1 is named, and its values, 95% upper and lower bound, and standard error is shown. The same is repeated for possible parameters 2 and 3. The last column show adjusted R<sup>2</sup> of the fit and a Boolean if the experiment is used for pooling (‘Used for pooling’).</p><p id="P210">For each assay (row, ‘Run’: E1, E2) the rate value estimates are shown. Below, in the row which contains ‘pooled’ in the ‘Run’ column, the pooled values of <italic>k</italic> estimates are stated (details on weighting of <italic>k</italic> for pooling and error propagation are given in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S11</xref>) The column ‘varied protein’ states which proteins were varied in the assay (i.e. for which proteins several dilutions were used). ‘Used for pooling’ indicates if experiment is used for pooling.</p><p id="P211">An experiment can be excluded from pooling if <italic>c</italic><sub><italic>corr</italic></sub> or standard errors of <italic>k</italic> are out of range. Decision criteria are set before analysing the data using two parameters (see Support Protocol 2): (1) <monospace>conc_corr_bounds</monospace> states which range of <italic>c</italic><sub><italic>corr</italic></sub> allows assays to be included in the pooling. (2) <monospace>k_low_err_filt.Ras</monospace> states if assays with low standard errors (1e-10 or lower) on the <italic>k</italic> values are excluded from pooling. In Support Protocol 2 (example 1) we used</p><p id="P212">conc_corr_bounds = [ 0. 5 1. 5 ] ;</p><p id="P213">k_low_err_filt. Ras = false ;</p><p id="P214">for analysing Ras data. <monospace>conc_corr_bounds</monospace> states which range of <italic>c</italic><sub><italic>corr</italic></sub> allows assays to be included in the pooling. It does not influence pooling of <italic>k</italic><sub>1</sub> and <italic>k</italic><sub>2</sub>, as <italic>c</italic><sub><italic>corr</italic></sub> only is used for fitting <italic>k</italic><sub>3,<italic>X</italic></sub> (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD4">Eq. 4</xref>,<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD5">5</xref>). We set <monospace>k_low_err_filt.Ras</monospace> to ‘false’ - experiments with low standard errors on <italic>k</italic> values are <italic>not</italic> excluded from pooling. This makes sense for Ras, as Ras is dominated by <italic>k</italic><sub>2</sub> has <italic>k</italic><sub>1</sub> ≈ 0 (and thus <italic>k</italic><sub>1</sub> errors are close to 0).</p><sec id="S39"><title>Example 2</title><p id="P215">For this example data of a set of GTPase assays is provided, including GTPase assays of
<list list-type="simple" id="L21"><list-item><label>(A)</label><p id="P216">Cdc42 dilutions (GTPase enzyme),</p></list-item><list-item><label>(B)</label><p id="P217">Cdc24 (GEF) dilutions using a constant Cdc42 concentration,</p></list-item><list-item><label>(C)</label><p id="P218">Rga2 (GAP) dilutions using a constant Cdc42 concentration, and</p></list-item><list-item><label>(D)</label><p id="P219">Cdc24 (GEF) dilutions and Rga2 (GAP) dilutions using a constant Cdc42 concentration.</p></list-item></list></p><p id="P220">The analysis is described in Support Protocol 2. In short, a GTPase cycling model (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S8</xref>) is fitted: <disp-formula id="FD9"><mml:math id="M18"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mtext>GTP</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mtext>GTP</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>exp</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mtext>using</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mtext>GTP</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mtext>and</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mn>24</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mn>24</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mtext>Cdc</mml:mtext><mml:mn>42</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mtext>Cdc</mml:mtext><mml:mn>42</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mn>24</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mtext>Cdc</mml:mtext><mml:mn>24</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mtext>Cdc</mml:mtext><mml:mn>42</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mtext>Rga</mml:mtext><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mtext>Cdc</mml:mtext><mml:mn>42</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mn>24</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mtext>Cdc</mml:mtext><mml:mn>24</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mtext>Rga</mml:mtext><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mtext>Cdc</mml:mtext><mml:mn>42</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="P221">Here <italic>K</italic> refers to the ‘overall GTP hydrolysis rate’ and depends on the concentration of the GTPase (and effector <italic>X</italic>).</p><p id="P222">First data of Cdc42 serial dilutions (data (A)) are fitted with an exponential to obtain estimates of GTPase cycling rates <italic>k</italic><sub>1</sub> and <italic>k</italic><sub>2</sub> for each experiment. These estimates are then bundled to get a isngle pooled estimate for <italic>k</italic><sub>1</sub> and <italic>k</italic><sub>2</sub>. Then, Cdc42 - Cdc24, Cdc42 - Rga2, and Cdc42 - Cdc24 - Rga2 mixtures (data (B), (C), (D)) are fitted to obtain estimates for the correction factors <italic>c</italic><sub><italic>corr</italic></sub> and cycling rates <italic>k</italic><sub>3</sub> (measuring the impact of the effector on GTPase cycling) for every experiment. These latter estimates can then be pooled to get single estimate for the <italic>k</italic><sub>3</sub>’s (a pooled estimate for <italic>c</italic><sub><italic>corr</italic></sub> has no function here).</p></sec></sec><sec id="S40"><title>Correction factors <italic>c</italic><sub><italic>corr</italic></sub></title><p id="P223">The correction factor <italic>c</italic><sub><italic>corr</italic></sub> accounts for variability between assays, i.e. for the observation that the rates for the GTPase can vary between assays. Possible reasons for this include small concentration differences introduced though pipetting of small volumes (as are required for this assay), temperature and shaker speed fluctuations during the incubation step, small changes in effective GTPase concentration through sequestration of GTPases in complexes with effectors, and/or intrinsic changes in the protein activities due to other external conditions. <italic>c</italic><sub><italic>corr</italic></sub> maps all factors that lead to variations between assays onto the GTPase concentration. The correction factor is estimated for each experiment individually, relative to a predefined GTPase serial dilution assay. This is done by matching the overall hydrolysis rate at zero effector concentration inferred from the fit, to the estimated overall hydrolysis rate based on the GTPase serial dilution assay. Concretely, <italic>c</italic><sub><italic>corr</italic></sub> follows from: <disp-formula id="FD10"><mml:math id="M19"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mtext>GTPase</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mtext>GTPase</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mtext>with</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="P224">Where <inline-formula><mml:math id="M20"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M21"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> are the estimates of cycling rates from the GTPase serial dilution assay and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M22"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> are the estimated median of the overall hydrolysis rate fit at zero effector concentration value (i.e <inline-formula><mml:math id="M23"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>). By using random draws of the fitted overall hydrolysis rate distribution, we can also obtain a distribution for <italic>c</italic><sub><italic>corr</italic></sub> as well. Consequently, <italic>c</italic><sub><italic>corr</italic></sub> = 1.0 means that relative to the serial dilution assay with the same GTPase (= reference assay), the GTPase in this assay has the same intrinsic activity, which is optimal. This is optimal. <italic>c</italic><sub><italic>corr</italic></sub> = 0.5 means that relative to the reference assay, the GTPase in this assay is 50% less active, and <italic>c</italic><sub><italic>corr</italic></sub> = 1.5 means that that the GTPase in this assay is 50% more active. Very low correction values indicate that in the assay the GTPase is behaving differently than before (possibly because the conditions are different) or that a fundamental error occurred (e.g. large pipetting error). To ensure consistency within an assay set we advice to disregard that assay from further analysis.</p><p id="P225">To implement this recommendation, we used conc_corr_bounds = [0.5 1.5] for analysing the data set in Support Protocol 2 (example 1). This means that assays yielding <italic>c</italic><sub><italic>corr</italic></sub> values lower than 0.5 and larger than 1.5 will be excluded from pooling. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Fig. 10</xref> shows a histogram of all correction factors. Apart from one assay, which yielded <italic>c</italic><sub><italic>corr</italic></sub> ≈ 0.1, all <italic>c</italic><sub><italic>corr</italic></sub> values are within range, with most values being close to 1.</p><p id="P226">‘Data_summay.xlsx’ states correction factors as ‘parameter 1’ for assays in which either Cdc24 or Rga2 or both effectors are varied (‘Varied protein 1’, ‘varied protein 2’). Correction factor errors are discussed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S11</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="S41"><title>GTPase cycling rates <italic>k</italic><sub>3</sub></title><p id="P227">GTPase cycling rates <italic>k</italic> describe the rate of the <italic>entire</italic> GTPase cycle of the GTPase, or the effect of an effector on the overall rate. Cycling rates <italic>k</italic><sub>3,<italic>X</italic></sub> can thus describe how strongly an effector <italic>X</italic> affects the GTPase cycle, but do not reveal which step of the GTPase cycle the effector is acting upon or how strongly the effector is effecting this step (or if the effector acts on multiple steps). To investigate these mechanism, other GTPase assays (e.g. those mentioned in the background information section), need to be conducted.</p><p id="P228">Assays of group (B) are used to fit cycling rates <italic>k</italic><sub>3,<italic>Cdc</italic>24</sub> which describe the effect of the GEF Cdc24 on Cdc42’s overall GTPase cycle. We choose a quadratic fit (<italic>K</italic><sub>3,<italic>Cdc</italic>24</sub> = <italic>k</italic><sub>3,<italic>Cdc</italic>24</sub>[<italic>Cdc</italic>42][<italic>Cdc</italic>24]<sup>2</sup>) because the data showed a non-linear dependence of the overall rate <italic>K</italic> on the Cdc24 concentration (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Fig. 11</xref>). The fit is a phenomenological description of the data and does not reveal where the non-linearity originates from. One possibility could be dimerisation, with Cdc24 dimers exhibiting an increased activity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">Tschirpke et al., 2023a</xref>]. <italic>k</italic><sub>3,<italic>Cdc</italic>24</sub> values are shown ‘Data_summay.xlsx’ as ‘parameter 2’ for assays in which Cdc24 is varied (‘Varied protein 1’).</p><p id="P229">In a similar fashion, assays of group (C) are used to fit cycling rates <italic>k</italic><sub>3,<italic>Rga</italic>2</sub> which describe the effect of the GAP Rga2 on Cdc42’s overall GTPase cycle. A linear fit (<italic>K</italic><sub>3,<italic>Rga</italic>2</sub> = <italic>k</italic><sub>3,<italic>Rga</italic>2</sub>[<italic>Cdc</italic>42][<italic>Rga</italic>2]) was used to describe the data.</p><p id="P230">Data of group (D) contains Cdc42 - Cdc24, Cdc42 - Rga2, and Cdc42 - Cdc24 - Rga2 mixtures. In these assays both Cdc24 and Rga2 are varied (‘varied protein 1’, ‘varied protein 2’). The data is fitted with 3 rate parameters (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">Fig. 12</xref>): <italic>k</italic><sub>3,<italic>Cdc</italic>24</sub> (= ‘parameter 2’), <italic>k</italic><sub>3,<italic>Rga</italic>2</sub> (= ‘parameter 3’), <italic>k</italic><sub>3,<italic>Cdc</italic>24,<italic>Rga</italic>2</sub> (= ‘parameter 4’). <italic>k</italic><sub>3,<italic>Cdc</italic>24</sub> describes the effect of Cdc24 on the entire GTPase cycle and <italic>k</italic><sub>3,<italic>Rga</italic>2</sub> describes the effect of Rga2. These rates should be close to those obtained in assays including only Cdc42 - Cdc24 (or Cdc42-Rga2 mixtures) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">Fig. 13</xref>). a large difference can indicate a problem with the fit or the assay. The cycling rate <italic>k</italic><sub>3,<italic>Cdc</italic>24,<italic>Rga</italic>2</sub> accounts for any potential synergy between both proteins. <italic>k</italic><sub>3,<italic>Cdc</italic>24,<italic>Rga</italic>2</sub> = 0 means that there is no interaction between both proteins. <italic>k</italic><sub>3,<italic>Cdc</italic>24,<italic>Rga</italic>2</sub> &lt; 0 suggests that the proteins antagonise/ inhibit each other. <italic>k</italic><sub>3,<italic>Cdc</italic>24,<italic>Rga</italic>2</sub> &gt; 0 suggests that there is synergy. The term states if there is an interaction between both protein, i.e. if the combined effect of both proteins is bigger than the sum of their individual contributions to the <italic>overall</italic> rate. (The significance of the deviation from zero is is also tested using [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">Ruxton, 2006</xref>]. The p-value for the null hypothesis of zero interaction is stored in the ‘Data_assays.mat’ output file in the ‘Assays_processed’ variable, in the field of that assay, in the sub-field ‘k_tot’, under ‘Interaction_p’.) While a positive <italic>k</italic><sub>3,<italic>Cdc</italic>24,<italic>Rga</italic>2</sub> indicates that there is some synergy when both Cdc24 and Rga2 are added to Cdc42, it does not reveal the origin of the synergy. The origin could be due to physical protein-protein interactions or due to rate-limiting steps in the cycle, which are relieved once both proteins are added [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">Tschirpke et al., 2023a</xref>]. One has to thus be careful in the interpretation of this rate.</p></sec><sec id="S42"><title>Comparison of cycling rates <bold><italic>k</italic></bold></title><p id="P231">Overall GTP hydrolysis rates <italic>K</italic> are concentration dependent and have the unit <italic>h</italic><sup>−1</sup>. Cycling rates <italic>k</italic> are concentration-independent, but have different units and are therefor difficult to compare: <italic>k</italic><sub>1</sub> : [μM−1<italic>h</italic><sup>−1</sup>], <italic>k</italic><sub>2</sub> : [μM−2<italic>h</italic><sup>−1</sup>], <italic>k</italic><sub>3,<italic>Cdc</italic>24</sub> : [μM−3<italic>h</italic><sup>−1</sup>], <italic>k</italic><sub>3,<italic>Rga</italic>2</sub> : [μM−2<italic>h</italic><sup>−1</sup>], <italic>k</italic><sub>3,<italic>Cdc</italic>24,<italic>Rga</italic>2</sub> : [μM−4<italic>h</italic><sup>−1</sup>]. The easiest way to represent all rates in one plot is to plot overall GTP hydrolysis rates <italic>K</italic> for 1 μM of each protein (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">Fig. 13</xref>). However, one has to consider the different concentration-dependencies when interpreting/comparing the rates <italic>K</italic>. A rate that scales quadratically with protein concentration will be twice as big as a rate that scales linearly when doubling the protein concentration. Some rates might also just be valid for the regime in which they were fitted in (they might show saturation in higher concentration regimes). Thus, one has consider which protein concentrations one uses to calculate <italic>K</italic> (in order to make cycling rates <italic>k</italic> comparable).</p></sec><sec id="S43"><title>Time Considerations</title><p id="P232">GTPase assays usually take a few hours, of which time is consumed by incubation steps. For an assay involving 8 samples, including one Ras postive control and 5 serial dilutions of the GTPase of interest (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>), using an incubation time of 1.5 h, we estimate 0.5 h for preparation of materials and solutions, 2 h for conducting the assay, and another 0.5 h for the luminescence readout. This amounts to a total of 3 h, of which 2 h account for incubation/measurement steps.</p><p id="P233">Assays encompassing more samples may involve longer preparation times (as more protein dilutions need to be prepared), and longer incubation times subsequently also prolong the total amount of time spent.</p><p id="P234">If proteins need to be dialysed into a suitable buffer first, an additional overnight step of dialysis is required.</p><p id="P235">The analysis time depends on the level of automatisation and can range from only a few to 30-40 min. If the first step is done manually in Excel, we estimate 30 min for this step. The following analysis in Matlab requires only a few minutes of runtime.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="SM"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1"><label>Supplementary Materials</label><media xlink:href="EMS191778-supplement-Supplementary_Materials.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" id="d19aAdGbB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack id="S44"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank D. McCusker (University of Bordeaux) for the plasmid pDM272 and N. Dekker (TU Delft) for the plasmid pET28a-His-mcm10-Sortase-Flag.</p><p>L. Laan gratefully acknowledges funding from the European Research Council under the European Union’s Horizon 2020 research and innovation programme (grant agreement 758132) and funding from the Netherlands Organization for Scientific Research (Nederlandse Organisatie voor Wetenschappelijk Onderzoek) through a Vidi grant (016.Vidi.171.060).</p></ack><sec id="S45" sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data Sharing and Data Availability</title><p id="P236">The data that support and exemplify the protocols are openly available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://data.4tu.nl">https://data.4tu.nl</ext-link> at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://doi.org/10.4121/ac196f25-1c20-4c0c-a0b9-f01cd3fadc45">http://doi.org/10.4121/ac196f25-1c20-4c0c-a0b9-f01cd3fadc45</ext-link>.</p></sec><fn-group><fn fn-type="conflict" id="FN1"><p id="P237"><bold>Conflict of interest statement</bold></p><p id="P238">The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="FN2"><p id="P239"><bold>Contributions</bold></p><p id="P240">S. Tschirpke: Conceptualization, Methodology, Validation, Investigation, Formal analysis, Writing - Original Draft, Writing - Review &amp; Editing, Visualization, Project administration. W. K.-G. Daalman: Conceptualization, Methodology, Validation, Investigation, Formal analysis, Writing - Original Draft, Writing - Review &amp; Editing, Software. L. Laan: Writing - Review &amp; Editing, Project administration, Funding acquisition, Supervision.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><ref id="R1"><label>[Bezeljak et al., 2020]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bezeljak</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Loya</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaczmarek</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Saunders</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name><name><surname>Loose</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Stochastic activation and bistability in a Rab GTPase regulatory network</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</source><year>2020</year><volume>117</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>6540</fpage><lpage>6549</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7104049</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32161136</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1921027117</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>[Bos et al., 2009]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bos</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Rehmann</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Wittinghofer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>GEFs and GAPs: Critical Elements in the Control of Small G Proteins</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2009</year><volume>16</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>374</fpage><lpage>383</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17540168</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>[Cherfils and Zeghouf, 2013]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cherfils</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeghouf</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regulation of small GTPases by GEFs, GAPs, and GDIs</article-title><source>Physiological Reviews</source><year>2013</year><volume>93</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>269</fpage><lpage>309</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23303910</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>[Kang et al., 2010]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Béven</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Hariharan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>HO</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Rsr1/Bud1 GTPase interacts with itself and the Cdc42 GTPase during bud-site selection and polarity establishment in budding yeast</article-title><source>Molecular Biology of the Cell</source><year>2010</year><volume>21</volume><issue>17</issue><fpage>3007</fpage><lpage>3016</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2929994</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20587777</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1091/mbc.E10-03-0232</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>[Kohyama et al., 2022]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kohyama</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Merino-Salomón</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwille</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In vitro assembly, positioning and contraction of a division ring in minimal cells</article-title><source>Nature Communications</source><year>2022</year><volume>13</volume><issue>1</issue><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9569390</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36243816</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-022-33679-x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>[Loose et al., 2008]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Loose</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fischer-Friedrich</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Ries</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kruse</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwille</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Spatial Regulators for Bacterial Cell Division Self-Organize into Surface Waves in Vitro</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2008</year><volume>320</volume><issue>5877</issue><fpage>789</fpage><lpage>792</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18467587</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>[Promega Corporation, 2015]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>Promega Corporation</collab><article-title>GTPase-Glo ™ Assay</article-title><year>2015</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>[Rapali et al., 2017]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rapali</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitteau</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Braun</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Massoni-Laporte</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ünlü</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bataille</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Arramon</surname><given-names>FS</given-names></name><name><surname>Gygi</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>McCusker</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Scaffold-mediated gating of Cdc42 signalling flux</article-title><source>eLife</source><year>2017</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>18</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5386590</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28304276</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.25257</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>[Ruxton, 2006]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ruxton</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The unequal variance t-test is an underused alternative to Student’s t-test and the Mann-Whitney U test</article-title><source>Behavioral Ecology</source><year>2006</year><volume>17</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>688</fpage><lpage>690</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>[Smith et al., 2015]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name><surname>van der Walt</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Firing</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Magma, inferno, plasma and viridis colormaps</article-title><year>2015</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>[Tschirpke et al., 2023a]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tschirpke</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Daalman</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Laan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The GEF Cdc24 and GAP Rga2 synergistically regulate Cdc42 GTPase cycling</article-title><source>BioRxiv</source><year>2023a</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>[Tschirpke et al., 2023b]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tschirpke</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>van Opstal</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>van der Valk</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Daalman</surname><given-names>WKG</given-names></name><name><surname>Laan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A guide to the in vitro reconstitution of Cdc42 activity and its regulation</article-title><source>BioRxiv</source><year>2023b</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>[Vendel et al., 2019]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vendel</surname><given-names>KJA</given-names></name><name><surname>Tschirpke</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Shamsi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Dogterom</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Laan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Minimal in vitro systems shed light on cell polarity</article-title><source>Journal of Cell Science</source><year>2019</year><volume>132</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>21</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30700498</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>[Vetter and Wittinghofer, 2001]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vetter</surname><given-names>IR</given-names></name><name><surname>Wittinghofer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The guanine nucleotide-binding switch in three dimensions</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2001</year><volume>294</volume><issue>5545</issue><fpage>1299</fpage><lpage>1304</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11701921</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>[Zhang et al., 2001]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Moon</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Oligomerization of Rac1 GTPase Mediated by the Carboxyl-terminal Polybasic Domain</article-title><source>Journal of Biological Chemistry</source><year>2001</year><volume>276</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>8958</fpage><lpage>8967</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11134022</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>[Zhang et al., 1997]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>ZX</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of the interactions between the small GT-Pase Cdc42 and its GTPase-activating proteins and putative effectors: Comparison of kinetic properties of Cdc42 binding to the Cdc42-interactive domains</article-title><source>Journal of Biological Chemistry</source><year>1997</year><volume>272</volume><issue>35</issue><fpage>21999</fpage><lpage>22007</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9268338</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>[Zhang et al., 1999]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>DI</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A built-in arginine finger triggers the self-stimulatory GTPase-activating activity of Rho family GTPases</article-title><source>Journal of Biological Chemistry</source><year>1999</year><volume>274</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>2609</fpage><lpage>2612</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9915787</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>[Zhang and Zheng, 1998]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Negative regulation of Rho family GTPases Cdc42 and Rac2 by homodimer formation</article-title><source>Journal of Biological Chemistry</source><year>1998</year><volume>273</volume><issue>40</issue><fpage>25728</fpage><lpage>25733</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9748241</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Schematic illustration of the assay steps and GTPase cycling reaction in the GTPase Glo™ assay (Promega). A GTPase, alone or in combination with effector proteins, is incubated with GTP at for a certain time (e.g 1.5 h) in which GTPase cycling occurs. After two processing steps, the amount of remaining GTP, measured as luminescence, is assessed. GTP hydrolysis cycling rates can be extracted by fitting the data with an exponential model.</p><p>Abbreviations:</p><p>AA amino acid</p><p>GAP GTPase activating protein</p><p>GEF GDP/GTP exchange factor</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS191778-f001"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Schematic illustrating the assays and protein dilutions required for conducting a GTPase assay set investigating GTPase, GEF, and GAP actitvity and GEF-GAP interaction (example 2).</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS191778-f002"/></fig><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Schematic illustration the steps necessary to conduct a GTPase assay using a serial diluton of 6 Ras GTPase concentrations. The preparatory steps to conduct this assay are illustrated in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S2</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS191778-f003"/></fig><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Data analysis part 1 for the GTPase assay described in the basic protocol (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S2</xref>): Time-averaging luminescence values. (Data is taken from ‘example1.xlsx’, tab: ‘E1’.)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS191778-f004"/></fig><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Data analysis part 2 for the GTPase assay described in the basic protocol (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S2</xref>): calculating the amount of remaining GTP from luminescence values. (Data is taken from ‘example1.xlsx’, tab: ‘E1’.)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS191778-f005"/></fig><fig id="F6" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Reformatting of data <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref> (e.g. using a python script provided in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S9</xref>). (Data is taken from ‘example1.xlsx’, tab: ‘E1’.)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS191778-f006"/></fig><fig id="F7" position="float"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p>Example 1: Measured luminescence values of buffer wells (top) and Ras GTPase dilutions (bottom) over the time course of the measurement. The green box indicates values that are used for averaging.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS191778-f007"/></fig><fig id="F8" position="float"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p>Example 1: The overall GTP hydrolysis rate <italic>K</italic> does not scale linearly with Ras concentration. (The figure is automatically generated when running the matlab code (using ‘plot_fits = true(1)’).)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS191778-f008"/></fig><fig id="F9" position="float"><label>Figure 9</label><caption><title>Example 1: GTPase cycling rates <italic>k</italic><sub>1</sub> and <italic>k</italic><sub>2</sub> for Ras.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS191778-f009"/></fig><fig id="F10" position="float"><label>Figure 10</label><caption><p>Example 2: Histogram plot of <italic>c<sub>corr</sub></italic> using a bin size of 0.1. Generated for all <italic>c<sub>corr</sub></italic> values of example 2 (using ‘Plot_c_corr_histogram.m’ (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S10</xref>) and ‘example2-histogram.xlsx’ in the folder ‘example2 matlab output’).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS191778-f010"/></fig><fig id="F11" position="float"><label>Figure 11</label><caption><p>Example 2: The overall GTP hydrolysis rate <italic>K</italic> scales non-linearly with Cdc24 concentration. (The figure is automatically generated when running the matlab code (using ‘plot_fits = true(1)’).)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS191778-f011"/></fig><fig id="F12" position="float"><label>Figure 12</label><caption><p>Example 2: Fit of Cdc42-Cdc24-Rga2 mixtures. (The figures are automatically generated when running the matlab code (using ‘plot_fits = true(1)’).)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS191778-f012"/></fig><fig id="F13" position="float"><label>Figure 13</label><caption><p>Example 2: Plot of rates <italic>K</italic><sub>3</sub>, <italic>X</italic> for Cdc42-Cdc24 (left: ‘C42-C24’), Cdc42-Rga2 (middle: ‘C42-R2’), and Cdc42-Cdc24-Rga2 (right: ‘C42-C24-R2’) assays. Rate values of individual experiments are shown as filled dots. The average is shown as a cross and error bars represent the standard error. Generated for assay names ‘C42-C24’, ‘C42-R2’, and ‘C42-C24-R2’ (using ‘Plot_pooled_values_std_err.m’ (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S10</xref>) and ‘Data_assays.mat’ in the folder ‘example2 matlab output’).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS191778-f013"/></fig><table-wrap id="T1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Summary of how the examples are used throughout the protocols. Data files are available at data.4tu.nl. More information can be found in the section: Data Sharing and Data Availability.</p></caption><table frame="box" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" style="border-top: 1px solid #000000;border-left: 1px solid"/><th valign="top" align="left" style="border-top: 1px solid #000000;border-left: 1px solid #000000;vertical-align: bottom">Example 1: A basic GTPase assay</th><th valign="top" align="left" style="border-top: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000;border-left: 1px solid #000000;vertical-align: bottom">Example 2: An elaborate GTPase assay set</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="3" style="border-top: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000;border-left: 1px solid #000000;vertical-align: bottom"><bold>Experimental procedure</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-top:solid 1px #000000;border-left:solid 1px #000000">Basic Protocol</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-top:solid 1px #000000;border-left:solid 1px #000000">described using this example (+ see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S2</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border:solid 1px #000000">-</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-top: 1px solid #000000;border-left: 1px solid">Strategic planning</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-top: 1px solid #000000;border-left: 1px solid">-</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-top: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000;border-left: 1px solid #000000;vertical-align: bottom">features consideration absolutely necessary for this assays set (esp. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>).</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-top: 1px solid #000000;border-left: 1px solid">Proteins</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-top: 1px solid #000000;border-left: 1px solid">Ras (GTPase)</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-top: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000;border-left: 1px solid #000000;vertical-align: bottom">Cdc42 (GTPase)<break/>Cdc24(GEF)<break/>Rga2 (GAP)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-top:solid 1px #000000;border-left:solid 1px #000000">Number of assays</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-top:solid 1px #000000;border-left:solid 1px #000000">2</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border:solid 1px #000000">23</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-top:solid 1px #000000;border-left:solid 1px #000000">Raw data</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-top:solid 1px #000000;border-left:solid 1px #000000">’examplel.xlsx’ (tab: ’E1’, ’E2’)</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border:solid 1px #000000">-</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="3" style="border-top: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000;border-left: 1px solid #000000;vertical-align: bottom"><bold>Data processing</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-top: 1px solid #000000;border-left: 1px solid">Support Protocol 1:Calculating the of amount of remaining GTP from luminescence values</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-top: 1px solid #000000;border-left: 1px solid #000000;vertical-align: bottom">described using this example<break/>→ input data: ’examplel.xlsx’(tab: ’E1’, ’E2’)<break/>→ output data: same file as input data<break/>→ re-formatting of SP1 output data to generate SP2 input data: see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S9</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-top: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000;border-left: 1px solid">-</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-top: 1px solid #000000;border-left: 1px solid">Support Protocol 2:Fitting GTPase cycling rates using an exponential model (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S8</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-top: 1px solid #000000;border-left: 1px solid">described using this example<break/>→ input: ’examplel.xlsx’ (tab: ’matlab’), ’Assaylist-examplel.xlsx’<break/>→output in folder ’examplei matlab output’:                ’Data_summary.xlsx’,’Data_assays.mat’, figure folder<break/>→ fitting parameters: <italic>k</italic><sub>1</sub>, <italic>k</italic><sub>2</sub></td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-top: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000;border-left: 1px solid #000000;vertical-align: bottom">described using this example<break/>→ input: ’example2-matlab.xlxs’, ’Assaylist-example2.xlsx’<break/>→output in folder ’example2 matlab output’:                ’Data_summary.xlsx’,’Data_assays.mat’, figure folder<break/>→ fitting parameters: <italic>k</italic><sub>1</sub>, <italic>k</italic><sub>2</sub>, <italic>k</italic><sub>3,<italic>Cdc</italic>24</sub>, <italic>k</italic><sub>3,<italic>Rga</italic>24</sub>, <italic>k</italic><sub>3,<italic>Cdc</italic>24<italic>Rga</italic>2</sub><italic>C</italic><sub><italic>corr</italic></sub></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="3" style="border-top: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000;border-left: 1px solid #000000;vertical-align: bottom"><bold>Understanding Results</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-top: 1px solid #000000;border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-left: 1px solid">Explanation of...</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border:solid 1px #000000">Luminescence<break/> <italic>k</italic><sub>1</sub>,  <italic>k</italic><sub>2</sub> <break/>output file structure pooling of rates  <italic>k</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border: 1px solid"><italic>C<sub>corr</sub></italic> <italic>k</italic><sub>3,<italic>Cdc</italic>24</sub>,<italic>k</italic><sub>3,<italic>Rga</italic>2</sub>, <italic>k</italic><sub>3,<italic>Cdc</italic>24,<italic>Rga</italic>2</sub> comparison of rates <italic>k</italic></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Pipetting scheme for the 2× GTP solution.</title></caption><table frame="box" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" style="border-top: 2px solid #000000;border-bottom: 1px solid;border-left: 1px solid #ffffff">Starting solution</th><th valign="top" align="left" style="border-top: 2px solid #000000;border-bottom: 1px solid">final concentration</th><th valign="top" align="left" style="border-top: 2px solid #000000;border-bottom: 1px solid">500 μL</th><th valign="top" align="left" style="border-top: 2px solid #000000;border-bottom: 1px solid">750 μL</th><th valign="top" align="left" style="border-top: 2px solid #000000;border-bottom: 1px solid;border-right: 1px solid #ffffff">1 mL</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-left: 1px solid #ffffff">protein buffer</td><td valign="top" align="left">-</td><td valign="top" align="left">494 μL</td><td valign="top" align="left">742 μL</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-right: 1px solid #ffffff">989 μL</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-left: 1px solid #ffffff;border-right: 1px solid #ffffff">DTT (100 mM)</td><td valign="top" align="left">1 mM</td><td valign="top" align="left">5 μL</td><td valign="top" align="left">7.5 μL</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-right: 1px solid #ffffff">10 μL</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 2px solid;border-left: 1px solid #ffffff">rGTP (10 mM)</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 2px solid">10 μM</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 2px solid">0.5 μL</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 2px solid">0.75 μL</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 2px solid;border-right: 1px solid #ffffff">1 μL</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Pipetting scheme for the Glo solution. Please note, to follow this pipetting scheme the ADP solution provided in the kit (ADP, 10 mM) has to be diluted to 1 mM (e.g. mix 2 μL ADP (10 mM) with 18 μL of ultra pure water)!</p></caption><table frame="box" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" style="border-top: 2px solid #000000;border-bottom: 1px solid;border-left: 1px solid #ffffff">Starting solution</th><th valign="top" align="left" style="border-top: 2px solid #000000;border-bottom: 1px solid">final concentration</th><th valign="top" align="left" style="border-top: 2px solid #000000;border-bottom: 1px solid">500 μL</th><th valign="top" align="left" style="border-top: 2px solid #000000;border-bottom: 1px solid">750 μL</th><th valign="top" align="left" style="border-top: 2px solid #000000;border-bottom: 1px solid;border-right: 1px solid #ffffff">1 mL</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-left: 1px solid #ffffff">GTPase-Glo™ buffer</td><td valign="top" align="left">-</td><td valign="top" align="left">496 μL</td><td valign="top" align="left">745 μL</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-right: 1px solid #ffffff">993 μL</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-left: 1px solid #ffffff">ADP (1 mM)</td><td valign="top" align="left">5 μM</td><td valign="top" align="left">2.5 μL</td><td valign="top" align="left">3.75 μL</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-right: 1px solid #ffffff">5 μL</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 2px solid;border-left: 1px solid #ffffff">GTPase-Glo™ reagent (500×)</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 2px solid">1×</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 2px solid">1 μL</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 2px solid">1.5 μL</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 2px solid;border-right: 1px solid #ffffff">2 μL</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 4</label><caption><title>Troubleshooting guide for GTPase Glo™ assays.</title></caption><table frame="box" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" style="border-top:solid 1px #000000;border-left:solid 1px #000000">Problem</th><th valign="top" align="left" style="border-top:solid 1px #000000;border-left:solid 1px #000000">Possible Cause</th><th valign="top" align="left" style="border:solid 1px #000000">Solution</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-top: 1px solid #000000;border-left: 1px solid">No or low luminescence</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-top:solid 1px #000000;border-left:solid 1px #000000">sample/ buffer components interfere with assay steps (e.g. fluorescent tags (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S3</xref>))<break/> one of the assay solutions is no longer active</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border:solid 1px #000000">dialyse sample into a new buffer (e.g. 50  mM  Tris-HCl (pH=7.5), 100  mM  NaCl, 10  mM  MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 1  mM  2-mercaptoethanol), also see assay manual<break/> use fresh aliquots of GTP, DTT, ADP, Glo reagnet, and detection reagent</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-top: 1px solid #000000;border-left: 1px solid">High luminescence</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-top: 1px solid #000000;border-left: 1px solid #000000;vertical-align: bottom">contamination with ATP, GTP, or other nucleotide triphosphates</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-top: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000;border-left: 1px solid #000000;vertical-align: bottom">dialyse the sample into a buffer, also see assay manual</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-top: 1px solid #000000;border-left: 1px solid">Luminescence of first and last buffer row differs a lot</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-top: 1px solid #000000;border-left: 1px solid">two different detection reagent aliquots were used for the same assay (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S7</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-top: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000;border-left: 1px solid #000000;vertical-align: bottom">calculate how much detection reagent every assay needs and prepare a sufficient volume through mixing several detection reagent aliquots</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-top: 1px solid #000000;border-left: 1px solid">Large error bars</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-top: 1px solid #000000;border-left: 1px solid #000000;vertical-align: bottom">2×   GTP solution is not fresh/ was re-used(<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S6</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-top: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000;border-left: 1px solid #000000;vertical-align: bottom">prepare a fresh 2 x  GTP solution for each assay</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-top: 1px solid #000000;border-left: 1px solid #000000;vertical-align: bottom">Low signal in non-GTPase samples</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-top: 1px solid #000000;border-left: 1px solid #000000;vertical-align: bottom">contamination with a componentthat interferes with assay steps or with a GTPase</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-top: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000;border-left: 1px solid #000000;vertical-align: bottom">dialyse sample into a new buffer or test a new sample batch</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-top: 1px solid #000000;border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-left: 1px solid">No change in luminescence with increasing GEF concentration</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-top: 1px solid #000000;border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-left: 1px solid #000000;vertical-align: bottom">GEF or GTPase batch is not active<break/> GEF conc. range is too narrow and too low buffer does not contain Mg<sup>2+</sup> <break/>the buffer contains chelating agents such as EDTAthat complex Mg<sup>2+</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border: 1px solid #000000;vertical-align: bottom">try a new purification batch of the GEF or GTPase<break/> try significantly higher GEF concentrations add a magnesium salt to the buffer, e.g.10  mM  MgCl<sub>2</sub>use a buffer that does not contain chelating agents</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></floats-group></article>