<!DOCTYPE article
 PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" article-type="preprint"><?all-math-mml yes?><?use-mml?><?origin ukpmcpa?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">bioRxiv</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>bioRxiv : the preprint server for biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub"/></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">EMS156775</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2022.11.06.515351</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="archive">PPR567812</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Malonyl-CoA is an ancient physiological ATP-competitive mTORC1 inhibitor</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Nicastro</surname><given-names>Raffaele</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Brohée</surname><given-names>Laurae</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Alba</surname><given-names>Josephine</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nüchel</surname><given-names>Julian</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Figlia</surname><given-names>Gianluca</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kipschull</surname><given-names>Stefanie</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gollwitzer</surname><given-names>Peter</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Romero-Pozuelo</surname><given-names>Jesus</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN2">†</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fernandes</surname><given-names>Stephanie A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lamprakis</surname><given-names>Andreas</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Vanni</surname><given-names>Stefano</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN1">§</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Teleman</surname><given-names>Aurelio A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN1">§</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>De Virgilio</surname><given-names>Claudio</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN1">§</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Demetriades</surname><given-names>Constantinos</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">5</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN1">§</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Department of Biology, University of Fribourg, 1700 Fribourg, Switzerland</aff><aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Max Planck Institute for Biology of Ageing (MPI-AGE), 50931 Cologne, Germany</aff><aff id="A3"><label>3</label>German Cancer Research Center (DKFZ), 69120 Heidelberg, Germany</aff><aff id="A4"><label>4</label>Heidelberg University, 69120 Heidelberg, Germany</aff><aff id="A5"><label>5</label>University of Cologne, Cologne Excellence Cluster on Cellular Stress Responses in Aging-Associated Diseases (CECAD), 50931 Cologne, Germany</aff><author-notes><corresp id="CR1">Correspondence and requests for materials should be addressed to Constantinos Demetriades: (<email>Demetriades@age.mpg.de</email>), Claudio De Virgilio (<email>claudio.devirgilio@unifr.ch</email>), Aurelio Teleman (<email>a.teleman@dkfz.de</email>), or Stefano Vanni (<email>stefano.vanni@unifr.ch</email>).</corresp><fn id="FN1"><label>§</label><p id="P1">These authors jointly supervised this work</p></fn><fn id="FN2" fn-type="present-address"><label>†</label><p id="P2">Present address: Center for Biological Research (CIB-CSIC), 28040 Madrid,Spain</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted"><day>08</day><month>11</month><year>2022</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="preprint"><day>06</day><month>11</month><year>2022</year></pub-date><permissions><ali:free_to_read/><license><ali:license_ref>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is licensed under a <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">CC BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license</ext-link>.</license-p></license><license><ali:license_ref>https://europepmc.org/downloads/openaccess</ali:license_ref><license-p>This preprint is made available via the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://europepmc.org/downloads/openaccess">Europe PMC open access subset</ext-link>, for unrestricted research re-use and secondary analysis in any form or by any means with acknowledgement of the original preprint source.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p id="P3">Cell growth is regulated primarily by the mammalian/mechanistic Target of Rapamycin Complex 1 (mTORC1) that functions both as a nutrient sensor and a master controller of virtually all biosynthetic pathways <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref></sup>. This ensures that cells are metabolically active only when conditions are optimal for growth. Notably, although mTORC1 is known to regulate fatty acid (FA) biosynthesis, how and whether the cellular lipid biosynthetic capacity signals back to fine-tune mTORC1 activity remains poorly understood. Here, we show that mTORC1 senses the capacity of a cell to synthesize FAs by detecting the levels of malonyl-CoA, an intermediate of this biosynthetic pathway. We find that, in both yeast and mammalian cells, this regulation is very direct, with malonyl-CoA binding to the mTOR catalytic pocket and acting as a specific ATP-competitive inhibitor. When ACC1 (acetyl-CoA carboxylase 1) is hyperactive or FASN (fatty acid synthase) is downregulated/inhibited, elevated malonyl-CoA levels are channelled to proximal mTOR molecules that form direct protein-protein interactions with ACC1 and FASN. Our findings represent a conserved, unique, homeostatic mechanism whereby impaired FA biogenesis leads to reduced mTORC1 activity to coordinatively link this metabolic pathway to the overall cellular biosynthetic output. Moreover, they reveal the first-described example of a physiological metabolite that directly inhibits the activity of a signalling kinase by competing with ATP for binding.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><p id="P4">Cell growth is a highly energy-consuming and, hence, tightly-regulated process. Cells accumulate mass by taking up essential nutrients from their environment and using them to build macromolecules, such as proteins, lipids, and sugars, through intricate metabolic pathways <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">2</xref></sup>. mTORC1 is a central integration point in cellular signalling, linking metabolic cues to cell growth and homeostasis. Work over the last 15 years has identified complex signalling cascades through which growth factors (GFs), nutrients (like amino acids; AAs), and energy availability regulate mTORC1 (reviewed in <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">4</xref></sup>). Accordingly, cholesterol levels were previously shown to influence mTORC1 activity at the lysosomal surface via mechanisms that involve the Niemann-Pick C1 (NPC1), SLC38A9 and Rag GTPase proteins <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref></sup>, with the latter also playing a central role in AA and glucose sensing by recruiting mTOR at this subcellular location <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">8</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref></sup>. In turn, mTORC1 upregulates multiple metabolic processes, including protein and cholesterol biosynthesis <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">4</xref></sup>. Similarly, active mTORC1 promotes FA biosynthesis by driving the expression of key enzymes in this process—like FASN—in response to GF signalling <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref></sup>. Interestingly, however, whether and how FA synthesis controls mTORC1 activity remains enigmatic.</p><p id="P5">Fatty acids serve both structural and regulatory roles in cells (e.g., by participating in membrane formation and by post-translationally modifying proteins, respectively), while also functioning as energy storage molecules <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref></sup>. In <italic>de novo</italic> FA biosynthesis, acetyl-CoA, generated from glucose catabolism, is converted to malonyl-CoA by ACC1-mediated, ATP-dependent carboxylation, which is then used by FASN to produce palmitate, the precursor of longer fatty acids <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref></sup>. This process is well conserved from human to yeast cells, where the homologous acetyl-CoA carboxylase, Acc1, and the Fas1- and Fas2-containing fatty acid synthase (FAS) complex catalyse the conversion of acetyl-CoA to FAs <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref></sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1a</xref>). Because various metabolites were previously shown to impact mTORC1 via regulating the activity of upstream signalling components (e.g., by AMP and inositol allosterically influencing AMPK activity <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref></sup>; or α-ketoglutarate and glutaminolysis somehow affecting the lysosomal Rag GTPases <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref></sup>), we hypothesized that a metabolic intermediate of FA biosynthesis may be signalling directly or indirectly to mTORC1, thus forming a regulatory feedback loop.</p><sec id="S1"><title>Functional pharmacogenetic interactions between TOR pathway components and the core FA biosynthesis machinery reveal a role for malonyl-CoA in TOR signalling</title><p id="P6">Our previous interactome studies of the Rag GTPases in yeast indicated that the RagA/B homologue, Gtr1, may directly or indirectly interact with Acc1 and the Fas1 subunit of the FAS complex (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplemental Table S1</xref> in <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">20</xref></sup>). Because both of these enzymes are part of essential protein complexes that work together to synthesize FAs, this suggested a possible functional interplay between TORC1 signalling and the core FA biosynthetic machinery. To study this, we first probed the pharmacogenetic interaction of TORC1 pathway mutants with the FAS inhibitor cerulenin <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">22</xref></sup>. Interestingly, loss of Gtr1/2, expression of the nucleotide-free Gtr1<sup>S20L</sup> allele, loss of other TORC1 pathway components (i.e., Ego1-3, Tor1, Tco89), or co-treatment with rapamycin, all of which reduce TORC1 activity <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">23</xref></sup>, rendered cells highly sensitive to cerulenin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Extended Data Fig. 1a,b</xref>). Conversely, expression of the GTP-locked Gtr1<sup>Q65L</sup> allele, which activates TORC1, caused cerulenin resistance (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Extended Data Fig. 1a</xref>). These observations match our targeted re-analyses of recently published SATAY (saturated transposon analyses in yeast) data <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">25</xref></sup>, showing that transposon events in TORC1 pathway genes were under-represented when cells were grown on cerulenin or rapamycin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Extended Data Fig. 1c,e</xref>). Intriguingly, however, in these datasets, TORC1 pathway genes were over-represented when cells were grown in the presence of soraphen A, which inhibits the antecedent enzyme in FA biosynthesis, Acc1 <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">26</xref></sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Extended Data Fig. 1d,e</xref>). One interpretation of these findings is that malonyl-CoA, the intermediate metabolite between Acc1 and FAS, may be functionally linked to TORC1 activity. In support of this hypothesis, cerulenin-mediated FAS inhibition, which increases intracellular malonyl-CoA levels more than 8-fold (as assayed with a specific reporter system <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27">27</xref></sup>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1b,c</xref>), strongly reduced TORC1 activity (assayed by the phosphorylation of its direct target Sch9) <italic>in vivo</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1b,d</xref>). Next, we hypothesised that FAS inhibition could be downregulating TORC1 either by increasing the levels of its substrate (i.e., malonyl-CoA) or by reducing the levels of its product (i.e., palmitate). To distinguish between these two possibilities, we used a hyperactive Acc1<sup>S1157A</sup> allele, which causes malonyl-CoA levels to increase (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Extended Data Fig. 2c,d</xref>) <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27">27</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">29</xref></sup>. This allele aggravated the sensitivity of cells to sublethal combinations of cerulenin and rapamycin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Extended Data Fig. 2a,b</xref>), indicating that the elevated malonyl-CoA—and not the reduced palmitate—is responsible for this phenotype. Together, these data suggest that TORC1 may be inhibited by malonyl-CoA, in response to perturbations in Acc1 and FAS activity.</p><p id="P7">Supporting this model, <italic>accl<sup>S1157A</sup></italic> cells exhibited significantly reduced TORC1 activity when grown exponentially, and were partially impaired in glutamine-stimulated reactivation of TORC1 in nitrogen-starved cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1e,f</xref>). These defects correlated well with significantly increased levels of malonyl-CoA in cells expressing Acc1<sup>S1157A</sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Extended Data Fig. 2c,d</xref>). Moreover, combining the <italic>accl<sup>S1157A</sup></italic> mutation with an <italic>acc1<sup>E392K</sup></italic> mutation (also known as <italic>acc1-7-1</italic> <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">30</xref></sup>), a temperature-sensitive allele (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Extended Data Fig. 2e</xref>) that is hypomorphic for malonyl-CoA production at the permissive temperature (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Extended Data Fig. 2c,d</xref>), suppressed both the elevated malonyl-CoA levels and the reduced TORC1 activity that are observed in <italic>acc1<sup>S1157A</sup></italic> cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Extended Data Fig. 2c,d,f,g</xref>). Similarly, C-terminal GFP-tagging of Acc1<sup>S1157A</sup> rendered this allele less active, which significantly reduced the cellular malonyl-CoA levels (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Extended Data Fig. 3a,b</xref>) and suppressed the cerulenin-sensitivity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Extended Data Fig. 3c</xref>), the rapamycin-sensitivity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Extended Data Fig. 3c</xref>), and the TORC1 activity defect (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Extended Data Fig. 3d,e</xref>) that are observed in untagged Acc1<sup>S1157A</sup>-expressing cells. In contrast, C-terminal GFP-tagging of Fas1 lead to cerulenin sensitivity in wild-type cells, and further enhanced this effect in <italic>accl<sup>S1157A</sup></italic> cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Extended Data Fig. 3c</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S2"><title>FASN inhibition controls mTORC1 activity independently from FA biosynthesis</title><p id="P8">A similar molecular machinery is responsible for FA biosynthesis in mammalian cells, which differ from yeast by expressing a single fatty acid synthase (FASN) enzyme that catalyses the conversion of malonyl-CoA to palmitate and other FAs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1a</xref>). Therefore, we sought to investigate if accumulation of malonyl-CoA influences mTORC1 activity also in mammalian cells. To test this, we blocked FASN activity in human HEK293FT cells, either by specific pharmacological inhibition using Fasnall (also known as benzenesulfonate) <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31">31</xref></sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1a,g,h</xref>) or cerulenin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1a,i,j</xref>), or by transient <italic>FASN</italic> knockdown by siRNA transfection (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1k,l</xref>). In accordance with the yeast data, all perturbations suppressed mTORC1 activity, as indicated by decreased phosphorylation of its direct substrates S6K and 4E-BP1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1g-l</xref>). As expected, cerulenin or <italic>FASN</italic> knockdown led to a detectable increase in total protein malonylation, detected by immunoblotting with an anti-malonyl-lysine (α-Mal-K) antibody (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2i,k</xref>), indicative of elevated intracellular malonyl-CoA levels <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32">32</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33">33</xref></sup>. Similar results were obtained by inhibiting or knocking down FASN in MEFs (mouse embryonic fibroblasts) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Extended Data Fig. 4a-c</xref>), MCF-7 human breast cancer cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Extended Data Fig. 4d,e</xref>), WI-26 human lung fibroblasts (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Extended Data Fig. 4f</xref>), or U2OS human osteosarcoma cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Extended Data Fig. 4g,h</xref>), showing that this effect is not cell type-specific. Further supporting that malonyl-CoA is able to inhibit mTORC1, exogenous addition of this metabolite <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34">34</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35">35</xref></sup> caused a significant drop in mTORC1 activity in HEK293FT cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Extended Data Fig. 5a,b</xref>). Importantly, FASN inhibition specifically affected mTORC1, but not mTORC2, as treatment with Fasnall or cerulenin did not significantly alter phosphorylation of Akt, a typical mTORC2 substrate in human cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Extended Data Fig. 5c-f</xref>). Similarly, treatment with cerulenin or expression of Acc1<sup>S1157A</sup> did not inhibit the phosphorylation state of Ypk1<sup>Thr662</sup>, a <italic>bona fide</italic> TORC2 target residue in yeast (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Extended Data Fig. 5g-j</xref>).</p><p id="P9">Palmitate, the main FASN product, was previously suggested to be important for mTORC1 activity in specialized cell types <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36">36</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38">38</xref></sup>. We therefore tested if FASN inhibition downregulates mTORC1 due to a decrease in palmitate or an increase in malonyl-CoA by modulating the levels of these two metabolites. Notably, neither culturing of cells in charcoal-stripped FBS that is depleted of lipids (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Extended Data Fig. 6a,b</xref>) nor supplementation of culture media with BSA-conjugated FAs modulated the inhibition of mTORC1 by Fasnall or cerulenin treatment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1m</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Extended Data Fig. 6b</xref>). In contrast, exogenous expression of the constitutively active ACC1<sup>S79A</sup> mutant demonstrated a synergistic effect with cerulenin towards mTORC1 inhibition, without significantly affecting the response to amino acid starvation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Extended Data Fig. 6c,d</xref>), also hinting that the inhibition of mTORC1 is due to elevated malonyl-CoA levels.</p><p id="P10">A previous study proposed that malonylation of mTOR on lysine 1218 (K1218) negatively impacts mTORC1 activity in endothelial cells <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39">39</xref></sup>. Therefore, we tested if the accumulation of malonyl-CoA upon FASN/Fas1 inhibition is downregulating mTORC1/TORC1 via this mechanism. However, by using an antibody that detects malonylated lysine (Mal-K) residues on proteins, we were not able to detect malonylation of immunopurified human mTOR or yeast Tor1, from control or cerulenin-treated cells, in our system (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Extended Data Fig. 6e,f</xref>). In contrast to mTOR, and in agreement with previous proteomics analyses of the human malonylome <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33">33</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40">40</xref></sup>, lysine malonylation was readily and robustly detectable on immunopurified human FASN and yeast Fas1 from control cells, with the malonylation increasing further in cerulenin-treated cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Extended Data Fig. 6e,f</xref>). Taken together, our data from yeast and mammalian cells indicate that hyperactivation of ACC1 or inhibition of FAS downregulate mTORC1/TORC1 via a mechanism that involves accumulation of malonyl-CoA, independently from mTOR malonylation and from its role in FA biosynthesis.</p></sec><sec id="S3"><title>Perturbations in yeast and mammalian ACC1/FAS activity control mTORC1 independently of upstream regulatory complexes</title><p id="P11">To study how malonyl-CoA may be regulating TORC1 activity, we first employed genetic epistasis in yeast. Nutrients such as amino acids regulate TORC1 in part via the Gtr/Rag GTPases <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">23</xref></sup>. Expression of constitutively active Acc1<sup>S1157A</sup>, however, rendered not only wild-type cells, but also <italic>gtr1Δ, gtr1<sup>S20L</sup>, gtr2Δ,</italic> and <italic>gtr2<sup>S23L</sup></italic> mutant cells cerulenin-sensitive (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Extended Data Fig. 2a,b</xref>), indicating that Acc1 or its product malonyl-CoA may impinge on TORC1 independently of Gtr1/2. To further corroborate this assumption, we assayed the effects of hyperactive Acc1<sup>S1157A</sup> expression on TORC1 upon combined loss of Gtr1 and Gtr2, which, in control experiments, did not prevent the Acc1<sup>S1157A</sup>-mediated increase in malonyl-CoA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Extended Data Fig. 7a</xref>). As expected, either expression of Acc1<sup>S1157A</sup> or loss of Gtr1/2 reduced TORC1 activity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Extended Data Fig. 7b,c</xref>). Expression of Acc1<sup>S1157A</sup> in the Gtr1/2 double-mutant background decreased TORC1 activity further, suggesting that Acc1<sup>S1157A</sup> acts on TORC1 independently of Gtr1/2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Extended Data Fig. 7b,c</xref>). Furthermore, the presence of the Acc1<sup>S1157A</sup> allele did not affect the vacuolar localization of GFP-tagged Tor1 or Gtr1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">Extended Data Fig. 8a,b</xref>), while expression of constitutively active Gtr1<sup>Q65L</sup> was unable to revert the Acc1<sup>S1157A</sup>-mediated TORC1 inhibition (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Extended Data Fig. 7d,e</xref>). Together, these results establish that the effects of uncontrolled, Acc1-dependent malonyl-CoA synthesis on TORC1 do not require the presence of the Rag GTPases in yeast cells.</p><p id="P12">The heterodimeric Rag GTPases and the TSC complex are two major signalling hubs upstream of mTORC1 in mammalian cells <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41">41</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R44">44</xref></sup>. Therefore, we next tested if malonyl-CoA regulates mTORC1 through one of these complexes. In agreement with our yeast data, FASN inhibition by Fasnall or cerulenin decreased mTORC1 activity to a similar extent in wild-type, RagA/B, or RagC/D double knockout cells, suggesting that it acts independently from the Rags (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Extended Data Fig. 7f-h</xref>). Furthermore, Fasnall treatment was equally capable of downregulating mTORC1 in both control cells and cells that exogenously express an ‘active’-locked RagA/C mutant dimer, which partially prevents mTORC1 inactivation upon amino acid starvation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Extended Data Fig. 7i,j</xref>). Finally, TSC1 knockout cells, that demonstrate a compromised response to amino acid removal <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42">42</xref></sup>, showed a similar mTORC1 downregulation when treated with Fasnall (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Extended Data Fig. 7k,l</xref>) or cerulenin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Extended Data Fig. 7m,n</xref>), compared to wild-type controls. Because inhibition of FASN can inactivate mTORC1 independently of the two major upstream signalling hubs, these data suggest that malonyl-CoA accumulation may act downstream of these regulatory complexes, possibly by directly acting on mTORC1.</p><p id="P13">The lysosomal recruitment of mTORC1 by the Rag GTPases is an important aspect of its reactivation in response to AA re-supplementation <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41">41</xref></sup>. Interestingly, we observed that FASN inhibition by Fasnall or cerulenin also led to a significant dissociation of mTOR from lysosomes, as assayed by its colocalization with the lysosomal marker LAMP2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">Extended Data Fig. 8c-f</xref>).</p><p id="P14">However, since active RagA/C overexpression or loss of TSC1 (both of which were previously shown to retain lysosomal mTOR even upon starvation <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41">41</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42">42</xref></sup>) still allow downregulation of mTORC1 upon treatment with FASN inhibitors (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Extended Data Fig. 7i-n</xref>), we conclude that the delocalization of mTOR away from lysosomes is not the cause of its inactivation.</p></sec><sec id="S4"><title>The mTOR-FASN-ACC1 proteins form reciprocal interactions in yeast and mammalian cells at multiple subcellular locations</title><p id="P15">Because our data in yeast and mammalian cells indicated that the modulation of the carbon flux through ACC and FAS affected TORC1/mTORC1 in a Rag GTPase-independent manner (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Extended Data Fig. 7a-j</xref>), we entertained the idea that either or both of these enzymes may directly interact with TORC1/mTORC1. In support of this assumption, we found myc-tagged Acc1 to interact with the yeast TORC1 subunits Kog1-HA or Tco89-HA both in the presence and absence of Gtr1/2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2a,b</xref>). Similarly, myc-tagged Fas1 also interacted with Kog1-HA even in the absence of Gtr1/2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2c</xref>). Notably, reciprocal interactions between endogenous FASN, ACC1 and mTOR proteins were also detected in mammalian cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2d-f</xref>), with mTOR and ACC1 co-immunoprecipitating with FASN even in RagA/B double knockout cells that lack an intact Rag GTPase dimer (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2g</xref>).</p><p id="P16">In conditions of amino acid sufficiency, the active Rag GTPase complex recruits mTORC1 to the lysosomal surface, while in cells that lack a functional Rag GTPase dimer mTORC1 demonstrates a diffuse cytoplasmic localization pattern <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41">41</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42">42</xref></sup>. Hence, our observation that FASN inhibition downregulates mTORC1 independently from the Rags (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Extended Data Fig. 7a-j</xref>), and that mTOR interacts with FASN and ACC to the same extent in both Rag-proficient (in which mTOR is lysosomal) and Rag-deficient cells (in which mTOR is non-lysosomal) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2g</xref>) prompted us to investigate where FASN localizes in cells. In line with the fact that FA biosynthesis takes place primarily in the cytoplasm, and in agreement with publicly available protein localization databases (e.g., the human protein atlas <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R45">45</xref></sup>), endogenous FASN immunostaining showed a diffuse cytoplasmic signal, a portion of which colocalized with the lysosomal marker LAMP2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2h</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">Extended Data Fig. 8g</xref>). Indeed, proximity ligation assay (PLA) experiments using antibodies against endogenous FASN and LAMP2 proteins confirmed that a subpopulation of FASN molecules specifically localize at—or proximal to—the lysosomal surface (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2i,j</xref>). Taken together, these data show that FASN (and possibly also ACC1) physically interact with mTOR both at the lysosomal surface and away from it, suggesting that FASN inhibition and the subsequent accumulation of malonyl-CoA may be directly affecting mTORC1 activity at multiple subcellular locations.</p></sec><sec id="S5"><title>Molecular dynamics simulations indicate mal-CoA can bind to the mTOR catalytic pocket, similar to ATP</title><p id="P17">Our genetic, pharmacological, and biochemical data hinted at a possible direct role of malonyl-CoA in the inhibition of mTORC1. Taking into consideration that the adenine-moiety of malonyl-CoA structurally resembles ATP (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3a</xref>), we hypothesized that malonyl-CoA may be inhibiting mTOR by binding to its catalytic pocket. To investigate this possibility further, we looked at the binding of malonyl-CoA, acetyl-CoA, and Coenzyme A (CoA) to mTOR at the atomistic level, by modelling the complexes starting from the crystallographic structure of mTOR bound to ADP (PDB ID: 3JBZ; see methods). Since the interaction between these compounds and mTOR has not been described before, we first hypothesized that the adenine ring, that is present in all compounds, would localise similarly to ADP in the binding pocket of the kinase domain (KD) of mTOR. Thus, the adenine ring of each compound was first aligned to ADP, and then, to find a good arrangement of the lateral chain in the pocket, site-specific docking simulations were performed, allowing the torsion of the lateral chain only (see also methods). For each compound, three best poses were selected considering the most favourable binding energy values (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">Extended Data Fig. 9a-c</xref>), and subsequently used as a starting point to perform all atom Molecular Dynamics (MD) simulations. As expected, ATP remained in the binding pocket during the entire simulation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3b,c</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD6">Extended Data Video 1</xref>). Similarly to ATP, the adenine ring of malonyl-CoA also remained stable in the binding pocket (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3b,c</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD7">Extended Data Video 2</xref>). In stark contrast, however, Coenzyme A and acetyl-CoA, quickly (after 15-45 ns and 67-80 ns, respectively) detached from the protein and moved away from the binding pocket of mTOR (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3c</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD8">Extended Data Videos 3</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD9">4</xref>). The origin of these differences in interactions between malonyl-CoA and the other CoA-containing compounds with mTOR is likely due to the negatively charged chain (COOH<sup>-</sup>) of its malonyl group that engages in multiple interactions with positively charged mTOR residues just outside the binding pocket (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">Extended Data Fig. 10a</xref>), such as R2168, R2170, and K2187. In contrast, the respective acetyl-CoA (-CH3) and CoA (-SH) groups are not charged and, thus, do not engage in similar interactions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">Extended Data Fig. 10b,c</xref>). Accordingly, MD simulations and <italic>in silico</italic> mutagenesis of mTOR in the R2168/R2170 residues, that seemingly participate in the stabilization of malonyl-CoA (mTOR<sup>R2168A/R2170A</sup>), hinted at a possible role of these residues in malonyl-CoA binding (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">Extended Data Fig. 10d</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD10">Extended Data Video 5</xref>). Intriguingly, these residues are strongly conserved in mTOR over a wide range of organisms, spanning from yeast to humans (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">Extended Data Fig. 10e</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S6"><title>Mal-CoA is a direct ATP-competitive inhibitor of mTORC1 activity</title><p id="P18">To experimentally test our <italic>in silico</italic> analyses, we next sought to investigate whether malonyl-CoA is able to inhibit mTORC1 activity directly, in a cell-free system. Strikingly, classical <italic>in vitro</italic> enzyme kinetics assays, using TORC1 purified from yeast cells and recombinant Lst4 <italic>(i.e.</italic> Lst4<sup>Loop 46</sup>) or co-purified Tco89 <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R47">47</xref></sup> proteins as substrates, showed that this was indeed the case. Similar to what we observed in cells, when added to the <italic>in vitro</italic> kinase (IVK) reaction, malonyl-CoA inhibited TORC1 in a dose-dependent manner with a calculated IC<sub>50</sub> of 0.73 mM, while the respective IC<sub>50</sub> values for acetyl-CoA and CoA were 2.98 mM and above our detection limit of 6 mM, respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4a,b</xref>). Accordingly, mTORC1 IVK assays with increasing amounts of malonyl-CoA, acetyl-CoA, and CoA, using immunoprecipitated mTORC1 from mammalian cells and recombinant 4E-BP1 as substrate, revealed a dose-dependent inhibition of mTORC1 by malonyl-CoA (IC<sub>50</sub> = 0.23 mM), with acetyl-CoA being substantially less potent (IC<sub>50</sub> = 1.03 mM), and CoA being unable to inhibit mTORC1 activity under our experimental conditions (IC<sub>50</sub> &gt; 5 mM) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4c-e</xref>). As a control, malonyl-CoA addition to cell lysates before immunoprecipitation, did not influence mTORC1 stability, as indicated by the interaction of mTOR with RAPTOR and mLST8 proteins (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">Extended Data Fig. 10f</xref>). Overall, our data confirm that malonyl-CoA (and, to a lesser extent, acetyl-CoA) can act as a direct mTORC1 inhibitor, without affecting complex composition.</p><p id="P19">The resemblance of malonyl-CoA to ATP and our MD simulation experiments suggested that malonyl-CoA may inhibit TORC1/mTORC1 directly, through competition with ATP. In strong support of this hypothesis, IVK assays performed with increasing ATP concentrations, using yeast TORC1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4g</xref>) or human mTORC1 complexes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4i</xref>), when subjected to regression analyses using the GraphPad Prism curve fitting program, indicated that the behaviour of malonyl-CoA matched best with that of an ATP-competitive TORC1/mTORC1 inhibitor with a calculated Ki of 0.76 mM or 0.77 mM, for yeast or human complexes, respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4h,j</xref>). In sum, our data reveal that malonyl-CoA is a direct, ATP-competitive inhibitor of mTORC1 in both yeast and human cells, thus serving as a key metabolite that directly connects the cellular FA biosynthetic capacity to the activity of the main cellular metabolic regulator (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4k</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S7" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p id="P20">A key characteristic of mTORC1 is that it forms homeostatic feedback loops, acting both as a molecular sensor and as a regulator of individual biosynthetic processes. For instance, mTORC1 is the master controller of protein synthesis via directly phosphorylating S6K and 4E-BP1, while it also senses the sufficiency of amino acids and energy, thus ensuring that cells only make proteins when all building blocks are available <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref></sup>. Whereas mTORC1 was previously described to regulate lipid biosynthesis at several levels, by controlling the activity and localization of Lipin-1 <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R48">48</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R50">50</xref></sup> and the activity of SREBP transcription factors <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R51">51</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R52">52</xref></sup>, how the FA biosynthetic metabolic status signals back to regulate mTORC1 activity is less clear. Here, we report that this interplay also happens in the opposite direction, with key components of the core FA biosynthesis machinery (namely ACC1 and FASN) interacting directly with mTOR, and their activity being tightly connected to that of mTORC1. This way, the FA biosynthesis capacity of a cell is closely coupled to cell growth, metabolism, and other mTORC1 downstream cellular functions. Accordingly, SREBPs are the best described transcription factors controlling FASN expression <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R53">53</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R54">54</xref></sup>. By mTORC1 controlling SREBP activity, and thereby FASN levels <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref></sup>, our findings reveal a positive feedback loop between mTORC1 and FASN that could function to sustain lipid biosynthesis when conditions are optimal.</p><p id="P21">Endogenous metabolites are known to control the activity of key signalling molecules by directly binding to them and modifying their structure and function. For instance, binding of four cAMP molecules to the two regulatory subunits of PKA (protein kinase A) cause their dissociation from the catalytic PKA subunits, which are then activated and directly regulate downstream effectors, such as the CREB transcription factor, to modulate cellular metabolism <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R55">55</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R57">57</xref></sup>. Similarly, under low energy conditions, AMP allosterically activates AMPK by binding directly to its γ subunit <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref></sup>. Along the same lines, a recent study showed that inositol directly competes with AMP for binding to AMPKγ, thereby allosterically inhibiting AMPK enzymatic activity, with low inositol driving the AMPK-dependent mitochondrial fission upon energetic stress <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref></sup>. Our work here describes another example of an endogenous metabolite (i.e., malonyl-CoA) that functions as a direct regulator of a central signalling complex (i.e., mTORC1). However, unlike the allosteric modulation of kinase activities described above, malonyl-CoA acts as a direct, ATP-competitive mTORC1 inhibitor, an attribute that stems from the structural similarity between the CoA moiety and ATP. Molecular dynamics simulation experiments also support a model where the charged malonyl group helps to stabilize malonyl-CoA binding to mTOR via interactions with residues just outside its catalytic pocket. Importantly, we find that this is an ancient mechanism that is present already in yeast cells, and is conserved through evolution all the way to humans.</p><p id="P22">We were, unfortunately, not able to experimentally test the role of the R2105/R2107 residues of Tor1 (R2168/R2170 in human mTOR) in cells, as the respective alanine mutant protein was extremely unstable. Moreover, when expression between WT and mutant Tor1 was artificially matched (by introducing additional DNA/cDNA copies to cells), the latter showed diminished Kog1/Raptor binding in co-immunoprecipitation experiments (data not shown). Therefore, in addition to participating in the stabilization of malonyl-CoA in the mTOR catalytic pocket (as shown from our <italic>in silico</italic> mutagenesis and MD simulation analyses), these residues seemingly also play important roles in mTORC1 formation and mTOR stability.</p><p id="P23">While the absolute concentration of malonyl-CoA in yeast and mammalian cells has not been accurately measured before, our IVK experiments show that malonyl-CoA inhibits mTORC1 with IC<sub>50</sub> = 0.23 mM and K<sub>i</sub> = 0.77 mM (IC<sub>50</sub> = 0.23 mM, K<sub>i</sub> = 0.76 mM, for yeast TORC1). Although it is possible that the average intracellular malonyl-CoA concentration does not increase to this extent, the direct physical association between ACC1/FASN and mTOR/Raptor indicates that, upon FASN blockage or ACC1 hyperactivation, a local increase in malonyl-CoA levels could inhibit proximal mTORC1. Because FASN can interact with both lysosomal and non-lysosomal mTOR, perturbations in its activity are able to control all subpopulations of mTORC1 in cells. Such metabolic proximity channelling principles have been described before <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R58">58</xref></sup> and can facilitate efficient transfer of a metabolite from one enzyme to the next, thus bypassing the need for alterations in total intracellular metabolite levels.</p><p id="P24">Because of its central role in FA biosynthesis, FASN has emerged as a critical player in cancer cell metabolism, growth and survival <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R59">59</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R61">61</xref></sup>, with several FASN inhibitors currently being tested in clinical trials <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R62">62</xref></sup>. Interestingly, previous work suggested that the accumulation of malonyl-CoA, rather than the inhibition of FASN itself, is the underlying cause in FASN-inhibitor-induced toxicity in breast cancer cells <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34">34</xref></sup>. In the present study, we find that FASN inhibition also leads to mTORC1 downregulation due to malonyl-CoA accumulation, in addition to its well-known role in FA biosynthesis. As mTOR activity is commonly dysregulated in the majority of human cancers, our work raises the plausible hypothesis that part of the beneficial effect of FASN inhibition in cancer treatment may be due to the concomitant drop in mTORC1 signalling <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R63">63</xref></sup>. Of note, in our experiments, mTORC1 and FASN inhibitors demonstrated synergistic effects in yeast, even when combined at sublethal doses for each individual compound. These data are in agreement with a previous report showing synthetic lethality of cerulenin and rapamycin in cancer cell lines <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R64">64</xref></sup>. In sum, our findings identify a direct connection between the core FA biosynthesis machinery and mTORC1 activity, reveal novel concepts of how metabolic signalling is coordinated in cells, and provide the basis for the development of advanced therapeutic tools to treat human conditions that are linked to hyperactive mTORC1 signalling.</p></sec><sec id="S8" sec-type="methods" specific-use="web-only"><title>Methods</title><sec id="S9"><title>Yeast culture</title><p id="P25">Yeast cells were grown in liquid to exponential growth phase in SC medium (1.7 g/l yeast nitrogen base (#1545, CONDA) 5 g/l ammonium sulfate (#4808211, MP Biomedicals), 20 g/l glucose (#1422, AppliChem), 2 g/l amino acid dropout -His (#D9520, US Biological), 35 mg/l histidine (#A1341, AppliChem)) at 30°C, unless otherwise stated in the figure legends. All yeast strains used in this study are listed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Suppl. Table 1</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="S10"><title>Yeast culture treatments</title><p id="P26">For starvation/re-addition experiments, yeast cells growing in exponential phase were filtered and shifted to prewarmed (30 °C) nitrogen starvation medium (1.7 g/l yeast nitrogen base, 20 g/l glucose) for 20 min. Subsequently, glutamine (#119951000, Acros) was added to a final concentration of 3.3 mM (using a 50x stock solution). Treatment with the pharmacological FAS inhibitor cerulenin (#C2389, Sigma-Aldrich) was carried out by adding the drug directly to the cell cultures at the concentration and times indicated in the figure legends.</p></sec><sec id="S11"><title>Mammalian cell culture</title><p id="P27">All cell lines were grown at 37 °C, 5% CO<sub>2</sub>. Human female embryonic kidney HEK293FT cells (#R70007, Invitrogen; RRID: CVCL_6911), human female breast adenocarcinoma MCF-7 cells (#HTB-22, ATCC; RRID:CVCL_0031), immortalized mouse embryonic fibroblasts (MEFs), and human female bone osteosarcoma U2OS cells (#HTB-96, ATCC; RRID:CVCL_0042) were cultured in high-glucose Dulbecco’s Modified Eagle Medium (DMEM) (#41965-039, Gibco), supplemented with 10% FBS (#F7524, Sigma; #S1810, Biowest). MCF-7 cells were also supplemented with 1x NEAA (non-essential amino acids) (#11140-035, Gibco). Human male diploid lung WI-26 SV40 fibroblasts (WI-26 cells; #CCL-95.1, ATCC; RRID: CVCL_2758) were cultured in DMEM/F12 GlutaMAX medium (#31331093, Thermo Fisher Scientific), containing 10% FBS. All media were supplemented with 1x Penicillin-Streptomycin (#15140-122, Gibco).</p><p id="P28">HEK293FT cells were purchased from Invitrogen. Wild-type control immortalized MEFs were a kind gift of Kun-Liang Guan (described in <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R65">65</xref></sup>). U2OS cells were a kind gift of Nils-Göran Larsson. The identity of the WI-26 cells was validated using the Short Tandem Repeat (STR) profiling service, provided by Multiplexion GmbH. The identity of the HEK293FT and MCF-7 cells was validated by the Multiplex human Cell Line Authentication test (Multiplexion GmbH), which uses a single nucleotide polymorphism (SNP) typing approach, and was performed as described at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.multiplexion.de">www.multiplexion.de</ext-link>. All cell lines were regularly tested for <italic>Mycoplasma</italic> contamination, using a PCR-based approach and were confirmed to be <italic>Mycoplasma-free.</italic></p></sec><sec id="S12"><title>Mammalian cell culture treatments</title><p id="P29">Amino acid starvation experiments were carried out as described before <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42">42</xref></sup>. Treatments with the pharmacological FASN inhibitors Fasnall (#SML1815, Sigma-Aldrich) and cerulenin (#C2389, Sigma-Aldrich) were performed by adding the drugs directly to the media at the concentrations and for times indicated in the figure legends, with DMSO (#4720.1, Roth) used as control. For lipid depletion experiments, cells were cultured in media containing 10% charcoal-stripped FBS (CD-FBS) (#A3382101, Thermo Fisher Scientific), instead of full FBS, for 24h prior to treatments with FASN inhibitors. For fatty acid supplementation, each fatty acid was first conjugated to 10% fatty-acid-free BSA (bovine serum albumin fraction V) (#10735086001, Roche) for 1 hour at 50°C in a 50:50 volumetric ratio. The BSA-conjugated C16:0, C16:1, C18:1, and C18:2 fatty acids (100 μM) were then added to the media both 16 h prior to and at the start of the treatment with FASN inhibitors. Exogenous Mal-CoA treatments were performed by adding 250 μM malonyl-CoA lithium salt (#M4263, Sigma-Aldrich) in the culture media for 30 min before cell lysis.</p></sec><sec id="S13"><title>Antibodies</title><p id="P30">All antibodies used in this study are listed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD3">Suppl. Table 2</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="S14"><title>Plasmids and molecular cloning</title><p id="P31">The pcDNA3-FLAG-hRagA<sup>QL</sup> (Q66L) and hRagC<sup>SN</sup> (S75N) vectors expressing the constitutively-active Rag GTPases were described previously <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42">42</xref></sup>. The pcDNA3-FLAG-Luc control vector was described in <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R66">66</xref></sup>. To generate the pcDNA3-FLAG-ACC1 expression vector, the long ACC1 isoform 4 (Uniprot ID Q13085-4; not used in this study) was PCR amplified from cDNA (prepared from MCF-7 cells) using appropriate primers and cloned in the XhoI/XbaI restriction sites of pcDNA3-FLAG. Next, the canonical, shorter ACC1 isoform 1 (Uniprot ID Q13085-1) was generated using the isoform 4 expression vector as a template and appropriate PCR primers, and cloned in the XhoI/BglII restriction sites of pcDNA3-FLAG-ACC1<sup>Iso4</sup>, thus replacing the long N-terminal part with that of ACC1 isoform 1. The respective pcDNA3-FLAG-ACC1<sup>S79A</sup> (isoform 1) plasmid was generated by site-directed mutagenesis using appropriate primers, and the insert was cloned in the XhoI/BglII restriction sites of pcDNA3-FLAG-ACC1. The pETM-11-4E-BP1 vector, used to express His6-tagged 4E-BP1 in bacteria, was generated by PCR-amplifying human 4E-BP1 from cDNA (prepared from HEK293FT cells) using appropriate primers and cloned in the NcoI-NotI restriction sites of pETM-11. The integrity of all constructs was verified by sequencing. All DNA oligonucleotides used in this study are listed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD4">Suppl. Table 3</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="S15"><title>mRNA isolation and cDNA synthesis</title><p id="P32">Total mRNA was isolated from cells using a standard TRIzol/chloroform-based method (#15596018, Thermo Fisher Scientific), according to manufacturer’s instructions. For cDNA synthesis, mRNA was transcribed to cDNA using the RevertAid H Minus First Strand cDNA Synthesis Kit (#K1631, Thermo Fisher Scientific) according to manufacturer’s instructions.</p></sec><sec id="S16"><title>Plasmid DNA transfections</title><p id="P33">Plasmid DNA transfections in HEK293FT cells were performed using Effectene transfection reagent (#301425, QIAGEN), according to the manufacturer’s instructions.</p></sec><sec id="S17"><title>Generation of knockout cell lines</title><p id="P34">The HEK293FT RagA/B, RagC/D and TSC1 knockout cell lines were generated using the pX459-based CRISPR/Cas9 method, as described elsewhere <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R67">67</xref></sup>. The sgRNA expression vectors were generated by cloning appropriate DNA oligonucleotides (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD4">Suppl. Table 3</xref>) in the BbsI restriction sites of pX459 (#62988, Addgene). An empty pX459 vector was used to generate matching negative control cell lines. In brief, transfected cells were selected with 3 μg/ml puromycin (#A11138-03, Thermo Fisher Scientific) 48 h post-transfection. Single-cell clones were generated by single cell dilution and knock-out clones were validated by immunoblotting.</p></sec><sec id="S18"><title>Gene silencing experiments</title><p id="P35">For mTORC1 activity assays, transient knockdown of <italic>FASN</italic> was performed using a pool of 4 siGENOME siRNAs (Horizon Discoveries). An siRNA duplex targeting the <italic>R. reniformis</italic> luciferase gene (RLuc) (#P-002070-01-50, Horizon Discoveries) was used as control. Transfections were performed using 20 nM siRNA and the Lipofectamine RNAiMAX transfection reagent (#13778075, Thermo Fisher Scientific), according to the manufacturer’s instructions. Cells were harvested or fixed 48 h post-transfection and knockdown efficiency was verified by immunoblotting.</p></sec><sec id="S19"><title>Yeast genomic manipulation</title><p id="P36">Site-directed mutagenesis in yeast was performed by CRISPR/Cas9 using the method described in <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R68">68</xref></sup> with minor optimizations. Gene deletions and genomic tagging were performed with a standard high-efficiency transformation protocol using cassettes amplified from various plasmids of the pFA6a PCR toolbox <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R69">69</xref></sup>, or by mating and tetrad dissection. See <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD5">Suppl. Table 4</xref> for the full list of the plasmids used.</p></sec><sec id="S20"><title>Yeast cell lysis and immunoblotting</title><p id="P37">For yeast protein extractions, 10 ml of cell culture were mixed with TCA (trichloroacetic acid) at a final concentration of 6%. After centrifugation, the pellet was washed with cold acetone and dried in a speed-vac. The pellet was resuspended with an amount of lysis buffer (50 mM Tris-HCl pH 7.5, 5 mM EDTA, 6 M urea, 1% SDS) that was proportional to the OD<sub>600mm</sub> of the original cell culture. Proteins were extracted by disruption in a Precellys machine in the presence of glass beads. Subsequently, a Laemmli-based sample buffer (350 mM Tris-HCl pH 6.8, 30% glycerol, 600 mM DTT, 10% SDS, 0.2 mg/ml bromophenol blue) was mixed (1:1) with whole cell extracts and boiled at 98°C for 5 minutes. The analysis was carried out by SDS-PAGE using antibodies as indicated in the figure legends. Band intensities were quantified using the ImageJ software.</p></sec><sec id="S21"><title>Mammalian cell lysis and immunoblotting</title><p id="P38">For standard SDS-PAGE and immunoblotting experiments, cells form a well of a 12-well plate were lysed in 250 μl of ice-cold Triton lysis buffer (50 mM Tris pH 7.5, 1% Triton X-100, 150 mM NaCl, 50 mM NaF, 2 mM Na-vanadate, 0.011 gr/ml beta-glycerophosphate), supplemented with 1x PhosSTOP phosphatase inhibitors (#4906837001, Sigma-Aldrich) and 1x cOmplete protease inhibitors (#11836153001, Roche), for 10 minutes on ice. Samples were clarified by centrifugation (14.000 rpm, 15 min, 4 °C) and supernatants were boiled in 1x SDS sample buffer (5x SDS sample buffer: 350 mM Tris-HCl pH 6.8, 30% glycerol, 600 mM DTT, 12.8% SDS, 0.12% bromophenol blue). Samples were analysed by SDS-PAGE using specific primary antibodies as indicated in the figures. Band intensities were quantified using the ImageJ software.</p></sec><sec id="S22"><title>Co-immunoprecipitation (co-IP)</title><p id="P39">For yeast co-immunoprecipitations experiments, cells were collected by filtration and immediately frozen in liquid nitrogen. Subsequently, the pellets were mechanically disrupted in a FastPrep machine in 50 ml tubes containing 5 ml of ice-cold lysis buffer (50 mM Tris-HCl pH 7.5, 150 mM NaCl, 10% glycerol, 0.1% Nonidet P40), supplemented with 1x EDTA-free protease inhibitor cocktail (#11697498001, Roche), 1x PhosSTOP phosphatase inhibitor (#04906837001, Roche) and 4 ml glass beads. Total cell extracts were recovered from beads and cleared by centrifugation. At this stage, samples were taken for input analysis and denatured with a Laemmli-based sample buffer (350 mM Tris-HCl pH 6.8, 30% glycerol, 600 mM DTT, 10% SDS, 0.2 mg/ml bromophenol blue). 10-20 mg of cleared lysates were incubated with anti-HA pre-conjugated magnetic beads (#88837, Pierce) for 2 hours at 4 °C. The beads were then washed 5 times with high salt lysis buffer (50 mM Tris-HCl pH 7.5, 300 mM NaCl, 10% glycerol, 0.1% Nonidet P40) and eventually resuspended in 20 μl lysis buffer and 20 μl 2x Laemmli buffer. Samples were analysed by SDS-PAGE using specific primary antibodies as indicated in the figures.</p><p id="P40">For mammalian endogenous protein co-immunoprecipitation experiments, cells of a near-confluent 10 cm dish were lysed in CHAPS IP buffer (50 mM Tris pH 7.5, 0.3% CHAPS, 150 mM NaCl, 50 mM NaF, 2 mM Na-vanadate, 0.011 gr/ml beta-glycerophosphate), supplemented with 1x PhosSTOP phosphatase inhibitors and 1x EDTA-free cOmplete protease inhibitors (11873580001, Roche) for 10 minutes on ice. Samples were clarified by centrifugation (14000 rpm, 15 min, 4 °C) and supernatants were subjected to IP by the addition of 3 μl of each antibody, incubation at 4 °C rotating for 3 h, followed by incubation (4 °C, rotating) with 30 μl of pre-washed Protein A agarose bead slurry (#11134515001, Roche) for an additional hour. Beads were then washed four times with CHAPS IP wash buffer (50 mM Tris pH 7.5, 0.3% CHAPS, 150 mM NaCl, 50 mM NaF) and boiled in 1x SDS loading buffer. A portion of the samples was kept aside as inputs, prior to the addition of antibodies. Samples were analysed by SDS-PAGE and the presence of co-immunoprecipitated proteins was detected by immunoblotting with appropriate specific antibodies.</p><p id="P41">To test if malonyl-CoA influences mTORC1 complex stability/composition, 1 mM malonyl-CoA lithium salt solution was added to the lysates before immunoprecipitation of mTOR, as described above. For mTORC1 <italic>in vitro</italic> kinase assays, endogenous mTOR was immunopurified from 1x 10 cm dish per condition as described above. To test malonylation of FASN and mTOR, endogenous proteins were immunopurified from 1x 10 cm dish per condition as described above, except for using a high-stringency Triton IP lysis buffer (50 mM Tris pH 7.5, 1% Triton X-100, 500 mM NaCl, 50 mM NaF, 2 mM Na-vanadate, 0.011 gr/ml beta-glycerophosphate, 1x PhosSTOP phosphatase inhibitors, 1x EDTA-free cOmplete protease inhibitors) and washing 3x with Triton IP wash buffer (50 mM Tris pH 7.5, 1% Triton X-100, 500 mM NaCl, 50 mM NaF) and 2x with Tris wash buffer (50 mM Tris pH 7.5) to remove interacting proteins. Protein malonylation was assayed by immunoblotting using a Mal-K-specific antibody.</p></sec><sec id="S23"><title>Production of recombinant His<sub>6</sub>-tagged 4E-BP1 protein in bacteria</title><p id="P42">Recombinant His6-tagged 4E-BP1 protein was produced by transforming <italic>E. coli</italic> BL21 RP electrocompetent bacteria with the pETM-11-4E-BP1 vector described above, according to standard procedures. In brief, protein expression was induced with IPTG (isopropyl-β-D-thiogalactopyranoside) for 3 h at 30 °C, and His<sub>6</sub>-4E-BP1 was purified using Ni-NTA agarose (#1018244, QIAGEN) and eluted with 250 mM imidazole (#A1073, Applichem).</p></sec><sec id="S24"><title>Yeast TORC1 kinase activity assays</title><p id="P43">TORC1 was purified from yeast cells and radioactive <italic>in vitro</italic> kinase assays were performed essentially as previously described <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R46">46</xref></sup>. In brief, kinase reactions (total volume 30 μl) were performed with 400 ng purified His<sub>6</sub>-Lst4<sup>Loop</sup> protein and 60 ng TORC1 in kinase buffer (50 mM HEPES/NaOH pH 7.5, 150 mM NaCl). To test the effect of Mal-CoA (#M4263, Sigma-Aldrich), Ac-CoA (#A2181, Sigma-Aldrich) and CoA (#C3144, Sigma-Aldrich), the kinase reaction was preincubated for 15 min with 2 μl of each compound from a 15x stock solution. Reactions were started by adding 2 μl of ATP mix (62.5 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 4.5 mM ATP, 0.8 μM [γ-<sup>32</sup>P]ATP (#SRP-501, Hartmann Analytic). For kinase assays with different ATP concentrations, reactions were started by adding 2 μl of serial 3-fold dilutions of a more concentrated ATP mix (72 mM ATP, 0.8 μM [γ-<sup>32</sup>P]ATP), always containing 62.5 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>. All reactions were carried out at 30°C for 10 min and stopped by the addition of 3x sample buffer (50 mM Tris-HCl pH 6.8, 5% SDS, 0.05% bromophenol blue, 630 mM DTT, 30% glycerol) and heating at 65°C for 10 min. Proteins were separated by SDS-PAGE and stained in-gel with SYPRO Ruby (#S4942, Sigma-Aldrich) as loading control. Substrate phosphorylation was analysed by autoradiography using a Typhoon FLA 9500 phosphorimager (GE Healthcare) and the raw density of the signals was quantified using the gel analysis tool of ImageJ.</p></sec><sec id="S25"><title>Mammalian mTORC1 kinase activity assays</title><p id="P44"><italic>In vitro</italic> mTORC1 kinase assays were developed based on previous reports <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R70">70</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R71">71</xref></sup>. In brief, endogenous mTORC1 complexes were purified from HEK293FT cells, essentially as described in the ‘Co-immunoprecipitation’ section, with minor modifications. Following the last wash step with CHAPS IP wash buffer, beads were washed once with kinase wash buffer (25 mM HEPES pH 7.4, 20 mM KCl) and excess liquid was removed with a Hamilton syringe, with final bead volume being approximately 10 μl. Kinase reactions were prepared by adding 10 μl 3x kinase assay buffer (75 mM HEPES/KOH pH 7.4, 60 mM KCl, 30 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>) to the beads. To test the effect of Mal-CoA (#M4263, Sigma-Aldrich), Ac-CoA (#A2181, Sigma-Aldrich), and CoA (#C3144, Sigma-Aldrich) on mTORC1 activity, 1 μl of each compound was pre-incubated with the kinase complex for 5 minutes prior to initiation of the reaction. Compound concentrations are indicated in the figures. Reactions were started by adding 10 μl of kinase assay start buffer (25 mM HEPES/KOH pH 7.4, 140 mM KCl, 10 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>), supplemented with 500 μM ATP (final concentration in the reaction) and 35 ng recombinant His6-4E-BP1 substrate. For competition assays, ATP concentrations are described in the respective figures. Reactions were incubated at 30 °C for 30 min, and stopped by the addition of one volume 2x SDS loading buffer and boiling (5 min, 95 °C). Samples were run in SDS-PAGE and the mTORC1-mediated phosphorylation on 4E-BP1<sup>T37/46</sup> was detected by immunoblotting with a specific antibody (#9459, Cell Signaling Technology). Signals were quantified using the gel analysis tool of ImageJ and shown as phospho-4E-BP1<sup>T37/46</sup>/4E-BP1 ratio.</p></sec><sec id="S26"><title>Immunofluorescence and confocal microscopy</title><p id="P45">Immunofluorescence / confocal microscopy experiments were performed as described previously <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42">42</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R72">72</xref></sup>. In brief, cells were seeded on glass coverslips (coated with fibronectin for experiments with HEK293FT cells), treated as described in the figure legends, and fixed with 4% paraformaldehyde (PFA) in 1x PBS (10 min, RT), followed by two permeabilization/washing steps with PBT (1x PBS, 0.1 % Tween-20). Cells were blocked in BBT (1x PBS, 0.1% Tween-20, 1% BSA) for 45 minutes. Staining with anti-mTOR (#2983, Cell Signaling Technology) and anti-LAMP2 (#H4B4, Developmental Studies Hybridoma Bank) primary antibodies diluted 1:200 in BBT solution was performed for 2h followed by three washes with PBT. Next, cells were stained with highly cross-adsorbed fluorescent secondary antibodies (Donkey anti-rabbit FITC, Donkey anti-mouse TRITC; both from Jackson ImmunoResearch) diluted 1:200 in BBT for 1 h. Nuclei were stained with DAPI (#A1001, VWR) (1:1000 in PBT) for 5 min and coverslips were washed three times with PBT solution before mounting on glass slides with Fluoromount-G (#00-4958-02, Invitrogen). All images were captured on an SP8 Leica confocal microscope (TCS SP8 X or TCS SP8 DLS, Leica Microsystems) using a 40x oil objective lens. Image acquisition was performed using the LAS X software (Leica Microsystems).</p></sec><sec id="S27"><title>Quantification of colocalization</title><p id="P46">Colocalization analysis in confocal microscopy experiments was performed as in <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43">43</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R72">72</xref></sup>, using the Coloc2 plugin of the Fiji software <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R73">73</xref></sup>. A minimum of 12 representative images captured from 3-4 independent experiments were used per condition and Manders’ colocalization coefficient (MCC) with automatic Costes thresholding <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R74">74</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R76">76</xref></sup> was calculated in individual cells. The area corresponding to the cell nucleus was excluded from the cell ROI to prevent false-positive colocalization due to automatic signal adjustments. MCC is defined as a part of the signal of interest (mTOR), which overlaps with a second signal (LAMP2). Values are displayed as mean ± SEM, and significance was calculated using Student’s t-test (for pairwise comparisons) and one-way ANOVA with <italic>post hoc</italic> Holm-Sidak comparisons using GraphPad Prism.</p></sec><sec id="S28"><title>Proximity Ligation Assays (PLA)</title><p id="P47">Proximity of endogenous FASN to lysosomes (LAMP2 as lysosomal marker) was assessed in MCF-7 cells by PLA assays, using the Duolink In Situ Red Starter Kit Mouse/Rabbit (#DUO92101, Sigma-Aldrich), according to the manufacturer’s instructions with minor modifications. To test specificity of the FASN/LAMP2 PLA signal in the respective assays, transient knockdown of FASN or LAMP2 was performed using a reverse transfection protocol with appropriate siRNAs (siGENOME, Horizon Discoveries) and Lipofectamine RNAiMAX transfection reagent, according to the manufacturer’s instructions. Cells were trypsinized 48 h post-transfection, re-seeded in 16-well chamber slides (#171080, Nunc Lab-Tek), and assayed approximately 24 h later. In brief, cells were fixed in 4% PFA (in 1x PBS), washed/permeabilized with PBT (1x PBS, 0.1 % Tween-20), and blocked with Blocking solution from the Duolink kit. Samples were incubated overnight at 4 °C with specific anti-FASN (#PA5-22061, Thermo Fisher Scientific; dilution 1:400) and anti-LAMP2 (#H4B4, Developmental Studies Hybridoma Bank; dilution 1:200) primary antibodies, processed according to the kit instructions and mounted on slides with a drop of DAPI-containing Duolink in situ mounting medium. Images were captured on a Leica TCS SP8 confocal microscope. A minimum of 10 randomly chosen fields were acquired per condition as z-stacks, and total PLA signal was calculated on the maximal projections of the single PLA channel using ImageJ. Data in graphs presented as the average PLA area per cell, with n<sub>siCtrl</sub> = 1100, n<sub>siFASN</sub> = 1272, and n<sub>siLAMP2</sub> = 1311 individual cells. Statistical analysis was performed with GraphPad Prism.</p></sec><sec id="S29"><title>Protein modelling</title><p id="P48">From the crystallographic structure of human mTOR (PDB ID: 3JBZ), the missing residues were built by means of the Modeller version 10.0 <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R77">77</xref></sup>, using the amino acid sequences provided by the Uniprot database (UniProtKB: P42345). Next, the kinase domain (KD) region (residues 684-1058) was extracted and used for the docking calculation. The mTOR R2168A/R2170A double mutant was modelled with UCSF Chimera, using the Dynameomics rotamer library <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R78">78</xref></sup>, starting from the mTOR structure described above.</p></sec><sec id="S30"><title>Ligand modelling</title><p id="P49">Starting from the x-ray structure of human mTOR in a complex with ADP (PDB ID: 3JBZ) initial placement of the different ligands inside the binding pocket was performed. For ATP, the missing phosphate group to obtain the ATP molecule from ADP was rebuilt manually. For malonyl-CoA, its structure was extracted from PDB ID: 5MY0 and subsequently aligned to the ATP structure in the mTOR catalytic pocket. Similar procedures were used for acetyl-CoA and Coenzyme A, and their coordinates were retrieved from PDB ID: 1MZJ and 4l8A, respectively. All compounds were parameterized using the Ligand Reader &amp; Modeller tool of the CHARMM-GUI software <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R79">79</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R81">81</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="S31"><title>Docking simulations</title><p id="P50">For each compound, ten docking simulations were performed using the AutoDock software (version 4.2) <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R82">82</xref></sup>. Polar hydrogens and Kollman charges were added to the macromolecule <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R83">83</xref></sup>. Gasteiger charges were added to the ligands <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R84">84</xref></sup> and, to confine the adenosine group in an ATP-like orientation, all rotatable bonds were blocked except for the lateral chain. The grid dimension was adjusted to 54 × 40 × 40 points, and the ligand-macromolecule interaction maps were computed using AutoGrid <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R85">85</xref></sup>. The automated docking software AutoDock Vina <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R86">86</xref></sup> was used to calculate the binding affinity of ligands and the mTOR kinase domain. Docking energies were evaluated by using empirical-free energy functions and Lamarckian genetic algorithms <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R87">87</xref></sup>. A regular precision and a rigid ligand-docking were set for each docking run. To assess the stability of each docked pose the energy values obtained by the docking were considered.</p></sec><sec id="S32"><title>Molecular Dynamics (MD) simulations</title><p id="P51">For ATP, MD simulations of the human mTOR kinase domain (KD) region (residues 684-1058) (PDB ID: 3JBZ) were started after manual addition of the missing phosphate group to the structure of ADP in complex with two Mg<sup>2+</sup> ions. For the other compounds (malonyl-CoA, acetyl-CoA, and CoA), the three most favourable poses from the docking calculation were selected as the starting point for the MD simulations. Each system was solvated with the TIP3P water model <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R88">88</xref></sup> and neutralized with Na<sup>+</sup> and Cl<sup>–</sup> ions at physiological concentration (0.15 M). An energy minimization step was performed using the steepest descent algorithm. After the minimization, a NVT equilibration of 50 ps at 300K was performed, using the V-rescale thermostat with a τT = 1 ps and an integration time step of 2 fs <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R89">89</xref></sup>. Then, NPT simulation was run with a time step of 2 fs, using the Parrinello-Rahman barostat <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R90">90</xref></sup>, isotropic coupling and τp = 2 ps. The temperature was kept constant at 310 K. The electrostatic interactions were calculated using the particle mesh Ewald method <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R91">91</xref></sup> with a cut-off of 1.2 nm. The same cut-off was also applied for the van der Waals interactions. The simulations were performed with GROMACS (version 2020) <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R92">92</xref></sup> and using the CHARMM-36 force field <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R93">93</xref></sup>. For each complex, we performed three replicate measurements lasting 400 ns, resulting in an aggregated time of 1.2 μs per system.</p></sec><sec id="S33"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="P52">Statistical analysis and presentation of quantification data was performed using GraphPad Prism (version 9.1.0). Data in graphs shown as mean ± SEM. Box plots: central line, median; box, interquartile range (IQR) [25<sup>th</sup> (Q1)-75<sup>th</sup> (Q3) percentile]; whiskers, Q3+1.5*IQR and Q1-1.5*IQR. Significance was calculated using Student’s t-test (for pairwise comparisons) or one-way ANOVA with <italic>post hoc</italic> Holm-Sidak test (pairwise comparisons to controls). Sample sizes (n) and significance values are indicated in figure legends (* p &lt; 0.05, ** p &lt; 0.005, *** p &lt; 0.0005, **** p &lt; 0.00005, ns = non-significant).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="extended-data" id="S34"><title>Extended Data</title><fig id="F5" position="anchor"><label>Extended Data Figure 1</label><caption><title>Functional pharmacogenetic interactions between TOR pathway genes and Acc1/Fas1 activity in yeast.</title><p id="P53"><bold>(a)</bold> Yeast Rag GTPase mutants that impair or promote TORC1 activity are cerulenin-sensitive or - resistant, respectively. Wild-type (wt), hyperactive Acc1<sup>S1157A</sup>-expressing (<italic>acc1<sup>S1157A</sup></italic>), and <italic>gtr1Δ</italic> cells that express plasmid-encoded wild-type <italic>GTR1</italic>, <italic>Gtr1<sup>Q65L</sup></italic> (TORC1-activating), <italic>Gtr1<sup>S20L</sup></italic> (TORC1-inactivating), or containing an empty vector, were 10-fold serially diluted, spotted on plates with the indicated concentrations of cerulenin or vehicle (Control), and grown at 30°C for 2 days.</p><p id="P54"><bold>(b)</bold> TORC1 and EGOC mutants are sensitive to cerulenin and hypersensitive to combined cerulenin and rapamycin treatments. Drop spot assays as in (a) using the indicated wt and mutant strains, with plates containing the indicated concentrations of rapamycin and/or cerulenin.</p><p id="P55"><bold>(c)</bold> Positive correlation between rapamycin- and cerulenin-induced SATAY transposition profiles in TORC1 and EGOC genes. The dot plot shows the ratio of transposition events (reads) per coding gene in rapamycin- and cerulenin-treated versus untreated SATAY libraries previously published in <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">25</xref></sup>.</p><p id="P56"><bold>(d)</bold> Negative correlation between rapamycin- and soraphen-A-induced SATAY transposition profiles in TORC1 and EGOC genes. The dot plot shows the ratio of transposition events (reads) per coding gene in rapamycin- and soraphen-A-treated versus untreated SATAY libraries previously published in <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">25</xref></sup>.</p><p id="P57"><bold>(e)</bold> Box plot summary of the pairwise correlations of the transposon profiles of TORC1 and EGOC genes shown in (c-d).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS156775-f005"/></fig><fig id="F6" position="anchor"><label>Extended Data Figure 2</label><caption><title>Perturbations in Acc1 influence Mal-CoA levels and TORC1 activity in yeast cells.</title><p id="P58"><bold>(a-b)</bold> Pharmacogenetic interactions of rapamycin and cerulenin indicate a potential inhibitory role of Mal-CoA in TORC1 signalling. <italic>gtr1Δ</italic> and <italic>acc1<sup>S1157A</sup>gtr1Δ</italic> mutant strains containing an empty vector or expressing plasmid-encoded wild-type <italic>GTR1</italic>, <italic>gtr1<sup>Q65L</sup></italic>, or <italic>gtr1<sup>S20L</sup></italic> were spotted and grown on plates with the indicated concentrations of rapamycin and/or cerulenin (a). The respective <italic>gtr2Δ</italic> and <italic>acc1<sup>S1157A</sup>gtr2Δ</italic> mutant strains expressing plasmid-encoded wild-type <italic>GTR2</italic>, <italic>gtr2<sup>Q66L</sup></italic>, or <italic>gtr2<sup>S23L</sup></italic> are shown in (b).</p><p id="P59"><bold>(c-d)</bold> Mal-CoA levels in wt and hyperactive <italic>acc1<sup>S1157A</sup></italic> cells are significantly reduced by introduction of the hypomorphic <italic>acc1<sup>E392K</sup></italic> mutation. Mal-CoA levels were assessed by GFP blots in cells grown at 24°C (c) and quantified (d) as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1b and Fig. 1c</xref>, respectively, n = 3.</p><p id="P60"><bold>(e)</bold> The <italic>acc1<sup>E392K</sup></italic> mutation causes temperature-sensitive growth even when combined with the <italic>acc1<sup>S1157A</sup></italic> mutation. Exponentially growing cells with the indicated genotypes were spotted on plates (10-fold serial dilutions) and grown for 3 days at 24°C or 37°C.</p><p id="P61"><bold>(f-g)</bold> Mutation of E392K in <italic>acc1<sup>S1157A</sup></italic> suppresses the TORC1-inhibitory effect of <italic>acc1<sup>S1157A</sup></italic>. Immunoblots (f) and quantifications of TORC1 activity (p-Sch9<sup>Thr737</sup>/Sch9) (g) were carried out as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1e and Fig. 1f</xref>, respectively, n = 4.</p><p id="P62">Data in graphs shown as mean ± SEM. * = p &lt; 0.05, ** = p &lt; 0.005</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS156775-f006"/></fig><fig id="F7" position="anchor"><label>Extended Data Figure 3</label><caption><title>C-terminal tagging of Acc1<sup>S1157A</sup> restrains its capacity to stimulate Mal-CoA levels and inhibit TORC1 in yeast.</title><p id="P63"><bold>(a-b)</bold> C-terminal GFP-tagging of endogenous Acc1<sup>S1157A</sup> significantly reduces Mal-CoA levels. See <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1b and Fig. 1c</xref> for details. Ponceau staining as loading control (a). Quantification of relative Mal-CoA levels (GFP/Ponceau signal) in (b), n = 3.</p><p id="P64"><bold>(c)</bold> C-terminal GFP-tagging of endogenous Acc1<sup>S1157A</sup> partially reverts its ability to render cells rapamycin- and cerulenin-sensitive. In control experiments, C-terminal GFP-tagging of endogenous Fas1 rendered wt cells cerulenin-sensitive and further enhanced the cerulenin-sensitivity of <italic>acc1<sup>S1157A</sup></italic> cells, while marginally affecting the rapamycin-sensitivity of the respective cells. Spot assays with the indicated yeast genotypes and rapamycin and/or cerulenin concentrations performed as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Extended Data Fig. 1a</xref>.</p><p id="P65"><bold>(d-e)</bold> C-terminal GFP-tagging of endogenous Acc1<sup>S1157A</sup> suppresses its ability to inhibit TORC1 in exponentially growing and Gln-restimulated cells. TORC1 activities assessed as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1e</xref> (d). Quantification of relative TORC1 activity (p-Sch9<sup>Thr737</sup>/Sch9) in (e), n = 3.</p><p id="P66">Data in graphs shown as mean ± SEM. * = p &lt; 0.05, ** = p &lt; 0.005.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS156775-f007"/></fig><fig id="F8" position="anchor"><label>Extended Data Figure 4</label><caption><title>FASN inhibition downregulates mTORC1 in a variety of different mammalian cell lines.</title><p id="P67"><bold>(a-b)</bold> Fasnall treatment downregulates mTORC1 activity in MEFs. Cells were treated for 30 min with 25 μM Fasnall or DMSO (–) as control (a). Quantification of mTORC1 activity (p-S6K<sup>T389</sup>/S6K) in (b), n = 7.</p><p id="P68"><bold>(c)</bold> Cerulenin treatment downregulates mTORC1 activity in MEFs. Cells were treated for 2 or 4 h with 50 μM Cerulenin (Ceru) or DMSO (4 h) as control (–), n = 3.</p><p id="P69"><bold>(d-e)</bold> Cerulenin treatment downregulates mTORC1 activity in MCF-7 cells. Cells were treated for 2 or 4 h with 50 μM Cerulenin (Ceru) or with DMSO (4 h) as control (–) (d). Quantification of mTORC1 activity (p-S6K<sup>T389</sup>/S6K) in (e), n = 9.</p><p id="P70"><bold>(f)</bold> <italic>FASN</italic> knockdown downregulates mTORC1 activity and increases Mal-CoA levels in WI-26 fibroblasts. mTORC1 activity assayed by phosphorylation of S6K. Mal-K blots show total protein malonylation, indicative of intracellular Mal-CoA levels.</p><p id="P71"><bold>(g)</bold> Fasnall treatment downregulates mTORC1 activity in U2OS cells. Cells were treated for 30 or 60 min with 25 μM Fasnall or DMSO as control (–), n = 3.</p><p id="P72"><bold>(h)</bold> Cerulenin treatment downregulates mTORC1 activity in U2OS cells. Cells were treated for 2 or 4 h with 50 μM Cerulenin (Ceru) or DMSO (4 h) as control (–).</p><p id="P73">Data in graphs shown as mean ± SEM. ** = p &lt; 0.005, *** = p &lt; 0.0005.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS156775-f008"/></fig><fig id="F9" position="anchor"><label>Extended Data Figure 5</label><caption><title>Exogenous Mal-CoA or perturbations in FASN/Fas1 or yeast Acc1 activity specifically downregulate mTORC1, but not mTORC2.</title><p id="P74"><bold>(a-b)</bold> Exogenous Mal-CoA addition is capable of downregulating mTORC1. HEK293FT cells were treated with 25 μM Fasnall or 250 μM Mal-CoA for 30 min. mTORC1 activity was monitored by S6K phosphorylation (a). Quantification of mTORC1 activity (p-S6K<sup>S389</sup>/S6K), in (b), n = 4.</p><p id="P75"><bold>(c-d)</bold> Fasnall treatment does not influence mTORC2 activity in HEK293FT cells, assessed by immunoblotting for AKT phosphorylation. Cells were treated for 30 min with 25 μM Fasnall or DMSO (–) as control (c). Quantification of mTORC2 activity (p-AKT<sup>S473</sup>/AKT) in (d), n = 4.</p><p id="P76"><bold>(e-f)</bold> Cerulenin treatment does not influence mTORC2 activity in HEK293FT cells, assessed by immunoblotting for AKT phosphorylation. Cells were treated for 4 h with 50 μM Cerulenin (Ceru) or DMSO (–) as control (e). Quantification of mTORC2 activity (p-AKT<sup>S473</sup>/AKT) in (f), n = 3.</p><p id="P77"><bold>(g-j)</bold> Expression of the <italic>acc1<sup>S1157A</sup></italic> allele or treatment of yeast cells with cerulenin (20 μM, 2 h) does not downregulate TORC2 activity. Immunoblotting with the indicated antibodies using lysates from control (–) or cerulenin-treated (+) wild-type (wt) or <italic>acc1<sup>S1157A</sup></italic> mutant cells. Phosphorylation of Ypk1 used as TORC2 read-out. Mal-K blots show total protein malonylation, indicative of intracellular Mal-CoA levels (g). Quantification of TORC2 activity (p-Ypk1<sup>T662</sup>/Ypk1), TORC1 activity (p-Sch9<sup>T737</sup>/Sch9), and lysine malonylation (Mal-K/Adh1) in (h), (i), (j), respectively, n = 3</p><p id="P78">Data in graphs shown as mean ± SEM. * = p &lt; 0.05, ** = p &lt; 0.005, *** = p &lt; 0.0005, **** = p &lt; 0.00005.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS156775-f009"/></fig><fig id="F10" position="anchor"><label>Extended Data Figure 6</label><caption><title>FASN inhibition downregulates mTORC1 activity independently from lipid availability and mTOR/Tor1 malonylation.</title><p id="P79"><bold>(a)</bold> Depletion of exogenous lipid sources does not influence the mTORC1 response to FASN inhibition. HEK293FT cells were cultured in full FBS- or charcoal-stripped FBS (CS-FBS)-containing media for 24 h, and then treated with 25 μM Fasnall for 30 or 60 min, or DMSO as control (–). mTORC1 activity assessed by phosphorylation of S6K.</p><p id="P80"><bold>(b)</bold> Immunoblots with lysates from control (–) or Cerulenin-treated (50 μM, 4 h) MCF-7 cells, supplemented with BSA-conjugated palmitate (C16:0) or BSA as control. Cells were cultured in full FBS- or charcoal-stripped FBS (CS-FBS)-containing media for 24 h prior to treatments. mTORC1 activity assayed by phosphorylation of S6K.</p><p id="P81"><bold>(c-d)</bold> Exogenous expression of a hyperactive ACC1 mutant (ACC1<sup>S79A</sup>) cooperates with FASN inhibition to downregulate mTORC1 in HEK293FT cells, without influencing the response to AA starvation. Cells were transfected with vectors expressing FLAG-tagged WT or S79A ACC1, or Luciferase (Luc) as control, and treated with Fasnall (25 μM, 30 min) or AA-starvation media (1 h) as indicated. mTORC1 activity assayed by phosphorylation of S6K (c). Quantification of mTORC1 activity (p-S6K<sup>T389</sup>/S6K) in (d). Data shown as mean ± SEM, n = 3. * = p &lt; 0.05, *** = p &lt; 0.0005.</p><p id="P82"><bold>(e)</bold> No detectable mTOR malonylation in HEK293FT cells. Endogenous mTOR (left) or FASN (right) proteins were immunopurified from control or cerulenin-treated (50 μM, 4 h) cells, and protein malonylation was assayed using an anti-malonyl-lysine (Mal-K) antibody.</p><p id="P83"><bold>(f)</bold> Tor1 is not malonylated in yeast cells. N-terminally HA-tagged Tor1 or C-terminally HA-tagged Fas1 were immunopurified from control (–) or cerulenin-treated (10 μM, 2 h) cells grown in exponential phase. Protein malonylation was assessed using an anti-malonyl-lysine (Mal-K) antibody.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS156775-f010"/></fig><fig id="F11" position="anchor"><label>Extended Data Figure 7</label><caption><title>Perturbations in FASN and Acc1 affect mTORC1 activity independently from the Rag and TSC complexes.</title><p id="P84"><bold>(a)</bold> Individual or combined loss of Gtr1 and Gtr2, alone or in combination with <italic>acc1<sup>S1157A</sup></italic>, does not influence Mal-CoA levels. Immunoblots with lysates from the indicated yeast strains, also expressing the fapR/fapOp-yeGFP reporter system, analysed as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1b</xref>. Mal-CoA levels indicated by GFP expression.</p><p id="P85"><bold>(b-c)</bold> Expression of the <italic>acc1<sup>S1157A</sup></italic> allele inhibits TORC1 in exponentially growing cells in a Gtr-independent manner. Immunoblots with lysates from the indicated yeast strains assayed for TORC1 activity as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1b</xref> (b). Quantification of TORC1 activity (p-Sch9<sup>T737</sup>/Sch9) in (c), n = 6.</p><p id="P86"><bold>(d-e)</bold> Expression of the GTP-locked Gtr1<sup>Q65L</sup> allele does not suppress the TORC1 inhibition mediated by the Acc1<sup>S1157A</sup> allele. The indicated yeast strains were grown exponentially and assayed for TORC1 activity as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1b</xref>. Plasmid-encoded genes shown in brackets (d). Quantification of TORC1 activity (p-Sch9<sup>T737</sup>/Sch9) in (e), n = 6.</p><p id="P87"><bold>(f-g)</bold> FASN inhibition downregulates mTORC1 activity independently from the Rags. WT or RagA/B KO HEK293FT cells were treated with 25 μM Fasnall for the indicated times and mTORC1 activity was assayed by immunoblotting (f). Quantification of mTORC1 activity (p-S6K<sup>S389</sup>/S6K), normalized to each DMSO-treated control, in (g), n = 4.</p><p id="P88"><bold>(h)</bold> WT, RagA/B KO, or RagC/D KO HEK293FT cells were treated with 50 μM cerulenin (Ceru) for the indicated times and mTORC1 activity was assayed by immunoblotting and S6K phosphorylation (f). n = 5.</p><p id="P89"><bold>(i-j)</bold> Constitutively active Rags that blunt the AA starvation response do not prevent mTORC1 downregulation by FASN inhibition. HEK293FT cells were transiently transfected with vectors expressing FLAG-tagged RagA<sup>QL</sup> and RagC<sup>SN</sup> mutants, or Luciferase (Luc) as control, and treated with 25 μM Fasnall for the indicated times or with AA starvation media for 1 h. mTORC1 activity assayed by immunoblotting (i). Quantification of mTORC1 activity (p-S6K<sup>S389</sup>/S6K), normalized to each DMSO-treated control, in (j), n = 3.</p><p id="P90"><bold>(k-l)</bold> FASN inhibition downregulates mTORC1 activity independently from the TSC. WT or TSC1 KO HEK293FT cells were treated with 25 μM Fasnall (30 min) or with AA starvation media (1 h). mTORC1 activity was assayed by immunoblotting (k). Quantification of mTORC1 activity (p-S6K<sup>S389</sup>/S6K), normalized to each DMSO-treated control, in (l), n = 6 for Fasnall (left), n = 3 for AA starvation (right). <bold>(m-n)</bold> As in (k-l), but using 50 μM Cerulenin (Ceru) (4 h) to inhibit FASN (m). Quantification of mTORC1 activity (p-S6K<sup>S389</sup>/S6K), normalized to each DMSO-treated control, in (n), n = 3.</p><p id="P91">Data in all graphs shown as mean ± SEM. * = p &lt;05, ** = p &lt;005, *** = p &lt;0005, **** = p &lt;00005.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS156775-f011"/></fig><fig id="F12" position="anchor"><label>Extended Data Figure 8</label><caption><title>mTOR/Tor1 and Gtr1 localization upon FASN inhibition or yeast Acc1 hyperactivation.</title><p id="P92"><bold>(a-b)</bold> Constitutive activation of Acc1 does not alter vacuolar morphology or the subcellular localization of GFP-Tor1 (a) or GFP-Gtr1 (b). Wild-type (wt) or <italic>acc1<sup>S1157A</sup></italic> cells expressing GFP-Tor1 or GFP-Gtr1 from plasmids were grown exponentially and localization of GFP fusion proteins was assayed by fluorescence microscopy. Vacuoles stained with the vacuolar membrane fluorescent dye FM4-64. Scale bars = 5 μm.</p><p id="P93"><bold>(c-d)</bold> Colocalization analysis of mTOR with LAMP2 (lysosomal marker) in HEK293FT cells treated with 25μM Fasnall for the indicated times using confocal microscopy. Magnified insets and intensity plots for selected regions shown to the right. Scale bars = 5 μm (c). Quantification of colocalization from individual cells in (d). Pooled data from n = 4 independent experiments.</p><p id="P94"><bold>(e-f)</bold> As in (c-d), but inhibiting FASN with 50 μM cerulenin for the indicated times. Scale bars = 5 μm (e). Quantification from individual cells in (f). Pooled data from n = 3 independent experiments.</p><p id="P95"><bold>(g)</bold> Specific staining of endogenous FASN by immunofluorescence. Control or <italic>FASN</italic> knockdown MCF-7 cells were stained with an anti-FASN antibody and signal from endogenous FASN was detected by confocal microscopy. Nuclei stained with DAPI. Scale bars = 20 μm.</p><p id="P96">Data in dot plots shown as mean ± SEM. * = p &lt;05, ** = p &lt;005, *** = p &lt;0005.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS156775-f012"/></fig><fig id="F13" position="anchor"><label>Extended Data Figure 9</label><caption><title>Site-specific docking simulations for Mal-CoA, Ac-CoA, and CoA in the catalytic pocket of mTOR.</title><p id="P97"><bold>(a)</bold> The best three docking poses of malonyl-CoA (Mal-CoA; shown in green) aligned to ATP (violet) in the mTOR catalytic pocket. The binding energy value (ΔGb) for each conformation is shown below the docking models. These conformations were selected as the starting point to perform all atom MD simulations.</p><p id="P98"><bold>(b)</bold> As in (a), but for acetyl-CoA (Ac-CoA), shown in cyan.</p><p id="P99"><bold>(c)</bold> As in (a), but for Coenzyme A (CoA), shown in yellow.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS156775-f013"/></fig><fig id="F14" position="anchor"><label>Extended Data Figure 10</label><caption><title>Molecular dynamics simulation and docking experiments suggest that charged interactions stabilize Mal-CoA in the mTOR pocket.</title><p id="P100"><bold>(a)</bold> The malonyl group of Mal-CoA forms salt bridges with charged residues at the edge of the mTOR catalytic pocket (lateral view). Representative Mal-CoA (green) conformation sampled by MD simulations. The hydrogen bonds established between Mal-CoA (final conformation in the simulation) and the amino acid residues of the mTOR pocket are shown as cyan dotted lines. Note that only a snapshot is shown, with multiple residues participating in the formation of dynamic interactions with the malonyl group, with R2168 being the most frequent.</p><p id="P101"><bold>(b-c)</bold> Representative acetyl-CoA (Ac-CoA) placement in the mTOR binding pocket (b). Representative CoA conformation sampled by MD simulations in (c). Hydrogen bonds between the compounds and the amino acid residues of the mTOR catalytic pocket indicated by cyan dotted lines.</p><p id="P102">(d) <italic>In silico</italic> mutagenesis of key mTOR residues weakens Mal-CoA interactions with mTOR. Distances of Mal-CoA from the mTOR binding pocket during the MD simulations as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3c</xref>, comparing mTOR<sup>WT</sup> and mTOR<sup>R2168A/R2170A</sup> molecules. Three replicas were run, with individual dots representing averages over 100 ns of MD simulation (n = 9). Data in box plots: central line, median; box, interquartile range (IQR) [25<sup>th</sup> (Q1) - 75<sup>th</sup> (Q3) percentile]; whiskers, Q3+1.5*IQR and Q1-1.5*IQR.</p><p id="P103"><bold>(e)</bold> Amino acid sequence alignment of the 2160-2196 aa region of human mTOR with the respective orthologous sequences from other organisms. Key conserved residues that participate in interactions with Mal-CoA shown in red.</p><p id="P104"><bold>(f)</bold> Mal-CoA does not affect mTORC1 complex stability. HEK293FT cells were lysed and endogenous mTOR was immunoprecipitated in the presence or absence of 1 mM Mal-CoA (added directly in the lysates 5 min prior to addition of the antibody). Co-immunoprecipitation of the mTORC1 subunits Raptor and mLST8 assayed by immunoblotting.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS156775-f014"/></fig></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="SM"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1"><label>Suppl Figures 1-10</label><media xlink:href="EMS156775-supplement-Suppl_Figures_1_10.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" id="d4aAdLbB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD2"><label>Suppl Table 1</label><media xlink:href="EMS156775-supplement-Suppl_Table_1.xlsx" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.spreadsheetml.sheet" id="d4aAdLcB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD3"><label>Suppl Table 2</label><media xlink:href="EMS156775-supplement-Suppl_Table_2.xlsx" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.spreadsheetml.sheet" id="d4aAdLdB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD4"><label>Suppl Table 3</label><media xlink:href="EMS156775-supplement-Suppl_Table_3.xlsx" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.spreadsheetml.sheet" id="d4aAdLeB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD5"><label>Suppl Table 4</label><media xlink:href="EMS156775-supplement-Suppl_Table_4.xlsx" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.spreadsheetml.sheet" id="d4aAdLfB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD6"><label>Suppl Video 1</label><media xlink:href="EMS156775-supplement-Suppl_Video_1.mpg" mimetype="video" mime-subtype="mpeg" id="d4aAdLgB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD7"><label>Suppl Video 2</label><media xlink:href="EMS156775-supplement-Suppl_Video_2.mpg" mimetype="video" mime-subtype="mpeg" id="d4aAdLhB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD8"><label>Suppl Video 3</label><media xlink:href="EMS156775-supplement-Suppl_Video_3.mpg" mimetype="video" mime-subtype="mpeg" id="d4aAdLiB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD9"><label>Suppl Video 4</label><media xlink:href="EMS156775-supplement-Suppl_Video_4.mpg" mimetype="video" mime-subtype="mpeg" id="d4aAdLjB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD10"><label>Suppl Video 5</label><media xlink:href="EMS156775-supplement-Suppl_Video_5.mpg" mimetype="video" mime-subtype="mpeg" id="d4aAdLkB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack id="S35"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank Filippo Artoni (MPI-AGE), Malika Jaquenoud, Marie-Pierre Péli-Gulli, and Susanne Stumpe (University of Fribourg) for technical support; Jin Hou (Shandong University) for the generous gift of plasmids; Robbie Loewith (University of Geneva) for providing antibodies; Andrea Annibal (MPI-AGE) for help with preparation of BSA-conjugated lipids; the MPI-AGE FACS &amp; Imaging Core Facility for support with confocal microscopy; and Patrick Giavalisco from the MPI-AGE Metabolomics core for suggestions and support. L.B. acknowledges support from the Boost! program of the Max Planck Society. C.D. is funded by the European Research Council (ERC) under the European Union’s Horizon 2020 research and innovation programme (grant agreement No 757729) and by the Max Planck Society. C.D.V is funded by the Canton of Fribourg and the Swiss National Science Foundation (310030_166474/184671). S.V. acknowledges support from the Swiss National Science Foundation (PP00P3_194807, 189996). This work was supported by grants from the Swiss National Supercomputing Centre under project ID s1030 and s1132.</p></ack><sec id="S36" sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p id="P105">The data that support the findings of this study (uncropped immunoblots, microscopy pictures, molecular dynamics) are available from the corresponding authors upon reasonable request.</p></sec><sec id="S37" sec-type="data-availability"><title>Code availability</title><p id="P106">No code was generated in this study.</p></sec><fn-group><fn id="FN3" fn-type="con"><p id="P107"><bold>Author Contributions</bold></p><p id="P108">Experimental work: R.N., L.B., J.N., G.F., S.K., P.G., J.R., S.A.F., A.L.; data analysis: R.N., L.B., J.N., G.F., J.R., A.A.T., C.D.V., C.D.; docking and molecular dynamics simulations: J.A., S.V.; project design &amp; conceptualisation: R.N., L.B., S.V., A.A.T., C.D.V., C.D.; project supervision: S.V., A.A.T., C.D.V., C.D.; funding acquisition: S.V., A.A.T., C.D.V., C.D.; figure preparation: R.N., L.B., J.A., C.D.; manuscript draft: C.D.V., C.D., with contributions from all authors. All authors approved the final version of the manuscript and agree on the content and conclusions.</p></fn><fn id="FN4" fn-type="conflict"><p id="P109"><bold>Declaration of Interests</bold></p><p id="P110">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><ref id="R1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fernandes</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Demetriades</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Multifaceted Role of Nutrient Sensing and mTORC1 Signaling in Physiology and Aging</article-title><source>Frontiers in Aging</source><year>2021</year><volume>2</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fragi.2021.707372</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Valvezan</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Manning</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular logic of mTORC1 signalling as a metabolic rheostat</article-title><source>Nature Metabolism</source><year>2019</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>321</fpage><lpage>333</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s42255-019-0038-7</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kennedy</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name><name><surname>Lamming</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Mechanistic Target of Rapamycin: The Grand ConducTOR of Metabolism and Aging</article-title><source>Cell Metab</source><year>2016</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>990</fpage><lpage>1003</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cmet.2016.05.009</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gonzalez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nutrient sensing and TOR signaling in yeast and mammals</article-title><source>EMBO J</source><year>2017</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>397</fpage><lpage>408</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15252/embj.201696010</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Castellano</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Lysosomal cholesterol activates mTORC1 via an SLC38A9-Niemann-Pick C1 signaling complex</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2017</year><volume>355</volume><fpage>1306</fpage><lpage>1311</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.aag1417</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>ER-lysosome contacts enable cholesterol sensing by mTORC1 and drive aberrant growth signalling in Niemann-Pick type C</article-title><source>Nat Cell Biol</source><year>2019</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>1206</fpage><lpage>1218</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41556-019-0391-5</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>OB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>NPC1-mTORC1 Signaling Couples Cholesterol Sensing to Organelle Homeostasis and Is a Targetable Pathway in Niemann-Pick Type C</article-title><source>Dev Cell</source><year>2021</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>260</fpage><lpage>276</lpage><elocation-id>e267</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.devcel.2020.11.016</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sancak</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The Rag GTPases bind raptor and mediate amino acid signaling to mTORC1</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2008</year><volume>320</volume><fpage>1496</fpage><lpage>1501</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1157535</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Goraksha-Hicks</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Neufeld</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name><name><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regulation of TORC1 by Rag GTPases in nutrient response</article-title><source>Nat Cell Biol</source><year>2008</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>935</fpage><lpage>945</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncb1753</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Efeyan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Regulation of mTORC1 by the Rag GTPases is necessary for neonatal autophagy and survival</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2013</year><volume>493</volume><fpage>679</fpage><lpage>683</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature11745</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Porstmann</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>SREBP activity is regulated by mTORC1 and contributes to Akt-dependent cell growth</article-title><source>Cell Metab</source><year>2008</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>224</fpage><lpage>236</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cmet.2008.07.007</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de Carvalho</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Caramujo</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Various Roles of Fatty Acids</article-title><source>Molecules</source><year>2018</year><volume>23</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/molecules23102583</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rohrig</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Schulze</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The multifaceted roles of fatty acid synthesis in cancer</article-title><source>Nat Rev Cancer</source><year>2016</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>732</fpage><lpage>749</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrc.2016.89</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maier</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Leibundgut</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ban</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The crystal structure of a mammalian fatty acid synthase</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2008</year><volume>321</volume><fpage>1315</fpage><lpage>1322</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1161269</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wakil</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Abu-Elheiga</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fatty acid metabolism: target for metabolic syndrome</article-title><source>J Lipid Res</source><year>2009</year><volume>50 Suppl</volume><fpage>S138</fpage><lpage>143</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1194/jlr.R800079-JLR200</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tehlivets</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Scheuringer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kohlwein</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fatty acid synthesis and elongation in yeast</article-title><source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source><year>2007</year><volume>1771</volume><fpage>255</fpage><lpage>270</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbalip.2006.07.004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oakhill</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>AMPK is a direct adenylate charge-regulated protein kinase</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2011</year><volume>332</volume><fpage>1433</fpage><lpage>1435</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1200094</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hsu</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Inositol serves as a natural inhibitor of mitochondrial fission by directly targeting AMPK</article-title><source>Mol Cell</source><year>2021</year><volume>81</volume><fpage>3803</fpage><lpage>3819</lpage><elocation-id>e3807</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molcel.2021.08.025</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Duran</surname><given-names>RV</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Glutaminolysis activates Rag-mTORC1 signaling</article-title><source>Mol Cell</source><year>2012</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>349</fpage><lpage>358</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molcel.2012.05.043</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bonfils</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Leucyl-tRNA synthetase controls TORC1 via the EGO complex</article-title><source>Mol Cell</source><year>2012</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>105</fpage><lpage>110</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molcel.2012.02.009</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Omura</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The antibiotic cerulenin, a novel tool for biochemistry as an inhibitor of fatty acid synthesis</article-title><source>BacteriolRev</source><year>1976</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>681</fpage><lpage>697</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/br.40.3.681-697.1976</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ono</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kesado</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Awaya</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Omura</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Target of inhibition by the anti-lipogenic antibiotic cerulenin of sterol synthesis in yeast</article-title><source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source><year>1974</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>1119</fpage><lpage>1124</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0006-291x(74)90812-2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Binda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The Vam6 GEF controls TORC1 by activating the EGO complex</article-title><source>Mol Cell</source><year>2009</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>563</fpage><lpage>573</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molcel.2009.06.033</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Michel</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Functional mapping of yeast genomes by saturated transposition</article-title><source>Elife</source><year>2017</year><volume>6</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.23570</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Michel</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>van Schie</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mosbach</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Scalliet</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Kornmann</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Exploiting homologous recombination increases SATAY efficiency for loss- and gain-of-function screening</article-title><source>bioRxiv</source><year>2019</year><elocation-id>866483</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/866483</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vahlensieck</surname><given-names>HF</given-names></name><name><surname>Pridzun</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Reichenbach</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hinnen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of the yeast ACC1 gene product (acetyl-CoA carboxylase) as the target of the polyketide fungicide soraphen A</article-title><source>Curr Genet</source><year>1994</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>95</fpage><lpage>100</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00309532</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Screening Phosphorylation Site Mutations in Yeast Acetyl-CoA Carboxylase Using Malonyl-CoA Sensor to Improve Malonyl-CoA-Derived Product</article-title><source>Front Microbiol</source><year>2018</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>47</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2018.00047</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Siewers</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Improving production of malonyl coenzyme A-derived metabolites by abolishing Snf1-dependent regulation of Acc1</article-title><source>mBio</source><year>2014</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>e01130</fpage><lpage>01114</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/mBio.01130-14</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hofbauer</surname><given-names>HF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Regulation of gene expression through a transcriptional repressor that senses acyl-chain length in membrane phospholipids</article-title><source>Dev Cell</source><year>2014</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>729</fpage><lpage>739</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.devcel.2014.04.025</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schneiter</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A yeast acetyl coenzyme A carboxylase mutant links very-long-chain fatty acid synthesis to the structure and function of the nuclear membrane-pore complex</article-title><source>Mol Cell Biol</source><year>1996</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>7161</fpage><lpage>7172</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/MCB.16.12.7161</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alwarawrah</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Fasnall, a Selective FASN Inhibitor, Shows Potent Anti-tumor Activity in the MMTV-Neu Model of HER2(+) Breast Cancer</article-title><source>Cell Chem Biol</source><year>2016</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>678</fpage><lpage>688</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chembiol.2016.04.011</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Lysine malonylation is elevated in type 2 diabetic mouse models and enriched in metabolic associated proteins</article-title><source>Mol Cell Proteomics</source><year>2015</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>227</fpage><lpage>236</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/mcp.M114.041947</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Colak</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Proteomic and Biochemical Studies of Lysine Malonylation Suggest Its Malonic Aciduria-associated Regulatory Role in Mitochondrial Function and Fatty Acid Oxidation</article-title><source>Mol Cell Proteomics</source><year>2015</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>3056</fpage><lpage>3071</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/mcp.M115.048850</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thupari</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name><name><surname>Pinn</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuhajda</surname><given-names>FP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fatty acid synthase inhibition in human breast cancer cells leads to malonyl-CoA-induced inhibition of fatty acid oxidation and cytotoxicity</article-title><source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source><year>2001</year><volume>285</volume><fpage>217</fpage><lpage>223</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/bbrc.2001.5146</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Knobloch</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A Fatty Acid Oxidation-Dependent Metabolic Shift Regulates Adult Neural Stem Cell Activity</article-title><source>Cell Rep</source><year>2017</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>2144</fpage><lpage>2155</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.celrep.2017.08.029</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Madak-Erdogan</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Free Fatty Acids Rewire Cancer Metabolism in Obesity-Associated Breast Cancer via Estrogen Receptor and mTOR Signaling</article-title><source>Cancer Res</source><year>2019</year><volume>79</volume><fpage>2494</fpage><lpage>2510</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-18-2849</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Calvo-Ochoa</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanchez-Alegria</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Gomez-Inclan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferrera</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Arias</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Palmitic acid stimulates energy metabolism and inhibits insulin/PI3K/AKT signaling in differentiated human neuroblastoma cells: The role of mTOR activation and mitochondrial ROS production</article-title><source>Neurochem Int</source><year>2017</year><volume>110</volume><fpage>75</fpage><lpage>83</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuint.2017.09.008</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yasuda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Fatty acids are novel nutrient factors to regulate mTORC1 lysosomal localization and apoptosis in podocytes</article-title><source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source><year>2014</year><volume>1842</volume><fpage>1097</fpage><lpage>1108</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbadis.2014.04.001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bruning</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Impairment of Angiogenesis by Fatty Acid Synthase Inhibition Involves mTOR Malonylation</article-title><source>Cell Metab</source><year>2018</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>866</fpage><lpage>880</lpage><elocation-id>e815</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cmet.2018.07.019</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Fung</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>XD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A chemical probe for lysine malonylation</article-title><source>Angew Chem Int Ed Engl</source><year>2013</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>4883</fpage><lpage>4886</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/anie.201300252</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R41"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sancak</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Ragulator-Rag complex targets mTORC1 to the lysosomal surface and is necessary for its activation by amino acids</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2010</year><volume>141</volume><fpage>290</fpage><lpage>303</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2010.02.024</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R42"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Demetriades</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Doumpas</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Teleman</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regulation of TORC1 in response to amino acid starvation via lysosomal recruitment of TSC2</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2014</year><volume>156</volume><fpage>786</fpage><lpage>799</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2014.01.024</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R43"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Demetriades</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Plescher</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Teleman</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lysosomal recruitment of TSC2 is a universal response to cellular stress</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2016</year><volume>7</volume><elocation-id>10662</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncomms10662</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R44"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carroll</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Control of TSC2-Rheb signaling axis by arginine regulates mTORC1 activity</article-title><source>Elife</source><year>2016</year><volume>5</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.11058</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R45"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thul</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A subcellular map of the human proteome</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2017</year><volume>356</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.aal3321</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R46"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nicastro</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Indole-3-acetic acid is a physiological inhibitor of TORC1 in yeast</article-title><source>PLoS Genet</source><year>2021</year><volume>17</volume><elocation-id>e1009414</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1009414</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R47"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Multilayered Control of Protein Turnover by TORC1 and Atg1</article-title><source>Cell Rep</source><year>2019</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>3486</fpage><lpage>3496</lpage><elocation-id>e3486</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.celrep.2019.08.069</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R48"><label>48</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huffman</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mothe-Satney</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Lawrence</surname><given-names>JC</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name></person-group><article-title>Insulin-stimulated phosphorylation of lipin mediated by the mammalian target of rapamycin</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>2002</year><volume>99</volume><fpage>1047</fpage><lpage>1052</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.022634399</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R49"><label>49</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Insulin controls subcellular localization and multisite phosphorylation of the phosphatidic acid phosphatase, lipin 1</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2007</year><volume>282</volume><fpage>277</fpage><lpage>286</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M609537200</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R50"><label>50</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eaton</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Mullins</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name><name><surname>Brindley</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phosphorylation of lipin 1 and charge on the phosphatidic acid head group control its phosphatidic acid phosphatase activity and membrane association</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2013</year><volume>288</volume><fpage>9933</fpage><lpage>9945</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M112.441493</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R51"><label>51</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bakan</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Laplante</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Connecting mTORC1 signaling to SREBP-1 activation</article-title><source>Curr Opin Lipidol</source><year>2012</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>226</fpage><lpage>234</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MOL.0b013e328352dd03</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R52"><label>52</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ricoult</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Manning</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The multifaceted role of mTORC1 in the control of lipid metabolism</article-title><source>EMBO Rep</source><year>2013</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>242</fpage><lpage>251</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/embor.2013.5</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R53"><label>53</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Horton</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldstein</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>SREBPs: activators of the complete program of cholesterol and fatty acid synthesis in the liver</article-title><source>J Clin Invest</source><year>2002</year><volume>109</volume><fpage>1125</fpage><lpage>1131</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1172/JCI15593</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R54"><label>54</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eberle</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Hegarty</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Bossard</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferre</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Foufelle</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>SREBP transcription factors: master regulators of lipid homeostasis</article-title><source>Biochimie</source><year>2004</year><volume>86</volume><fpage>839</fpage><lpage>848</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biochi.2004.09.018</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R55"><label>55</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Knighton</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ten Eyck</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name><name><surname>Sowadski</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structural framework for the protein kinase family</article-title><source>Annu Rev Cell Biol</source><year>1992</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>429</fpage><lpage>462</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.cb.08.110192.002241</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R56"><label>56</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Das</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>cAMP activation of PKA defines an ancient signaling mechanism</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2007</year><volume>104</volume><fpage>93</fpage><lpage>98</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0609033103</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R57"><label>57</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sassone-Corsi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The cyclic AMP pathway</article-title><source>Cold Spring Harb Perspect Biol</source><year>2012</year><volume>4</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/cshperspect.a011148</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R58"><label>58</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pareek</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Sha</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wingreen</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name><name><surname>Benkovic</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Metabolic channeling: predictions, deductions, and evidence</article-title><source>Mol Cell</source><year>2021</year><volume>81</volume><fpage>3775</fpage><lpage>3785</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molcel.2021.08.030</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R59"><label>59</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Flavin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Peluso</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name><surname>Loda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fatty acid synthase as a potential therapeutic target in cancer</article-title><source>Future Oncol</source><year>2010</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>551</fpage><lpage>562</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2217/fon.10.11</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R60"><label>60</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Natural fatty acid synthase inhibitors as potent therapeutic agents for cancers: A review</article-title><source>Pharm Biol</source><year>2016</year><volume>54</volume><fpage>1919</fpage><lpage>1925</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/13880209.2015.1113995</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R61"><label>61</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koundouros</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Poulogiannis</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reprogramming of fatty acid metabolism in cancer</article-title><source>Br J Cancer</source><year>2020</year><volume>122</volume><fpage>4</fpage><lpage>22</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41416-019-0650-z</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R62"><label>62</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fhu</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fatty Acid Synthase: An Emerging Target in Cancer</article-title><source>Molecules</source><year>2020</year><volume>25</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/molecules25173935</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R63"><label>63</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Loss of fatty acid synthase suppresses the malignant phenotype of colorectal cancer cells by down-regulating energy metabolism and mTOR signaling pathway</article-title><source>J Cancer Res Clin Oncol</source><year>2016</year><volume>142</volume><fpage>59</fpage><lpage>72</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00432-015-2000-8</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R64"><label>64</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The mTOR inhibitor rapamycin synergizes with a fatty acid synthase inhibitor to induce cytotoxicity in ER/HER2-positive breast cancer cells</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2014</year><volume>9</volume><elocation-id>e97697</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0097697</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R65"><label>65</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jewell</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Metabolism. Differential regulation of mTORC1 by leucine and glutamine</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2015</year><volume>347</volume><fpage>194</fpage><lpage>198</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1259472</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R66"><label>66</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Plescher</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Teleman</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Demetriades</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>TSC2 mediates hyperosmotic stress-induced inactivation of mTORC1</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2015</year><volume>5</volume><elocation-id>13828</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep13828</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R67"><label>67</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ran</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genome engineering using the CRISPR-Cas9 system</article-title><source>Nat Protoc</source><year>2013</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>2281</fpage><lpage>2308</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nprot.2013.143</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R68"><label>68</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Generoso</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name><name><surname>Gottardi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Oreb</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Boles</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Simplified CRISPR-Cas genome editing for Saccharomyces cerevisiae</article-title><source>J Microbiol Methods</source><year>2016</year><volume>127</volume><fpage>203</fpage><lpage>205</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mimet.2016.06.020</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R69"><label>69</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Janke</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A versatile toolbox for PCR-based tagging of yeast genes: new fluorescent proteins, more markers and promoter substitution cassettes</article-title><source>Yeast</source><year>2004</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>947</fpage><lpage>962</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/yea.1142</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R70"><label>70</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mahoney</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A small molecule inhibitor of Rheb selectively targets mTORC1 signaling</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2018</year><volume>9</volume><elocation-id>548</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-018-03035-z</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R71"><label>71</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sancak</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>PRAS40 is an insulin-regulated inhibitor of the mTORC1 protein kinase</article-title><source>Mol Cell</source><year>2007</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>903</fpage><lpage>915</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molcel.2007.03.003</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R72"><label>72</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fitzian</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>TSC1 binding to lysosomal PIPs is required for TSC complex translocation and mTORC1 regulation</article-title><source>Mol Cell</source><year>2021</year><volume>81</volume><fpage>2705</fpage><lpage>2721</lpage><elocation-id>e2708</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molcel.2021.04.019</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R73"><label>73</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schindelin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Fiji: an open-source platform for biological-image analysis</article-title><source>Nat Methods</source><year>2012</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>676</fpage><lpage>682</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.2019</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R74"><label>74</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Manders</surname><given-names>EMM</given-names></name><name><surname>Verbeek</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Aten</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Measurement of co-localization of objects in dualcolour confocal images</article-title><source>J Microsc</source><year>1993</year><volume>169</volume><fpage>375</fpage><lpage>382</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2818.1993.tb03313.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R75"><label>75</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Costes</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Automatic and quantitative measurement of protein-protein colocalization in live cells</article-title><source>Biophys J</source><year>2004</year><volume>86</volume><fpage>3993</fpage><lpage>4003</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1529/biophysj.103.038422</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R76"><label>76</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dunn</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamocka</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>McDonald</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A practical guide to evaluating colocalization in biological microscopy</article-title><source>Am J Physiol Cell Physiol</source><year>2011</year><volume>300</volume><fpage>C723</fpage><lpage>742</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/ajpcell.00462.2010</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R77"><label>77</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Webb</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Sali</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparative Protein Structure Modeling Using MODELLER</article-title><source>Curr Protoc Bioinformatics</source><year>2016</year><volume>54</volume><fpage>5 6 1</fpage><lpage>5 6 37</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cpbi.3</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R78"><label>78</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Towse</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Rysavy</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Vulovic</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name><name><surname>Daggett</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>New Dynamic Rotamer Libraries: Data-Driven Analysis of Side-Chain Conformational Propensities</article-title><source>Structure</source><year>2016</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>187</fpage><lpage>199</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.str.2015.10.017</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R79"><label>79</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Iyer</surname><given-names>VG</given-names></name><name><surname>Im</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>CHARMM-GUI: a web-based graphical user interface for CHARMM</article-title><source>JComput Chem</source><year>2008</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>1859</fpage><lpage>1865</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jcc.20945</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R80"><label>80</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brooks</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>CHARMM: the biomolecular simulation program</article-title><source>J Comput Chem</source><year>2009</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>1545</fpage><lpage>1614</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jcc.21287</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R81"><label>81</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>CHARMM-GUI Input Generator for NAMD, GROMACS, AMBER, OpenMM, and CHARMM/OpenMM Simulations Using the CHARMM36 Additive Force Field</article-title><source>J Chem Theory Comput</source><year>2016</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>405</fpage><lpage>413</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.jctc.5b00935</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R82"><label>82</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>AutoDock4 and AutoDockTools4: Automated docking with selective receptor flexibility</article-title><source>J Comput Chem</source><year>2009</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>2785</fpage><lpage>2791</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jcc.21256</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R83"><label>83</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>UC</given-names></name><name><surname>Kollman</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An approach to computing electrostatic charges for molecules</article-title><source>Journal of Computational Chemistry</source><year>1984</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>129</fpage><lpage>145</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jcc.540050204</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R84"><label>84</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gasteiger</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Marsili</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Iterative partial equalization of orbital electronegativity—a rapid access to atomic charges</article-title><source>Tetrahedron</source><year>1980</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>3219</fpage><lpage>3228</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0040-4020(80)80168-2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R85"><label>85</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Forli</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Computational protein-ligand docking and virtual drug screening with the AutoDock suite</article-title><source>Nat Protoc</source><year>2016</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>905</fpage><lpage>919</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nprot.2016.051</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R86"><label>86</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Trott</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>AutoDock Vina: improving the speed and accuracy of docking with a new scoring function, efficient optimization, and multithreading</article-title><source>J Comput Chem</source><year>2010</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>455</fpage><lpage>461</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jcc.21334</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R87"><label>87</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ning</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>EDGA: A Population Evolution Direction-Guided Genetic Algorithm for Protein-Ligand Docking</article-title><source>JComputBiol</source><year>2016</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>585</fpage><lpage>596</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/cmb.2015.0190</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R88"><label>88</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mark</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Nilsson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structure and Dynamics of the TIP3P, SPC, and SPC/E Water Models at 298 K</article-title><source>The Journal of Physical Chemistry A</source><year>2001</year><volume>105</volume><fpage>9954</fpage><lpage>9960</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jp003020w</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R89"><label>89</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bussi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Donadio</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Parrinello</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Canonical sampling through velocity rescaling</article-title><source>JChem Phys</source><year>2007</year><volume>126</volume><elocation-id>014101</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1063/1.2408420</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R90"><label>90</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parrinello</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rahman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Polymorphic transitions in single crystals: A new molecular dynamics method</article-title><source>Journal of Applied Physics</source><year>1981</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>7182</fpage><lpage>7190</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1063/1.328693</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R91"><label>91</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Darden</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>York</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Pedersen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Particle mesh Ewald: An Nolog(N) method for Ewald sums in large systems</article-title><source>The Journal of Chemical Physics</source><year>1993</year><volume>98</volume><fpage>10089</fpage><lpage>10092</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1063/1.464397</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R92"><label>92</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abraham</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>GROMACS: High performance molecular simulations through multi-level parallelism from laptops to supercomputers</article-title><source>SoftwareX</source><year>2015</year><volume>1-2</volume><fpage>19</fpage><lpage>25</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.softx.2015.06.001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R93"><label>93</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>MacKerell</surname><given-names>AD</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name></person-group><article-title>CHARMM36 all-atom additive protein force field: validation based on comparison to NMR data</article-title><source>JComput Chem</source><year>2013</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>2135</fpage><lpage>2145</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jcc.23354</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Increasing malonyl-CoA levels by genetic and pharmacological perturbation of Fas1/Acc1 activity reduces mTORC1 activity in yeast and mammalian cells.</title><p><bold>(a)</bold> Schematic diagram of <italic>de novo</italic> fatty acid biosynthesis. Yeast and mammalian proteins shown in orange or blue, respectively.</p><p><bold>(b-d)</bold> Cerulenin boosts malonyl-CoA levels and inhibits TORC1 activity. Immunoblots with lysates from yeast cells expressing the fapR/fapOp-yeGFP malonyl-CoA reporter system, treated with 20 μM cerulenin (Ceru) for the indicated times. GFP expression shows Mal-CoA levels. TORC1 activity assessed by Sch9 phosphorylation (b). Quantification of relative Mal-CoA levels (GFP/Adh1 ratio) in (c). Quantification of relative TORC1 activity (p-Sch9<sup>T737</sup>/Sch9 ratio) in (d), n = 4.</p><p><bold>(e-f)</bold> Immunoblots with lysates from wild-type (wt) or Acc1<sup>S1157A</sup>-expressing yeast cells, exponentially growing (Ctrl), starved for nitrogen (-N), or starved and restimulated with Gln for the indicated times. TORC1 activity assessed by Sch9 phosphorylation (e). Quantification of relative TORC1 activity (p-Sch9<sup>T737</sup>/Sch9 ratio) in (f), n = 3.</p><p><bold>(g-h)</bold> Pharmacological inhibition of FASN downregulates mTORC1. Immunoblots with lysates from HEK293FT cells treated with 25 μM Fasnall for the indicated times. mTORC1 activity assayed by phosphorylation of S6K and 4E-BP1 (g). Quantification of p-S6K<sup>T389</sup>/S6K ratio in (h), n = 6.</p><p><bold>(i-j)</bold> Immunoblots with lysates from HEK293FT cells treated with 50 μM Cerulenin (Ceru) for the indicated times. mTORC1 activity assayed by phosphorylation of S6K. Malonyl-lysine (Mal-K) blots indicate total protein malonylation, as a read-out for Mal-CoA levels (i). Quantification of p-S6K<sup>T389</sup>/S6K ratio in (j), n = 8.</p><p><bold>(k-l)</bold> Immunoblots with lysates from control (siCtrl) or FASN knockdown (siFASN) HEK293FT cells. mTORC1 activity assayed by phosphorylation of S6K and 4E-BP1. Mal-K blots show total protein malonylation (k). Quantification of p-S6K<sup>T389</sup>/S6K ratio in (l), n = 6.</p><p><bold>(m)</bold> FASN inhibition downregulates mTORC1 activity independently from lipid availability. Immunoblots with lysates from control (–) or Fasnall-treated (25 μM, 30 min) HEK293FT cells, supplemented with BSA-conjugated FAs as indicated, or BSA as control. mTORC1 activity assayed by phosphorylation of S6K and 4E-BP1.</p><p>Data in graphs shown as mean ± SEM. * = p &lt;0.05, ** = p &lt;0.005, *** = p &lt;0.0005.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS156775-f001"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>The mTORC1-FASN-ACC1 proteins form reciprocal interactions in yeast and mammalian cells.</title><p><bold>(a-b)</bold> Acc1 physically interacts with TORC1 in a Rag-independent manner. Wild-type and <italic>gtr1Δ gtr2Δ</italic> cells expressing genomically tagged Acc1-myc<sub>13</sub> and untagged (–) or genomically HA<sub>3</sub>-tagged (+) TORC1 subunits Kog1 (a) or Tco89 (b) were grown exponentially. Lysates (Input) and anti-HA immunoprecipitates (α-HA IP) were analysed by immunoblotting with anti-myc and anti-HA antibodies.</p><p><bold>(c)</bold> Fas1 physically interacts with TORC1 in a Rag-independent manner. As in (a-b), using wild-type and <italic>gtrlΔ gtr2Δ</italic> cells harbouring genomically tagged Fas1-myc<sub>13</sub> and untagged (–) or genomically HA<sub>3</sub>-tagged (+) Kog1.</p><p><bold>(d)</bold> FASN directly interacts with mTOR, Raptor and ACC1. Endogenous FASN was immunoprecipitated from HEK293FT cell lysates and co-immunoprecipitated proteins were identified by immunoblotting as indicated.</p><p><bold>(e)</bold> As in (d), but with ACC1 immunoprecipitation.</p><p><bold>(f)</bold> As in (d), but with mTOR immunoprecipitation.</p><p><bold>(g)</bold> The interaction between FASN, mTOR/Raptor and ACC1 is independent from the Rags. FASN was immunoprecipitated from WT or RagA/B KO HEK293FT cell lysates and coimmunoprecipitated proteins were identified by immunoblotting as indicated.</p><p><bold>(h)</bold> Immunofluorescence of FASN and LAMP2 (lysosomal marker) in MCF-7 cells shows primarily diffuse cytoplasmic FASN localization. Scale bar = 10 μm.</p><p><bold>(i-j)</bold> FASN shows proximity to lysosomes. PLA assays in MCF-7 cells using FASN and LAMP2 antibodies. Specificity of the PLA signal (red dots) verified by FASN and LAMP2 knockdowns.</p><p>Scale bars = 25 μm (i). Quantification of PLA signal intensity in (j). Data shown as mean ± SEM.</p><p>*** = p &lt;0.0005.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS156775-f002"/></fig><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Molecular dynamics simulation of Mal-CoA binding to the mTOR catalytic pocket.</title><p><bold>(a)</bold> Chemical structures of ATP (left) and malonyl-CoA (right) highlight structural similarities between the two molecules. Identical parts marked in blue.</p><p><bold>(b)</bold> Structural alignment of representative snapshots of malonyl-CoA (green; initial conformation shown) and ATP (magenta) bound to the mTOR catalytic pocket (top view).</p><p><bold>(c)</bold> Distances of the ligands from the mTOR binding pocket during the MD simulations. The distances were computed between the center of mass (COM) of the adenine ring and the COM of the amino acid residues defining the pocket. Three replicas were run for each compound, and individual dots represent averages over 100 ns of MD simulation (n = 9). Data in box plots: central line, median; box, interquartile range (IQR) [25<sup>th</sup> (Q1) - 75<sup>th</sup> (Q3) percentile]; whiskers, Q3+1.5*IQR and Q1-1.5*IQR.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS156775-f003"/></fig><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Mal-CoA is a direct ATP-competitive inhibitor of mTORC1.</title><p><bold>(a-b)</bold> Malonyl-CoA, and to a lesser extent acetyl-CoA, inhibit TORC1 activity <italic>in vitro.</italic> IVK assays using TORC1 purified from yeast with recombinant Lst4<sup>Loop</sup> and co-purified Tco89 proteins as substrates, in the presence of increasing Mal-CoA, Ac-CoA, or CoA amounts. Substrate phosphorylation detected by autoradiography (<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32">32</xref></sup>P). Total protein detected by Sypro Ruby staining (a). Quantification of TORC1 activity (Lst4<sup>Loop</sup> phosphorylation) in (b). Curve fitting and IC<sub>50</sub> calculations performed with GraphPad Prism. Data shown as mean ± SEM, n = 3.</p><p><bold>(c-f)</bold> IVKs as in (a), but with mTORC1 purified from HEK293FT cells and recombinant 4E-BP1 protein used as substrate in the presence of increasing Mal-CoA (c), Ac-CoA (d), or CoA (e) amounts. 4E-BP1 phosphorylation detected by immunoblotting. Quantification of mTORC1 activity in (f). Curve fitting and IC<sub>50</sub> calculations performed with GraphPad Prism. Data shown as mean ± SEM, n = 4.</p><p><bold>(g-h)</bold> Malonyl-CoA inhibits TORC1 in an ATP-competitive manner. IVKs performed as in (a) using increasing ATP concentrations without or with 0.66 or 2 mM Mal-CoA. Quantification of TORC1 activity (Lst4<sup>Loop</sup> phosphorylation) in (h). Curve fitting and calculations of K<sub>mATP</sub> and K<sub>i Mal-CoA</sub> performed with GraphPad Prism. Data shown as mean ± SEM, n = 3.</p><p><bold>(i-j)</bold> IVKs as in (c) using increasing ATP concentrations, in the presence or absence of 2 mM Mal-CoA (i). Quantification of mTORC1 activity in (j). Curve fitting and calculations of K<sub>mATP</sub> and K<sub>iMal-CoA</sub> performed with GraphPad Prism using a mixed inhibition model. Data shown as mean ± SEM, n = 4.</p><p><bold>(k)</bold> Model of mTOR inhibition by Mal-CoA. When the FA biosynthesis machinery is active, ACC1 converts Ac-CoA to Mal-CoA, which is, in turn, rapidly converted to palmitate by FASN (left). In contrast, when ACC1 is hyperactive or FASN is downregulated, accumulating Mal-CoA competes with ATP for binding to proximal mTOR molecules causing its inactivation. Hence, by complexing with ACC1 and FASN, mTORC1 functions as a direct sensor for Mal-CoA to adjust growth and coordinate cellular metabolic activity in response to decreased cellular FA biosynthesis capacity (right).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS156775-f004"/></fig></floats-group></article>