<!DOCTYPE article
 PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" article-type="preprint"><?all-math-mml yes?><?use-mml?><?origin ukpmcpa?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">bioRxiv</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>bioRxiv : the preprint server for biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub"/></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">EMS157998</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2022.12.02.518824</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="archive">PPR578675</article-id><article-version-alternatives><article-version article-version-type="status">preprint</article-version><article-version article-version-type="number">2</article-version></article-version-alternatives><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Estimating the fitness cost and benefit of antimicrobial resistance from pathogen genomic data</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Helekal</surname><given-names>David</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Keeling</surname><given-names>Matt</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Grad</surname><given-names>Yonatan H</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Didelot</surname><given-names>Xavier</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CR1">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Centre for Doctoral Training in Mathematics for Real-World Systems, University of Warwick, UK</aff><aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Mathematics Institute and School of Life Sciences, University of Warwick, UK</aff><aff id="A3"><label>3</label>Department of Immunology and Infectious Diseases, TH Chan School of Public Health, Harvard University, USA</aff><aff id="A4"><label>4</label>School of Life Sciences and Department of Statistics, University of Warwick, UK</aff><author-notes><corresp id="CR1">
<label>*</label>Corresponding author. Tel: 0044 (0)2476 572827. <email>xavier.didelot@warwick.ac.uk</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted"><day>04</day><month>12</month><year>2022</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="preprint"><day>02</day><month>12</month><year>2022</year></pub-date><permissions><ali:free_to_read/><license><ali:license_ref>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is licensed under a <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0 International license</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p id="P1">Increasing levels of antibiotic resistance in many bacterial pathogen populations is a major threat to public health. Resistance to an antibiotic provides a fitness benefit when the bacteria is exposed to this antibiotic, but resistance also often comes at a cost to the resistant pathogen relative to susceptible counterparts. We lack a good understanding of these benefits and costs of resistance for many bacterial pathogens and antibiotics, but estimating them could lead to better use of antibiotics in a way that reduces or prevents the spread of resistance. Here, we propose a new model for the joint epidemiology of susceptible and resistant variants, which includes explicit parameters for the cost and benefit of resistance. We show how Bayesian inference can be performed under this model using phylogenetic data from susceptible and resistant lineages and that by combining data from both we are able to disentangle and estimate the resistance cost and benefit parameters separately. We applied our inferential methodology to several simulated datasets to demonstrate good scalability and accuracy. We analysed a dataset of <italic>Neisseria gonorrhoeae</italic> genomes collected between 2000 and 2013 in the USA. We found that two unrelated lineages resistant to fluoroquinolones shared similar epidemic dynamics and resistance parameters. Fluoroquinolones were abandoned for the treatment of gonorrhoea due to increasing levels of resistance, but our results suggest that they could be used to treat a minority of around 10% of cases without causing resistance to grow again.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>genomic epidemiology</kwd><kwd>phylodynamics</kwd><kwd>antimicrobial resistance</kwd><kwd>resistance fitness cost</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="S1" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p id="P2">The levels of antimicrobial resistance of many pathogens have risen worryingly over the past few decades. In a report on the threat posed by antibiotic resistance published by the CDC (Centres for Disease Control and Protection), three microorganisms including <italic>N. gonorrhoeae</italic> are classified as posing an urgent threat level, and twelve more represent a serious threat to public health [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref>]. A review on antimicrobial resistance estimated that resistance claims at least 700,000 lives per year worldwide and that the death toll could go up to 10 million per year by 2050 if current trends are allowed to continue [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">2</xref>], and a recent study estimated that there were almost 5 million deaths associated with resistance in 2019 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">3</xref>]. Few new antimicrobials have been developed and deployed since the 1970s, whereas resistance to new drugs often emerges soon after initial introduction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">4</xref>], so that several pathogens are dangerously close to becoming completely untreatable. Effectively tackling antimicrobial resistance requires greater understanding of epidemiological and evolutionary factors leading to emergence of resistance and the spread of resistance through pathogen populations. Achieving this goal requires development of mathematical models of antimicrobial resistance and robust statistical analysis of epidemiological models with informative observations. This modelling approach to resistance was initiated in the late 1990s [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref>] and has led to the development of many models, appropriate for different organisms, mode of spread, study scale and context [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref>].</p><p id="P3">Resistance brings a clear fitness benefit to pathogens acquiring it in the presence of antimicrobials. The net value of this fitness benefit therefore increases with the frequency with which the specific antimicrobial is employed, either against the pathogen itself or more generally in the case of a pathogen that can be carried asymptomatically. However, resistance also typically comes with a fitness cost to the pathogen [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">8</xref>]. The simplest demonstration of this effect is when discontinued use of an antimicrobial leads to reductions in resistance rates. The fitness costs and benefits of resistance remain poorly understood for many pathogens and antimicrobials [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref>]. A better quantification of resistance benefits and costs is required to provide a solid basis for evaluating the potential effectiveness of public health intervention measures proposed to exploit fitness costs in the hope of stopping or even reversing the spread of resistance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref>]. For example, the numbers of gonorrhoea cases sensitive and resistant to cefixime in England over a decade was recently analysed to quantify the cost and benefit associated with resistance to this antibiotic [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>]. These estimates were used to predict that cefixime could be reintroduced to treat a minority (~ 25%) of gonorrhoea cases without causing an increase in cefixime resistance levels, which would reduce the risk of emergence of resistance to the currently used antibiotics. Moreover, the extent of the fitness cost of resistance can vary by genomic background [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref>], such that the effect of interventions that seek to capitalize on the fitness costs of resistance may be lineage dependent. Therefore, it is necessary to estimate fitness costs at the per lineage level. The aim of this study is to quantify the contribution that changes in prescription policy have on the population dynamics of particular resistant lineages. This is in contrast to studies that are interested in the overall ecology of resistance or the eventual fate of a resistant phenotypes, see for example [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref>].</p><p id="P4">Pathogen genomic data has great potential to help us understand the evolutionary and epidemiological dynamics of infectious disease [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref>]. An important advantage of this phylodynamic approach is that analysis of genomic data is less sensitive to sampling biases, especially when using a coalescent framework which describes the ancestry process conditional on sampling [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref>]. A few studies have used this approach to shed light on the fitness cost associated with antimicrobial resistance. For example, a study showed the association between the growth rate of a methicillin-resistant <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> lineage and consumption of beta-lactams [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref>]. Other studies quantified the relative transmission fitness of resistance mutations in HIV [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref>] and <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref>]. Here, we take a different approach by modelling explicitly the phylodynamic trajectories of the sensitive and resistant lineages as a function of the fitness cost, which is constant, and the fitness benefit, which depends on the antimicrobial consumption. Our method therefore requires three inputs: the amount of antimicrobial being used over time, genomic data from a sensitive lineage, and genomic data from a resistant lineage. From this we disentangle the fitness cost and benefit of resistance, thereby providing the parameters needed to predict phylodynamic trajectories and inform recommendations on how to use antimicrobials without worsening the resistance threat. Overall, the scenario we are interested in is that of overall resistance dynamics at a large population level. In such a scenario the bulk of incidence is going to be caused by local transmission rather than imports. We do not intend for the methods presented in this paper to be applicable to small population dominated by imports and complex, heterogeneous routes of transmission, such as within hospital setting of hospital acquired infections. For such a scenario, a different approach using Birth-Death type models would be more appropriate [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="S2" sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec id="S3"><title>Overall approach</title><p id="P5">Pathogen phylogenetic data contains information about past population size dynamics of the pathogen under study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref>]. Under assumptions of the epidemic process being characterised well enough by a simple compartmental epidemic model, this information about population size dynamics can be translated into epidemic trajectories [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">20</xref>]. These epidemic trajectories can be described using an epidemic model which accounts for the effects of a fitness cost and benefit of resistance to a specific antimicrobial. As the use of this antimicrobial changes through time, so will the net fitness of the particular lineage in consideration. This will in turn lead to changes in the behaviour of the epidemic trajectory. However, not all changes in the behaviour of the epidemic trajectory will be due to changes in the fitness of the resistant phenotype. Confounding factors, such as as depletion of susceptibles or changes in host behaviour will also affect the epidemic trajectory. Under relatively mild assumptions detailed below changes in these confounding factors will affect other lineages equally. We can therefore use as “control” some data from a susceptible lineage, ideally closely related and with the same resistance profile to other antimicrobials used in significant amounts as primary treatment. Differences between the trajectories of the sensitive and resistant lineages can then be ascribed specifically to resistance, allowing us to estimate the associated fitness cost and benefit parameters.</p><p id="P6">Let us consider a pathogen causing infections at the level of a large population that are or were treated with a certain antimicrobial compound. We assume that at some point in the past one or several lineages with resistance to this antimicrobial compound have arisen. Our aim is to quantify the fitness cost and benefit of the resistance to this antimicrobial for a given lineage as a function of use of the antimicrobial of interest through time. To this end we need data that quantify the use over time of the given antimicrobial to treat infections caused by this pathogen, as well as a reasonable sample of sequenced case isolates from infections caused by the pathogen over time. Furthermore, we need information that characterises the resistance profiles of the individual isolates, which can be obtained either by resistance screening <italic>in vitro</italic>, or predicted from the sequences <italic>in silico</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">21</xref>]. A dated phylogeny of these samples is estimated, for example using BEAST [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">22</xref>], BEAST2 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">23</xref>] or BactDating [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref>]. This phylogeny is then used as the starting point for analysis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">25</xref>], to identify which samples belong to resistant and susceptible lineages and to select related lineages for further study that are wholly resistant or susceptible to the antimicrobial of interest, but otherwise similar in their resistance profiles. Note that for simplicity resistance is treated as a binary trait, with samples being either resistant or susceptible to antimicrobials, as is usually the case in resistance modelling studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="S4"><title>Transmission model derivation</title><p id="P7">In order to estimate the fitness cost and benefit of antimicrobial resistance, a transmission model needs to be specified. We focus on estimating the fitness parameters of a particular lineage harbouring a certain treatment resistant phenotype when previous infection does not confer immunity against 7 reinfection. Under the simplifying assumptions that the host population is unstructured and that past infections do not confer any immunity, the multi-lineage Susceptible-Infected-Susceptible (SIS) is a reasonable model [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">26</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27">27</xref>]. This model is more commonly referred to as multi-strain SIS. Fluctuations in the carriage levels of different lineages can also be due to external factors, such as changes in host demography or behaviours. Left unaccounted, such fluctuations would bias estimates of the fitness cost and benefit of resistance to a given antimicrobial. Therefore, we modify the model with time-varying a transmission rate <italic>β(t)</italic> and population size <italic>N(t)</italic>. This leads to an <italic>n</italic>-lineage model described by a system of the following <italic>n</italic>-coupled ordinary differential equations (ODEs): <disp-formula id="FD1"><label>(1)</label><mml:math id="M1"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable columnalign="left"><mml:mtr columnalign="left"><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>d</mml:mtext><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>d</mml:mtext><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mo>−</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr columnalign="left"><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>d</mml:mtext><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>d</mml:mtext><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mo>−</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr columnalign="left"><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mo>⋮</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr columnalign="left"><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>d</mml:mtext><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>d</mml:mtext><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mo>−</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="P8">Where <italic>I<sub>j</sub>(t)</italic> denotes the number of people infected with the <italic>j</italic>-th lineage at time <italic>t</italic>. <italic>β(t)</italic> is the transmission rate that varies with time due for example to changes that are not specific to any lineage, for example host behaviour. <italic>N(t)</italic> is the host population size which may also change with time due to a demographic factors. <italic>γ<sub>j</sub>(t)</italic> is the recovery rate of the <italic>j</italic>-th lineage at time <italic>t</italic>. These may or may not a vary with time through their dependency on the antimicrobial usage which changes with time. Finally <italic>S(t)</italic> denotes the number of susceptible hosts <disp-formula id="FD2"><label>(2)</label><mml:math id="M2"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:munderover><mml:mi>∑</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:munderover><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="P9">Typically this model could simply be reduced to a two lineage model, averaging over all lineages that are phenotypically similar in their resistance profiles. However, this is undesirable, as some of the lineages with the same resistance phenotype could differ in fitness due to different genomic background which would confound our estimates. Furthermore this sort of model would not be readily tractable in a genomic framework, because phylogenetic data is generally going to be informative about the dynamics of a particular lineage only. Note that this also means that the analysis produced is valid for the lineages being studied, and cannot be extrapolated to the overall dynamics of resistance for a given pathogen.</p><p id="P10">We therefore need to focus on the resolution of individual lineages. We note that environmental effects such as fluctuations in host population size or behaviour affect all lineages equally, if the population is well mixed. We denote the combination of these effects as <italic>b</italic>(<italic>t</italic>) = <italic>α</italic>(<italic>t</italic>)<italic>S</italic>(<italic>t</italic>)/<italic>N</italic>(<italic>t</italic>). Conditional on the knowledge trajectory of <italic>b</italic>(<italic>t</italic>) the ODEs in <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD1">Equation 1</xref> become uncoupled, and this allows us to reduce the system to uncoupled equations corresponding to the lineage we will be focusing on. As such we will treat <italic>b</italic>(<italic>t</italic>) as a random object that needs to be inferred. We further assume that for the susceptible lineages the average recovery rate denoted <italic>γ<sub>s</sub></italic> does not change over time, whereas for the resistant.6 lineage it takes one of two values: <inline-formula><mml:math id="M3"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> if a given patient is treated with the antimicrobial of interest, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M4"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mi>U</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mi>U</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> otherwise. If we also consider the known proportion of registered cases treated with the antimicrobial of interest <italic>u(t)</italic>, this fully determines the average recovery rate of the resistant lineages as: <disp-formula id="FD3"><label>(3)</label><mml:math id="M5"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mi>U</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="P11">We can now fully write down the equations of the model we will be using for the sensitive and resistant lineages, respectively: <disp-formula id="FD4"><label>(4)</label><mml:math id="M6"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable columnalign="left"><mml:mtr columnalign="left"><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>d</mml:mtext><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>d</mml:mtext><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr columnalign="left"><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>d</mml:mtext><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>d</mml:mtext><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mi>U</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="P12">In practice, we are interested in the difference in recovery rates between the susceptible and the resistant lineage and sensitive lineage when every case gets treated with the antimicrobial of interest, and when the antimicrobial of interest is not used at all. We denote these by <disp-formula id="FD5"><label>(5)</label><mml:math id="M7"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable columnalign="left"><mml:mtr columnalign="left"><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr columnalign="left"><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mi>U</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mi>U</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="P13">The interpretation is therefore that <italic>q<sub>T</sub></italic> captures the fitness benefit of resistance in the case <italic>q<sub>T</sub></italic> &lt; 0 and <italic>q<sub>U</sub></italic> captures the fitness cost of resistance in the case <italic>q<sub>U</sub></italic> &gt; 0.</p><p id="P14">This model can be applied to any number of resistant and sensitive lineages, simply by adding lineages associated terms to the likelihood and adding required parameters. This is straightforward as the individual lineages are independent conditional on <italic>b</italic>(<italic>t</italic>). but for simplicity the remainder of methods description focuses on the case of a single sensitive and a single resistant lineage, with the general case being a straightforward extension.</p></sec><sec id="S5"><title>Link to phylogenies</title><p id="P15">Having defined the epidemiological model, we can now link it to the phylogenetic process. Based on [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">28</xref>], the instantaneous coalescent rates for a single pair of lineages can be derived as <disp-formula id="FD6"><label>(6)</label><mml:math id="M8"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mtext>and</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:msub><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="P16">in the susceptible and resistant populations, respectively. The likelihood of a dated phylogeny <bold>g</bold> with n leaves at times <italic>s</italic><sub>1</sub> &lt; … &lt; <italic>s<sub>n</sub></italic> and <italic>n</italic> – 1 coalescent events at times <italic>c</italic><sub>1</sub> &lt; … &lt; <italic>c<sub>n – 1</sub></italic> and <italic>A(t)</italic> lineages at time t is therefore given by [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">29</xref>]: <disp-formula id="FD7"><label>(7)</label><mml:math id="M9"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mstyle><mml:mtext mathvariant="bold">g</mml:mtext></mml:mstyle><mml:mo>∣</mml:mo><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>exp</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mo>∫</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>∞</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>∞</mml:mi></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow><mml:mi>𝟙</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>≥</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mtext>d</mml:mtext><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:munderover><mml:mo>∏</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:munderover><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="P17">Where <italic>λ(t)</italic> = <italic>λ<sub>s</sub>(t)</italic> and <italic>λ(t)</italic> = <italic>λ<sub>r</sub>(t)</italic> for the susceptible and resistant phylogenies, respectively. However, in most cases, and indeed in our case, the integral in <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD7">Equation 7</xref> is not analytically intractable. Furthermore, the antibiotic use data is unlikely to span the entire phylogeny. Therefore, we define the approximate likelihood for the phylogeny truncated to [<italic>t</italic><sub>min</sub>, <italic>t</italic><sub>max</sub>], which is the intersection interval spanned by the antibiotic use data and the phylogenies under study.</p><p id="P18">As such we resort to the standard way of approximating coalescent likelihoods [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">30</xref>], partitioning the interval [<italic>t</italic><sub>min</sub>, <italic>t</italic><sub>max</sub>] into a fine mesh <italic>t</italic><sub>min</sub> = <italic>t</italic><sub>1</sub> &lt; <italic>t</italic><sub>2</sub> &lt; <italic>t</italic><sub>3</sub> &lt; … &lt; <italic>t<sub>N</sub></italic> = <italic>t</italic><sub>max</sub> such that <italic>t<sub>i</sub></italic> — <italic>t<sub>i-1</sub></italic> &lt; <italic>∆<sub>t</sub></italic> and that all sampling and coalescent times between <italic>t</italic><sub>min</sub>and <italic>t</italic><sub>max</sub>are included in the mesh: <disp-formula id="FD8"><label>(8)</label><mml:math id="M10"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mstyle><mml:mtext mathvariant="bold">g</mml:mtext></mml:mstyle><mml:mo>∣</mml:mo><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>exp</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:munderover><mml:mi>∑</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:munderover><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:munderover><mml:mo>∏</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:munderover><mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">1</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>min</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>max</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="P19">We note that the approach of how we treat the relationship between the phylogenies and epidemic is effectively a structured coalescent with no migration and time varying <italic>N<sub>e</sub>(t)</italic> determined by the deterministic epidemic model. Approaches reminiscent of ours have been used to formally study the expected age of a mutation in both presence or absence of selection [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31">31</xref>]. However in that case the populations correspond to different alleles, and the <italic>N<sub>e</sub>(t)</italic> curves follow the proportion of population with a given allele as determined by Wright-Fisher diffusion forwards in time. Migration between the demes corresponding to individual alleles can also further be added corresponding to recombination [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32">32</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="S6"><title>Bayesian inference</title><p id="P20">We first re-scale time from the interval [<italic>t</italic><sub>min</sub>, <italic>t</italic><sub>max</sub>] to [—1, 1]. Denoting the scale factor <italic>D</italic> = (<italic>t</italic><sub>max</sub>— <italic>t</italic><sub>min</sub>)/2 associated with this re-scaling, we account for this in the model by defining <inline-formula><mml:math id="M11"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo>¯</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mi>D</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. The model consists of independent first-order linear homogeneous ODEs for each lineage with time-varying coefficients. The solutions at time t subject to initial conditions <italic>I<sub>s</sub>(0)</italic> = <italic>I<sub>s0</sub></italic> and <italic>I<sub>r</sub></italic> (0) = <italic>I<sub>r0</sub></italic> can be obtained in terms of the integral of the instantaneous rates up to time <italic>t</italic>: <disp-formula id="FD9"><label>(9)</label><mml:math id="M12"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable columnalign="left"><mml:mtr columnalign="left"><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>exp</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mo>∫</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mtext>d</mml:mtext><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr columnalign="left"><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>exp</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mo>∫</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mi>U</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>d</mml:mtext><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
</p><p id="P21">As it stands, this model would not be well-suited for performing inference under, primarily due to the difficulty in choosing a sensible prior on <italic>b</italic>(<italic>t</italic>), and a very complicated dependency structure between the initial conditions and <italic>b</italic>(<italic>t</italic>). As such we re-parameterise the model by directly modelling the logarithm of <italic>I<sub>s</sub>(t)</italic> as a Gaussian Process: <disp-formula id="FD10"><label>(10)</label><mml:math id="M13"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>log</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="P22">Where <italic>C</italic>(<italic>t</italic>) is an appropriately chosen zero mean Gaussian Process, and <italic>µ<sub>s</sub></italic> is the susceptible intercept which relates to the susceptible initial condition <italic>I<sub>s0</sub></italic> as follows: <disp-formula id="FD11"><label>(11)</label><mml:math id="M14"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>log</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="P23">We use this formulation principally to loosen the coupling between the intercept parameter and the Gaussian Process in order to speed up sampling. From this we can compute <italic>b</italic>(<italic>t</italic>) and log <italic>I<sub>r</sub>(t)</italic> as <disp-formula id="FD12"><label>(12)</label><mml:math id="M15"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mtext>d</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>d</mml:mtext><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula> and <disp-formula id="FD13"><label>(13)</label><mml:math id="M16"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable columnalign="left"><mml:mtr columnalign="left"><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>log</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mo>∫</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mtext>d</mml:mtext><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mo>∫</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mi>u</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mtext>d</mml:mtext><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mo>∫</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mi>U</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mtext>d</mml:mtext><mml:mi>𝒯</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr columnalign="left"><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mo>∫</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mi>U</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mi>U</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mtext>d</mml:mtext><mml:mi>𝒯</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr columnalign="left"><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mi>U</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mi>U</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mo>∫</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mi>u</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mtext>d</mml:mtext><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="P24">Once again we follow the same reasoning for the resistant trajectory intercept <italic>µ<sub>r</sub></italic>, relating it to <italic>I<sub>r0</sub></italic> as: <disp-formula id="FD14"><label>(14)</label><mml:math id="M17"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>log</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="P25">Note that <inline-formula><mml:math id="M18"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mtext>d</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>d</mml:mtext><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> exists as long as the associated covariance kernel is sufficiently smooth such as in the case of the radial basis function (RBF) kernel [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33">33</xref>] which we used. Evaluating a full-rank, Gaussian process with differentiable trajectories on the entirety of the mesh would be prohibitively expensive due to the O(<italic>n</italic><sup>3</sup>) computational complexity, where <italic>n</italic> is the number of grid points. Such a high computational cost would make the model infeasible. Instead, we work with a low-rank representation of <italic>C</italic>(<italic>t</italic>) based on the framework introduced in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34">34</xref>]. This leads to the representation of the low-rank projection of <italic>C</italic>(<italic>t</italic>), denoted by <italic>Ĉ(t)</italic> <disp-formula id="FD15"><label>(15)</label><mml:math id="M19"><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:munderover><mml:mi>∑</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:munderover><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>RBF</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msqrt><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>π</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:msqrt><mml:mo>;</mml:mo><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msqrt><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:msqrt><mml:mi>sin</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>π</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula> and <disp-formula id="FD16"><label>(16)</label><mml:math id="M20"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mtext>d</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>d</mml:mtext><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:munderover><mml:mi>∑</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:munderover><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>RBF</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msqrt><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>π</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:msqrt><mml:mo>;</mml:mo><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msqrt><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:msqrt><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>π</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mi>cos</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>π</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="P26">This reduces the evaluation complexity of the Gaussian process prior from <italic>O</italic>(<italic>n</italic><sup>3</sup>) to <italic>O(nm)</italic>. <italic>L</italic> and <italic>m</italic> are approximation parameters that need to be specified a-priori, see [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34">34</xref>] for details. In practice we used the Hilbert Space Gaussian Process (HSGP) approximation with parameters <italic>L</italic> = 6.5 and m = 60. These approximation parameters are appropriate for the 99% interval of the length-scale prior used as per [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34">34</xref>]. Where <italic>f<sub>j</sub></italic> are independent and identically distributed random variables following the standard Gaussian distribution, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M21"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>RBF</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:mo>;</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the appropriate spectral density for the RBF kernel, <italic>ρ</italic> is the kernel length scale and <italic>α</italic> is the marginal standard deviation of the kernel [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34">34</xref>].</p><p id="P27">Denote by <inline-formula><mml:math id="M22"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">θ</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mo>γ</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mo>γ</mml:mo><mml:mi>U</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mo>γ</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> the parameters of the pathogen dynamics model. We can now factorise the model posterior <inline-formula><mml:math id="M23"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>π</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>∣</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mstyle><mml:mtext mathvariant="bold">g</mml:mtext></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mstyle><mml:mtext mathvariant="bold">g</mml:mtext></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, suppressing dependency on <italic>t</italic> where appropriate: <disp-formula id="FD17"><label>17</label><mml:math id="M24"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>π</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>∣</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mstyle><mml:mtext mathvariant="bold">g</mml:mtext></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mstyle><mml:mtext mathvariant="bold">g</mml:mtext></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>∝</mml:mo><mml:mi>π</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mstyle><mml:mtext mathvariant="bold">g</mml:mtext></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>∣</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>π</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mstyle><mml:mtext mathvariant="bold">g</mml:mtext></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>∣</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>π</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>∣</mml:mo><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>π</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>∣</mml:mo><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>π</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="P28">The first two terms are computed using the coalescent likelihood in <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD7">Equation 7</xref>. The third term is given by combining <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD6">Equations 6</xref>, <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD10">10</xref> and <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD12">12</xref>. The fourth term is obtained by combining <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD6">Equations 6</xref>,<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD12">12</xref> and <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD13">13</xref>. Finally, the last term is given by: <disp-formula id="FD18"><label>(18)</label><mml:math id="M25"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>π</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>π</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>∣</mml:mo><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>π</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mo>γ</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>∣</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>π</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mo>γ</mml:mo><mml:mi>U</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>∣</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mo>γ</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>π</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mo>γ</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>π</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>π</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>π</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mi>π</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mi>π</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula> where the first term is given by the Gaussian process (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD15">Equations 15</xref> and <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD16">16</xref>) and the remaining terms correspond to the prior distributions listed below.Choice of prior and parameterisation</p></sec><sec id="S7"><title>Choice of prior and parameterisation</title><p id="P29">The model is parameterised with the priors summarised in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>. The data is not expected to be very informative about the value of <italic>γ<sub>s</sub></italic>. As such, we impose a fairly informative prior on this parameter, centred around a guess <italic>γ</italic>* which must be known and supplied <italic>a priori</italic>. <italic>σ</italic> then governs how informative the prior is. We typically use a value of <italic>σ</italic> = 0.3, which includes relative fluctuations of over 50% in its 95% interval. The higher the value of a, the more complicated the geometry and subsequently sampling of the posterior becomes. <italic>γ<sub>T</sub></italic> and <italic>γ<sub>U</sub></italic> represent the recovery rates for the resistant lineage when the resistant lineage is treated with the focal antibiotic of interest, or another antibiotic, respectively. A normal distribution centred at <italic>γ<sub>s</sub></italic> and truncated to positive values only is a natural choice. We choose its standard deviation to be 0.3<italic>γ</italic>* as this puts &gt; 99% of the weight within 2<italic>γ</italic>* thus making implausibly large fluctuations unlikely. Such large fluctuations are hardly of interest here since they would lead to a very rapid selective sweep or extinction. The recovery rates <italic>γ<sub>T</sub></italic> and <italic>γ<sub>U</sub></italic> are related to the absolute changes in recovery and therefore fitness parameters using <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD5">Equation 5</xref>. <italic>γ<sub>U</sub></italic> &gt; <italic>γ<sub>S</sub></italic> corresponds to faster recovery when the resistant lineage is treated with an antimicrobial it is sensitive to and therefore a cost of resistance. <italic>γ<sub>T</sub></italic> &lt; <italic>γ<sub>S</sub></italic> corresponds to slower recovery when the resistant lineage is treated with the antimicrobial of interest and therefore a benefit of resistance. If instead a large proportion of posterior probability mass has <italic>γ<sub>U</sub></italic> &lt; <italic>γ<sub>S</sub></italic> or <italic>γ<sub>T</sub></italic> &gt; <italic>γ<sub>S</sub></italic>, we conclude that the result is consistent with either the cost or the benefit of resistance not being significantly present. The prior on p was chosen so that approximately 1% of mass lies on values of <italic>ρ</italic> &lt; 0.2 and approximately 1% of mass lies on <italic>ρ</italic> &gt; 2. The lower bound was chosen to avoid over-fitting, and the upper bound to suppress length scales that exceed the range of data and thus cannot be informed about by the data.</p><p id="P30">In practice, due to our choice of a sampling approach we need to parametrise <italic>γ<sub>U</sub></italic> and <italic>γ<sub>T</sub></italic> on an unconstrained space, and ideally also weaken the dependency on <italic>γ<sub>S</sub></italic>. To do so we introduce parameters <inline-formula><mml:math id="M26"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mo>˜</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mi>U</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M27"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mo>˜</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, and define <italic>γ<sub>U</sub></italic> and <italic>γ<sub>T</sub></italic> to be a deterministic transformation of these <disp-formula id="FD19"><label>19</label><mml:math id="M28"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mo>γ</mml:mo><mml:mi>U</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>log</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>exp</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mo>˜</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mi>U</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>log</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mo>γ</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="FD20"><label>20</label><mml:math id="M29"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>log</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>exp</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mo>˜</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>log</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
</p><p id="P31">The Jacobian adjustment to the likelihood associated with this transformation is proportional to <disp-formula id="FD21"><label>(21)</label><mml:math id="M30"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>|</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>det</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>J</mml:mi><mml:mi>q</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>|</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>∝</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>exp</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mo>˜</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>log</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>exp</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mo>˜</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mi>U</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>log</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p></sec><sec id="S8"><title>Computational implementation</title><p id="P32">The posterior in <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD17">Equation 17</xref> is a high dimensional distribution and we expect many parameters to have a high degree of interdependency. In order to sample from this distribution, we use Dynamic Hamiltonian Monte Carlo, a Hamiltonian Monte Carlo (HMC) sampler available in Stan [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35">35</xref>]. HMC is a Markov chain Monte Carlo approach that due to possessing energy conserving properties is able to take large steps between individual states while maintaining a high acceptance rates. This makes it efficient at sampling from moderately high dimensional posterior distributions with differentiable likelihoods, while requiring a much lower number of iterations. We implemented the model and inference method in a R package which is available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/dhelekal/ResistPhy/">https://github.com/dhelekal/ResistPhy/</ext-link>. All results shown used 4 chains with 2000 iterations for warmup and 2000 iterations for sampling. For all model parameters and all analysis the bulk effective sample size (bulk-ESS) was always greater than 500, and all <inline-formula><mml:math id="M31"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:math></inline-formula> statistics were lower than 1.05 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36">36</xref>], values that indicate no issues with mixing. We also checked that there were no divergent transitions at least during the sampling phase.</p></sec><sec id="S9"><title>Use of simulated and real datasets</title><p id="P33">For all simulations we use a stochastic, discrete state-space version of the multi-lineage SIS in <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD1">Equation 1</xref>. The system is simulated using tau-leaping [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37">37</xref>]. More specifically we consider a scenario with three lineages simulated over the course of 19 years. Two lineages are set to be susceptible and thus unaffected by antibiotic usage fluctuations and one is set to be resistant. The first lineage aims to represent the unobserved bulk of the population and thus is set to start at much higher prevalence. Conditional on the trajectories of the two lineages, we sample phylogenies under Kingman’s coalescent with varying effective population size <italic>N<sub>e</sub>(t)</italic> following <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD6">Equation 6</xref> conditional on the trajectories [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">28</xref>]. The parameters for the simulation were selected as to consistently provide a reasonable range of plausible behaviours so that resistant lineages would reach prevalence with orders of magnitude between 10<sup>2</sup> to 10<sup>4</sup>.</p><p id="P34">A total of 1102 genomes were collected between 2000 and 2013 by the CDC Gonococcal Isolate Surveillance (GISP) Project [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38">38</xref>]. A maximum-likelihood phylogeny was computed using PhyML [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39">39</xref>], which was corrected for recombination using ClonalFrameML [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40">40</xref>] and dated using BactDating [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref>]. This dated phylogeny is the same as previously used in an analysis of hidden population structure [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41">41</xref>]. The distribution of primary antimicrobial drugs used to treat gonorrhoea among participants of the GISP project between 1988 and 2019 was obtained from the GISP reports available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.cdc.gov/std/statistics/archive.htm">https://www.cdc.gov/std/statistics/archive.htm</ext-link>. Note that usage of ciprofloxacin and ofloxacin were combined into a single fluoroquinolone category. All the data and code used in the simulated and real datasets analyses is available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/dhelekal/ResistPhy/tree/main/run">https://github.com/dhelekal/ResistPhy/tree/main/run</ext-link>.</p></sec></sec><sec id="S10" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="S11"><title>Detailed analysis of a single simulated dataset</title><p id="P35">To validate the performance of this model we first resort to simulation from a 3-lineages stochastic SIS with population size <italic>N</italic>(<italic>t</italic>), transmission rate <italic>β</italic>(<italic>t</italic>) and antimicrobial usage function <italic>u</italic>(<italic>t</italic>) varying over the past 20 years, as illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>. The first two lineages are susceptible and thus unaffected by fluctuations in antimicrobial usage, whereas the third lineage is resistant and therefore affected. The first lineage represents the bulk of the susceptible lineages and is thus left unobserved. The remaining two lineages represent the observed lineages, susceptible and resistant, respectively. The per-day recovery rate of the sensitive lineage was set to <italic>γ<sub>s</sub></italic> = 1/60, the fitness cost of resistance to <italic>q<sub>U</sub></italic> = 1.25 and the fitness benefit of resistance to <italic>q<sub>T</sub></italic> = –2.7. From each of these two observed lineages, a dated phylogeny with 200 leaves was simulated. The sampling dates were randomly assigned to one of the first six years, with the relative probability of a particular year being chosen proportional to the total prevalence in that year. We performed inference on this simulated dataset; the traces are shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure S1</xref> and the posterior distribution of the kernel parameters in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure S2</xref>. The prevalence and reproduction number <italic>R(t)</italic> of both the susceptible and resistant lineages are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>. As expected, the inferred values followed the correct values used in the simulation. The inferred values of the susceptible lineage recovery rate <italic>γ</italic><sub>s</sub> and the cost and benefit of resistance <italic>q<sub>U</sub></italic> and <italic>q<sub>T</sub></italic> were also found to be close to their correct values, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>. The posterior distribution of <italic>γ<sub>s</sub></italic> was almost identical to the prior, which was centered on the correct value 1/60, reflecting the fact that the data is uninformative about this parameter and stressing the importance of using an informative prior. There was a strong negative correlation between the inferred values of <italic>q<sub>U</sub></italic> and <italic>q<sub>T</sub></italic>, as expected since these two parameters play opposite roles in the overall fitness of the resistant lineage relative to the sensitive lineage. Nevertheless, we detected both the cost and the benefit associated with resistance, since the ranges of inferred values for <italic>q<sub>U</sub></italic> and <italic>q<sub>T</sub></italic> were respectively above and below one, contrary to their log-normal priors with mean one (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>). Finally, we computed the posterior predictive distribution [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42">42</xref>] for the number of ancestral lineages through time <italic>A(t)</italic> and compared this with the input phylogenetic data (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure S3</xref>). The data and posterior predictive trajectories were similar, indicating a good fit of the model to the data as indeed would be expected here since the same model was used for simulation and inference.</p></sec><sec id="S12"><title>Benchmark using multiple simulated datasets</title><p id="P36">We repeated the same application of our inference method to data simulated in the same conditions as described above and illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>, except the values of the fitness cost and benefit of resistance were varied. A total of 50 simulated datasets were generated and analysed, with the fitness cost <italic>q<sub>U</sub></italic> increasing linearly from 1 to 1.2, and the fitness benefit <italic>q<sub>T</sub></italic> decreasing linearly from 1 to 0.5. The prevalence of the susceptible and resistant lineages in these simulations are shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure S4</xref>. The results of inference are illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref> and show that in almost all cases the posterior 95% credible intervals covered the correct values of the fitness cost and benefit of resistance used in the simulations.</p></sec><sec id="S13"><title>Application to fluoroquinolone resistant <italic>N. gonorrhoeae</italic> in USA</title><p id="P37">We demonstrate the use of our model and inferential framework by estimating the cost and benefit of fluoroquinolone resistance in <italic>N. gonorrhoeae.</italic> Based on the 1102 genomes collected between 2000 and 2013 by the CDC Gonococcal Isolate Surveillance Project [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38">38</xref>], a recombination-corrected tree was constructed using ClonalFrameML [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40">40</xref>] and dated using BactDating [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref>]. As there are two major fluoroquinolone resistant lineages present in this phylogeny [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38">38</xref>], we decided to do a comparative study. The two fluoroquinolone resistant lineages and one fluoroquinolone susceptible lineage were selected based on similar resistance profiles against other relevant antibiotics. By inspecting the antibiotic usage data and the resistance profiles for the the three lineages (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>) we can see that the resistance profiles match for antimicrobials that were in use as primary treatment at significant levels after 1995. As such this is the year we set as the analysis start date (<italic>t</italic><sub>min</sub> = 1995) and the end date is the date a when the last genomes were collected (<italic>t</italic><sub>max</sub> = 2013). Note that a subclade within the susceptible lineage that displayed a <italic>de novo</italic> gain of resistance to cefixime has been removed. The prior mean for the per-day recovery rate for the susceptible lineage was set to <italic>γ</italic>* = 1/90 based on previous gonorrhoea modelling studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43">43</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R44">44</xref>].</p><p id="P38">We performed inference for this dataset; the traces are shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure S5</xref> and the posterior distribution of kernel parameters in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure S6</xref>. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref> depicts the summary of posterior latent transmission dynamics for the two resistant lineages, whereas <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure S7</xref> shows the same for the susceptible lineage. The two resistant lineages have similar dynamics, with a peak in prevalence around 2007, which corresponds to the moment when fluoroquinolone use dropped (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref> depicts the marginal and joint posterior distributions for the resistance parameters <italic>q<sub>U</sub></italic> and <italic>q<sub>T</sub></italic> for both resistant lineages. This is consistent with there being both a cost and benefit to fluoroquinolone resistance for both lineages, since both <italic>q<sub>T</sub></italic> and <italic>q<sub>U</sub></italic> are respectively localised below 1 and above 1, with high posterior probability. It is noteworthy that while both of these lineages come from distinct genetic background, their resistance profile is qualitatively very similar, indicating both of these lineages faced similar selective pressures and neither seems to have successfully adapted to overcome the fitness cost associated with fluoroquinolone resistance. We used a posterior predictive approach to ensure that the model can explain the data appropriately [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42">42</xref>]. Posterior predictive trajectories for the function of ancestral lineages through time <italic>A</italic>(<italic>t</italic>) were simulated and found to be very similar to the ones implied by the phylogenetic data (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure S8</xref>).</p><p id="P39">Under the assumption of perfect competition between lineages, if we want to ensure to that a resistant lineage cannot establish, and its proportion decays sufficiently fast, we fix a decay factor <italic>c</italic> &gt; 0 and aim to ensure that the growth rate of the resistant lineage is c units lower than that of the sensitive lineage, that is <italic>r<sub>s</sub></italic>(<italic>t</italic>) — <italic>r<sub>r</sub></italic>(<italic>t</italic>) &gt; <italic>c</italic>. Note that <italic>r(t)</italic> is the growth rate through time, not <italic>R</italic>(<italic>t</italic>), the time varying reproduction number. We choose to work with growth rates as these are less sensitive to susceptible recovery rate mispecification. Given that the lineages have the same transmission rate function <italic>b</italic>(<italic>t</italic>), this condition is equivalent to <italic>γ<sub>s</sub></italic>(<italic>t</italic>) — <italic>γ<sub>r</sub></italic>(<italic>t</italic>) &gt; <italic>c</italic>, and using the definition of <italic>γ<sub>r</sub></italic>(<italic>t</italic>) from <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD3">Equation 3</xref>, this is equivalent to <italic>u</italic>(<italic>t</italic>)<italic>q<sub>T</sub></italic> + (1 — <italic>u</italic>(<italic>t</italic>))<italic>q<sub>U</sub></italic> &gt; <italic>c</italic>. We use this to estimate posterior probabilities the differences in growth rates between the susceptible lineage and each of both resistant lineages exceed c as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figure 8</xref>. In order to be 95% certain that the resistant lineages remain at a lower fitness than the susceptible lineage, fluoroquinolone should not be prescribed to more than ~ 20% and ~ 15% of infected individuals, for resistant lineages 1 and 2, respectively.</p></sec></sec><sec id="S14" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p id="P40">A bacterial pathogen lineage that is resistant to a given antibiotic incurs both a fitness cost and a fitness benefit compared to similar susceptible lineages [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">8</xref>]. When the antibiotic is used extensively, the benefit is likely to be greater than the cost. In that case, a resistant lineage has a selective advantage over susceptible lineages, and therefore grows at a faster rate. Conversely, if the antibiotic is used rarely or not at all, the benefit is likely to become smaller than the cost, which will lead to the resistant lineage decreasing in frequency. Estimating these parameters is therefore of primary importance to determine how antibiotics should be prescribed without causing an increase in resistance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref>]. Here, we have shown how genome sequencing data coupled with data on antibiotic prescriptions can be used for this purpose, following on previous work that demonstrated the link between epidemic dynamics and phylogenetics [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">28</xref>]. By comparing the phylodynamic trajectories of susceptible and resistant lineages, and relating them with a known function of antibiotic use, we show that it is possible to estimate separately the parameters corresponding to the fitness cost and benefit of resistance. In particular, we reanalysed a large published collection of <italic>N. gonorrhoeae</italic> genomes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38">38</xref>]. We were able to infer these parameters for two lineages of <italic>N. gonorrhoeae</italic> resistant to fluoroquinolones, and found similar estimates of cost and benefit in both (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref>). We were able to use this knowledge to make recommendations on antibiotic stewardship of fluoroquinolones (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figure 8</xref>).</p><p id="P41">Dated phylogenies for both susceptible and resistant lineages are needed as input into our method. Several software tools can be used to produce this either from a sequence alignment, for example BEAST [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">22</xref>] and BEAST2 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">23</xref>], or from an undated phylogeny, for example treedater [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R45">45</xref>] and BactDating [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref>]. Building such a dated phylogeny requires either the population to be measurably evolving over the sampling period [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R46">46</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R47">47</xref>], or a previous estimate of the molecular clock rate [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R48">48</xref>]. Another input required by our method is the antibiotic usage function over a relevant timeframe and geographical location. This may not always be available in all historical contexts, but efforts are increasingly being made to capture this data [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R49">49</xref>]. Finally, our method requires an informative prior of the recovery rate for the susceptible lineage (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>), since this is typically not identifiable from the data, as in many similar compartmental epidemic models [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R50">50</xref>]. This prior needs to be chosen carefully depending on the infectious disease under study and based on the existing scientific literature.</p><p id="P42">Our inferential methodology is based on a well-defined and relatively simple epidemic model (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD4">Equation 4</xref>) which means making a number of assumptions the validity of which was considered before performing our analysis. Our model assumes multiple-lineage pathogen dynamics driven by person-to-person transmission in a well mixed host population in the absence of any significant population structure, so that there is perfect competition between lineages. It also assumes that individuals become infectious as soon as they are infected, that their infectiousness remains constant until they recover, after which they become susceptible again without any immunity being gained. This list of relatively strong assumptions may seem to preclude application to any real infectious disease, but they are necessary to obtain a model under which inference can be performed. Furthermore, violation of some of these assumptions does not necessarily invalidate the results of inference. For example, if infection causes immunity, this will effectively reduce the number <italic>S(t)</italic> of susceptible individuals (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD2">Equation 2</xref>), but this number is not assumed to be constant in our model. In fact both the size N(t) of the host population and the number <italic>S(t)</italic> of susceptible individuals are integrated out as part of our parameterisation in terms of the function <italic>b</italic>(<italic>t</italic>) (cf <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD4">Equation 4</xref>), so the inference is robust as long as the immunity conferred applies to all lineages under study. Likewise the assumption of an unstructured population may seem problematic, including in our application to <italic>N. gonorrhoeae</italic> throughout the USA, but for anything other than small local outbreaks the genomes available for analysis are sparsely sampled from the whole infected population [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R51">51</xref>]. In these conditions, any effect of the host population structure on phylodynamics is likely to be insignificant as long as an effective rather than actual number of infections is considered [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R52">52</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R53">53</xref>].</p><p id="P43">The compatibility of our model with the phylogenetic data under analysis can be tested using posterior predictive distribution checks (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figures S3 and S8</xref>). If these tests fail, or if the model assumptions are thought to be inappropriate, a solution may be to resort to other methods that postprocess a dated phylogeny [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">25</xref>] but make less assumptions, at the cost of not inferring directly the parameters of resistance. Alternative approaches includes non-parametric methods that detect differences in the branching patterns in different lineages [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41">41</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R54">54</xref>] as well as methods parameterised in terms of the pathogen population size growth rather than underlying epidemiological drivers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R55">55</xref>]. However, our model-based approach is both general and flexible, so that we expect it to be applicable in many settings using our software implementation which is available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/dhelekal/ResistPhy/">https://github.com/dhelekal/ResistPhy/</ext-link>. We believe that this methodology, applied to the increasingly large genomic databases on many bacterial pathogens, will help quantify the exact link between antibiotic usage and resistance and therefore provide a much-needed evidence basis for the design of future antibiotic prescription strategies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R56">56</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R57">57</xref>].</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="SM"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1"><label>Supplementary Material</label><media xlink:href="EMS157998-supplement-Supplementary_Material.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" id="d96aAdEbB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack id="S15"><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>We acknowledge funding from the National Institute for Health Research (NIHR) Health Protection Research Unit in Genomics and Enabling Data. This work was supported by the UK Engineering and Physical Sciences Research Council (EPSRC) grant EP/S022244/1 for the EPSRC Centre for Doctoral Training in Mathematics for Real-World Systems II.</p></ack><ref-list><ref id="R1"><label>[1]</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><collab>CDC</collab><source>Antibiotic resistance threats in the United States, 2013</source><publisher-name>Current</publisher-name><year>2013</year><fpage>114</fpage><comment>ISSN 10985530. doi:CS239559-B</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>[2]</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>O’;Neill</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><source>Tackling drug-resistant infections globally: final report and recommendations</source><publisher-name>Wellcome Trust &amp; HM Government</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc><year>2016</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>[3]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ikuta</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharara</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Swetschinski</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Aguilar</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name><name><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bisignano</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Wool</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Global burden of bacterial antimicrobial resistance in 2019: a systematic analysis</article-title><source>The Lancet</source><year>2022</year><volume>399</volume><fpage>629</fpage><lpage>655</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8841637</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35065702</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(21)02724-0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>[4]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clatworthy</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Pierson</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Hung</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Targeting virulence: a new paradigm for antimicrobial therapy</article-title><source>Nat Chem Biol</source><year>2007</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>541</fpage><lpage>548</lpage><comment>ISSN 1552-4450</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17710100</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>[5]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bonhoeffer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lipsitch</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Levin</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluating treatment protocols to prevent antibiotic resistance</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>1997</year><volume>94</volume><fpage>12106</fpage><lpage>12111</lpage><comment>ISSN 0027-8424</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC23718</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9342370</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.94.22.12106</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>[6]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Austin</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kristinsson</surname><given-names>KG</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The relationship between the volume of antimicrobial consumption in human communities and the frequency of resistance</article-title><source>PNAS’</source><year>1999</year><volume>96</volume><fpage>1152</fpage><lpage>1156</lpage><comment>ISSN 0027-8424</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC15366</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9927709</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.96.3.1152</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>[7]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Spicknall</surname><given-names>IH</given-names></name><name><surname>Foxman</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Marrs</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name><name><surname>Eisenberg</surname><given-names>JNS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A modeling framework for the evolution and spread of antibiotic resistance: Literature review and model categorization</article-title><source>Am J Epidemiol</source><year>2013</year><volume>178</volume><fpage>508</fpage><lpage>520</lpage><comment>ISSN 00029262</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3736756</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23660797</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/aje/kwt017</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>[8]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Andersson</surname><given-names>DI</given-names></name><name><surname>Levin</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The biological cost of antibiotic resistance</article-title><source>Curr Opin Microbiol</source><year>1999</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>489</fpage><lpage>493</lpage><comment>ISSN 13695274.</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10508723</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>[9]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Andersson</surname><given-names>DI</given-names></name><name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antibiotic resistance and its cost: is it possible to reverse resistance?</article-title><source>Nat Rev Microbiol</source><year>2010</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>260</fpage><lpage>271</lpage><comment>ISSN 1740-1526</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20208551</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>[10]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Whittles</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Didelot</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Estimating the fitness benefit and cost of cefixime resistance in Neisseria gonorrhoeae to inform prescription policy: A modelling study</article-title><source>PLoS Med</source><year>2017</year><volume>14</volume><elocation-id>e1002416</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5663337</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29088226</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.1002416</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>[11]</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rubin</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name><name><surname>Westervelt</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hullahalli</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Waldor</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Grad</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Variation in supplemental carbon dioxide requirements defines lineage-specific antibiotic resistance acquisition in neisseria gonorrhoeae</article-title><source>bioRxiv</source><publisher-name>Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory</publisher-name><year>2022</year><comment>eprint: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.biorxiv.org/content/early/2022/02/25/2022.02.24.481660.full.pdf">https://www.biorxiv.org/content/early/2022/02/25/2022.02.24.481660.full.pdf</ext-link></comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2022.02.24.481660</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>[12]</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lehtinen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Blanquart</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Lipsitch</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fraser</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><collab>Collaboration, w t M P</collab></person-group><article-title>On the evolutionary ecology of multidrug resistance in bacteria</article-title><source>PLOS Pathogens</source><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><year>2019</year><volume>15</volume><elocation-id>e1007763</elocation-id><comment>ISSN 1553-7374</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6532944</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31083687</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1007763</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>[13]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pybus</surname><given-names>OG</given-names></name><name><surname>Rambaut</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evolutionary analysis of the dynamics of viral infectious disease</article-title><source>Nat Rev Genet</source><year>2009</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>540</fpage><lpage>50</lpage><comment>ISSN 1471-0064</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7097015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19564871</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrg2583</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>[14]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Volz</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Frost</surname><given-names>SDW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sampling through time and phylodynamic inference with coalescent and birth - death models</article-title><source>J R Soc Interface</source><year>2014</year><volume>11</volume><elocation-id>20140945</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4223917</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25401173</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rsif.2014.0945</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>[15]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Volz</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Didelot</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Modeling the Growth and Decline of Pathogen Effective Population Size Provides Insight into Epidemic Dynamics and Drivers of Antimicrobial Resistance</article-title><source>Syst Biol</source><year>2018</year><volume>67</volume><fpage>719</fpage><lpage>728</lpage><comment>ISSN 1063-5157</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6005154</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29432602</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sysbio/syy007</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>[16]</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kuhnert</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kouyos</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Shirreff</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Pecerska</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Scherrer</surname><given-names>AU</given-names></name><name><surname>Boni</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Yerly</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Klimkait</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Aubert</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Gunthard</surname><given-names>HF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Quantifying the fitness cost of HIV-1 drug resistance mutations through phylodynamics</article-title><source>PLOS Pathogens</source><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><year>2018</year><volume>14</volume><elocation-id>e1006895</elocation-id><comment>ISSN 1553-7374</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5877888</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29462208</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1006895</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>[17]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pecerska</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuhnert</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Meehan</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Coscolla</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>de Jong</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><name><surname>Gagneux</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Stadler</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quantifying transmission fitness costs of multi-drug resistant tuberculosis</article-title><source>Epidemics</source><year>2021</year><volume>36</volume><elocation-id>100471</elocation-id><comment>ISSN 1755-4365</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34256273</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>[18]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>SYW</given-names></name><name><surname>Shapiro</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Skyline-plot methods for estimating demographic history from nucleotide sequences</article-title><source>Molecular Ecology Resources</source><year>2011</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>423</fpage><lpage>434</lpage><comment>ISSN 1755098X</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21481200</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>[19]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Volz</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kosakovsky Pond</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Leigh Brown</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Frost</surname><given-names>SDW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phylodynamics of infectious disease epidemics</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>2009</year><volume>183</volume><fpage>1421</fpage><lpage>30</lpage><comment>ISSN 1943-2631</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2787429</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19797047</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1534/genetics.109.106021</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>[20]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dearlove</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Coalescent inference for infectious disease: Meta-analysis of hepatitis C</article-title><source>Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society B</source><year>2013</year><volume>368</volume><elocation-id>20120314</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3678333</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23382432</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rstb.2012.0314</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>[21]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Didelot</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Bowden</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Peto</surname><given-names>TEA</given-names></name><name><surname>Crook</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transforming clinical microbiology with bacterial genome sequencing</article-title><source>Nature Reviews Genetics</source><year>2012</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>601</fpage><lpage>612</lpage><comment>ISSN 1471-0056</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5049685</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22868263</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrg3226</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>[22]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Suchard</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lemey</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Baele</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Ayres</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Drummond</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Rambaut</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bayesian phylogenetic and phylodynamic data integration using BEAST 1.10</article-title><source>Virus Evol</source><year>2018</year><volume>4</volume><elocation-id>vey016</elocation-id><comment>ISSN 2057-1577</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6007674</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29942656</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ve/vey016</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>[23]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bouckaert</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Vaughan</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name><name><surname>Fourment</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gavryushkina</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Heled</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Denise</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Maio</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name><name><surname>Matschiner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ogilvie</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Plessis</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>BEAST 2.5: An Advanced Software Platform for Bayesian Evolutionary Analysis</article-title><source>PLoS Comput Biol</source><year>2019</year><volume>15</volume><elocation-id>e1006650</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6472827</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30958812</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006650</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>[24]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Didelot</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Croucher</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bentley</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bayesian inference of ancestral dates on bacterial phylogenetic trees</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2018</year><volume>46</volume><elocation-id>e134</elocation-id><comment>ISSN 0305-1048</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6294524</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30184106</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gky783</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>[25]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Didelot</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Parkhill</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A scalable analytical approach from bacterial genomes to epidemiology</article-title><source>Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society B: Biological Sciences</source><year>2022</year><volume>377</volume><elocation-id>20210246</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9393561</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35989600</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rstb.2021.0246</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>[26]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kirupaharan</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>SIS epidemic models with multiple pathogen strains</article-title><source>Journal of Difference Equations and Applications</source><year>2004</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>53</fpage><lpage>75</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>[27]</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Keeling</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Rohani</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><source>Modeling Infectious Diseases in Humans and Animals</source><publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name><year>2008</year><comment>ISSN 9780691116174</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>[28]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Volz</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Complex population dynamics and the coalescent under neutrality</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>2012</year><volume>190</volume><fpage>187</fpage><lpage>201</lpage><comment>ISSN 1943-2631</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3249372</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22042576</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1534/genetics.111.134627</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>[29]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Griffiths</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Tavare</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sampling theory for neutral alleles in a varying environment</article-title><source>Philos Trans R Soc B</source><year>1994</year><volume>344</volume><fpage>403</fpage><lpage>410</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7800710</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>[30]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gill</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Lemey</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Faria</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name><name><surname>Rambaut</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Shapiro</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Suchard</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Improving bayesian population dynamics inference: A coalescent-based model for multiple loci</article-title><source>Mol Biol Evol</source><year>2013</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>713</fpage><lpage>724</lpage><comment>ISSN 07374038</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3563973</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23180580</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/molbev/mss265</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>[31]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Griffiths</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The frequency spectrum of a mutation, and its age, in a general diffusion model</article-title><source>Theoretical Population Biology</source><year>2003</year><volume>64</volume><fpage>241</fpage><lpage>251</lpage><comment>ISSN 0040-5809</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12948685</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><label>[32]</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Etheridge</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pfaffelhuber</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Wakolbinger</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An approximate sampling formula under genetic hitchhiking</article-title><source>The Annals of Applied Probability</source><publisher-name>Institute of Mathematical Statistics</publisher-name><year>2006</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>685</fpage><lpage>729</lpage><comment>ISSN 1050-5164, 2168-8737</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1214/105051606000000114</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><label>[33]</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rasmussen</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name></person-group><source>Gaussian Processes in Machine Learning</source><publisher-name>Springer Berlin Heidelberg</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Berlin, Heidelberg</publisher-loc><year>2004</year><fpage>63</fpage><lpage>71</lpage><comment>ISBN 978-3-540-28650-9</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-3-540-28650-9_4</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><label>[34]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Riutort-Mayol</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Burkner</surname><given-names>P-C</given-names></name><name><surname>Andersen</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Solin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Vehtari</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Practical hilbert space approximate bayesian gaussian processes for probabilistic programming</article-title><source>arXiv</source><year>2022</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.48550/arXiv.2004.11408</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><label>[35]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carpenter</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Gelman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoffman</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Goodrich</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Betancourt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Brubaker</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Riddell</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Stan: A probabilistic programming language</article-title><source>J Stat Softw</source><year>2017</year><volume>76</volume><comment>ISSN 15487660</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9788645</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36568334</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18637/jss.v076.i01</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><label>[36]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vehtarh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gelman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Simpson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Carpenter</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Burkner</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rank-Normalization, Folding, and Localization: An Improved R hat for Assessing Convergence of MCMC</article-title><source>Bayesian Anal</source><year>2021</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>667</fpage><lpage>718</lpage><comment>ISSN 19316690</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1214/20-BA1221</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R37"><label>[37]</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gillespie</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Approximate accelerated stochastic simulation of chemically reacting systems</article-title><source>The Journal of Chemical Physics</source><publisher-name>American Institute of Physics</publisher-name><year>2001</year><volume>115</volume><fpage>1716</fpage><lpage>1733</lpage><comment>ISSN 0021-9606</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22239763</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R38"><label>[38]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grad</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Kirkcaldy</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Marks</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Bentley</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Trees</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Lipsitch</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Diseases</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Health</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genomic epidemiology of gonococcal resistance to extended spectrum cephalosporins, macrolides, and fluoroquinolones in the US, 2000-2013</article-title><source>J Infect Dis</source><year>2016</year><volume>214</volume><fpage>1579</fpage><lpage>1587</lpage><comment>ISSN 0022-1899</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5091375</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27638945</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/infdis/jiw420</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R39"><label>[39]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guindon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Dufayard</surname><given-names>J-F</given-names></name><name><surname>Lefort</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Anisimova</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hordijk</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Gascuel</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>New algorithms and methods to estimate maximum-likelihood phylogenies: Assessing the performance of PhyML 3.0</article-title><source>Systematic biology</source><year>2010</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>307</fpage><lpage>21</lpage><comment>ISSN 1076-836X</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20525638</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R40"><label>[40]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Didelot</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>ClonalFrameML: Efficient Inference of Recombination in Whole Bacterial Genomes</article-title><source>PLoS Comput Biol</source><year>2015</year><volume>11</volume><elocation-id>e1004041</elocation-id><comment>ISSN 1553-7358</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4326465</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25675341</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1004041</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R41"><label>[41]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Volz</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Wiuf</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Grad</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name><surname>Frost</surname><given-names>SDW</given-names></name><name><surname>Dennis</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Didelot</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of hidden population structure in time-scaled phylogenies</article-title><source>Systematic Biology</source><year>2020</year><volume>69</volume><fpage>884</fpage><lpage>896</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8559910</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32049340</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sysbio/syaa009</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R42"><label>[42]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gelman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Stern</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Posterior predictive assessment of model fitness via realized discrepancies</article-title><source>Stat Sinica</source><year>1996</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>733</fpage><lpage>807</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R43"><label>[43]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fingerhuth</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonhoeffer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Low</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Althaus</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antibiotic-Resistant Neisseria gonorrhoeae Spread Faster with More Treatment, Not More Sexual Partners</article-title><source>PLOS’ Pathog</source><year>2016</year><volume>12</volume><elocation-id>e1005611</elocation-id><comment>ISSN 1553-7374</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4872991</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27196299</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1005611</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R44"><label>[44]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Whittles</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Didelot</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A dynamic power-law sexual network model of gonorrhoea outbreaks</article-title><source>PLoS Comput Biol</source><year>2019</year><volume>15</volume><elocation-id>e1006748</elocation-id><comment>ISSN 1553-7358</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6426262</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30849080</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1006748</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R45"><label>[45]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Volz</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Frost</surname><given-names>SDW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Scalable relaxed clock phylogenetic dating</article-title><source>Virus Evolution</source><year>2017</year><volume>3</volume><elocation-id>vex025</elocation-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R46"><label>[46]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Drummond</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Pybus</surname><given-names>OG</given-names></name><name><surname>Rambaut</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Forsberg</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodrigo</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Measurably evolving populations</article-title><source>Trends in Ecology and Evolution</source><year>2003</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>481</fpage><lpage>488</lpage><comment>ISSN 01695347</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0169-5347(03)00216-7</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R47"><label>[47]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Biek</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Pybus</surname><given-names>OG</given-names></name><name><surname>Lloyd-Smith</surname><given-names>JO</given-names></name><name><surname>Didelot</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Measurably evolving pathogens in the genomic era</article-title><source>Trends in Ecology &amp; Evolution</source><year>2015</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>306</fpage><lpage>313</lpage><comment>ISSN 0169-5347</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4457702</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25887947</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tree.2015.03.009</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R48"><label>[48]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Duchene</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Holt</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name><surname>Weill</surname><given-names>F-X</given-names></name><name><surname>Le Hello</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hawkey</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Fourment</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genome-scale rates of evolutionary change in bacteria</article-title><source>Microbial Genomics</source><year>2016</year><volume>2</volume><elocation-id>e000094</elocation-id><comment>ISSN 2057-5858</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5320706</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28348834</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/mgen.0.000094</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R49"><label>[49]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Curtis</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldacre</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Openprescribing: normalised data and software tool to research trends in english nhs primary care prescribing 1998-2016</article-title><source>BMJ open</source><year>2018</year><volume>8</volume><elocation-id>e019921</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5855401</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29476029</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2017-019921</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R50"><label>[50]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roosa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Chowell</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assessing parameter identifiability in compartmental dynamic models using a computational approach: application to infectious disease transmission models</article-title><source>Theoretical Biology and Medical Modelling</source><year>2019</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>15</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6332839</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30642334</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12976-018-0097-6</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R51"><label>[51]</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Klinkenberg</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Colijn</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Didelot</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Methods for Outbreaks Using Genomic Data</chapter-title><source>Handbook of Infectious Disease Data Analysis</source><publisher-name>CRC Press</publisher-name><year>2019</year><fpage>245</fpage><lpage>263</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R52"><label>[52]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nordborg</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structured coalescent processes on different time scales</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>1997</year><volume>146</volume><fpage>1501</fpage><lpage>1514</lpage><comment>ISSN 0016-6731</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1208092</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9258691</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/genetics/146.4.1501</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R53"><label>[53]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Frost</surname><given-names>SDW</given-names></name><name><surname>Volz</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Viral phylodynamics and the search for an ‘effective number of infections’</article-title><source>Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society B</source><year>2010</year><volume>365</volume><fpage>1879</fpage><lpage>1890</lpage><comment>ISSN 0962-8436</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2880113</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20478883</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rstb.2010.0060</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R54"><label>[54]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dearlove</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Frost</surname><given-names>SDW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biased phylodynamic inferences from analysing clusters of viral sequences</article-title><source>Virus Evolution</source><year>2017</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>10</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5570026</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28852573</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ve/vex020</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R55"><label>[55]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Helekal</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Ledda</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Volz</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Wyllie</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Didelot</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bayesian inference of clonal expansions in a dated phylogeny</article-title><source>Systematic Biology</source><year>2021</year><elocation-id>syab095</elocation-id><comment>ISSN 1063-5157</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9366454</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34893904</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sysbio/syab095</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R56"><label>[56]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Michael</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Dominey-Howes</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Labbate</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Antimicrobial Resistance Crisis: 8 Causes, Consequences, and Management</article-title><source>Frontiers in Public Health</source><year>2014</year><volume>2</volume><comment>ISSN 2296-2565</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4165128</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25279369</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpubh.2014.00145</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R57"><label>[57]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name><name><surname>Sundsfjord</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Steinbakk</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Regmi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Karkey</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Guerin</surname><given-names>PJi</given-names></name><name><surname>Piddock</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Understanding the mechanisms and drivers of antimicrobial resistance</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>2016</year><volume>387</volume><fpage>176</fpage><lpage>187</lpage><comment>ISSN 1474547X</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26603922</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Host population size function <italic>N</italic>(<italic>t</italic>), transmission rate over time <italic>α</italic>(<italic>t</italic>) and antibiotic usage function <italic>u</italic>(<italic>t</italic>) used in the simulated datasets.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS157998-f001"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Posterior summary of dynamics for the sensitive (left) and resistant (right) lineages, showing prevalence (top) and reproduction number (bottom). Bold solid red lines indicates simulated values. Posterior median in bold dashed black line. Shaded bands indicate 95% posterior credible intervals. Solid light lines represent posterior draws.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS157998-f002"/></fig><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Marginal and joint posterior distributions for the recovery rate of the sensitive lineage (<italic>γ<sub>s</sub></italic>), fitness cost (<italic>q<sub>U</sub></italic>) and fitness benefit (<italic>q<sub>T</sub></italic>) of resistance. Bold red solid lines indicate simulation values. Bold blue dashed lines indicate prior density values.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS157998-f003"/></fig><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Inferred parameters versus correct values. A total of 50 simulated datasets were generated, with decreasing values of <italic>q<sub>T</sub></italic> and increasing values of <italic>q<sub>U</sub></italic> as shown by the dotted lines in grey and blue, respectively. For each simulated dataset we applied our inference method. The grey and blue dots show the mean inferred values of <italic>q<sub>T</sub></italic> and <italic>q<sub>U</sub></italic>, respectively, with vertical bars representing the 95% credible intervals for both parameters.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS157998-f004"/></fig><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>Antibiotic usage data and phylogeny used for the application to fluoroquinolone resistant <italic>N. gonorrhoeae</italic>.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS157998-f005"/></fig><fig id="F6" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title>Posterior epidemic dynamics for both fluoroquinolone resistant lineages of <italic>N. gonorrhoeae</italic>.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS157998-f006"/></fig><fig id="F7" position="float"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><title>Marginal and joint posterior distribution for the cost <italic>(q<sub>u</sub></italic>) and benefit <italic>(q<sub>T</sub></italic>) of both fluoroquinolone resistant lineages of <italic>N. gonorrhoeae.</italic></title></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS157998-f007"/></fig><fig id="F8" position="float"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p>Posterior probabilities of <italic>R<sub>r</sub></italic>(<italic>t</italic>)/<italic>R<sub>s</sub></italic>(<italic>t</italic>) &lt; <italic>C</italic> given usage <italic>u</italic>(<italic>t</italic>) in the x-axis and value of <italic>C</italic> in the y-axis, for both fluoroquinolone resistant lineages of <italic>N. gonorrhoeae</italic>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS157998-f008"/></fig><table-wrap id="T1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Summary of the parameters and priors used in the model.</title></caption><table frame="box" rules="all"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top">Parameter</th><th align="left" valign="top">Symbol</th><th align="left" valign="top">Prior</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top">Susceptible lineage recovery rate</td><td align="left" valign="top"><italic>γ<sub>s</sub></italic></td><td align="left" valign="top"><monospace>log-normal</monospace>(log <italic>γ</italic>*, <italic>σ</italic>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">Resistant lineage recovery rate if treated with focal antibiotic</td><td align="left" valign="top"><italic>γ<sub>T</sub></italic></td><td align="left" valign="top"><monospace>normal</monospace>(<italic>γ<sub>s</sub></italic>, 0.3<italic>γ</italic>*)𝟙[<italic>x</italic> &gt; 0]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">Resistant lineage recovery rate if treated with other antibiotic</td><td align="left" valign="top"><italic>γ<sub>U</sub></italic></td><td align="left" valign="top"><monospace>normal</monospace>(<italic>γ<sub>s</sub></italic>, 0.3<italic>γ</italic>*)𝟙[<italic>x</italic> &gt; 0]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">Initial prevalence of sensitive lineage</td><td align="left" valign="top"><italic>I<sub>s0</sub></italic></td><td align="left" valign="top"><monospace>log-normal</monospace>(6, 2)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">Initial prevalence of resistant lineage</td><td align="left" valign="top"><italic>I<sub>r0</sub></italic></td><td align="left" valign="top"><monospace>log-normal</monospace>(6, 2)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">GP kernel marginal variance</td><td align="left" valign="top"><italic>α</italic></td><td align="left" valign="top"><monospace>gamma</monospace>(4, 4)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">GP kernel length scale</td><td align="left" valign="top"><italic>ρ</italic></td><td align="left" valign="top"><monospace>inverse-gamma</monospace>(4.63, 2.21)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">Approximate GP functions</td><td align="left" valign="top"><italic>f<sub>1:m</sub></italic></td><td align="left" valign="top">𝒩(0,1)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></floats-group></article>