<!DOCTYPE article
 PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" article-type="preprint"><?all-math-mml yes?><?use-mml?><?origin ukpmcpa?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">bioRxiv</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>bioRxiv : the preprint server for biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub"/></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">EMS156372</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2022.10.24.513610</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="archive">PPR563885</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="europepmc-category"><subject>Covid-19</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Fever temperatures modulate intraprotein dynamics and enhance the binding affinity between monoclonal antibodies and the Spike protein from SARS-CoV-2</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7989-0402</contrib-id><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Dong Gun</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4034-1892</contrib-id><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Hak Sung</given-names></name></contrib><aff id="A1">Department of Biological Sciences, Korea Advanced Institute of Science and Technology, Daejeon 34141, Republic of Korea</aff></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9687-8093</contrib-id><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>Yoonjoo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CR1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9539-6532</contrib-id><name><surname>Stan</surname><given-names>Razvan C.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CR1">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="CR1">Corresponding authors: Yoonjoo Choi – Combinatorial Tumor Immunotherapy MRC, Chonnam National University Medical School, Hwasun 58128, Republic of Korea. <email>yoonjoo.choi@jnu.ac.kr</email>; Razvan C. Stan – Department of Basic Medical Science, Chonnam National University, Hwasun 58128, Republic of Korea. <email>strazvan@jnu.ac.kr</email>. Previous address: Cantacuzino Military-Medical Research and Development National Institute, Bucharest, Romania.</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted"><day>30</day><month>10</month><year>2022</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="preprint"><day>25</day><month>10</month><year>2022</year></pub-date><permissions><ali:free_to_read/><license><ali:license_ref>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is licensed under a <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">CC BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p id="P1">Fever is a typical symptom of most infectious diseases. While prolonged fever may be clinically undesirable, mild reversible fever (&lt; 39°C, 312K) can potentiate the immune responses against pathogens. Here, using molecular dynamics, we investigated the effect of febrile temperatures (38°C to 40 C, 311K to 313K) on the immune complexes formed by the SARS-CoV-2 spike protein with two neutralizing antibodies. We found that, at mild fever temperatures (311-312K), the binding affinities of the two antibodies improve when compared to the physiological body temperature (37°C, 310K). Furthermore, only at 312K, antibodies exert distinct mechanical effects on the receptor binding domains of the spike protein that may hinder SARS-CoV-2 infectivity. Enhanced antibody binding affinity may thus be obtained using appropriate temperature conditions.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>fever</kwd><kwd>monoclonal antibodies</kwd><kwd>SARS-CoV-2</kwd><kwd>Spike</kwd><kwd>binding affinity</kwd></kwd-group><kwd-group><title>Classification</title><kwd>Biophysics and computational biology</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><p id="P2">SARS-CoV-2 is a new coronavirus responsible for the ongoing pandemic of coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19). To gain entry into human cells, SARS-CoV-2 uses the transmembrane viral S glycoprotein (Spike) that protrudes from the viral surface and constitutes the main target of current vaccines [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref>]. On COVID-19 infection, fever is a main symptom and a key feature of the immune response [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">2</xref>]. Fever that accompanies COVID-19 is generally treated with the aim of eliminating it [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">3</xref>]. Recently, a study showed that at 313K (40°C). Spike attachment to ACE2 receptor is impaired [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">4</xref>]. It is unclear, however, what the role of fever may be on the formation of immune complexes. Here, we show that protein complexes formed between therapeutic antibodies and Spike proteins benefit from the effects of febrile temperatures. We chose two potent monoclonal antibodies (mAb), CV30 and S309, which are reported to neutralize SARS-CoV-2 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref>]. We indicate that at 312K (39C), the binding affinity of mAb towards Spike is highest when compared to 310K (37C, core body temperature), 311K (38C, mild fever) or 313K (40C, acute fever). Further, the detailed modes of the mechanisms of antibody neutralization under fever temperatures were uncovered: at 312K, CV30 “pulls away” the receptor binding domain (RBD<sub>1</sub>) off the Spike monomer it is bound to, from the RBD<sub>2</sub> and RBD<sub>3</sub> belonging to the other chains that do not contact the mAb. In so doing, CV30 exposes the RBD<sub>2,3</sub> to cell receptor binding or to further mAb attachment. In contrast, at 312K and at 313K, the S309 has the reverse role on Spike organization and in effect closes the trimer structure, rendering cell entry impossible. An overview of the dynamics between Spikes and these mAb at relevant temperatures is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>.</p><p id="P3">We established the center of mass (COM) for each of the three RBDs and determined the extent of translations with respect to each other, at fixed intervals of 0 ns, 250 ns and 500 ns, using the positions of COM of each RBD at 310K are used as references (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 1</xref>). For the CV30: Spike system, at 312K, the distances between RBD<sub>1</sub> (chain A) versus RBD<sub>2,3</sub> of chain B or chain C increase by 6.2Å and 20.1Å, respectively. For the S309: Spike complex, at 312 K, RBD<sub>1</sub> approaches RBD<sub>2</sub> by 10.6Å, while at 313K, the distance between same RBDs is reduced by 13.8Å. Further, to gauge the extent of the changes in position of each RBD with respect to itself, across all temperatures, we determined the shifts along their rotation axes, using the RBD positions at 310K as reference (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>).</p><p id="P4">At 312K, each RBD in the CV30: Spike complex exhibits the largest translation away against own positions at 310K, while the opposite situation is encountered for the RBDs from the S309: Spike immune protein complex at 312K and 313K. For either immune complex, the origins of these RBD movements within the Spike trimer are found in the presence of short β-strands (RBD<sub>1</sub> sequence residues 354-358, 452-455 and 492-494) that are connected by interstrands hydrogen bonds and help maintain a rigid binding interface with CV30 at 310, 311 and 313K. Conversely, at 312K, these secondary structures are lost and enhanced flexibility is gained that allows for the RBD<sub>1</sub> swing motions away from the other two RBDs (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Figure 1</xref>). While the same phenomenon occurs with the immune complex formed with S309, the presence of β-strands (at 310K and 311K) or their absence (at 312K and 313K) involves residues that are not part of RBD<sub>1</sub> (residues 312-319); additionally, more extended β-strands are comparatively found at 310K and 311K, that help maintain the position of RBD<sub>1</sub> with respect to other RBDs (residues 592-594, 661-663).</p><p id="P5">We quantified the extent of global structural changes across temperatures using the RMSD and Rg parameters (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Figure 2</xref>) as well as complex formation or dissociation between the mAb and the Spikes, using the Buried Surface Area (BSA) parameter (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>) and. For the CV30 bound to Spikes, BSA decreases by 18% at 312K, mirroring the movement away from the other RBDs, while it monotonically increases from 310K to 312K. In contrast, for the S309: Spike system, the increase in BSA is nonlinear with temperatures, peaking at 312K, in line with RBD<sub>1</sub> movement towards the other RBDs.</p><p id="P6">Next, we determine the extent of intra-monomer movements, using again BSA as a proxy for the formation of interfaces, as shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 2</xref>. While modest changes in BSA within the Spike monomers occur for the CV30: Spike complex (a 7% increase at 312K and at 313K with respect to 310K), a 21% peak increase at 312K versus 310K is present in the S309: Spike immune complex. Dissociation between the Spike monomers has two key roles for viral infectivity: to expose the fusion molecular machinery required for cell entry [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref>] and to promote RBD opening necessary for binding to cell entry receptor ACE2 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">8</xref>]. Fever modulation of increased intramonomer BSA may thus affect Spike stability, such that viral entry could be impaired.</p><p id="P7">In order to further quantify the strength in the binding affinity between the mAb and the RBD<sub>1</sub>, we estimate the changes in hydrogen bond formation across temperatures (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Figure 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 4</xref>) and further calculated the free binding energy, as shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">Table 3</xref>.</p><p id="P8">In agreement with the results presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Tables 1</xref>–<xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>, we measured an inverse relation between increasing temperatures and the binding energy of CV30 in complex with RBD<sub>1</sub>, peaking at 311K. In contrast, the highest affinity is present at 312K for S309 bound to RBD<sub>1</sub>, in line with the movements of this RBD within the Spike at various febrile temperatures.</p><p id="P9">To control the ongoing pandemic, it is imperative to modulate the fundamental dynamics of the SARS-CoV-2 Spike, as its motions are key to the infection machinery [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref>]. Despite the increasing interest in the use of fever as an adjuvant to therapy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>], temperature modulation of immune complex formation, has just recently been put investigated, but only at 313K [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref>]. Observational studies reported worse outcomes among COVID-19 patients having a lower body temperature (&lt;36°C, 309K) on admission, suggesting an impaired immune response [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref>]. We here present the first results wherein a range of febrile temperatures are shown to: (1) modulate domain movements in a viral protein and (2) increase mAb binding affinity against viral epitopes at particular fever values. In this study, antibodies bind directly to RBD, as with CV30 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref>], or away from RBD, as in the case of S309 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref>], revealing a possible allosteric effect of febrile temperatures in the formation of immune complexes. Fever is a beneficial [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref>] and conserved [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref>] reaction to acute infections. Temporarily maintaining a fever temperature in relevant patients may thus potentiate the role of antibodies in recognizing viral epitopes and in reducing viral infectivity.</p><sec id="S1" sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><p id="P10">The complex structure of SARS-CoV-2 spike and each antibody was obtained from the Protein Data Bank (PDB ID: 6VSB for Spike alone, 6WPS for S309 and 6XE1 for CV30). As the complex structure of CV30 was defined only using the receptor binding domain (RBD) of the spike protein, the spike bound state was modelled using Modeller. Simulations were performed using GROMACS 2020.2. Structures were pre-minimized using amber99sb forcefield with SPC/E explicit solvent model, equilibrated to each tested temperature (310-313 K) using NVT ensemble, followed by NPT ensemble equilibration. The production run was conducted for 500 nanoseconds (400 nanoseconds for Spike alone system) with 2 femtosecond time step and snapshots were taken every 10 picoseconds. The leapfrog integration method, V-rescale thermostat and Parrinello-Rahman barostat were used. LINCS constraints were applied to hydrogen bonds and long range interactions were included using Particle Mesh Ewald method. The changes in root-mean-square deviation (RMSD) of the whole complex, radius of gyration of the system, and the total solvent accessible surface area (SASA) vs. time were calculated using GROMACS. The preservation of the binding event was examined from the changes in BSA of receptor binding motif (Asn437-Tyr508). Binding free energy was computed using MM-PBSA method from designated snapshots. Center of mass for each RBD and RBD translational movements with respect to each other were calculated using Chimera and the Domain Rotation tool.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="SM"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1"><label>Supplementary Table 1</label><media xlink:href="EMS156372-supplement-Supplementary_Table_1.docx" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document" id="d86aAdJbB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD2"><label>Supplementary Table 2</label><media xlink:href="EMS156372-supplement-Supplementary_Table_2.docx" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document" id="d86aAdJcB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD3"><label>Supplementary Table 3</label><media xlink:href="EMS156372-supplement-Supplementary_Table_3.docx" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document" id="d86aAdJdB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD4"><label>Supplementary Table 4</label><media xlink:href="EMS156372-supplement-Supplementary_Table_4.docx" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document" id="d86aAdJeB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD5"><label>Supporting Information</label><media xlink:href="EMS156372-supplement-Supporting_Information.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" id="d86aAdJfB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack id="S2"><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>We thank Dr. Aura Precupas for the initial input on this manuscript. This work was funded by the Korean National Supercomputing Center (grant KSC-2020-CRE-0203). Y.C. was supported by National Research Foundation of Korea (NRF-2020M3A9G3080281 and NRF-2020R1A5A2031185). RSC was supported by Chonnam National University (grant 2022-2574) and by National Research Foundation of Korea (NRF-2021R1I1A2059587).</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="con" id="FN1"><p id="P11"><bold>Author Contributions:</bold></p><p id="P12">RSC conceived of the study. RSC and YC secured funding. DGK performed the experiments. RSC wrote the manuscript. DGK, HSK, YC revised the final draft.</p></fn><fn id="FN2" fn-type="conflict"><p id="P13"><bold>Declarations of interest</bold>: None.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><ref id="R1"><label>[1]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruan</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>SARS-CoV-2 Viral Load in Upper Respiratory Specimens of Infected Patients</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2020</year><volume>382</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>1177</fpage><lpage>1179</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>[2]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jamerson</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name><name><surname>Haryadi</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The use of ibuprofen to treat fever in COVID-19: A possible indirect association with worse outcome?</article-title><source>Med Hypotheses</source><year>2020</year><volume>144</volume><elocation-id>109880</elocation-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>[3]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rinott</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Kozer</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Shapira</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Bar-Haim</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Youngster</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ibuprofen use and clinical outcomes in COVID-19 patients</article-title><source>Clin Microbiol Infect</source><year>2020</year><volume>26</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>1259.e5</fpage><lpage>1259.e7</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>[4]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Ou</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Temperature dependence of the SARS-CoV-2 affinity to human ACE2 determines COVID-19 progression and clinical outcome</article-title><source>Comput Struct Biotechnol J</source><year>2021</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>161</fpage><lpage>167</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>[5]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hurlburt</surname><given-names>NK</given-names></name><name><surname>Seydoux</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Wan</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name><surname>Edara</surname><given-names>VV</given-names></name><name><surname>Stuart</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Suthar</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>McGuire</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name><surname>Stamatatos</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Pancera</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structural basis for potent neutralization of SARS-CoV-2 and role of antibody affinity maturation</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2020</year><volume>11</volume><issue>1</issue><elocation-id>5413</elocation-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>[6]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pinto</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Beltramello</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Walls</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Tortorici</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bianchi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Jaconi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Culap</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Zatta</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>De Marco</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Peter</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cross-neutralization of SARS-CoV-2 by a human monoclonal SARS-CoV antibody</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2020</year><volume>583</volume><issue>7815</issue><fpage>290</fpage><lpage>295</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>[7]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>SARS-CoV-2 spike-protein D614G mutation increases virion spike density and infectivity</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2020</year><volume>11</volume><elocation-id>6013</elocation-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>[8]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mansbach</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The SARS-CoV-2 spike variant D614G favors an open conformational state</article-title><source>Sci Adv</source><year>2021</year><volume>7</volume><elocation-id>eabf3671</elocation-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>[9]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Enhanced receptor binding of SARS-CoV-2 through networks of hydrogen-bonding and hydrophobic interactions</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2020</year><volume>117</volume><issue>25</issue><fpage>13967</fpage><lpage>13974</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>[10]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Habash</surname><given-names>RWY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Therapeutic hyperthermia</article-title><source>Handb Clin Neurol</source><year>2018</year><volume>157</volume><fpage>853</fpage><lpage>868</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>[11]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stan</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Françoso</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Alves</surname><given-names>RPS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferreira</surname><given-names>LCS</given-names></name><name><surname>Soares</surname><given-names>IS</given-names></name><name><surname>de Camargo</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Febrile temperatures increase in vitro antibody affinity for malarial and dengue antigens</article-title><source>PLoS Negl Trop Dis</source><year>2019</year><volume>13</volume><issue>4</issue><elocation-id>e0007239</elocation-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>[12]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tharakan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nomoto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Miyashita</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ishikawa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Body temperature correlates with mortality in COVID-19 patients</article-title><source>Crit Care</source><year>2020</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>298</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>[13]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tofan</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Lenghel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>de Camargo</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Stan</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fever as an evolutionary agent to select immune complexes interfaces</article-title><source>Immunogenetics</source><year>2022</year><month>May</month><day>11</day><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>10</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00251-022-01263-8</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>[14]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hasday</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Garrison</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antipyretic therapy in patients with sepsis</article-title><source>Clin Infect Dis</source><year>2000</year><volume>31</volume><issue>Suppl 5</issue><fpage>S234</fpage><lpage>41</lpage></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Snapshots taken after 500 ns of the Spike proteins in complexes with CV30 or with S309, at the indicated temperatures. Chain A (red cartoon) contains the RBD<sub>1</sub> that is solely bound to respective antibodies (shown as green ribbons). Chains B and C are colored in yellow or blue cartoons, respectively; RBDs are shown as surfaces. Arrows indicate the translational movements of RBD<sub>1</sub> at 312K or at 313K.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS156372-f001"/></fig><table-wrap id="T1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Translational shifts along the axes of rotations between the position of RBDs at 310 K and the positions of RBDs from the immune complexes under relevant febrile temperatures. The negative sign indicates translations away from the rotation axes.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="rows"><thead><tr><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="2" style="border-right: solid thin">Shift along axis of rotation (Å)</th><th align="center" valign="top" colspan="3" style="border-right: solid thin">CV30: Spike</th><th align="center" valign="top" colspan="3">S309: Spike</th></tr><tr><th align="center" valign="top" style="border-right: solid thin">311K</th><th align="center" valign="top" style="border-right: solid thin">312K</th><th align="center" valign="top" style="border-right: solid thin">313K</th><th align="center" valign="top" style="border-right: solid thin">311K</th><th align="center" valign="top" style="border-right: solid thin">312K</th><th align="center" valign="top">313K</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top">RBD<sub>1</sub> (0 ns)</td><td align="left" valign="top">+2.1</td><td align="left" valign="top">-1.1</td><td align="left" valign="top">-1.5</td><td align="left" valign="top">+0.2</td><td align="left" valign="top">+0.1</td><td align="left" valign="top">+0.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">RBD<sub>1</sub> (500 ns)</td><td align="left" valign="top">+13.4</td><td align="left" valign="top">-35</td><td align="left" valign="top">-5.8</td><td align="left" valign="top">+3.5</td><td align="left" valign="top">+16.4</td><td align="left" valign="top">+0.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">RBD<sub>2</sub> (0 ns)</td><td align="left" valign="top">-1.2</td><td align="left" valign="top">-0.3</td><td align="left" valign="top">-0.4</td><td align="left" valign="top">+0.2</td><td align="left" valign="top">-0.2</td><td align="left" valign="top">-0.04</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">RBD<sub>2</sub> (500 ns)</td><td align="left" valign="top">+20</td><td align="left" valign="top">-40</td><td align="left" valign="top">-13</td><td align="left" valign="top">+3.9</td><td align="left" valign="top">+14</td><td align="left" valign="top">+14</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">RBD<sub>3</sub> (0 ns)</td><td align="left" valign="top">+1</td><td align="left" valign="top">+0.6</td><td align="left" valign="top">+1.1</td><td align="left" valign="top">+0.2</td><td align="left" valign="top">-0.1</td><td align="left" valign="top">-0.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">RBD<sub>3</sub> (500 ns)</td><td align="left" valign="top">+15</td><td align="left" valign="top">-58</td><td align="left" valign="top">+15</td><td align="left" valign="top">+5.5</td><td align="left" valign="top">+16</td><td align="left" valign="top">+10.7</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Changes in BSA between the mAb and the Spike proteins throughout the simulations at the indicated temperatures. In brackets, percentage increase or decrease against values at 0 ns.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="rows"><thead><tr><th align="center" valign="top">BSA (Å<sup>2</sup>)</th><th align="center" valign="top">310K CV30: Spike</th><th align="center" valign="top">311K CV30: Spike</th><th align="center" valign="top">312K CV30: Spike</th><th align="center" valign="top">313K CV30: Spike</th><th align="center" valign="top">310K S309: Spike</th><th align="center" valign="top">311K S309: Spike</th><th align="center" valign="top">312K S309: Spike</th><th align="center" valign="top">313K S309: Spike</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center" valign="top">0 ns</td><td align="center" valign="top">1285</td><td align="center" valign="top">1296</td><td align="center" valign="top">1533</td><td align="center" valign="top">1313</td><td align="center" valign="top">1287</td><td align="center" valign="top">1078</td><td align="center" valign="top">1068</td><td align="center" valign="top">1327</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top">500 ns</td><td align="center" valign="top">1412 (+9%)</td><td align="center" valign="top">1480 (+14%)</td><td align="center" valign="top">1260 (-18%)</td><td align="center" valign="top">1679 (+27%)</td><td align="center" valign="top">1534 (+19%)</td><td align="center" valign="top">1510 (+40%)</td><td align="center" valign="top">1660 (+55%)</td><td align="center" valign="top">1936 (+45%)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T3" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Interaction energies between Spike and the two paratopes, at physiological and at febrile temperatures. In brackets, percentage increase or decrease with respect to the reference values at 310K. Standard deviations are approximately 10% for the CV30: RBD<sub>1</sub> complex and 15% for the S309:RBD<sub>1</sub> system, respectively. Values taken from structures obtained after 500 ns of simulations.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="all"><thead><tr><th align="center" valign="top">Binding Free Energy (kCal/mol)</th><th align="center" valign="top">310K</th><th align="center" valign="top">311K</th><th align="center" valign="top">312K</th><th align="center" valign="top">313K</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center" valign="top">CV30: RBD<sub>1</sub></td><td align="center" valign="top">-18.6</td><td align="center" valign="top">-24 (+29%)</td><td align="center" valign="top">-23 (+23%)</td><td align="center" valign="top">-19 (+2%)</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top">S309: RBD<sub>1</sub></td><td align="center" valign="top">-71</td><td align="center" valign="top">-59 (-17%)</td><td align="center" valign="top">-96 (+35%)</td><td align="center" valign="top">-88 (+23%)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></floats-group></article>