<!DOCTYPE article
 PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" article-type="preprint"><?all-math-mml yes?><?use-mml?><?origin ukpmcpa?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">bioRxiv</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>bioRxiv : the preprint server for biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub"/></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">EMS157446</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2022.11.21.517338</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="archive">PPR573872</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="europepmc-category"><subject>Covid-19</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Ultrasound treatment inhibits SARS-CoV-2 in vitro infectivity</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="short">Viral load decrease with Ultrasound exposition therapy</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Veras</surname><given-names>Flavio P.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CR1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Martins</surname><given-names>Ronaldo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A6">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Arruda</surname><given-names>Eurico</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A6">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cunha</surname><given-names>Fernando Q.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bruno</surname><given-names>Odemir M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">5</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CR1">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Center of Research in Inflammatory Diseases, Ribeirão Preto Medical School, University of São Paulo, Ribeirão Preto, São Paulo, Brazil</aff><aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Department of Pharmacology, Ribeirão Preto Medical School, University of São Paulo, Ribeirão Preto, São Paulo, Brazil</aff><aff id="A3"><label>3</label>School of Pharmaceutical Sciences of Ribeirao Preto, University of São Paulo, Ribeirão Preto, São Paulo, Brazil</aff><aff id="A4"><label>4</label>Institute of Mathematics and Computer Science, University of São Paulo, São Carlos, São Paulo, Brazil</aff><aff id="A5"><label>5</label>São Carlos Institute of Physics, University of São Paulo, São Carlos, São Paulo, Brazil</aff><aff id="A6"><label>6</label>Virology Research Center, Ribeirão Preto Medical School, University of São Paulo, Ribeirão Preto, São Paulo, Brazil</aff><author-notes><corresp id="CR1"><label>*</label>Correspondence should be addressed: Flavio P Veras; Center of Research in Inflammatory Diseases (CRID), Ribeirão Preto Medical School, University of São Paulo, Av. Bandeirantes; 14049-900, Ribeirao Preto, SP, Brazil; <email>fprotasio@usp.br</email> Odemir M. Bruno; São Carlos Institute of Physics, University of São Paulo, São Carlos, São Paulo, Brazil; Av. Trab. São Carlense, 400, São Carlos, SP, Brazil; 13566-590; <email>bruno@ifsc.usp.br</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted"><day>23</day><month>11</month><year>2022</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="preprint"><day>22</day><month>11</month><year>2022</year></pub-date><permissions><ali:free_to_read/><license><ali:license_ref>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is licensed under a <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">CC BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec id="S1"><title>Background</title><p id="P1">COVID-19 (coronavirus disease 2019) is a disease caused by infection with the severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2), affecting millions of people worldwide, with a high rate of deaths. The present study aims to evaluate ultrasound (US) as a physical method for virus inactivation.</p></sec><sec id="S2"><title>Materials and methods</title><p id="P2">The US-transductor was exposed to the SARS-CoV-2 viral solution for 30 minutes. Vero-E6 cells were infected with medium exposure or not with the US, using 3-12, 5-10, or 6-18MHz as frequencies applied. We performed confocal microscopy to determine virus infection and replicative process. Moreover, we detected the virus particles with a titration assay.</p></sec><sec id="S3"><title>Results</title><p id="P3">We observed an effective infection of SARS-CoV-2 Wuhan, Delta, and Gamma strains in comparison with mock, an uninfected experimental group. The US treatment was able to inhibit the Wuhan strain in all applied frequencies. Interestingly, 3-12 and 6-18MHz did not inhibit SARS-CoV-2 delta and gamma variants infection, on the other hand, 5-10MHz was able to abrogate infection and replication in all experimental conditions.</p></sec><sec id="S4"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="P4">These results show that SARS-CoV-2 is susceptible to US exposure at a specific frequency 5-10MHz and could be a novel tool for reducing the incidence of SARS-CoV-2 infection.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Ultrasound</kwd><kwd>SARS-CoV-2</kwd><kwd>virucidal effect</kwd><kwd>COVID-19</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="S5" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p id="P5">Critical situations and great challenges facing humanity historically tend to drive scientific advances. It was no different in the current pandemic. Since 2020, a large mobilization of scientists and public and private scientific entities has been observed, seeking to better understand the viruses and diseases caused by their infection in humans, as well as the solutions to the crisis, whether through treatment or vaccines, or even tests and sensors. Many works in different areas of science were proposed in areas as distant as biology, physics, medicine, engineering, computing, and others areas, focusing on solutions to face the problem.</p><p id="P6">Among different works, one of them caught our attention. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">Wierzbicki et al, in 2021</xref>, proposed the possibility of acoustic waves at the Ultrasound (US) frequency being able to damage and consequently neutralize the SARS-CoV-2 virus. The authors found high frequencies, between 100 and 500 MHz as possible resonance points of the virus carapace and its t-spike proteins. In a second work, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">Wierzbicki and Bai, in 2022</xref>, carried out a new theoretical study suggesting that frequencies, lower between 1 and 20 MHz, can also damage the SARS-CoV-2 spikes structures.</p><p id="P7">In this work, we carried out experiments to verify if the SARS-CoV-2 virus can be inactivated by resonance caused by sound waves at the US frequency. Although both theoretical works mention the physical possibility of ultrasound harmonics interacting with SARS-CoV-2 spike proteins, this has not yet been experimentally proven. In this work, in vitro experiments are carried out, the results of which validate previous theoretical works and strongly suggest that ultrasound can be used to neutralize SARS-CoV-2.</p></sec><sec id="S6" sec-type="materials | methods"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="S7"><title>Virus stock production</title><p id="P8">The SARS-CoV-2 parental Wuhan, SARS CoV-2 gamma (P1), and SARS CoV-2 delta variants were used for in vitro experiments, under strict biosafety level 3 (BSL3) conditions at the Ribeirao Preto Medical school (Ribeirao Preto, Brazil). Briefly, viral inoculum (1:100 ratio) was added to the Vero E6 cells, and the culture was incubated (48 h, 37 °C, 5% CO2 humidified atmosphere) in DMEM without FBS but supplemented with antibiotic/antimycotic mix (Penicillin 10,000 U/mL; Streptomycin 10,000 µg/mL; Sigma-Aldrich; cat. P4333) to optimize virus adsorption to the cells. After confirming the cytopathic effects of the viral replication over cell monolayer, cells were detached by scraping, harvested, and centrifuged (10000 ×g, 10 minutes, room temperature). The resulting supernatants were stored at -80 °C until use. SARS CoV-2 variants titration was assessed using standard limiting dilution to determine the 50% tissue culture infectious dose (TCID50).</p></sec><sec id="S8"><title>In vitro SARS-CoV-2 infection and US-exposure</title><p id="P9">Vero E6 cells were infected with SARS-CoV-2 before being exposed to 3-12, 5-10, or 6-18 MHz US frequencies from linear array transducers at room temperature for 30 minutes. An ultrasound high-resolution machine for routine images, MyLab 60 (Esaote) or Envisor (Philips), was used. Cells were infected at a multiplicity of infection (MOI) of 1.0 with infectious clone SARS-CoV-2 or mock with infection media for 24 hours to evaluate the infection and replication process by immunofluorescence and confocal microscopy. The productive viral particle was assessed by TCID50 assay. The treatment was performed in technical triplicate. The culture medium temperature was measured as a control using a thermal camera (FLIR One Pro, Flir).</p></sec><sec id="S9"><title>Immunostaining and confocal</title><p id="P10">For SARS-CoV-2 detection in vitro, Vero-E6 cells were plated in 24-well plates containing glass coverslips, fixed with PFA 4% at RT for 10 minutes, and blocked with 1% bovine serum albumin (BSA; Sigma-Aldrich; cat. A7906) and 22.52 mg/mL glycine (Sigma-Aldrich; cat. G8898) in PBST (Phosphate Buffer Saline + 0.1% Tween 20) at RT for 2 hours. The coverslips were stained with the following antibodies: rabbit anti-spike protein (Invitrogen; cat. 703959; 1:500) and mouse anti-dsRNA (J2; dsRNA, SCICONS English &amp; Scientific Consulting Kft., clone J2-1909, cat.10010200; 1:1,000). After this, samples were washed in PBS and incubated with secondary antibodies: alpaca anti-mouse IgG AlexaFluor 488 (Jackson ImmunoReseacher; Cat. 615-545-214; 1:1,000) and alpaca anti-rabbit IgG AlexaFluor 594 (Jackson ImmunoReseacher; Cat. 611-585-215; 1:1,000). Slides were then mounted using Vectashield Antifade Mounting Medium with DAPI (Vector Laboratories; cat. H-1200-10). Images were acquired by Axio Observer combined with an LSM 780 confocal microscope (Carl Zeiss) at 630X magnification at the same setup of zoomed and laser rate Images were acquired and analyzed using Fiji by Image J.</p></sec><sec id="S10"><title>Titration TCID50</title><p id="P11">To evaluate the effect of exposure to the US on SARS-CoV-2 infectivity, the virus stock was diluted 1:100 in each of the following: DMEM and/or US-exposed SARS-CoV-2. These two SARS-CoV-2 preparations were incubated for 1 min at room temperature, serially diluted 10-fold in DMEM, and then 100 µL of each dilution was inoculated in quadruplicate monolayers to determine the virus titer by TCID50 in Vero CCL-81 cells in 96-well plates.</p></sec><sec id="S11"><title>Statistics</title><p id="P12">Statistical significance was determined by one-way ANOVA followed by Bonferroni’s post hoc test. P&lt;0.05 was considered statistically significant. Statistical analyses and graph plots were performed and built with GraphPad Prism 9.3.1 software.</p></sec></sec><sec id="S12" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><p id="P13">The potential virucidal effects of US on SARS-CoV-2 were experimentally assessed for different frequencies and SARS-CoV-2 virus strains, such as delta and gamma variants. We exposed a solution containing SARS-CoV-2 particles with US-transductor for 30 minutes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1A</xref>). Then, we infected Vero-E6 cells with culture medium exposed or not with the US, using 3-12, 5-10, or 6-18MHz as frequencies applied. We performed immunofluorescence and confocal microscopy 24 hours post-infection to determine virus infection with staining for SARS-CoV-2 spike protein and double-stranded(ds) RNA (dsRNA), which indicates a replicative process. The US treatment was able to inhibit the Wuhan strain in 3-12, 5-10, and 6-18 MHz frequencies. The virucidal effect in delta or gamma variants was observed only in the 5-12MHz group. We did not observe a virucidal effect in 6-18MHz (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1B</xref>).</p><p id="P14">We next investigated whether the US exposition in SARS-CoV-2 can affect the number of productive SARS-CoV-2 particles. We observed an effective infection of SARS-CoV-2 Wuhan, delta, and gamma strains in comparison with mock, an uninfected experimental group (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>). In the Wuhan group, we observed the reduction of viral tilter at 3-12 and 5-10MHz (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2A</xref>). The 6-18MHz frequency did not inhibit the SARS-CoV-2 viral tilter (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>). Interestingly, the 3-12MHz frequency did not reduce SARS-CoV-2 delta and gamma strains. Using aesthetic ultrasound with 1-3 MHz, we did not observe an effect in neutralizing SARS-CoV-2 (Data not shown). In addition, the temperature of the culture medium did not alter upon US exposition (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Figure 1</xref>). These results show that SARS-CoV-2 is susceptible to US exposure at a specific frequency 5-10MHz and could be a novel tool for reducing the incidence of SARS-CoV-2 infection.</p></sec><sec id="S13" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p id="P15">The development of effective virus inactivation methods is of great importance to control their SARS-CoV-2 spread(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">Patterson et al., 2020</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">Rabenau et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">Darnell et al., 2004</xref>). This study investigated the effect of low-intensity US on the infectivity SARS-CoV-2 virus.</p><p id="P16"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">Wierzbicki et al, in 2021</xref>, proposed the possibility of acoustic waves at the US frequency being able to damage and consequently neutralize the SARS-CoV-2 virus (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">Wierzbicki et al., 2021</xref>). The study carried out was theoretical. The authors used finite element modeling and simulated the vibration interaction caused by ultrasound resonance with the virus. The work did not consider the propagation medium, and the authors found high frequencies between 100 and 500 MHz as possible resonance points of the virus carapace and its t-spike proteins. In a second work, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">Wierzbicki and Bai, in 2022</xref>, carried out a new theoretical study suggesting that frequencies, lower between 1 and 20 MHz, can also damage the α-helices and tropocollagen molecules of the SARS-CoV-2 spikes structures, consequently neutralizing the virus (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">Wierzbicki and Bai, 2022</xref>).</p><p id="P17">Frequencies of this magnitude would allow the use of US equipment for everyday use in medicine, properly regulated and safe for human use, in neutralizing SARS-CoV-2. Indeed, using US devices from medical diagnostics, we experimentally validate that lower frequencies can inhibit the infectivity of SARS-CoV-2. Interestingly, our results indicate a specific frequency rate of US exposition in an aqueous culture medium. We showed that 5-10 MHz was the most effective in reducing the SARS-CoV-2 viable particles, including the SARS-CoV-2 strains, gamma, and delta, compared with other used frequencies. Of note, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">Soto-Torres et al, in 2021</xref> showed no significant differences in abnormal fetal US and Doppler findings observed between pregnant women who were positive for SARS‐CoV‐2 and controls that indicated equipment safety in humans (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">Soto-Torres et al., 2021</xref>). The increase in temperature is related to the US exposition and elevated temperature inhibits SARS-CoV-2 replication (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">Ghoshal et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">Herder et al., 2021</xref>). We did not observe differences in the temperature of the culture medium during the US exposition. This result supports the specific virucidal effect of US treatment.</p><p id="P18">Further testing, using US-exposition to determine the microscopy-affected virus structure and different time points may help clarify the mechanisms involved, develop the optimal time for inactivation of SARS-CoV-2, and perform in vivo experiments with preclinical models.</p></sec><sec id="S14" sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="P19">It was clearly shown that lower frequencies of the US contribute to SARS-CoV-2 virus inactivation. In addition, influences on virus inactivation occurred in different applied energy ranges without the interference of temperature. In addition, this novel method could potentially be combined with existing physical, and chemical methods and antiviral agents.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="SM"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1"><label>Supplementary Figure</label><media xlink:href="EMS157446-supplement-Supplementary_Figure.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" id="d100aAdFbB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ref-list><ref id="R1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Darnell</surname><given-names>MER</given-names></name><name><surname>Subbarao</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Feinstone</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inactivation of the coronavirus that induces severe acute respiratory syndrome, SARS-CoV</article-title><source>J Virol Methods</source><year>2004</year><volume>121</volume><fpage>85</fpage><lpage>91</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7112912</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15350737</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jviromet.2004.06.006</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ghoshal</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Luchies</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Blue</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Oelze</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Temperature dependent ultrasonic characterization of biological media</article-title><source>J Acoust Soc Am</source><year>2011</year><volume>130</volume><elocation-id>2203</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3206913</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21973375</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1121/1.3626162</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Herder</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Dee</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Wojtus</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Epifano</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldfarb</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Rozario</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>da Silva Filipe</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Nomikou</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Nichols</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Jarrett</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Elevated temperature inhibits SARS-CoV-2 replication in respiratory epithelium independently of IFN-mediated innate immune defenses</article-title><source>PLoS Biol</source><year>2021</year><volume>19</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8765667</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34932557</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.3001065</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Patterson</surname><given-names>EI</given-names></name><name><surname>Prince</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name><name><surname>Casas-Sanchez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Cansado-Utrilla</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Solomon</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Griffiths</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Acosta-Serrano</surname><given-names>Á</given-names></name><name><surname>Turtle</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Methods of Inactivation of SARS-CoV-2 for Downstream Biological Assays</article-title><source>J Infect Dis</source><year>2020</year><volume>222</volume><fpage>1462</fpage><lpage>1467</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7529010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32798217</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/infdis/jiaa507</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rabenau</surname><given-names>HF</given-names></name><name><surname>Cinatl</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Morgenstern</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Bauer</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Preiser</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Doerr</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Stability and inactivation of SARS coronavirus</article-title><source>Med Microbiol Immunol</source><year>2005</year><volume>194</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7086689</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15118911</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00430-004-0219-0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Soto-Torres</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Hernandez-Andrade</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Huntley</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Mendez-Figueroa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Blackwell</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ultrasound and Doppler findings in pregnant women with SARS‐CoV‐2 infection</article-title><source>Ultrasound Obstet Gynecol</source><year>2021</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>111</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8251118</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33794060</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/uog.23642</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wierzbicki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Finite element modeling of α-helices and tropocollagen molecules referring to spike of SARS-CoV-2</article-title><source>Biophys J</source><year>2022</year><volume>121</volume><fpage>2353</fpage><lpage>2370</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9162829</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35598047</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bpj.2022.05.021</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wierzbicki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of receptors on the resonant and transient harmonic vibrations of Coronavirus</article-title><source>J Mech Phys Solids</source><year>2021</year><volume>150</volume><elocation-id>104369</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7890278</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33623172</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jmps.2021.104369</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>US treatment inhibits SARS-CoV-2 infection and replication</title><p><bold>(A)</bold> Representative model of US exposition. <bold>(B)</bold> Immunofluorescence analysis of Spike (green) and dsRNA (red) expression of SARS-CoV-2-infected Vero-E6 cells and treated with US. DAPI (blue) was used for nuclei staining. Scale bar indicates 50 µm. Data are representative of at least two independent experiments.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS157446-f001"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>US treatment reduces infectious SARS-CoV-2</title><p>Vero-E6 cells were treated with a US-treated medium for 30 min. Titration of infectious SARS-CoV-2 Wuhan strain (A), Delta strain (B) and Gamma (C) by TCID50 assay Data are representative of at least two independent experiments and are shown as mean ± SEM. P values were determined by one-way ANOVA Followed by Bonferroni’s post hoc test.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS157446-f002"/></fig></floats-group></article>