<!DOCTYPE article
 PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" article-type="preprint"><?all-math-mml yes?><?use-mml?><?origin ukpmcpa?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">bioRxiv</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>bioRxiv : the preprint server for biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub"/></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">EMS156212</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2022.10.20.513047</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="archive">PPR562540</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Birds multiplex spectral and temporal visual information via retinal On- and Off-channels</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Seifert</surname><given-names>Marvin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>Paul A</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kafetzis</surname><given-names>George</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Osorio</surname><given-names>Daniel</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Baden</surname><given-names>Tom</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1"><label>1</label>School of Life Sciences, University of Sussex, Brighton, UK</aff><aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Institute of Ophthalmic Research, University of Tübingen, Germany</aff><author-notes><corresp id="CR1">Correspondence: <email>m.seifert@sussex.ac.uk</email>, <email>d.osorio@sussex.ac.uk</email>, <email>t.baden@sussex.ac.uk</email>,</corresp><fn id="FN1"><p id="P1">Twitter: @MawaSeifert, @PAR_EyeMath, @Geor_Kafetzis, @NeuroFishh</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted"><day>27</day><month>10</month><year>2022</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="preprint"><day>21</day><month>10</month><year>2022</year></pub-date><permissions><ali:free_to_read/><license><ali:license_ref>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is licensed under a <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0 International license</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><title>Summary</title><p id="P2">Early retinal circuits divide incoming visual information into functionally opposite elementary signals: On and Off, transient and sustained, chromatic and achromatic. Together these signals can yield an efficient representation of the scene for transmission to the brain via the optic nerve. For example, primate On- and Off-parasol circuits are transient, while On- and Off-midget circuits are sustained. But this long-standing interpretation of retinal function is based on mammals, and it is unclear whether this functional arrangement is common to all vertebrates. Here we show that poultry chicks use a fundamentally different strategy to communicate information from the eye to the brain. Rather than using functionally opposite pairs of retinal output channels, chicks encode the polarity, timing, and spectral composition of visual stimuli in a highly correlated manner: fast achromatic information is encoded by Off-circuits, and slow chromatic information overwhelmingly by On-circuits. Moreover, most retinal output channels combine On- and Off-circuits to simultaneously encode, or multiplex, both achromatic and chromatic information.</p><p id="P3">Our results from birds conform to evidence from fish, amphibians, and reptiles which retain the full ancestral complement of four spectral types of cone photoreceptors. By contrast, mammals lost two of these cones early in their evolution, and we posit that this loss drove a radical simplification and reorganisation of retinal circuits, while birds and many other extant non-mammalian lineages retain the ancestral strategy for retinal image processing.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec id="S1" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p id="P4">Vertebrate retinal circuits process a stream of spatial, temporal, and spectral information into parallel channels for transmission to the brain<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref></sup>. The number of channels, what each channel encodes, and why, is a subject of active debate<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">2</xref></sup>, but some general principles have emerged<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">3</xref></sup>. For example, that to save energy, and to expand dynamic range, retinal circuits divide the visual signal into an approximately equal number of On- and Off-channels<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">4</xref></sup>, and into transient and sustained channels<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref></sup>. Information about polarity and kinetics is thereby represented by independent ‘elementary building blocks’ with decorrelated signals<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref></sup>. Similarly, wavelength information is efficiently funnelled into a subset of chromatic channels in parallel to the achromatic channels that dominate the retinal output<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref></sup>.</p><p id="P5">These long-standing principles are overwhelmingly based on research on mammals, such as mice, primates, cats, and rabbits, and evidence from non-mammalian species is beginning to question their generality. For example, zebrafish lack the approximately balanced representations of On- and Off-, and of transient and sustained channels of mammalian retinas<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref></sup>. Similarly, the profusion of colour-opponent responses in turtles<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref></sup>, or the heavy dominance of OnOff channels in salamanders<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref></sup>, do not easily map onto the current framework. Yet, a systematic overview of retinal functions is lacking for most non-mammalian lineages, and especially for birds<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref></sup>. This is in part due to the difficulty of recording from the <italic>ex-vivo</italic> bird retina<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">21</xref></sup>, where minor mechanical insult causes pathological waves of depression<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">22</xref></sup>. Consequently, to date insights into the operation of avian retinas are largely<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">23</xref></sup> restricted to non-invasive techniques such as electroretinograms<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">25</xref></sup>.</p><p id="P6">Working on the retina of poultry chicks<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref></sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1a-c</xref>) we have overcome these limitations by suppressing pathological signal spread during dissection (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplemental Figure 1</xref>). We can record light-driven spiking activity from neurons in the retina’s ganglion cell layer with a high-density multielectrode array (MEA) for several hours (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1d,e</xref>), and now present what to our knowledge is the first large-scale study of light-driven retinal function in a bird.</p><p id="P7">We find that unlike mammals<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">26</xref></sup>, chicks represent information about the polarity, kinetics, and wavelength in a highly correlated manner, with fast and achromatic Off-circuits, and slow and chromatic On-circuits. Moreover, most retinal outputs combine both On- and Off-circuits to simultaneously inform about both sets of information.</p></sec><sec id="S2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="S3"><title>Most recorded cells correspond to retinal ganglion cells</title><p id="P8">We recorded from n = 17 pieces of dorsal retina (n = 14 animals), yielding n = 3,987 spike sorted cells that passed a minimum response criterion (<xref ref-type="sec" rid="S18">Methods</xref>). To estimate what fraction of these cells stemmed from retinal ganglion cells (RGCs), which are the retina’s output neurons, rather than from displaced amacrine cells (dACs)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">3</xref></sup>, we computed the ‘electrical image’<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">20</xref></sup> (EI) for a subset of spike-sorted cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1f-l</xref>, <xref ref-type="sec" rid="S18">Methods</xref>, see also <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplemental Video S1</xref>). This image permits inferring (i) each cell’s spike initiation zone and soma, (ii) the trajectory of its axon, if present and well-attached (e.g. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1f</xref>), (iii) its conduction velocity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1g</xref>), and (iv) whether it displayed saltatory (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1h</xref>) or non-saltatory spike propagation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figures 1f,I, cf. Figure 1j</xref>). We reasoned that axon bearing cells projecting towards the optic disc were likely to be RGCs. In contrast, axon-less cells likely included dACs and any RGCs whose axons were not detected (e.g. because they were on the array-edge, or because their axon was far from the retinal surface). No EIs had multiple axons radiating from the centre, as for polyaxonal dACs in mammals<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27">27</xref></sup>. Accordingly, we took the fraction of EIs with a clear axon (<xref ref-type="sec" rid="S18">Methods</xref>) as the lower bound of RGCs. The reliability of axon-detection scaled with the number of available spikes before reaching an asymptote at ~87% (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1k</xref>), suggesting that at least 87% of recorded cells were RGCs. For these, we then quantified conduction velocities (<xref ref-type="sec" rid="S18">Methods</xref>), which in line with recent work<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">20</xref></sup> varied by a factor of more than four, from &lt;0.5 m/s for the slowest non-myelinated axons, to &gt;2 m/s for the fastest axons (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1l</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S4"><title>A large-scale functional survey of the avian retina</title><p id="P9">To begin understanding how the chick retina functions, we focussed on temporal and colour vision. Like most birds, the chick eye has seven<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">28</xref></sup> distinct types of photoreceptors (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1a-c</xref>). These include rods (RH1), the full complement of four ancestral<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">29</xref></sup>,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">30</xref></sup> single cones (SWS1, SWS2, RH2, LWS, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1a</xref>), and the principal and accessory members of the double cone (expressing LWS opsin).</p><p id="P10">We presented four complementary sets of widefield light-stimuli, which were chosen to characterise achromatic and spectral responses within a limited recording time, and allow direct comparison with other species<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref></sup>,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31">31</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33">33</xref></sup> (<xref ref-type="sec" rid="S18">Methods</xref>): <list list-type="simple" id="L1"><list-item><label>(i)</label><p id="P11">A series of ‘white steps’ (WS) from dark to light at different contrasts (2 s On, 2 s Off at 100-10% contrast; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1m</xref> showing 100% step).</p></list-item><list-item><label>(ii)</label><p id="P12">A corresponding series of full contrast ‘coloured steps’ (CS) from dark at different wavelengths. (630, 560, 505, 480, 420, 360 nm, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1n</xref> showing the first five, cf. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1b</xref>).</p></list-item><list-item><label>(iii)</label><p id="P13">A 100% contrast ‘white’ chirp stimulus, exponentially accelerating from 1-30 Hz over 30 s (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1o</xref>).</p></list-item><list-item><label>(iv)</label><p id="P14">A 20 minute 20 Hz pseudorandom sequence of ‘coloured’ noise (420, 480, 505, 630 nm) to compute spectral kernels, which correspond to the linear component of the impulse response<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34">34</xref></sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1p</xref>).</p></list-item></list>
</p><p id="P15">Because our multielectrode array is opaque, stimuli were presented from the photoreceptor side, by-passing the spectral filtering by oil droplets that occurs in the intact eye<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35">35</xref></sup>.</p><p id="P16"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figures 1m-p</xref> show responses of four individual cells to the stimuli, chosen to capture some of the diversity found. Cell 1 responded transiently to light offset (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1m</xref>), preferred long- over short-wavelengths (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1n</xref>), and had bandpass temporal tuning centred around 10 Hz (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1o</xref>). The cell’s spectral kernels were correspondingly narrow, indicating high-frequency temporal tuning, and confirmed the cell’s non-opponent long wavelength preference (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1p</xref>). Cells 2 and 3 were both OnOff cells but differed in their kinetics and spectral tuning. Cell 2 was On-sustained but Off-transient, with broad, low-pass tuning to temporal flicker, and its spectral kernels were colour opponent. Cell 3 had transient responses to light onset and offset with a preference for ‘white’ over ‘coloured’ light (compare <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figures 1m,n</xref>) and low-pass tuning to temporal flicker that did not respond above 5 Hz. Cell 4 responded transiently to light onset with little response to temporal flicker or to spectral noise (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figures 1o,p</xref>). Instead, it had selective spectral sensitivity to ‘red’- and ‘yellow’ wavelengths, alongside a relatively weak response to ‘white’ light (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figures 1m,n</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S5"><title>An interactive online data explorer of avian retinal ganglion cell functions</title><p id="P17">To identify major functional structures across the dataset we clustered responses to the four stimuli using a Mixture of Gaussian model, followed by manual curation (<xref ref-type="sec" rid="S18">Methods</xref>). This yielded n = 36 clusters, of which n = 22 had a minimum of 20 members and were retained for further analysis (n = 3,914 cells, 98.1%). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2a</xref> plots a representative selection of these clusters, while all 22 clusters are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Extended Data 1.</xref> The full dataset, including further analysis, is interactively plotted and available for download at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://chicken-data.retinal-functomics.net/">http://chicken-data.retinal-functomics.net/</ext-link>.</p><p id="P18">To what extent the 22 clusters correspond to anatomically and molecularly distinct types of RGCs and/or dACs is unknown. However, the 41 transcriptomically described RGC types in the adult chicken<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36">36</xref></sup> and a similar anatomical RGC diversity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref></sup> imply that some of our clusters comprise more than one type. Further probing the response space may well reveal additional functional diversity.</p><p id="P19">We now describe the basic complement of neural responses in the chick retina. For simplicity, and unless otherwise specified, analysis was performed on the cluster means. Cell-wise summaries of key indices are available in the interactive online data explorer.</p></sec><sec id="S6"><title>Response polarity, kinetics, and colour opponency are linked</title><p id="P20">We began by exploring the clusters’ light response properties based on the polarity (On, Off, OnOff) and kinetics (‘transient’ or ‘sustained’) of their ‘white’ step responses (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2b</xref>, <xref ref-type="sec" rid="S18">Methods</xref>). This revealed surprising trends. First, rather than forming segregated On- and Off-channels, most clusters responded both to light onset and offset. Second, polarity and kinetics were linked: Off-dominated clusters were transient, while On-dominated clusters were sustained. Third, analysis of the spectral kernels (<xref ref-type="sec" rid="S18">Methods</xref>) revealed that colour processing was also linked to polarity: Most OnOff clusters had large-amplitude colour opponent kernels, whereas most Off- or On-dominated clusters were non-opponent or had low-amplitude kernels (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2c</xref>). As subset of these latter clusters responded more strongly to ‘coloured’ steps than to the white steps that were used to define their polarity and transience (discussed below) we also computed these measures from their peak responses to the ‘coloured’ stimuli (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplemental Figure S2a</xref>). This allowed characterisation of On-dominated clusters as distinct transient and sustained groups.</p><p id="P21">Accordingly, our 22 clusters fell into four groups: <list list-type="simple" id="L2"><list-item><label>(i)</label><p id="P22">Off, transient, non-opponent (C<sub>1</sub>, n = 180 cells, 4.5%)</p></list-item><list-item><label>(ii)</label><p id="P23">OnOff, kinetically mixed, colour-opponent (C<sub>2-13</sub>, n = 2,688 cells, 67.4%)</p></list-item><list-item><label>(iii)</label><p id="P24">On, transient, non-opponent (C<sub>14-19</sub>, n = 784 cells, 19.7%)</p></list-item><list-item><label>(iv)</label><p id="P25">On, sustained, non-opponent (C<sub>19-22</sub>, n = 262 cells, 6.6%)</p></list-item></list>
</p><p id="P26">The cluster-means shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2a</xref> illustrate these groups, and their key differences (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplemental Figure 2b</xref> summarises how clusters and response groups are distributed across experimental sessions). The groups and their associated analysis are colour-coded in black, brown, orange, and grey, respectively (e.g. in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2b,c</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S7"><title>OnOff dominance as a hallmark of non-mammalian retinas?</title><p id="P27">To compare chick RGC responses to those of other vertebrates, we sourced widefield ‘white-step’ response datasets of RGCs from larval zebrafish<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref></sup>, mice<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37">37</xref></sup>, and humans<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38">38</xref></sup> and computed their corresponding distributions of polarity and transience (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2d-f</xref>, cf. <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplemental Figure 2c-f</xref>). This revealed similarities between the chick and zebrafish datasets, which systematically differed from the mammalian systems.</p><p id="P28">Chicks (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2a</xref>), and to a lesser extent zebrafish (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2d</xref>), feature a sizable complement of OnOff channels (see also <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplemental Figure 2c,e,f</xref>). OnOff channels are also dominant in salamanders<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref></sup> and turtles<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39">39</xref></sup>. In contrast, segregated On- and Off-channels predominate in mice and humans (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2e,f</xref>). Even the few well-described mammalian OnOff channels, such as the OnOff direction selective RGCs of mice or the small bistratified RGCs of primates, are dominated by either their On- or their Off-components when probed with ‘white’ steps of light. Second, the link between polarity and kinetics observed for chicks (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2a</xref>) was also a feature of the zebrafish dataset (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2d</xref>), but no such trend was detectable for mice or humans, whose RGCs occupy the full coding space encompassed by polarity and kinetics (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2e,f</xref>).</p><p id="P29">What might be the benefit for chicks, and perhaps also of other non-mammalian vertebrates, to have combined OnOff-channels, rather than segregated channels for encoding On- and Off-events? And why are polarity, kinetics, and colour opponency linked?</p><p id="P30">To address these questions, we now analyse each system in turn: Off-, On- and then OnOff. We find that Off-channels encode fast achromatic contrast, On-channels primarily deal with spectral information, while their combination into OnOff-channels simultaneously carries information about both achromatic and chromatic aspects of the visual stimulus.</p></sec><sec id="S8"><title>Off-circuits encode achromatic temporal contrast</title><p id="P31">No cluster yielded exclusively Off-responses, but the most Off-dominated cluster C<sub>1</sub> was distinctive as the only cluster having large amplitude kernels without appreciable colour opponency (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3a</xref>, cf. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2b</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Extended Data 1</xref>), and the fastest response, with centroids (<xref ref-type="sec" rid="S18">Methods</xref>) peaking above 5 Hz for red-, green- and cyan- components (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figures 3b,c</xref>). Correspondingly, the cluster’s chirp response (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3d, top</xref>) exhibited bandpass tuning that peaked around 10 Hz (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3e-f</xref>), and was phase locked to temporal flicker up to the maximum tested frequency of 30 Hz (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3g,h</xref>). Most other clusters had low pass tuning to the chirp stimulus and did not follow flicker above 5 Hz. The exception was C<sub>2</sub>, the second-most Off-biased transient cluster (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2b</xref>), which was allocated to the OnOff group due to its strong colour opponency (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2c</xref>). C<sub>2</sub> frequency tuning matched C<sub>1</sub>, as described by their spectral kernels (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3b,c</xref>), and for temporal flicker (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3d-g</xref>), but had a weaker preference for high- (4 - 14 Hz) over low- (&lt;2 Hz) frequencies (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplemental Figure 3a</xref>, cf. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3e</xref>) and weaker phase locking (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3g</xref>). Both C<sub>1,2</sub> had smaller On- than Off- responses to intensity steps.</p><p id="P32">Although C<sub>1,2</sub> were the two most Off-dominated clusters and had the fastest temporal tuning, their flicker responses were On- at low and Off- at high-frequencies (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3h</xref>). Importantly the same reversal of response polarity applied to all clusters with any phase locking (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplemental Figure 3b</xref>).</p><p id="P33">Thus, it appears that chicks use On- and Off-circuits to encode slow and fast temporal contrast respectively. Axonal conduction velocities of the four groups supported this conclusion: Off-RGCs were faster than OnOff-RGCs, which in turn were faster than On-RGCs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3i</xref>).</p><p id="P34">Beyond speed, Off-circuits had three properties suited to encoding achromatic intensity, exemplified by cluster C<sub>1</sub>. First, Off-responses had linear contrast-response functions to white steps (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3j</xref>). Second, their spectral tuning matched a log-sensitivity function of the LWS opsin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3k</xref>), which is expressed in red single cones and the double cone (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1b</xref>) – the latter having long been implicated in fast, achromatic vision<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40">40</xref></sup>. Third, key features of Off-responses were common to all clusters, namely their kinetics to white-steps (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplemental Figure 2d</xref>), their contrast-response functions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3l</xref>), and their spectral tunings (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3m</xref>). By comparison On-responses were diverse (cf. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>, discussed below).</p><p id="P35">Cluster C<sub>1</sub> and C<sub>2</sub>, which contain the chick’s rapid achromatic Off-circuits, comprised 4.6% and 2.8% of recorded cells respectively. By comparison, the functionally similar primate parasol cells comprise 10-16% of RGCs<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41">41</xref></sup>, while the types of alpha cells in mice make up about 5%<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31">31</xref></sup>,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42">42</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R44">44</xref></sup>. Unlike in chicks, these mammalian fast achromatic contrast systems have equal proportions of On- and Off-cells.</p></sec><sec id="S9"><title>On-circuits encode wavelength information</title><p id="P36">In contrast to the homogeneous, fast, and achromatic Off-circuits, On-circuits tended to be heterogeneous, slow, and spectrally nuanced. For example, On<sub>tr</sub>-cluster C<sub>18</sub> had a highly selective On-response to blue-light (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4a-c</xref>), while cluster C15 was selective for red-light (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4d-f</xref>). Both clusters were selective for coloured over white light with the peak response to the spectral stimuli exceeding the corresponding ‘white’ response. Both C<sub>15</sub> and C<sub>18</sub> lacked any overt sign of colour-opponency but their’ spectral tuning was narrower than those of the spectrally closest opsins (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4b,e</xref>), unlike the Off-cluster C<sub>1</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3k</xref>). The remaining three Ontr-clusters had similar properties to C<sub>15,18</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4c,f</xref>, C<sub>14,16,17</sub>). By contrast, the four On<sub>sus</sub>-clusters (C<sub>19-22</sub>, (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4g-i</xref>) has larger responses to white compared to coloured light (e.g. C<sub>20</sub> in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4g</xref>, cf. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Extended Data 1</xref> for C<sub>19,21,22</sub>), and their spectral tuning functions were broader than a single opsin in isolation.</p><p id="P37">To explore how On- and Off-responses encode wavelength information we computed two indices (<xref ref-type="sec" rid="S18">Methods</xref>): The spectral dominance index compares a cluster’s largest colour step response to its 100% white-step response, such that -1 and 1 indicate exclusive response to white and colour steps, respectively, while 0 indicates equal responses. Conversely, the spectral tuning index compares the width of a cluster’s spectral tuning function to that of its spectrally nearest log-opsin template, such that -1 and 1 respectively indicate infinitely narrow or broad tuning functions, while 0 indicates that the cluster’s tuning matches that of a single opsin. Together these two indices revealed systematic differences in how On- and Off-responses encode spectral information. For On-responses, spectral dominance and spectral tuning were strongly correlated, and spanned much of the possible coding space (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figures 4j</xref>, cf. <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplemental Figure S4a</xref>). In the lower left quadrant, the four On<sub>sus</sub> clusters exhibited spectrally broad and white-dominant responses, while in the upper right quadrant, several of the Ontr clusters had some of the most spectral-dominant and/or narrow responses. The remaining Off and OnOff clusters lie between these extremes. By contrast, Off-responses generally fell around the origin of both indices, indicating no preference for white or coloured light, and spectral tuning consistent with drive from a single opsin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4k</xref>, cf. <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplemental Figure S4b</xref>). Accordingly, On-circuits had spectrally distinct responses, while Off-circuits exhibited low spectral diversity. This difference was also illustrated by spectral tuning functions for On-responses (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4l</xref>) compared to the tunings of Off-responses (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3m</xref>). Moreover, most clusters had markedly sub-linear On- contrast-response functions to white light (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4m</xref>), rather than the more linear contrast-response functions of Off-circuits (cf. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3l</xref>). The On<sub>sus</sub> group was an exception to this rule, with supra-linear contrast-response functions.</p><p id="P38">Taken together, it therefore appears that the chick retina disproportionately leverages Off-circuits to encode rapid achromatic contrast (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>), and On-circuits to encode wavelength (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S10"><title>OnOff channels multiplex spectral and temporal information</title><p id="P39">Building on the foregoing observations, we asked what happens when the chick’s functionally distinct On- and Off-circuits are combined to form OnOff-channels. The combination might allow emergence of new functions but degrade one or both incoming messages. Alternatively, if On- and Off-signals remain partly decodable – for example in time – the new channel could encode aspects of both sets of incoming information. Such multiplexed signal transmission might allow efficient use of the optic nerve’s limited bandwidth, as in communications technology<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R45">45</xref></sup>.</p><p id="P40">Accordingly, we explored the possibility that OnOff-channels in the chick retina might be simultaneously informative about both spectral and temporal contrast (i.e. “colour” and “greyscale”).</p><p id="P41">Evidence for multiplexing comes from the spectral kernels of OnOff cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5a</xref>). The full kernels were colour opponent in all OnOff clusters (C<sub>2-13</sub>), but their opponency was usually time-dependent with the spectral kernels converging to a non-opponent Off-signal in the final ~100 ms preceding the spike. This effect is illustrated by cluster C<sub>7</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5a</xref>, fifth entry): at ~500 ms preceding the spike, the cluster is ‘red/green’-On ‘blue’-Off opponent (shaded in brown), but as the blue-kernel was monophasic (i.e. ‘slow’) and the red/green-kernels were biphasic (i.e. ‘fast’), all three converged to yield an achromatic late Off-period immediately preceding the spike (shaded in grey). Thus, cluster C<sub>7</sub> combines “colour” and “greyscale”-information, segregated in time.</p><p id="P42">To systematically quantify this property, we defined colour-opponent (+1) and non-opponent (-1) phases in each OnOff cluster’s spectral kernels (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5a</xref>, brown and grey shadings, respectively). We also normalised each cluster’s kernels in time (with “-1” and “0” indicating the timepoints where the kernels’ first exceed a minimum threshold amplitude, and the time of the spike, respectively). For all twelve OnOff clusters we then computed the mean±SD ‘opponency fraction’ over normalised time (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5b</xref>; 1 and - 1 on the y-axis denoting that all clusters were opponent or non-opponent, respectively, <xref ref-type="sec" rid="S18">Methods</xref>). This confirmed the systematic nature of the spectro-temporal responses: On average, spectral kernels were colour opponent over long time scales, but non-opponent over short time scales.</p><p id="P43">Even though OnOff clusters differed by nearly an order of magnitude in their overall kernel kinetics (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5a</xref>, cf. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Extended Data 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4b,c</xref>), within each cluster, kinetic order was stereotyped: Red-kernels tended to be the fastest, followed by green-, then cyan-, and finally blue. Accordingly, most OnOff clusters encoded a similar spectral hierarchy over different time-scales. Clusters C<sub>2-4</sub> were fast at all four wavelengths, C<sub>5,6</sub> intermediate and C<sub>7-12</sub> were remarkably slow. The achromatic and strongly Off-dominated cluster C<sub>1</sub> fitted the fast extreme of this pattern, as the fast non-opponent fraction of the kernel was retained but the slow opponent fraction lost (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Extended Data 1</xref>). Overall, the analysis of spectral kernels suggests that OnOff channels simultaneously encode slow spectral and fast achromatic information, with the two sets of features being segregated, and thus decodable, by their relative timings.</p></sec><sec id="S11"><title>“Time-dependent opponency” in OnOff channels emerges from differential spectral integration across On- and Off-circuits</title><p id="P44">We next asked how these time-wavelength features might relate to the properties of the On- and Off-circuits in isolation. To this end, we analysed the OnOff clusters’ On- and Off-responses to ‘white’ and ‘coloured’ steps of light (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5c-f</xref>). In line with corresponding observations at the level of the kernels, this revealed a systematic wavelength-dependence of clusters’ step responses: For both On- and Off-transitions, the largest amplitudes tended to occur for red, followed in turn by yellow, green, and cyan. For of the Off-channel, this trend extended to blue, while for On, blue-responses tended to be larger than cyan responses. Together, these spectral responses accounted for the previously observed biphasic and monophasic spectral tuning functions of the On- and Off-channel, respectively (On: <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4l</xref>, Off: <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3m</xref>).</p><p id="P45">Step responses differed in their latencies as well as their amplitudes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5c,d</xref>). For example, red responses tended to be large, with short latencies, while cyan responses were smaller and delayed. An inverse link between response amplitude and latency is expected, but the variance across these two parameters was sometimes substantial. For example, the latencies of red- and green-On responses of cluster C6 differed by more than 60 milliseconds (red: 104 ms, green: 167 ms) despite their almost identical slopes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5c</xref>, fourth entry). By comparison, the On-response to the 100% white step was intermediate at 110 ms. In fact, within the On-channel, the latencies of red-responses tended to be slightly below those of the corresponding 100% contrast white step responses. Conversely, in the Off channel the white response was generally dominant (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5d</xref>).</p><p id="P46">To explore if and how these types of amplitude and kinetic differences might encode stimulus wavelength and/or intensity, we quantified the OnOff clusters’ ‘colour’ and ‘white’ step-response amplitudes and latencies and normalised each relative to their respective red-response. (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5e,f</xref>). This revealed that for the On-, but not for the Off-channel, the combination of these two simple metrics alone sufficed to substantially disentangle wavelength from intensity information. Red-responses were systematically faster than white-responses, allowing their detection by latency alone (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5e</xref>), whereas, green- and blue-, but not cyan- or yellow-, could be distinguished from the ‘white’ contrast series by their long latencies, despite their large amplitudes. While white-responses increased in latency while dropping in amplitude with decreasing contrast, blue- and green-On responses had almost equal amplitudes to red-responses but a nearly two-fold greater latency. In contrast, the Off-responses to ‘coloured’ and ‘white’-steps had similar amplitudes and latencies, precluding their differentiation by these metrics (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5f</xref>).</p><p id="P47">Beyond amplitude and latency, step responses of the OnOff cells differed in their overall temporal envelopes. Accordingly, to capture amplitude and kinetic differences across ‘coloured’ and ‘white’-step responses we used Principal Component Analysis (PCA). We first averaged step responses to all red-, yellow-, green-, cyan- and blue- step as well as to the 100, 80, 60, 40 and 20% contrast steps (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5g,h</xref>, top), which as expected reproduced the amplitude and kinetic features discussed previously. From these averages, we performed PCA separately on On- and Off-responses, both of which yielded a relatively slow first component followed by a faster second component that together captured &gt;99% of the total variance (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5g,h</xref>, middle). We then projected each response’s loading onto these two components (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5g,h</xref>, bottom). As predicted from our analysis of amplitudes and latencies alone (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5e,f</xref>), this highlighted systematic differences in the encoding of ‘coloured’ versus ‘white’ stimuli for the On-channel, but a common encoding scheme for the Off-channel. For On-responses, the white contrast series was almost completely captured by the first principal component, while colour steps exhibited an approximately fixed loading onto PC1 but wavelength-dependent differences onto PC2. As expected, for Off-responses colour and white steps followed essentially the same trajectory in PC-space.</p><p id="P48">Finally, to establish the generality of this encoding strategy, we performed PCA separately for a subset of individual OnOff-clusters (C<sub>3-8</sub>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5i,j</xref>). In each case, ensuring a common polarity of the first two components (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5i,j</xref>, top), we normalised the loadings onto the two PCs between -1 and 1 to enable side-by-side comparison (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5i,j</xref>, bottom). By and large, this strategy recapitulated the same distribution of loadings in PC space across coloured and white steps. White-On responses mostly followed PC1 with generally only weak loadings onto PC2, while conversely, red-, yellow, green- and blue-On-responses required a relatively fixed loading onto PC1 but systematically distinct loadings onto PC2. In contrast, as before, coloured, and white Off-responses followed a common, intermixed trajectory.</p><p id="P49">Taken together, we conclude that in the chick retina, and perhaps also in some other non-mammalian species, On- and Off-channels predominately encode slow-spectral and fast-achromatic information, respectively, while a majority of OnOff-channels simultaneously capture both types of information.</p></sec></sec><sec id="S12" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p id="P50">We have shown that the spiking output from the chick retina comprises multiple kinetically and spectrally diverse OnOff-channels, alongside sparser populations of fast achromatic Off-, and slow chromatic On-channels. These correlations between polarity, kinetics, and wavelength selectivity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2a-c</xref>) imply that there is a general organising principle in this avian retina, where Off- and On-channels represent fundamentally different aspects of the visual scene namely: time and colour.</p><sec id="S13"><title>Pathway splitting in non-mammalian retinas</title><p id="P51">The division of the visual signal into On- and Off-pathways at the retina’s first synapse is a fundamental and ancient<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R46">46</xref></sup> feature of vertebrate vision<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">4</xref></sup>. The division reduces energy requirements and increases the dynamic range<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R47">47</xref></sup> so it is not surprising that sensory systems should balance On- and Off-channels, as exemplified in mammal RGCs<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">2</xref></sup> (cf. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2d-f</xref>). Well-segregated and coordinated On- and Off-channels also emerge <italic>de novo</italic> in retina-inspired computational models aiming to capture as much information as possible from natural scenes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R48">48</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R49">49</xref></sup>. Why, then, do chicks not comply with this arrangement?</p><p id="P52">One partial explanation might be that beyond efficient use of neural bandwidth and energy, other aspects of visual processing benefit from combining On- and Off-signals. Specifically, encoding wavelength independent of intensity, which is an essential feature of colour vison, requires opponency between spectrally distinct On- and Off-inputs<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">28</xref></sup>. One example of an OnOff chromatic opponent channel is the primate small bistratified RGC<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R50">50</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R51">51</xref></sup>, which has two notable parallels to the multiple colour opponent OnOff cells of chicks. First, as in chicks, the Off-circuit is driven by LWS cones, and second, the blue On- and yellow Off-circuits have different time-courses: On is slow, but Off is fast<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R50">50</xref></sup>. In primates, this feature is probably inherited from corresponding kinetic differences between SWS1 and LWS cones<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R52">52</xref></sup>. It is unknown if also in chicks the different spectral photoreceptors have systematically different kinetics – but if they do, it might partly account for the correspondingly systematic kinetic differences in spectral kernels observed at the level of RGCs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5a</xref>).</p><p id="P53">Nevertheless, with ~67% of all recorded cells, the numerical abundance of chick colour-opponent OnOff RGCs is superficially at odds with efficient coding theory<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R53">53</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R55">55</xref></sup>. Spectral variance makes up only a small fraction of information in natural scenes, which are dominated by achromatic contrasts<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref></sup>. Correspondingly<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R53">53</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R55">55</xref></sup>, visual systems including our own are thought to prioritise the encoding of intensity rather than wavelength<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R56">56</xref></sup>. This implies that beyond wavelength, OnOff RGCs in chicks might encode other aspects of the visual scene, such as time: while the spectral and kinetic order of OnOff clusters’ kernels was remarkably consistent (from ‘red and fast’, to ‘blue and slow’), the overall response kinetics of these clusters varied by more than a log unit in speed. The different OnOff clusters therefore systematically encoded similar sets of spectral and kinetic contrasts, but for a rage of temporal regimes.</p><p id="P54">To what extent these considerations will stand the scrutiny of systematic computational exploration will be important to explore in the future. It will then also be key to establish whether and how such a system might be extendable to the encoding of space. Based on long-standing work on the retinal output of mammals<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R57">57</xref></sup>, a central prediction would be that the slow and fast cells should correspondingly encode small and large-scale spatial features, respectively.</p></sec><sec id="S14"><title>Why are chick and mammal retinas so different?</title><p id="P55">The systematic functional differences in the retinal organisation of chicks, and perhaps of other vertebrate lineages, from that of mammals (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>) implies that different clades have evolved divergent strategies for communicating visual information from the eye to the brain (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>). Exploring these differences, their computational consequences, and how they may have come about, will be important in the future, but for now it may be useful to posit one possible avenue of exploration; namely that birds, reptiles, amphibians, and fish differ from mammals in their complements of photoreceptors (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6a</xref>). While some lineages in each of the former clades retain the full complement of four ancestral single cones<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R58">58</xref></sup> – often elaborating them in various ways – early mammals lost their SWS2 and RH2 cones<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">29</xref></sup>, so that typical mammalian retinas are driven by two cone inputs, but many non-mammalian retinas are driven by four or more.</p><p id="P56">This systematic difference in inputs may lead to different retinal processing challenges. Perhaps the complex interplay of time and wavelength coding in the chick is a consequence of their relatively complex input system that is carried over from ancestral vertebrates, while the loss of two cones more than 200 million years ago, alongside – presumably - freeing up a substantial diversity of now disused inner retinal circuits, left mammals with an opportunity to evolve new, powerful processing strategies that were previously precluded.</p><p id="P57">In support, mammalian retinas also differ from those of birds, reptiles, amphibians, and fish in other ways (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6b</xref>). For example, their neuronal density is substantially lower<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">26</xref></sup> (with the exception of salamanders<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref></sup>, but not frogs<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R59">59</xref></sup>). The only other major vertebrate lineage with consistently low cellular density retinas are elasmobranchs<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R60">60</xref></sup> (sharks, rays, and skates), which, like mammals, have lost two or more of the four ancestral cones<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">28</xref></sup>. Mammals<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43">43</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R61">61</xref></sup> and elasmobranchs<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R62">62</xref></sup> are also unusual among vertebrates in that most of their bipolar cells and RGCs are mono- or at most bistratified, rather than routinely multistratified as is the case in birds<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R63">63</xref></sup>, reptiles<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R64">64</xref></sup>, amphibians<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R65">65</xref></sup>, and fish<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R66">66</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R67">67</xref></sup>. In view of the well-documented links between inner retinal depth, response polarity, and kinetics<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R68">68</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R69">69</xref></sup>, these anatomical differences may directly feed into the observed functional differences. Future functional exploration of other vertebrate retinas, especially those that like mammals have lost a subset of their original photoreceptor complement, may be instructive.</p></sec><sec id="S15"><title>The avian double cone as the input to the fast, achromatic Off-circuit?</title><p id="P58">Bird and reptile eyes are unique having ‘double cones’ that are distinct from the full complement of ancestral single cones<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40">40</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R63">63</xref></sup>. Double cones are made up of two tightly associated cells: a principal and an accessory member, which are independently wired into outer retinal circuits<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R63">63</xref></sup>. Both members express the same ‘red’ LWS opsin that is also found in the ancestral LWS single cones. However, unlike LWS single cones of other species, which are generally associated with achromatic processing<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">30</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33">33</xref></sup>, direct recordings from either member of avian double cones have not been achieved, leaving insights as to their functions speculative<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R70">70</xref></sup>. In general, their numerical abundance in the periphery<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R71">71</xref></sup>, but absence from the fovea<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R72">72</xref></sup>, hints at a key role in finely resolved temporal rather than spatial processing<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R73">73</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R74">74</xref></sup>.</p><p id="P59">In chick, the only robust responses to fast achromatic flicker occurred in the Off channel, whose spectral tuning was consistent with near-exclusive drive from an LWS-expressing photoreceptor system (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>). The simplest explanation for these observations is that the chick’s rapid and achromatic Off-circuits are driven by either or both members of the double cone, and/or the red-single cone. In tentative agreement, at least two anatomical types of chick bipolar cells receive exclusive direct input from the principal member of double cones alongside inputs from rods<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R63">63</xref></sup>. Both these cells stratify in the upper to middle fraction of the inner retina which is generally associated with Off-dominated processing<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref></sup>. Our data therefore lends further credence to the idea that the avian double-cone system might support fast, achromatic vision<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40">40</xref></sup>, and add the perhaps surprising notion that this signal appears to be exclusively carried by Off-circuits.</p></sec><sec id="S16"><title>On for ‘colour’, Off as a common reference</title><p id="P60">To distinguish wavelength from intensity, circuits for colour vision use colour opponency as their fundamental ‘currency’<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">28</xref></sup>. However, beyond a basic requirement of combining spectrally distinct On-and Off-signals, there are many options to build an opponent circuit. A short-wavelength On-pathway could be combined with a long-wavelength Off-pathway, but it is equally plausible to do the reverse, i.e. to combine short-Off with long-On. And yet, overwhelmingly, vertebrate circuits for colour vision, including in mammals, appear to favour the former<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32">32</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R75">75</xref></sup>. Second, when more than one colour opponent axis is established, the second axis could either oppose two entirely new wavelength ranges, or it could reuse one of the two signals from the first axis. Here, the spectral heterogeneity of the On-channels (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>), but homogeneity of the Off-channels (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>), suggests that chicks do the latter: They systematically oppose their spectrally diverse On-signals to a common, LWS-driven Off reference. Similarly, the zebrafish brain appears to be dominated by spectrally narrow and diverse On-signals, but spectrally homogenous, broad and LWS-shaped Off-signals<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="S17"><title>Cortex-like hue-coding in the avian retina?</title><p id="P61">Despite lacking overt signs of colour opponency, many cells were ‘spectrally selective’ in that they exhibited sharper-than-opsin spectral tuning and a preference for spectrally narrow over ‘white’ light (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>). Sharper-than-opsin tuning can, in principle, be achieved by rectification of a spectrally broader, non-opponent drive. However, in that case the cell would nevertheless be expected to respond strongly to ‘white’ stimulation, which was not the case for many of the spectrally narrow clusters (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4j</xref>). Alternatively, narrow tuning could be built by rectifying an already opponent input. For example, a hypothetical RGC rectifying an incoming drive from a colour opponent BC<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R69">69</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R76">76</xref></sup> such that only the On-lobe of the opponency persists could readily account for the profusion of ‘colour-selective’ On-RGCs in our dataset. Neurons with similar properties have long been discussed as part of the colour vision machinery of the primate cortex, where they are usually referred to as hue-selective<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R77">77</xref></sup>. Similarly, narrower-than-opsin On-responses also exist in the zebrafish tectum<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R78">78</xref></sup> and in the mushroom bodies of butterflies<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R79">79</xref></sup>. To our knowledge, they have not been described in a vertebrate retina.</p></sec></sec><sec id="S18" sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec id="S19"><title>Lead Contact</title><p id="P62">Further information and requests for resources and reagents should be directed to and will be fulfilled by the Lead Contact, Tom Baden (<email>t.baden@sussex.ac.uk</email>).</p></sec><sec id="S20"><title>Materials Availability</title><p id="P63">No unique materials were generated as part of this study.</p></sec></sec><sec id="S21"><title>Experimental Model And Subject Details</title><sec id="S22"><title>Animals</title><p id="P64">All procedures were performed in accordance with the UK Animals (Scientific Procedures) act 1986 and approved by the animal welfare committee of the University of Sussex. Male chicks, breed Shaver Brown, aged between 1 and 14-days post hatching were obtained from Joice and Hill (part of Hendrix Genetics, Peterborough, UK) and kept in a specifically designed cage in the university’s animal facility. Food (chick crumb) was provided ad libitum and elements for facilitating play behaviour were provided. Chicks were kept on a 12h:12h light:dark cycle, and never kept in isolation for prolonged periods of time.</p></sec><sec id="S23"><title>Ringer solution</title><p id="P65">Ringer solution for the experiment was based on Ref<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R80">80</xref></sup>, calibrated to 0.331 osmol. In moles per l: 0.1 NaCl, 0.006 KCl, 0.002 MgSO<sub>4</sub>, 0.001 CaCl<sub>2</sub>, 0.03 NHCO<sub>3</sub>, 0.001 NaH2PO<sub>4</sub>, 0.05 sucrose. Two litres of ringer solution were freshly prepared for each experiment. The solution was bubbled with carboxygen (95% O<sub>2</sub> / 5% CO<sub>2</sub>) for at least one hour before experiments and heated to 37°C. A second batch of the same ringer solution, however with added 0.4 mM MgSO<sub>4</sub>, was prepared for dissection.</p></sec><sec id="S24"><title>Enucleation and dissection</title><p id="P66">Chicks were dark adapted for at least 12 hours overnight. In total darkness using infrared goggles, chicks were sacrificed by cervical dislocation followed cutting of the aorta. Eyes were enucleated by first cutting the eyelid around the cornea, followed by a single anterior leading cut between eyes and beak. Using curved forceps (FST 11652-10, FST Heidelberg, Germany), the eyes were then lifted, and the optic nerve was cut using scissors with a partially blunt tip (FST 14083-08). In the following the remaining muscle tissue around the eyes were removed and lifted from the skull. The eyes were cut two times proximal to the edge of the cornea using pointed scissors (FST 15017-10) and transferred into two bottles containing preheated, high-magnesium oxygenated ringer solution at 37°C. The bottles were light sealed. Eyes were transferred to the experimental site for retinal dissection. Total time for the above was ~15 min. Dissection followed procedures detailed in Ref<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R80">80</xref></sup>. However, all steps were performed under infrared light using night vision googles (PSV-14, ACT in Black, Luxembourg), and in a high-magnesium dissection ringer solution. The following steps were performed in a petri dish unless otherwise stated: <list list-type="order" id="L3"><list-item><p id="P67">Removal of the cornea from the eyeball with as few cuts around the horizon as possible (FST 15017-10).</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P68">Cutting the eyeball along the dorsal – ventral axis using two cuts from opposite sides.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P69">Removing the vitreous from the eyeball using forceps.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P70">Cutting a ~4x4 mm piece out of the central area of the dorsal hemisphere.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P71">Transfer of this piece onto a filter paper, with the RGCs facing the filter paper and the remaining sclera facing up.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P72">The filter paper and tissue were then transferred onto a kitchen roll paper to draw solution, which flattened the tissue and aided attachment to the filter paper.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P73">The remaining sclera, choroid and retinal pigment epithelium were removed from the retina by using forceps to peel those layers off the retina, which remained attached to the filter paper.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P74">The filter paper and retina were transferred back to the petri dish.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P75">The retina was removed from the filter paper using forceps.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P76">A smaller, about 2.5 mm<sup>2</sup> piece was cut. The retina would commonly get folded at a few places during step 6 due to flatting of what normally is a curved tissue. In this step, an area without folds was chosen. Folded parts of the retina were avoided even if this resulted in smaller preparation. In addition, corners in the tissue were rounded off since these sites tended to trigger the degenerative waves.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P77">The retina was transferred to the MEA chamber using a spoon. The tissue was guided onto the spoon using forceps and was continuously guided while being on the spoon to avoid strong movement of the tissue during transfer.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P78">In the MEA chamber the corners of the tissue were cut. This was done, to remove parts of the tissue that had been damaged by the forceps during tissue guiding steps.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P79">The tissue was placed onto the electrode array with a fine paintbrush.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P80">The MEA chamber was dried using kitchen roll to suck out the ringer solution. As soon as the tissue was exposed to the air new ringer solution was added directly on top of the tissue. This would normally attach the tissue to the MEA.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P81">The MEA chamber was connected to the head stage.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P82">The tissue was left to further attach to the MEA for ~ 30 minutes.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P83">The tissue was perfused throughout the experiment using the low magnesium-ringer solution. The MEA chamber was heated to 37°C and the perfusion solution was preheated inline to the same temperature.</p></list-item></list>
</p></sec></sec><sec id="S25"><title>Method Details</title><sec id="S26"><title>Light Stimulation</title><p id="P84">Since our multielectrode array was opaque, all light stimuli were delivered from the photoreceptor side by a combination of two custom-modified 3-channel light projection engines (“Lightcrafters”) that together were driven with six spectral LEDs (UV: 360 nm, LED365-06Z, 20 nW; Blue, B: 420 nm, ROHS 247-1757, 65 nW; Cyan, C: 480 nm, ROHS 810-0492, 60 nW; Green, G: 505 nm, RoHS 769-3551, 65 nW; Yellow, Y: 560 nm, RoHS 247-1735, 59 nW; Red, R: 630 nm, RoHS 904-7367, 100 nW) as described previously<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R81">81</xref></sup>. All stimuli used in this study were applied as widefield, exceeding the active area of the multielectrode array (2.67 mm<sup>2</sup>). The framerates of the stimulators were 60 Hz. LEDs 420 nm – 630 nm were bandpass filtered using Edmund Optics’ 65-137, 65-145, 34-506, 88-011, 65-166 and combined using Chroma Optics beam splitters: NC474265, AT455DC, T550lpxr and T600lpxr. Four types of full-field stimuli were used: (i) flashes of light with all 6 LEDs driven together, at ten different contrast levels (‘white steps’ WS, 100-10%, 2 s On, 2 s Off), (ii) flashes of light at each of the six wavelengths individually (‘colour steps’, CS, 2 s On, 2 s Off), (ii) a 100% contrast white’ chirp stimulus<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R68">68</xref></sup> (exponentially accelerating from 1-30 Hz over 30 s), and (iv) a binary dense and spectrally flat white noise, in which four of the six LEDs (R, G, C, B) were flickered independently in a known binary M-sequence at 20 Hz for 20 minutes. This allowed us to estimate spike-triggered averages (STA) per LED and cell, hereafter referred to as spectral kernels (SK, below).</p></sec><sec id="S27"><title>Multielectrode array recordings</title><p id="P85">MEA recordings were performed on a BIOCAM X platform produced by 3Brain AG, Wädenswil, Switzerland. The chip was Arena HD-MEA. It consists of 4,096 electrodes in a 2.67 × 2.67 mm square area (64*64 21 μm electrodes with 42 μm interelectrode spacing. The chamber above the array is 7 mm deep and 25 mm in diameter. The software for data acquisition was Brainwave 4. It was run on a bespoke PC provided as part of the MEA by 3Brain. The integration time was set to medium, resulting in a sampling frequency of ~18 kHz.</p></sec><sec id="S28"><title>Data analysis</title><p id="P86">Data analysis was performed using custom written Python (v. 3.9.5, Python Software Foundation, Wilmington, Delaware, USA) scripts executed in JuypterLab, IGOR Pro 6.3 (Wavemetrics), Fiji (NIH) and Matlab R2019b / R2020b (Mathworks).</p></sec><sec id="S29"><title>Spike sorting</title><p id="P87">Herding Spikes 2 (HS2) algorithm<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R82">82</xref></sup> was used for spike sorting. HS2 uses a combination of spike location and spike shapes information and performs a mean shift clustering approach to separate spikes coming from different cells. The following parameters were used: clustering_bandwidth: 8; clustering_alpha: 5.5; clustering_n_jobs: -1; clustering_bin_seeding: True; clustering_min_bin_freq: 16; clustering_subset: None; left_cutout_time: 0.3; right_cutout_time: 0.3; detect_threshold: 5; probe_masked_channels: []; probe_inner_radius: 70; probe_neigbor_radius: 90; probe_event_length: 0.26; probe_peak_jitter: 0.2; num_com_centers: 1; maa: 12; ahpthr: 11; out_file_name: HS2_sorted.hdf5; decay_filtering: False; save_all: False; amp_evaluation_time: 0.4; spk_evaluation_time: 1.0; pca_components: 2; pca_whiten: True; freq_min: 300.0; freq_max: 6000.0; filter: True; pre_scale: True; pre_scale_value: 20.0; filter_duplicates: True. After spike sorting, cells that spiked &gt;10 spikes per second on average over a period of one hour were excluded from any further analysis.</p></sec><sec id="S30"><title>Electrical footprints</title><p id="P88">Spike triggered averages (STA) were computed by reverse correlating spikes from each cell with the voltage signal of all MEA channels within a window of 10 frames before and 40 frames after a spike resulting in 4,096 STAs (one for each channel), consisting of 50 frames. For this, all spikes that occurred within the first half hour of a recording were considered. Electrical footprints were computed for a subset of 5 recordings.</p></sec><sec id="S31"><title>Processing electrical images (EIs)</title><p id="P89">To identify which channels had recorded an electrical signal from a cell, channels were filtered by calculating a signal strength matrix: <disp-formula id="FD1"><mml:math id="M1"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>max</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>max</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mo>…</mml:mo><mml:mi>max</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mn>4096</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>min</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>min</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>…</mml:mo><mml:mi>min</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mn>4096</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>diff</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mtext>diff</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>…</mml:mo><mml:mtext>diff</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mn>4096</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="P90">The resulting <italic>Esignal</italic> matrix was median-normalised and all channels with a score below 0 were filtered out. The matrix was reshaped according to the MEA array (64 × 64) and channels with a zscore above 0 but without neighbouring channels were filtered out. If the remaining number of channels was above 400 the EI was not further considered. In most cases only a handful of channels would remain (called filtered channels in the following), of which most would show a typical spike waveform in their STA. We next detected and traced the axon, where present, as follows: The channel with the highest <italic>Esignal</italic> value was defined as the spatial origin of the spike <italic>Smin<sub>0</sub>,</italic> an the frame with the lowest number of counts in the corresponding STA was defined as the temporal origin of the spike signal <italic>Fmin<sub>0</sub>.</italic> The soma of the cell was identified by identifying all filtered channels within a radius of 6 channels around <italic>S<sub>0</sub></italic>. Those channels were not considered for the axon tracing. To trace the axon, an array was created storing x and y positions of all remaining filtered channels and their respective <italic>Fmin</italic> values. The array was sorted from low to high <italic>Fmin</italic>. Based on the x and y positions a <italic>random_geometric_graph</italic> was created using the networkx Python package (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://networkx.org/documentation/stable/index.html">https://networkx.org/documentation/stable/index.html</ext-link>). Using the function <italic>shortest_path,</italic> the shortest path between the origin of the signal at <italic>S<sub>0</sub></italic>/<italic>Fmin<sub>0</sub></italic> and <italic>S<sub>max</sub>/</italic>Fmin<sub>max</sub>, was calculated. The distance of the part <italic>D<sub>short</sub></italic> was calculated as the total length of the path multiplied by the width of the array in mm.</p><p id="P91">The speed of the signal in m / s was calculated as: <disp-formula id="FD2"><mml:math id="M2"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>max</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>q</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1000</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula> with <italic>Freq</italic> corresponding to the reciprocal of the MEA’s sampling frequency.</p></sec><sec id="S32"><title>Clustering and initial computation of STAs</title><p id="P92">Clustering was performed on a dataset containing the functional responses of ‘cells’ recovered from the spike sorting ‘coloured’ (CS) and ‘white’ steps (WS) of light, chirp (Chirp) stimuli, and spectral kernels (SK) derived from the spectral noise (SN) stimulus. In all experiments, the complete CS and WS stimuli were repeated 5 times, the chirp stimulus was repeated 3 times and the SN stimulus ran for 18,000 stimulus frames (20 mins) without repeat (using the R, G, C and B LEDs).</p><p id="P93">In what follows we describe the procedures followed to cluster the data. We clustered using all four of the above stimuli: CS, WS, Chirp and SK.</p><p id="P94">To determine the spiking rate over time for each cell in response to each of the CS, WS and Chirp stimuli we mapped all spike times onto the time interval spanned by the first repeat of that stimulus and applied kernel density estimation (KDE) using the Matlab routine ksdensity. We used the default probability density function for the KDE, such that the area under the resulting curve is equal to one, thus normalising the spiking rate across cells and stimuli. The KDE was computed at 1,000 equally spaced points and a smoothing bandwidth of 0.05 employed for all three stimuli.</p><p id="P95">Spectral kernels were computed by collecting the stimulus segments preceding each spike to form a spike-triggered ensemble (STE) and taking the mean of this ensemble. We then subtracted the mean raw stimulus, calculated as the mean of all possible stimulus segments. Stimulus segments were calculated over the one second interval preceding each spike (-1 sec to 0 sec inclusive) at 51 evenly spaced time points (0.02 second intervals). Thus, the segments were calculated at a finer temporal resolution than the stimulus (20 Hz = 0.05 second intervals) resulting in smoother and more detailed SKs (since a spike may occur at any time within a given stimulus window, a higher temporal resolution results in different stimulus segments depending upon the spike’s location within that window). For the mean raw stimulus, the mean was taken over all stimulus segments during the interval over which the stimulus was played, segment initiation times ranging from the earliest to the latest possible time that will allow a full stimulus segment, in intervals of 0.02 seconds. The spectral kernels were further normalised, by subtracting the mean and dividing by the standard deviation of the SK in the [-2,-1] second interval preceding each spike, where this SK is calculated in the same way as the original spectral kernels. This allows us to determine spectral kernel quality (see below) in those cases where the spike count is low.</p><p id="P96">Cells with low-quality responses to all four stimuli were identified and removed from the data set, cells with a high-quality response to at least one stimulus being retained in all cases. The quality of response to the CS, WS and Chirp stimuli was determined using the signal-to-noise ratio quality index: <inline-formula><mml:math id="M3"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>〈</mml:mo><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold"><mml:mtext>C</mml:mtext></mml:mstyle><mml:mo>〉</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>〈</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold"><mml:mtext>C</mml:mtext></mml:mstyle><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>〉</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, where C is the <italic>T</italic> by <italic>R</italic> response matrix (time samples by stimulus repetitions), and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M4"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>〈</mml:mo><mml:mo>⋅</mml:mo><mml:mo>〉</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <italic>Var</italic>[·]<sub><italic>x</italic></sub> denote the mean and variance respectively across the indicated dimension, <italic>x</italic> ∈ {<italic>r, t</italic>} (see Ref<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31">31</xref></sup>). This quality index was applied to the KDE-derived spiking rates, where KDE was applied to each repeat separately rather than mapping all spikes onto the first repeat as for the computation of the spiking rates used for clustering (described above). A quality threshold of 0.4 was chosen, below which CS, WS and Chirp responses were judged to be of poor quality. We calculated the standard deviation in the light intensity over time for each stimulus colour in the kernel (R, G, C and B). The kernel quality of each cell was defined as the maximum standard deviation across the four LEDs. A kernel quality threshold of 2.5 was chosen, below which kernels were judged to be of poor quality. The raw data set was of size n = 60,713, spread across 17 separate experiments. Following quality control, the data set was of size: n = 4,230 (7.00% (3 s.f.) of the original).</p><p id="P97">We used principal component analysis (PCA) to reduce the dimensions of the problem prior to clustering. PCA was performed using the Matlab routine <bold>pca</bold> (default settings). We applied PCA separately to each of the 10 segments of the WS stimulus (100%, 90%, …10% contrast segments), to each of the 10 WSs, the Chirp stimulus, each of the 6 CSs, and four SKs. We retained the minimum number of principal components necessary to explain ≥50% of the variance. The resulting 23 ‘scores’ matrices were then concatenated into a single matrix ready for clustering. The following numbers of principal components were used – CS: 24 components in total (3 R components, 3 Y components, 4 G components, 5 C components, 2 B components and 7 U components); WS: 61 components in total ([4,4,5,6,6,7,7,7,7,8] [100,90,80,70,60,50,40,30,20,10]% contrast components); Chirp: 47 components; SK: 8 components in total (2 R components, 2 G components, 2 C components and 2 B components), giving a grand total of 140 PCA components.</p><p id="P98">We clustered the combined ‘scores’ matrix using Gaussian Mixture Model (GMM) clustering, performed using the Matlab routine <bold>fitgmdist</bold>. We initially sorted the data into 100 clusters using i) shared-diagonal, ii) unshared-diagonal, iii) shared-full and iv) unshared-full covariance matrices, such that four different clustering options were explored in total. For each clustering option 20 replicates were calculated (each with a different set of initial values) and the replicate with the largest loglikelihood chosen. A regularisation value of 10<sup>-5</sup> was chosen to ensure that the estimated covariance matrices were positive definite, while the maximum number of iterations was set at 10<sup>4</sup>. All other <bold>fitgmdist</bold> settings were set to their default values.</p><p id="P99">The optimum clustering was judged to be that which minimised the Bayesian information criterion (BIC), which balances the explanatory power of the model (loglikelihood) with model complexity (number of parameters). Using the above procedure, we found that unshared diagonal covariance matrices provided the optimal solution. From here we combined 100 initial clusters into 36 merged clusters by hand based on similarity in cluster mean responses. Finally, of the 36 remaining “compound-clusters”, 14 that comprised fewer than 20 members were discarded, yielding a final total of 22. The full dataset, including allocations to the original 100 clusters and their subsequent combinations are available online at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://chicken-data.retinal-functomics.net/">http://chicken-data.retinal-functomics.net/</ext-link>.</p></sec><sec id="S33"><title>Quality indices</title><p id="P100">We computed three separate response quality indices pertaining to the WS and CS stimuli as well as the spectral kernels. The quality indices for WS and CS stimuli were calculated as: <disp-formula id="FD3"><mml:math id="M5"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>max</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>max</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>H</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>H</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula> where SYNC denotes the SPIKE-synchronization, ISI the inter spike interval and PSTH being the peri stimulus histogram calculated over all 5 repeats of stimulus repetition. SYNC, ISI and PSTH were calculated using the Pyspike Python package<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R83">83</xref></sup>. Kernel quality was calculated by adding the sum of the 100 highest counts and the absolute sum of the 100 lowest counts of z-normalised STAs across all chromatic channels. Based on these, we then computed a ‘compound QI’ for each cell by first normalising the distributions of each of the three individual QIs (CS, WS, kernels) to a mean of 1, followed by averaging across the three normalised QIs. As such, the three stimuli were given equal weighting. This compound QI was used as the basis of sorting cell by quality within each cluster. Note that a different set of QIs was used to preselect cells for inclusion in the clustering in the first place (see above).</p></sec><sec id="S34"><title>Step-responses (WS, CS)</title><sec id="S35"><title>Response amplitudes</title><p id="P101">We computed three basic response amplitude measures for each step-transition. (i) The total On and Off response amplitudes were taken as the mean number of spikes elicited during the 2 seconds of stimulus presentation. These are used as the basis of all plots showing spectral tunings and contrast response functions (e.g. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3j,k</xref>), to compute the polarity index (e.g. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2b</xref>) and to compute the spectral tuning index (e.g. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4j</xref>). We also computed a baseline value per cell as follows: A 1,000-bin amplitude histogram was computed based on the concatenated, cluster-averaged responses to WS and CS, and the peak of this histogram was taken as the baseline. Accordingly, the baseline was defined as the most common amplitude value throughout the full response trace to these two stimuli, which yielded reasonable estimates as judged by manual inspection. This cluster-wise baseline estimate was also individually associated with each cell within a cluster because this procedure was judged to yield more robust cell-wise estimates compared to computing the same metric based on each cell. The baseline value was used in two ways: As a display item in the spectral tuning and contrast-response plots (e.g. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3j,k</xref>), and as a means to normalise response amplitudes across clusters, where tuning functions were normalised between 0 (baseline) and 1 (peak response, e.g. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3l,m</xref>).</p><p id="P102">For each step transition (i.e. On and Off), we also computed ‘transient’ and ‘sustained’ response measured based on the peak spike rate within time windows of 80-160 and 240 – 2,000 ms following the step transition, respectively. To ameliorate the effects of noise, we used box-smoothed (window size of 40 ms) response traces to estimate these latter two metrics. The transient and sustained response metrics were used as the basis of the transience indices (e.g. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2b</xref>). The transient-response amplitude was further used as the basis of spectral dominance index (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4j,k</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplemental Figure 4</xref>), and to compute normalised amplitudes used for relating latencies and amplitudes in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5e,f</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="S36"><title>Polarity index (PI)</title><p id="P103">For clusters, the polarity index (PI) was computed based on On- and Off-response amplitudes (see above) of the 100% contrast WS as: <disp-formula id="FD4"><mml:math id="M6"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="P104">Where A<sub>On</sub> and A<sub>Off</sub> are the On- and Off-response amplitudes, respectively. Accordingly, PI ranged from -1 to 1 to denote entirely Off- and On-dominated responses, respectively. A PI of 0 denotes a cell with equal amplitude On- and Off-responses. The same measure was also used to compute polarity of the zebrafish, mouse and human datasets (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2d-f</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplemental Figure 2c</xref>), with the exception that in this case, A<sub>On</sub> and A<sub>Off</sub> were taken as the total response for 1 second (rather than 2 seconds) following a step-transition. This adjustment was necessary because the step-duration in the mouse dataset was 1 second.</p></sec><sec id="S37"><title>Transience index (TI)</title><p id="P105">As for polarity (above), the transience index (TI) was computed as the contrast between transient and sustained responses per 100% contrast WS as follows: <disp-formula id="FD5"><mml:math id="M7"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="P106">Where A<sub>Tr</sub> and A<sub>sus</sub> are the transient and sustained response amplitudes as described above. Accordingly, TI ranged from -1 to 1 to refer to cells entirely dominated by their sustained and transient response component, respectively.</p><p id="P107">For each dataset, the TI was computed three times: As On- and Off versions, based on the respective On- and Off- measures of transient and sustained responses, and as a ‘compound TI’ where the associated polarity index would dictate which of the On- or Off-versions would be used for transience. This ‘compound TI’ was used for <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2b-e</xref>, while the individual On- and Off- TIs were used for <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplemental Figure 2d</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="S38"><title>Spectral dominance (SD)</title><p id="P108">Spectral dominance (SD) was computed as follows: <disp-formula id="FD6"><mml:math id="M8"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula> where A<sub>colour</sub> and A<sub>white</sub> are the transient response measures of the largest CS responses, and that of the 100% contrast white response. SD ranged from -1 to 1, indicating responses entirely dominated by WS and CS stimuli, respectively.</p></sec><sec id="S39"><title>Spectral tuning (ST)</title><p id="P109">An index of “spectral tuning” (ST) was devised to indicate how closely the spectral tuning of a given response matches that of any of the four opsins expressed across the chick’s cones (LWS, RH2, SWS2, SWS1<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref></sup>). To compute ST, we first log-transformed Govadovski-templates<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R84">84</xref></sup> of each of the four opsins and stretched it over one log-unit, such that in each case a linear response of 10% and 100% maximum was mapped to zero and 1, respectively. Such a ~10-fold log-transform is expected based on the phototransduction cascade of cones<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R85">85</xref></sup>. The resultant transforms are also used as the basis of all opsin-templates presented across the figures. For each cell or cluster’s normalised spectral tuning function (see above) we next determined which of the four templates provided the closest match based on their correlation coefficient. We then subtracted the normalised tuning functions from their respective template, and computed ST as the mean of their difference, multiplied by -1. As such, ST was zero when the opsin template and response were perfectly matched, but negative and positive, respectively, if the response was spectrally broader or narrower than the opsin. Throughout, we applied a minimum response threshold of 3 spikes as the peak response – tuning functions based on fewer spikes were not considered.</p></sec><sec id="S40"><title>Latency</title><p id="P110">Response latency was computed separately from On- and Off-transitions of all time-smoothed WS and CS responses (40 ms window size) as the time to half peak.</p></sec><sec id="S41"><title>Principal Component Analysis (PCA)</title><p id="P111">To compare the temporal response-envelopes elicited by CS and WS stimuli, we used principal component analysis. Computing separately for On- and Off-transitions, for a given cluster (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5i,j</xref>), or the mean responses of all OnOff clusters (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5g,h</xref>), we combined the first five CS (i.e. excluding UV) and first five WS (100, 90, 80, 70, 60% contrast) into a 50x10 input matrix (50 time bins of 20 ms each, 10 responses). To exclude residual activity from the preceding stimulus, we zeroed the first 4 bins (=80 ms). The first two principal components emerging from PCA across this matrix consistently explained &gt;94% of the total variance. Accordingly, higher PCs were discarded. To relate the results from the PCA across clusters (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5i,j</xref>), sets of loadings were individually peak normalised to 1.</p></sec></sec><sec id="S42"><title>Spectral Kernels (SK)</title><sec id="S43"><title>Kernel amplitudes</title><p id="P112">Kernels were individually (R, G, C, B) z-normalised based on timepoints between 1,000 and 500 ms preceding the spike, and amplitudes were subsequently computed (in z-scores) as the difference between their maximum and minimum values. Cluster-mean kernels with an amplitude &lt;2.5 were discarded from further analysis.</p></sec><sec id="S44"><title>Spectral Centroids</title><p id="P113">To quantify the kinetics of each kernel, we estimated their central frequency in the Fourier domain (‘spectral centroid’) as follows. We first computed each (R, G, C, B) kernels’ probability mass function as its area-normalised magnitude-squared Fourier transform. We then multiplied each entry by the reciprocal of its associated frequency in Hz. The kernels’ central tendency in Hz was then taken as the sum of this product.</p></sec><sec id="S45"><title>Colour Opponency</title><p id="P114">Colour opponency was determined based on the relative trajectories of each cell or cluster’s group of four spectral kernels (R, G, C, B). Due to the complex interplay between time and polarity across the group of kernels, we started by categorising each kernel-group’s 1 ms time-bin as either non-responsive, responsive and non-opponent, or responsive and opponent. Time-bins where none of the four kernels exceeded a minimum absolute amplitude of 3 (or 1.5 for cluster means) were defined as non-responsive and set to NaN. All remaining responsive bins were categorised as either opponent (1) or non-opponent (0) depending on the relative signs of all four kernels amplitudes. Next, for all kernel-groups where at least 20 (of 1,000) time bins were categorised as opponent (i.e. 20 out of 1,000 ms maximal kernel duration), a colour opponency index (COI) was defined as the mean of this vector. Accordingly, colour opponency ranged from 0 (entirely non-opponent) to 1 (entirely opponent). Kernel-groups with a Kernel-QI (see above) &lt; 1,000 were excluded from this analysis and categorised as non-opponent. The time-dependent opponency vectors were further used as the basis of aligning the opponent and non-opponent time-regions of each OnOff cluster (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5a,b</xref>). To this end, we time-compressed each associated vector between its beginning (time -1), defined as the first timepoint where the group of kernels exceeded a minimum amplitude of 1, and the time of the spike (time 0). In this case, non-opponent kernel bins were set to -1 instead of 0 (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5a,b</xref>)</p></sec></sec><sec id="S46"><title>Chirps</title><sec id="S47"><title>Fourier analysis, best frequency, and high-frequency index (HFI)</title><p id="P115">For each cluster mean, we computed the magnitude-squared Fourier transform for the full chirp-response (accelerating from 1 – 30 Hz over 30 s – shown as area normalised in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3e,f</xref>), and used this as the basis of a high-frequency index (HFI): <disp-formula id="FD7"><mml:math id="M9"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>w</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>w</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula> where P<sub>high</sub> and P<sub>low</sub> were the mean power between 0.9 and 2 Hz, and between 4 and 15 Hz, respectively. As such, HFI varied between -1 and 1 to indicate clusters entirely dominated by a low- and high-frequency response, respectively. Clusters that exhibited fewer than 20% additional spikes during the chirp-stimulus compared to the 5 seconds preceding it were considered unresponsive and excluded from this analysis.</p><p id="P116">Best frequency was taken as the peak of each cluster’s magnitude-squared Fourier transform.</p></sec><sec id="S48"><title>Phaselocking analysis</title><p id="P117">For each spike elicited during chirp stimulation, we computed the phase relative to the stimulus as follows. First, to compensate for the phototransduction delay and inner retinal processing, all spikes were negatively time-shifted by 100 ms relative to the stimulus. The value of 100 ms was chosen based on the mean of On- and Off-latencies (time at half maximum) across all cells’ 100% contrast WS-responses (= 99.4 ms). We next divided the 30 s chirp segment (1-30 Hz) into ten equal time bins of 3 seconds each, with their corresponding mean frequencies centred at 1.2, 1.7, 2.4, 3.3, 4.7, 6.5, 9.8, 12.5, 22.5 and 25.0 Hz. We then computed the phase angle θ for each spike (ranging from 0 to T, where 0 and T/2 denote the onset of the On and Off-phase, respectively, as indicated e.g. in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3h</xref>). For each cell and time bin we then determined resultant median vector strength r (ranging from 0 to 1 to indicate a random relationship between each spike and the stimulus, and perfect phase locking, respectively) as described elsewhere<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R86">86</xref></sup>. For statistical testing, we also computed the same metrics based on 1,000 Poisson statistics but time-randomised artificial neurons that comprised the same number of average spikes as each cluster. We then used the upper 95% confidence intervals from the distribution of vector strengths emerging from this artificial set of neurons as the basis of determining statistical significance (i.e. p&lt;0.05): Any cluster-entries that failed to exceed this confidence boundary of their corresponding bootstrapped distribution were deemed non-significant. For clarity, these data points are removed from the presented data (e.g. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3h</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="S49"><title>Choice and pre-processing of functional RGC datasets other vertebrate species</title><p id="P118">To relate our data from chick retina to those of other species, we sourced previously published RGC-response datasets from human, mice, and zebrafish. To ensure good compatibility, we specifically looked for step-responses to spectrally broad stimulation, and for datasets that comprised representative fraction of most, if not all RGC types in that species. However, since the state-of-the-art with regards to different species is not fully equivalent, some compromises had to be made. The mouse dataset was sourced from Ref<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37">37</xref></sup> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://rgc-types.org">rgc-types.org</ext-link>) as probably the most comprehensive available to date. The dataset presents mean spike-responses of all 42 RGC types currently described in mice, to a 1-second step of scotopic light aimed to stimulate the rod-system. The relative abundance of each type was then complemented by assessing their corresponding abundance on Eyewire<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43">43</xref></sup>. Next, as an example for primates, we chose a multielectrode array dataset collected from post-mortem human donors, published as part of Ref<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38">38</xref></sup>. While our understanding of the functional RGC types in the human retina is perhaps still lagging that of some other primate species, we nevertheless chose this dataset because it included systematically recorded ‘white’ step responses – in this case for 3-second 100% contrast low-photopic steps of light. The dataset consisted of n = 411 individual neurons. From here, we clustered the data using Kmeans into 20 clusters that capture some of the major structure. We chose the value of 20 as a compromise between a very conservative estimate of the full RGC diversity in primate retina, and in view of the limited dataset which is likely to lack some of the rarer types. The exact number of clusters had no notable effect on the overall distribution of clusters with regards to polarity and transience (see also the original publication<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38">38</xref></sup> which shows a very similar distribution based on 5 clusters). Finally, we also included our previously published functional RGC dataset from larval zebrafish<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref></sup>, which included 3-second step responses to 100% contrast low-photopic white light. Because this data was collected by 2-photon mGCaMP6f imaging of RGC-responses in the live eye, rather than by recording ex-vivo RGC spikes, we approximated spiking activity by deconvolving responses with a Tau = 0.4 s decaying time kernel. The exact value of this deconvolution did not notably affect results. A correspondingly comprehensive zebrafish dataset based on direct measurements of spike responses has not been published. Because compared to mice and primates, in larval zebrafish the link between functional<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref></sup>, anatomical<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R67">67</xref></sup> and genetic<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R87">87</xref></sup> RGC types remains notably less complete, we opted to use the n = 16 functional RGC clusters and their relative abundances that were described in the original study as the basis of our analysis. It is likely that this relatively low number of clusters underestimates the full RGC diversity in larval zebrafish. Since the duration of step responses used across the 4 datasets were not identical, we cropped the first 1 second following each On- and Off-transition and resampled each into fifty time-bins of 20 ms. From here, analysis for all datasets was identical, and followed the steps for computing polarity and transience indices described above. When separately computing histograms of On- and Off-transience, applying a minimum response threshold of 20% for each type/cluster’s ‘weaker’ polarity for inclusion, where applicable (such that e.g. a cluster that exhibited a more than 5-fold stronger response to Onversus Off was included for the On-histogram, but not the Off).</p></sec></sec><sec id="S50"><title>Quantification And Statistical Analysis</title><sec id="S51"><title>Statistics</title><p id="P119">No statistical methods were used to predetermine sample size. Owing to the exploratory nature of our study, we did not use randomization or blinding.</p><p id="P120">Linear correlation tests were used to establish the correlation coefficient and significance of relationships between polarity and transience indices (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figures 2a,d-f</xref>).</p><p id="P121">Wilcoxon Rank Sum tests were used to probe for differences in conduction velocity between different cluster groups (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3i</xref>). The custom bootstrapping approach associated with evaluating vector strengths (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figures 3g</xref>) is detailed in the section on phase-locking.</p><p id="P122"><xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplemental Video S1</xref>. Video-montage of the three electrical images (EIs) shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1f,h,I</xref>, shown at 1:500<sup>th</sup> real time.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="extended-data" id="S52"><title>Extended Data</title><fig id="F7" position="anchor"><label>Extended Data 1</label><caption><p id="P123"><bold>related to Figure 2 a-e,</bold> Overview of each cluster’s mean light responses to the presented battery of visual stimuli, showing every second ‘white’ contrast step (a), the ‘red’ and ‘blue’ colour steps (b), all four spectral kernels (c), chirp-responses (d) and an indication of the relative number of cells in each cluster (e). Full detail can be interactively explored in the online plotter at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://chicken-data.retinal-functomics.net/">http://chicken-data.retinal-functomics.net/</ext-link>. Spike histograms are shown as peak-normalised to the largest response in each stimulus group.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS156212-f007"/></fig></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="SM"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1"><label>Supplemental Video 1</label><media xlink:href="EMS156212-supplement-Supplemental_Video_1.gif" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="gif" id="d85aAdIbB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD2"><label>Supplemental Figure</label><media xlink:href="EMS156212-supplement_Supplemental_Figure.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" id="d85aAdIcB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack id="S53"><title>Acknowledgements and Funding</title><p>We thank Thomas Euler for critical feedback. Funding was provided by the Wellcome Trust (Investigator Award in Science 220277/Z20/Z to TB), the European Research Council (ERC-StG “NeuroVisEco” 677687 to TB), UKRI (BBSRC, BB/R014817/1 and BB/W013509/1 to TB), the Leverhulme Trust (PLP-2017-005 and RPG-2021-026 to TB; GK was supported by the Leverhulme DTP DS-2017-011) and the Lister Institute for Preventive Medicine (to TB). This research was funded in part by the Wellcome Trust [220277/Z20/Z]. For the purpose of Open Access, the authors have applied a CC BY public copyright licence to any Author Accepted Manuscript version arising from this submission.</p></ack><sec id="S54" sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data and Code Availability</title><p id="P124">All pre-processed spike data (cellwise trial-averaged means and kernels) are available for interactive display and download from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://chicken-data.retinal-functomics.net/">http://chicken-data.retinal-functomics.net/</ext-link>. The underlying individual spike timings, corresponding stimuli, and an explanation of the file structures can be downloaded from the same site.</p></sec><fn-group><fn id="FN2" fn-type="con"><p id="P125"><bold>Author contributions</bold>. Conceptualization, MS, DO, TB; Methodology, MS, PAR, GK; Investigation, MS, TB; Data Curation, MS, PAR; Writing – Original Draft, TB; Writing – Review &amp; Editing, MS, PAR, GK, DO, TB; Visualization, MS, TB; Supervision, DO, TB; Project Administration, DO, TB; Funding Acquisition, DO, TB. The authors declare no conflict of interest, nor interest in conflict.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><ref id="R1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wässle</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Parallel processing in the mammalian retina</article-title><source>Nat Rev Neurosci</source><year>2004</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>747</fpage><lpage>57</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baden</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Euler</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Berens</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Understanding the retinal basis of vision across species</article-title><source>Nat Rev Neurosci</source><year>2020</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>5</fpage><lpage>20</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Masland</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The fundamental plan of the retina</article-title><source>Nat Neurosci</source><year>2001</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>877</fpage><lpage>86</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Westheimer</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The ON-OFF dichotomy in visual processing: From receptors to perception</article-title><source>Prog Retin Eye Res</source><year>2007</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>636</fpage><lpage>648</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Euler</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Haverkamp</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Schubert</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Baden</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Retinal Bipolar Cells: Elementary Building Blocks of Vision</article-title><source>Nat Rev Neurosci</source><year>2014</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>507</fpage><lpage>519</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roska</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Werblin</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Vertical interactions across ten parallel, stacked representations in the mammalian retina</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2001</year><volume>410</volume><fpage>583</fpage><lpage>7</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Awatramani</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name><name><surname>Slaughter</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Origin of transient and sustained responses in ganglion cells of the retina</article-title><source>J Neurosci Off J Soc Neurosci</source><year>2000</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>7087</fpage><lpage>95</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Buchsbaum</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Gottschalk</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Trichromacy, opponent colours coding and optimum colour information transmission in the retina</article-title><source>Proc R Soc Lond Ser B Contain Pap Biol Character R Soc G B</source><year>1983</year><volume>220</volume><fpage>89</fpage><lpage>113</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dacey</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Packer</surname><given-names>OS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Colour coding in the primate retina: Diverse cell types and cone-specific circuitry</article-title><source>Curr Opin Neurobiol</source><year>2003</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>421</fpage><lpage>427</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Zebrafish Retinal Ganglion Cells Asymmetrically Encode Spectral and Temporal Information across Visual Space</article-title><source>Curr Biol</source><year>2020</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>2927</fpage><lpage>2942</lpage><elocation-id>e7</elocation-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshimatsu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Lagnado</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Baden</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Amacrine cells shape retinal functions while dynamically preserving circuits for colour vision</article-title><year>2022</year><elocation-id>2022.01.22.477338</elocation-id><comment>Preprint at</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2022.01.22.477338v1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bartel</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshimatsu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Janiak</surname><given-names>FK</given-names></name><name><surname>Baden</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Spectral inference reveals principal cone-integration rules of the zebrafish inner retina</article-title><source>Curr Biol</source><year>2021</year><volume>0</volume></element-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bartel</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Janiak</surname><given-names>FK</given-names></name><name><surname>Osorio</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Baden</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Colourfulness as a possible measure of object proximity in the larval zebrafish brain</article-title><source>Curr Biol</source><year>2021</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>R235</fpage><lpage>R236</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rocha</surname><given-names>FAF</given-names></name><name><surname>Saito</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Silveira</surname><given-names>LCL</given-names></name><name><surname>De Souza</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ventura</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Twelve chromatically opponent ganglion cell types in turtle retina</article-title><source>Visual Neuroscience</source><year>2008</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>307</fpage><lpage>315</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacoby</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Physiological and morphological characterization of ganglion cells in the salamander retina</article-title><source>Vision Res</source><year>2016</year><volume>119</volume><fpage>60</fpage><lpage>72</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rozenblit</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Gollisch</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>What the salamander eye has been telling the vision scientist’s brain</article-title><source>Semin Cell Dev Biol</source><year>2020</year><volume>106</volume><fpage>61</fpage><lpage>71</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seifert</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Baden</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Osorio</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The retinal basis of vision in chicken</article-title><source>Semin Cell Dev Biol</source><year>2020</year><volume>106</volume><fpage>106</fpage><lpage>115</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Potier</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitkus</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelber</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Visual adaptations of diurnal and nocturnal raptors</article-title><source>Semin Cell Dev Biol</source><year>2020</year><volume>106</volume><fpage>116</fpage><lpage>126</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Diedrich</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Schaeffel</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Spatial resolution, contrast sensitivity, and sensitivity to defocus of chicken retinal ganglion cells in vitro</article-title><source>Vis Neurosci</source><year>2009</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>467</fpage><lpage>476</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Saltatory axonal conduction in the avian retina</article-title><source>bioRxiv</source><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2022.07.04.498722v1">https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2022.07.04.498722v1</ext-link>.</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Deepak</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Krishnan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Narayan</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Temporal Characteristics of Neonatal Chick Retinal Ganglion Cell Responses: Effects of Luminance, Contrast, and Color</article-title><year>2022</year><elocation-id>2022.07.28.499133</elocation-id><comment>Preprint at</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2022.07.28.499133</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martins-Ferreira</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Nedergaard</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nicholson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Perspectives on spreading depression</article-title><source>Brain Res Brain Res Rev</source><year>2000</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>215</fpage><lpage>234</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sibille</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>High-density electrode recordings reveal strong and specific connections between retinal ganglion cells and midbrain neurons</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2022</year><volume>13</volume><elocation-id>5218</elocation-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Potier</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lieuvin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pfaff</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelber</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>How fast can raptors see?</article-title><source>J Exp Biol</source><year>2020</year><volume>223</volume></element-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Spectral sensitivity of monochromatic ERG c-wave of chicken under color adaptation</article-title><source>Jpn J Ophthalmol</source><year>1993</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>88</fpage><lpage>92</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baden</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Vertebrate vision: Lessons from non-model species</article-title><source>Semin Cell Dev Biol</source><year>2020</year><volume>106</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>4</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Greschner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Field</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A Polyaxonal Amacrine Cell Population in the Primate Retina</article-title><source>J …</source><year>2014</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baden</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Osorio</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Retinal Basis of Vertebrate Color Vision</article-title><source>Annu Rev Vis Sci</source><year>2019</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>177</fpage><lpage>200</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baden</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Circuit-mechanisms for colour vision in zebrafish</article-title><source>Curr Biol</source><year>2021</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>PR807</fpage><lpage>R80</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yoshimatsu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Ancestral circuits for vertebrate color vision emerge at the first retinal synapse</article-title><source>Sci Adv</source><year>2021</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>6815</fpage><lpage>6828</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baden</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The functional diversity of retinal ganglion cells in the mouse</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2016</year><volume>529</volume><fpage>345</fpage><lpage>50</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Szatko</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Neural circuits in the mouse retina support color vision in the upper visual field</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2020</year><volume>11</volume><elocation-id>3481</elocation-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Field</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Functional connectivity in the retina at the resolution of photoreceptors</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2010</year><volume>467</volume><fpage>673</fpage><lpage>7</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chichilnisky</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A simple white noise analysis of neuronal light</article-title><source>Netw Comput Neural Syst</source><year>2001</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>199</fpage><lpage>213</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Toomey</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Corbo</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evolution, development and function of vertebrate cone oil droplets</article-title><source>Front Neural Circuits</source><year>2017</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>97</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamagata</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanes</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A cell atlas of the chick retina based on single-cell transcriptomics</article-title><source>eLife</source><year>2021</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>39</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goetz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Unified classification of mouse retinal ganglion cells using function, morphology, and gene expression</article-title><source>Cell Rep</source><year>2022</year><volume>40</volume><elocation-id>111040</elocation-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cowan</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cell Types of the Human Retina and Its Organoids at Single-Cell Resolution</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2020</year><volume>182</volume><fpage>1623</fpage><lpage>1640</lpage><elocation-id>e34</elocation-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ammermüller</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Muller</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Kolb</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The organization of the turtle inner retina. II. Analysis of color-coded and directionally selective cells</article-title><source>J Comp Neurol</source><year>1995</year><volume>358</volume><fpage>35</fpage><lpage>62</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kelber</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bird colour vision - from cones to perception</article-title><source>Curr Opin Behav Sci</source><year>2019</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>34</fpage><lpage>40</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R41"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dacey</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>20 Origins of Perception: Retinal Ganglion Cell Diversity and the Creation of Parallel Visual Pathways</chapter-title><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Gazzaniga</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group><source>The Cognitive Neurosciences Iii</source><publisher-name>MIT Press</publisher-name><year>2004</year><fpage>281</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R42"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bleckert</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name><name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Rieke</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>ROL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Visual space is represented by nonmatching topographies of distinct mouse retinal ganglion cell types</article-title><source>Curr Biol CB</source><year>2014</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>310</fpage><lpage>5</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R43"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bae</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Digital Museum of Retinal Ganglion Cells with Dense Anatomy and Physiology</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2018</year><volume>173</volume><fpage>1293</fpage><lpage>1306</lpage><elocation-id>e19</elocation-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R44"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>De</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>OFF-transient alpha RGCs mediate looming triggered innate defensive response</article-title><source>Curr Biol</source><year>2021</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>2263</fpage><lpage>2273</lpage><elocation-id>e3</elocation-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R45"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><source>Applications of Digital Signal Processing - Alan V. Oppenheim</source><publisher-name>Google Books</publisher-name><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://books.google.co.uk/books/about/Applications_of_Digital_Signal_Processin.html?id=LfRSAAAAMAAJ&amp;redir_esc=y">https://books.google.co.uk/books/about/Applications_of_Digital_Signal_Processin.html?id=LfRSAAAAMAAJ&amp;redir_esc=y</ext-link>.</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="R46"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Separate ON and OFF pathways in vertebrate vision first arose during the Cambrian - PubMed</article-title><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32516608</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R47"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gjorgjieva</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sompolinsky</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Meister</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Benefits of pathway splitting in sensory coding</article-title><source>J Neurosci Off J Soc Neurosci</source><year>2014</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>12127</fpage><lpage>12144</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R48"><label>48</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ocko</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindsey</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ganguli</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Deny</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The emergence of multiple retinal cell types through efficient coding of natural movies</article-title><source>Adv Neural Inf Process Syst</source><year>2018</year><fpage>9389</fpage><lpage>9400</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/458737</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R49"><label>49</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Jun</surname><given-names>NY</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name><name><surname>Pearson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Field</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inter-mosaic coordination of retinal receptive fields</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2021</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41586-021-03317-5</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R50"><label>50</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Field</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Spatial Properties and Functional Organization of Small Bistratified Ganglion Cells in Primate Retina</article-title><source>J Neurosci</source><year>2007</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>13261</fpage><lpage>13272</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R51"><label>51</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ghosh</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name><name><surname>Grünert</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Synaptic input to small bistratified (blue-ON) ganglion cells in the retina of a new world monkey, the marmoset Callithrix jacchus</article-title><source>J Comp Neurol</source><year>1999</year><volume>413</volume><fpage>417</fpage><lpage>428</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R52"><label>52</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baudin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Angueyra</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Sinha</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Rieke</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>S-cone photoreceptors in the primate retina are functionally distinct from L and M cones</article-title><source>eLife</source><year>2019</year><volume>8</volume></element-citation></ref><ref id="R53"><label>53</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barlow</surname><given-names>HBH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Possible principles underlying the transformation of sensory messages</article-title><source>Sensory Communication</source><year>1961</year><fpage>217</fpage><lpage>234</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/15459620490885644</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R54"><label>54</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Attneave</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Some informational aspects of visual perception</article-title><source>Psychol Rev</source><year>1954</year><volume>61</volume><fpage>183</fpage><lpage>193</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R55"><label>55</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Simoncelli</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name><name><surname>Olshausen</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Natural image statistics and neural representation</article-title><source>Annu Rev Neurosci</source><year>2001</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>1193</fpage><lpage>1216</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R56"><label>56</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhaoping</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Are cone sensitivities determined by natural color statistics?</article-title><source>J Vis</source><year>2006</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>285</fpage><lpage>302</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R57"><label>57</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baden</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Schubert</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Berens</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Euler</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Functional Organization of Vertebrate Retinal Circuits for Vision</article-title><source>Oxf Res Encycl Neurosci</source><year>2018</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/acrefore/9780190264086.013.68</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R58"><label>58</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baden</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Circuit mechanisms for colour vision in zebrafish</article-title><source>Curr Biol</source><year>2021</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>R807</fpage><lpage>R820</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R59"><label>59</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Donner</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yovanovich</surname><given-names>CAM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A frog’s eye view: Foundational revelations and future promises</article-title><source>Semin Cell Dev Biol</source><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.semcdb.2020.05.011</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R60"><label>60</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hart</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Vision in sharks and rays: Opsin diversity and colour vision</article-title><source>Semin Cell Dev Biol</source><year>2020</year><volume>106</volume><fpage>12</fpage><lpage>19</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R61"><label>61</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Behrens</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Connectivity map of bipolar cells and photoreceptors in the mouse retina</article-title><source>eLife</source><year>2016</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>1206</fpage><lpage>1217</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R62"><label>62</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Witkovsky</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Stell</surname><given-names>WK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Retinal structure in the smooth dogfish, Mustelus canis: light microscopy of bipolar cells</article-title><source>J Comp Neurol</source><year>1973</year><volume>148</volume><fpage>47</fpage><lpage>59</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R63"><label>63</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Günther</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Double cones and the diverse connectivity of photoreceptors and bipolar cells in an avian retina</article-title><source>J Neurosci</source><year>2021</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>5015</fpage><lpage>5028</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R64"><label>64</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kolb</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahnelt</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Cuenca</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Chapter 1 Cellular organization of the vertebrate retina</chapter-title><source>Progress in Brain Research</source><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name><year>2001</year><volume>131</volume><fpage>3</fpage><lpage>26</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R65"><label>65</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pang</surname><given-names>J-J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Stratum-by-stratum projection of light response attributes by retinal bipolar cells of Ambystoma</article-title><source>J Physiol</source><year>2004</year><volume>558</volume><fpage>249</fpage><lpage>262</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R66"><label>66</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>YN</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsujimura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawamura</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Dowling</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bipolar cell-photoreceptor connectivity in the zebrafish (Danio rerio) retina</article-title><source>J Comp Neurol</source><year>2012</year><volume>520</volume><fpage>3786</fpage><lpage>3802</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R67"><label>67</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Robles</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Laurell</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Baier</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Retinal Projectome Reveals Brain-Area-Specific Visual Representations Generated by Ganglion Cell Diversity</article-title><source>Curr Biol</source><year>2014</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>2085</fpage><lpage>2096</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R68"><label>68</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baden</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Berens</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Bethge</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Euler</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Spikes in mammalian bipolar cells support temporal layering of the inner retina</article-title><year>2013</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2012.11.006</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R69"><label>69</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zimmermann</surname><given-names>MJY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Zebrafish Differentially Process Color across Visual Space to Match Natural Scenes</article-title><source>Curr Biol</source><year>2018</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>2018</fpage><lpage>2032</lpage><elocation-id>e5</elocation-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R70"><label>70</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Osorio</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Discrimination of oriented visual textures by poultry chicks</article-title><source>Vision Res</source><year>2004</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.visres.2003.08.014</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R71"><label>71</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kram</surname><given-names>YA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Avian cone photoreceptors tile the retina as five independent, self-organizing mosaics</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2010</year><volume>5</volume><elocation-id>e8992</elocation-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R72"><label>72</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mitkus</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Olsson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Toomey</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Corbo</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelber</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Specialized photoreceptor composition in the raptor fovea</article-title><source>J Comp Neurol</source><year>2017</year><volume>529</volume><fpage>2152</fpage><lpage>2163</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R73"><label>73</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sinha</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cellular and Circuit Mechanisms Shaping the Perceptual Properties of the Primate Fovea</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2017</year><volume>168</volume><fpage>413</fpage><lpage>426</lpage><elocation-id>e12</elocation-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R74"><label>74</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yoshimatsu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Schröder</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Nevala</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></name><name><surname>Berens</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Baden</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fovea-like Photoreceptor Specializations Underlie Single UV Cone Driven Prey-Capture Behavior in Zebrafish</article-title><source>Neuron</source><year>2020</year><volume>107</volume><fpage>320</fpage><lpage>337</lpage><elocation-id>e6</elocation-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R75"><label>75</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Breuninger</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Puller</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Haverkamp</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Euler</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chromatic bipolar cell pathways in the mouse retina</article-title><source>J Neurosci Off J Soc Neurosci</source><year>2011</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>6504</fpage><lpage>6517</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R76"><label>76</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haverkamp</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Möckel</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Ammermüller</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Different types of synapses with different spectral types of cones underlie color opponency in a bipolar cell of the turtle retina</article-title><source>Vis Neurosci</source><year>1999</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>801</fpage><lpage>809</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R77"><label>77</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zeki</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The representation of colours in the cerebral cortex</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1980</year><volume>284</volume><fpage>412</fpage><lpage>418</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R78"><label>78</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fornetto</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Tiso</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Pavone</surname><given-names>FS</given-names></name><name><surname>Vanzi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Colored visual stimuli evoke spectrally tuned neuronal responses across the central nervous system of zebrafish larvae</article-title><source>BMC Biol</source><year>2020</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>17</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R79"><label>79</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kinoshita</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cortical-like colour-encoding neurons in the mushroom body of a butterfly</article-title><source>Curr Biol</source><year>2022</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>R114</fpage><lpage>R115</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R80"><label>80</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stett</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Barth</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Haemmerle</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Zrenner</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Electrical multisite stimulation of the isolated chicken retina</article-title><source>Vision Res</source><year>2000</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>1785</fpage><lpage>1795</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R81"><label>81</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Franke</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>An arbitrary-spectrum spatial visual stimulator for vision research</article-title><source>eLife</source><year>2019</year><volume>8</volume><elocation-id>e48779</elocation-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R82"><label>82</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hilgen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Unsupervised Spike Sorting for Large-Scale, High-Density Multielectrode Arrays</article-title><source>Cell Rep</source><year>2017</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>2521</fpage><lpage>2532</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R83"><label>83</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mulansky</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kreuz</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>PySpike—A Python library for analyzing spike train synchrony</article-title><source>SoftwareX</source><year>2016</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>183</fpage><lpage>189</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R84"><label>84</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Govardovskii</surname><given-names>VI</given-names></name><name><surname>Fyhrquist</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Reuter</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuzmin</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Donner</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In search of the visual pigment template</article-title><source>Vis Neurosci</source><year>2000</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0952523800174036</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R85"><label>85</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schnapf</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Nunn</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Meister</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Baylor</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Visual transduction in cones of the monkey Macaca fascicularis</article-title><source>J Physiol</source><year>1990</year><volume>427</volume><fpage>681</fpage><lpage>713</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R86"><label>86</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goldberg</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Response of binaural neurons of dog superior olivary complex to dichotic tonal stimuli: some physiological mechanisms of sound localization</article-title><source>J Neurophysiol</source><year>1969</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>613</fpage><lpage>636</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R87"><label>87</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kölsch</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Molecular classification of zebrafish retinal ganglion cells links genes to cell types to behavior</article-title><source>Neuron</source><year>2020</year><volume>109</volume><fpage>645</fpage><lpage>662</lpage><elocation-id>e9</elocation-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R88"><label>88</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ellis</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Frederiksen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Morshedian</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Fain</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name><name><surname>Sampath</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Separate ON and OFF pathways in vertebrate vision first arose during the Cambrian</article-title><source>Curr Biol CB</source><year>2020</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>R633</fpage><lpage>R634</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R89"><label>89</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Asteriti</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Grillner</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Cangiano</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A Cambrian origin for vertebrate rods</article-title><source>eLife</source><year>2015</year><volume>4</volume></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><boxed-text id="BX1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Highlight</title></caption><list list-type="bullet" id="L4"><list-item><p>First large-scale survey of visual functions in an avian retina</p></list-item><list-item><p>Off-circuits are fast and achromatic, On-circuits are slow and chromatic</p></list-item><list-item><p>Most avian RGCs are OnOff and encode both types of information</p></list-item><list-item><p>Colour and greyscale information can be decoded based on the kinetics</p></list-item></list></boxed-text><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Recording light-driven spiking activity from the chick retina.</title><p><bold>a</bold>, phylogenetic tree of extant vertebrates based on Ref<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">29</xref></sup>, indicating key evolutionary transitions in photoreceptor complements leading to birds. <bold>b</bold>, Summary of birds’ seven types of ciliary photoreceptors and their expressed opsins (top), the respective spectral sensitivity functions of their four cone opsins (shadings), and spectral positions of the six LEDs used for visual stimulation. <bold>c</bold>, Schematic of chicken retina modified from Ref<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">2</xref></sup> illustrating the multielectrode array (MEA) recoding strategy. GCL, ganglion cell layer. <bold>d</bold>, Representative recording frame from the 64×64 MEA array, indicating localised activity on a subset of electrodes (top) and example trace from a single electrode (bottom). <bold>e</bold>, Overview of all spike-sorted units detected in an example recording (top) and spike waveforms of two example ‘cells’ (bottom). <bold>f</bold>, Minimum intensity projection across 50 time bins (corresponding to ~3 ms) of a representative electrical image (EI) computed from a single spike sorted unit, revealing the position of the soma, hillock and axon, as indicated. <bold>g</bold>, Time-series from the EI shown in (g), illustrating how the spike travels down the axon towards the optic disc. <bold>h-j</bold>, as (f) but for two different spike sorted units (h,i) and for 100 such units superimposed (j). Note that the axonal footprint in (h) is fractionated, indicating saltatory conduction, while the footprints in (f) and (i) are continuous, indicating non-saltatory conduction (cf. Ref<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">20</xref></sup>). <bold>k</bold>, Fraction of EIs with a clearly detectable axon (y-axis, <xref ref-type="sec" rid="S18">Methods</xref>) plotted for different subsets of the full EI dataset, staggered by the minimum number of spikes available to compute each EI (x-axis). The asymptote of an exponential fit to this data (red) indicates the presumed fraction of EIs that have an axon independent of the signal quality was ~87%. <bold>l</bold>, Distribution of axonal conduction velocities estimated from all presumed RGCs (n = 842). <bold>m-p</bold>, spiking light responses of four example cells to the battery of presented stimuli, including the 100% contrast ‘white’ (m) and ‘coloured’ steps (n), the chirp stimulus (o) and the groups of spectral kernels recovered from spectral noise stimulation (p). Solid histograms indicate the trial-averaged means per cell, with spike-rasters beneath showing the individual repeats.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS156212-f001"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>A tight link between polarity, kinetics, and colour opponency.</title><p><bold>a</bold>, Overview of selected cluster means to the full set of presented stimuli, illustrating some of their systematic differences. For simplicity, only the 100% contrast response is shown for WS, while only the red- and blue-responses are shown for CS. The full set of cluster means are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Extended Data 1</xref>. The full dataset alongside a basic, cluster wise analysis, is interactively plotted and available for download at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://chicken-data.retinal-functomics.net/">http://chicken-data.retinal-functomics.net/</ext-link>. <bold>b,c</bold>, Relationships of transience (b) and colour opponency (c) with polarity for all clusters based on their mean 100% contrast WS responses (<xref ref-type="sec" rid="S18">Methods</xref>). Symbol size denotes the number of cells allocated to a cluster as indicated, while colouration indicates the four response groups: Off (black), OnOff (brown), On (orange/grey). Note that On-responses are further divided by the kinetics of their CS-responses into a transient (orange) and a sustained group (grey) – cf. <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplemental Figure 2a</xref>. (b) further shows the mean±SD shadings for the same relationship based on all individual cells (light grey). <bold>d-f</bold>, As (b), transience and polarity indices of RGCs found in the retina of larval zebrafish (d, based on Ref<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref></sup>), mice (e, based on Ref<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37">37</xref></sup>), and humans (f, based on Ref<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38">38</xref></sup>). For further detail see also <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplemental Figure S2c-f</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS156212-f002"/></fig><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Off-responses encode achromatic temporal contrast.</title><p><bold>a</bold>, Spectral kernels of the most Off-dominated cluster C1, showing the cluster mean (top) and a heatmap of all constituent cells’ kernels (bottom), as indicated. Note lack of opponency, kinetic similarity between spectral components, and the overall long-wavelength dominance. <bold>b, c</bold>, comparison of kernel amplitudes and kinetics (spectral centroids, <xref ref-type="sec" rid="S18">Methods</xref>), here shown for ‘red’ kernels of all clusters (b), and for the full complement of R, G, C, B kernels for three exemplary clusters (c). <bold>d-f</bold>, Mean chirp-responses of four example clusters as indicated (d), their corresponding area normalised magnitude squared Fourier transform (e) and heatmap of all clusters’ Fourier transforms (f). “Low” and “High” frequency windows that were used as the basis of computing a High Frequency Index (<xref ref-type="sec" rid="S18">Methods</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplemental Figure 3a</xref>) and for (i) are shaded into the background. <bold>g</bold>, Degree of phase locking at different frequencies for all clusters, quantified as vector strength (means±s.e.m.). Three exemplary clusters are highlighted with solid lines, the remainder of clusters is plotted faintly in the background. Non-significant entries (<xref ref-type="sec" rid="S18">Methods</xref>) are not shown. <bold>h</bold>, Area-normalised phase histograms (<xref ref-type="sec" rid="S18">Methods</xref>) of three example clusters across two frequency windows as indicated in (e,f) (for all clusters, see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplemental Figure 3b</xref>). Note that clusters tended to lock to the On-phase of the stimulus (grey shading) at low frequencies, but to the Off-phase at high frequencies. <bold>i</bold> Histograms of axonal conduction velocities computed from electrical images for the four cluster-groups as indicated (cf. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1l</xref>). Wilcoxon Rank Sum Test, 1 tailed: Off vs OnOff: p&lt;0.001, Off vs. On<sub>(tr+sus)</sub>: p&lt;0.001; OnOff vs. On<sub>(tr+sus)</sub>: p=0.041; (For the purposes of statistical comparison, On<sub>tr</sub> and On<sub>sus</sub> data were combined in view of the relatively small number of Ontr cells that yielded a reliable electrical image due to their generally very low spike counts). <bold>j,k</bold>, Cluster C<sub>1</sub> mean±SEM number of spikes elicited when probed with the WS (j) and CS (k) stimuli. The background shading in (k) indicate the log-transformed spectral sensitivity functions of the chicks’ four cone-opsins - note match of the C1 tuning to the ‘red’ (LWS) opsin. <bold>l,m</bold>, as (j,k), respectively, for all clusters that showed a strong off-component. Shown are means±SD across all peak-normalised cluster means (<xref ref-type="sec" rid="S18">Methods</xref>) allocated to the OnOff group C<sub>2-13</sub> (brown), and the corresponding normalised entries for the only cluster in the Off group C<sub>1</sub> (black). Note that by and large, clusters’ Off responses exhibited approximately linear contrast-response functions (l) and spectral tunings that were reasonably captured by the LWS opsin (m).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS156212-f003"/></fig><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>On-responses encode wavelength information.</title><p><bold>a-i,</bold> Mean±SEM spike-responses to the 100% WS and all six CS stimuli of On-clusters as indicated, showing spike-histograms (a,d,g), spike counts per On-response during CS stimulation (b,e,h), and normalised mean response amplitudes of all On-clusters that exhibited blue- (c) or red-dominated tunings (f), and for those that are broadly tuned (i). <bold>j,k</bold>, Relationship of ‘spectral dominance’ and ‘spectral tuning’ (<xref ref-type="sec" rid="S18">Methods</xref>) for all clusters’ On- (j) and, where applicable, Off-responses (k). cf. <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplemental Figures 4a,b</xref> for a cell-wise plot of the same data. Symbols above the plots indicate spectral width (from left: broader-, equal-, narrower-than-opsin), while symbols to the side indicate a dominant response to ‘coloured’ (top) or ‘white’ (bottom) stimulation. <bold>l, m</bold>, as <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3m,l</xref>, respectively, but here shown for On-responses. Note that unlike for Off-responses (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>), the spectral tuning of On-responses could generally not be captured by a single opsin (l), and contrast-response functions were generally non-linear (m).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS156212-f004"/></fig><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>OnOff circuits multiplex spectral and temporal information.</title><p><bold>a</bold>, Example spectral kernels for six of the twelve OnOff clusters as indicated. For each cluster, shadings indicate the parts of the kernels that were classed as either colour opponent (brown) or non-opponent (grey, <xref ref-type="sec" rid="S18">Methods</xref>). The timepoint of each cluster’s onset is indicated by a short vertical line (kernel time: -1). <bold>b</bold>, Mean±SD ‘kernel-opponency over normalised time’ for all twelve OnOff clusters C<sub>2-13</sub>, based on the temporal and opponency measures indicated in (a); see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="S18">Methods</xref> for details. On average, OnOff cluster kernels tended to be colour opponent over long timescales (1, brown), but converged onto a non-opponent (-1, brown) period on short time-scales (i.e. closer in time to the spike event at kernel time 0). The time-normalisation was required in view of the very different overall kinetic regimes across clusters. <bold>c-f</bold>, Mean On- (c,e) and Off- (d,f) step responses as indicated for the same OnOff clusters listed in (a), illustrating some of their diversity in kinetics and amplitudes. Note that for On-, but not Off-, red-responses tended to exhibit the largest amplitudes and shortest latencies. The summary plots in (e) and (f) show the mean±SD response amplitudes and latencies of all CS and WS responses for all twelve OnOff clusters, each normalised to their respective red response. <bold>g, h</bold>, Principal component analysis (PCA) of average On- (g) and Off- (h) WS and CS responses across all twelve OnOff clusters. Top: Traces going into the PCA, which comprised all CS responses except UV, which was generally weak, and 5 of the 10 WS responses (every second contrast value, i.e. 100, 80, 60% etc.). middle: First and second principal component, as indicated, and bottom: Peak-normalised loadings (<xref ref-type="sec" rid="S18">Methods</xref>) of each step response onto the two components. Note that for On-, but not Off-, WS and CS step responses followed approximately orthogonal trajectories in this PC space (indicated by the shaded arrows). <bold>i,j</bold>, (as g,h), but computed separately for the six OnOff clusters shown across (a,c,d). By and large, individual OnOff clusters behaved similarly to the population means (g,h).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS156212-f005"/></fig><fig id="F6" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title>Retinal organisation in the context of vertebrate phylogeny.</title><p><bold>a</bold>, approximate vertebrate phylogeny, indicating key events in the evolution of retinal circuits (based on Refs<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">29</xref></sup>): The split of the visual signal into On- and Of-circuits likely predates the divergence of jawed from jawless species in the early Cambrian<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R88">88</xref></sup>, while an ancestral RH-opsin expressing photoreceptor probably gave rise to vertebrate rods and green-cones soon thereafter<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">29</xref></sup> (but see Ref<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R89">89</xref></sup>). Oil droplets are absent in mammals and elasmobranchs, but present in species of fish, amphibians, reptiles and birds, and non-placental mammals<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35">35</xref></sup> – accordingly the mostly likely origin of oil droplets was between the split of cartilaginous and teleost fish, later followed by their loss in early placental mammals. Amphibians further evolved ‘blue’ rods, while diapsid reptiles evolved the double cone that is still present in extant birds. By contrast, placental mammals lost ancestral SWS2 and RH2 single cones, while cartilaginous fish lost SWS1 and SWS2 cones (and sharks also lost LWS cones). The resultant maximal cone-complement is indicated for each lineage: RH1 rods (grey), LWS/double cones (red), RH2 cones (green), SWS2 cones (blue), SWS1 cones (pink) and SWS2 rods (faded blue). <bold>b</bold>, Approximate typical anatomical and functional arrangement of retinal circuits in each lineage. The question marks indicate entries that have not been studied. References for each entry are provided in the relevant sections throughout the main text.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS156212-f006"/></fig></floats-group></article>