<!DOCTYPE article
 PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" article-type="preprint"><?all-math-mml yes?><?use-mml?><?origin ukpmcpa?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">bioRxiv</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>bioRxiv : the preprint server for biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub"/></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">EMS155877</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2022.10.17.512581</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="archive">PPR559263</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Cellular and environmental dynamics influence species-specific extents of organelle gene retention</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pascual</surname><given-names>Belén García</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nordbotten</surname><given-names>Jan M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>Iain G.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CR1">3</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Department of Mathematics, University of Bergen, Bergen, Norway</aff><aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Computational Biology Unit, University of Bergen, Bergen, Norway</aff><author-notes><corresp id="CR1"><label>3</label>correspondence to <email>iain.johnston@uib.no</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted"><day>19</day><month>10</month><year>2022</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="preprint"><day>17</day><month>10</month><year>2022</year></pub-date><permissions><ali:free_to_read/><license><ali:license_ref>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is licensed under a <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0 International license</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p id="P1">Mitochondria and plastids rely on many nuclear-encoded genes, but retain small subsets of the genes they need to function in their own organelle DNA (oDNA). Different species retain different numbers of oDNA genes, and the reasons for these differences are not completely understood. Here we use a mathematical model to explore the hypothesis that the energetic demands imposed by an organism’s changing environment influence how many oDNA genes it retains. The model couples the physical biology of cell processes of gene expression and transport to a supply-and-demand model for the environmental dynamics to which an organism is exposed. The tradeoff between fulfilling metabolic and bioenergetic environmental demands, and retaining genetic integrity, is quantified for a generic gene encoded either in oDNA or in nuclear DNA. Species in environments with high-amplitude, intermediate-frequency oscillations are predicted to retain the most organelle genes, whereas those in less dynamic or noisy environments the fewest. We discuss support for, and insight from, these predictions with oDNA data across eukaryotic taxa, including high oDNA gene counts in sessile organisms exposed to day-night and intertidal oscillations (including plants and algae) and low counts in parasites and fungi.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec id="S1" sec-type="intro"><label>1</label><title>Introduction</title><p id="P2">Most eukaryotic cells contain bioenergetic organelles: mitochondria and, in the case of photosynthetic organisms, plastids (including chloroplasts, being a type of plastid). These organelles were originally independent bacteria with their own genomes, and through processes of endosymbioses, they transferred most of their genes to the nuclear genome of the host cell or lost them completely (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38">Martin et al., 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R50">Sagan, 1967</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R53">Sloan et al., 2018</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">Adams and Palmer, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R49">Roger et al., 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R60">Zaremba-Niedzwiedzka et al., 2017</xref>). However, they have retained a small subset of their genes in their own organelle DNA (oDNA), with oDNA in different species containing strikingly different gene counts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">Adams and Palmer, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">Giannakis et al., 2022</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">Daley and Whelan, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33">Johnston and Williams, 2016</xref>).</p><p id="P3">Transfer to the nucleus provides some genetic advantages to organelle genes that are absent in the organelle genome (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R53">Sloan et al., 2018</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">Adams and Palmer, 2003</xref>). Nuclear encoding helps avoid sources of mutation in the organelle compartments, which include chemical damage from free radicals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">Allen and Raven, 1996</xref>) and replicative errors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36">Kennedy et al., 2013</xref>) (which may be more dominant (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">Itsara et al., 2014</xref>)). Nuclear encoding also helps the avoidance of Muller’s ratchet (the irreversible process of accumulation of deleterious mutations) present in the organelles (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">Daley and Whelan, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">Blanchard and Lynch, 2000</xref>) and allows sexual recombination and DNA repair in the nucleus (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">Allen and Raven, 1996</xref>). Given these advantages, the question of why bioenergetic organelles retain the genes that they do has been debated for years. At the most fundamental level, there are two pertinent subquestions. The first, gene-centric, question is what makes a given gene more or less likely to be retained in oDNA. The second, species-centric, question is what makes a given species more or less likely to retain a higher or lower number of oDNA genes.</p><p id="P4">The first question, why a given gene is more or less likely to be retained in oDNA, has had several potential answers proposed over time (summarised in Giannakis et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">2022</xref>)). It has recently been shown that the combination of these can help explain gene-specific patterns of oDNA retention across organelles and eukaryotes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">Giannakis et al., 2022</xref>). Of particular note here are the hydrophobicity hypothesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R56">von Heijne, 1986</xref>) and the co-localisation for redox regulation (CoRR) hypothesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">Allen and Raven, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">Allen, 2015</xref>). The hydrophobicity hypothesis asserts that hydrophobic gene products are harder to import to the organelle from the outside (either due to translocation into the organelle (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42">Popot and de Vitry, 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">Adams and Palmer, 2003</xref>) or mistargeting (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R56">von Heijne, 1986</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">Björkholm et al., 2015</xref>), proposing that organelle genes encoding hydrophobic gene products are more likely to be retained in the organelles. The CoRR hypothesis proposes that genes are retained in oDNA to allow local, tight control of the energetic machinery (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">Allen, 2015</xref>), so that organelles can better adapt to imposed energetic demands. This idea is supported by the importance of retained oDNA genes in controlling redox processes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38">Martin et al., 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">Allen, 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">Giannakis et al., 2022</xref>).</p><p id="P5">The second question, why some species retain more organelle genes than others, remains more open. There exists substantial diversity in oDNA gene counts across eukaryotes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R49">Roger et al., 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">Giannakis et al., 2022</xref>). Some jakobid protists retain over 60 protein-coding mitochondrial DNA (mtDNA) genes, plants retain fewer and metazoa fewer still with a common 13-protein gene profile shared by a large majority of taxa (including humans). The highest plastid gene counts found so far appear in the group of red alga Rhodophyta with over 200 protein-coding plastid DNA (ptDNA) genes and up to 35 protein-encoding mtDNA genes. In contrast, parasitic species (notably including alveolates) contain very few protein-coding mtDNA genes and some have even lost mtDNA entirely (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">Hjort et al., 2010</xref>). Parasitic organisms can hijack metabolic and energetic budgets of their hosts, so presumably, organelle genes are lost since their bioenergetic organelles have fewer required functions, but how can the diversity of oDNA gene counts in other taxa be explained?</p><p id="P6">To address this species-specific question, we focus on how the energetic demand imposed by the environment changes over time. Following the CoRR idea that retaining genes in oDNA improves organelles’ local responses to changing conditions, we hypothesise that organisms facing large and/or rapid environmental changes in bioenergetic demand require more local control over organelle machinery to respond to these changes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">Johnston, 2019a</xref>). The hypothesis suggests that organisms in stable and low-demand environments (including parasites) require less organelle control, as the production of energy is not so challenging. Organisms subject to more dynamic environmental demands (for example, the diurnal oscillations of light, or semidiurnal oscillations of tide) require tighter control over challenging energetic and metabolic demands, so these organisms are predicted to retain a higher count of oDNA genes.</p><p id="P7">Hypotheses about evolutionary processes can be challenging to test with experiments. Quantitative modelling can shed light on evolutionary pressures and dynamics, as demonstrated by powerful theoretical studies exploring the co-evolution of oDNA and the host cell (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R46">Radzvilavicius et al., 2016</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R47">2017</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R45">2021</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">Hadjivasiliou et al., 2012</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">2013</xref>), and models of the specific features involved in oDNA gene retention (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35">Kelly, 2021</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">Giannakis et al., 2022</xref>), although few quantitative models to our knowledge have explored CoRR in the same depth. Here, to test our hypothesis, we propose and analyse a mathematical model for a given organelle gene in a given organism. This model captures the interplay of cellular processes (like gene expression, import of gene product to the organelle and degradation), environmental dynamics (like the amplitude and frequency of an environmental wave, also understood as the energetic demand placed on the organism) and the proportion of wild-type organelle DNA which allows the organelle to functionally synthesise the gene products it needs. We use the model to probe how environmental dynamics influence the organism’s ability to meet energetic demands for each of the two cases of encoding compartments: the nucleus and the organelle, providing a general quantitative framework to explore links between CoRR, environmental dynamics and gene retention.</p></sec><sec id="S2" sec-type="methods"><label>2</label><title>Methods</title><sec id="S3"><label>2.1</label><title>Model description</title><p id="P8">The mathematical model explores the ability of an organism to meet environmental demands, considering the interplay of cell biological processes and particular model environments. It is summarised in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref> and built up in stages as follows.</p><sec id="S4"><label>2.1.1</label><title>Cell biological processes: gene expression, transport and degradation</title><p id="P9">The set up of the model is for a generic gene encoding organelle machinery. The gene may be encoded in the organelle or in the nucleus of the cell, in which case it must be transported to the organelle through the cytosol. Working at a coarse-grained level, we will use this general picture to describe both mitochondria and plastids. The model has two dynamic variables: <italic>x<sub>m</sub></italic>(<italic>t</italic>) is the available amount of functional gene product in the organelle at time <italic>t</italic> (for example, the various protein subunits of electron transport chain complexes) and <italic>x<sub>c</sub></italic>(<italic>t</italic>) is the available amount of gene product in the cytosol at time <italic>t</italic>.</p><p id="P10">The parameters of the model for the cellular processes are the following non-negative constant rates: <italic>λ</italic> is the synthesis rate of gene product (which will be scaled by the cell’s response to the environment, see below), <italic>D</italic> is the import or transport rate of gene product from the cytosol to the organelle, <italic>ν<sub>m</sub>, ν<sub>c</sub></italic> are the degradation rates of gene product in the organelle and in the cytosol, respectively, and <italic>p</italic> is the proportion of wild-type oDNA, also called the genetic integrity, which allows the synthesis of functional gene product in the organelle. The cell processes whose rates are the ones described above are illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1A</xref>.</p><p id="P11">The parameters <italic>D</italic> and <italic>ν<sub>c</sub></italic> describe the ability of a nuclear-encoded gene product to translocate to its required position in the organelle. These can be used to model different mechanisms proposed for the hydrophobicity hypothesis. One mechanism is that hydrophobic gene products cannot readily be unpacked to import into the organelle (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42">Popot and de Vitry, 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">Adams and Palmer, 2003</xref>), corresponding to a high value of the degradation rate in the cytosol <italic>ν<sub>c</sub></italic>, as the gene product is merely lost and hence can be considered as degraded. Another mechanism is that the gene product is mistargeted, usually to the endoplasmic reticulum (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R56">von Heijne, 1986</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">Björkholm et al., 2015</xref>), so that the import to the organelle takes a much longer time: corresponding to a low value of the transport rate <italic>D</italic>.</p></sec><sec id="S5"><label>2.1.2</label><title>Coupling of the environmental supply-and-demand model and the cell biology processes</title><p id="P12">We denote by <italic>E</italic>(<italic>t</italic>) the energetic demand placed on the cell by the environment. The goal of the cell is to match <italic>x<sub>m</sub></italic>(<italic>t</italic>), the ‘supply’ of gene product present in the organelle, to environmental demand <italic>E</italic>(<italic>t</italic>). We picture the cell as sensing, and able to respond to, environmental demands by expressing genes that support organelle function. Hence we define a feedback signalling function <italic>f</italic>(<italic>E</italic>(<italic>t</italic>), <italic>x<sub>m</sub></italic>(<italic>t</italic>)) that controls the production of gene product as <disp-formula id="FD1"><label>(1)</label><mml:math id="M1"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mtable columnalign="left"><mml:mtr columnalign="left"><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>if</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>&lt;</mml:mo><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr columnalign="left"><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>if</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>≥</mml:mo><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="P13">Since the dynamics depend on the compartment where the organelle gene is encoded (the organelle itself or the nucleus), we use a coefficient <italic>α</italic> as a model index representing the encoding compartment, where <italic>α</italic> = 0 if the gene is in the organelle or <italic>α</italic> = 1 if the gene is in the nucleus.</p><p id="P14">We then have our model of first-order, linear ordinary differential equations describing the instantaneous rates of change of the variables <italic>x<sub>m</sub></italic>(<italic>t</italic>) and <italic>x<sub>c</sub></italic>(<italic>t</italic>) as follows: <disp-formula id="FD2"><label>(2)</label><mml:math id="M2"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mtable columnalign="left"><mml:mtr columnalign="left"><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>ν</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr columnalign="left"><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>ν</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula> for either <italic>α</italic> = 0 or <italic>α</italic> = 1. We take initial conditions (<italic>x<sub>m</sub></italic>(0), <italic>x<sub>c</sub></italic>(0)) = (0, 0), but we focus on long-term behaviour after the corresponding transient periods have disappeared, described below.</p><p id="P15">The mathematical properties of <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD2">Eq (2)</xref> are studied in the appendixes (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Information</xref>), including well-posedness (A.1) together with existence and stability of equilibrium points (A.2 and A.3).</p></sec><sec id="S6"><label>2.1.3</label><title>Bioenergetic cost</title><p id="P16">The model is of supply-and-demand nature by <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD1">Eq (1)</xref>, so as in previous quantitative work (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">Hoitzing et al., 2019</xref>), we can define a cost function that measures how well the organelle supplies the organism with the energy that its environment demands. A high cost corresponds to supply far away from the demand, either surplus or deficit. This cost function is for a specific encoding compartment, so that the compartment incurring the lowest cost is interpreted as the most favourable in which to encode the gene. We define the cost function as the absolute difference between environmental demand <italic>E</italic>(<italic>t</italic>) and supply of functional gene product in the organelle <italic>x<sub>m</sub></italic>(<italic>t</italic>) integrated over the time window [<italic>t<sub>i</sub>, t<sub>f</sub></italic>]: <disp-formula id="FD3"><label>(3)</label><mml:math id="M3"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mo>∫</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>|</mml:mo><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>|</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="P17">This supply-and-demand model is illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1B</xref>.</p><p id="P18">To ensure the robustness of our results we consider different choices of cost functions in the <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplemental Information</xref> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figures S3</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S12</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S13</xref>) and show that the model’s behaviour is similar across several choices.</p></sec><sec id="S7"><label>2.1.4</label><title>Specific types of environmental demands</title><p id="P19">We explore the extent of oDNA genes that an organisms is most likely to retain by looking at the influences that different types of environmental demands <italic>E</italic>(<italic>t</italic>) have on the system. We consider static environments, periodically changing environments and randomly changing environments.</p><p id="P20">Static environments are simply modelled with <italic>E</italic>(<italic>t</italic>) = <italic>a</italic>. For the case of a periodically changing environment, let <italic>a &gt;</italic> 0 be the time-averaged value of environmental demand, <italic>ab</italic> the amplitude of the oscillation (with <italic>b</italic> seen as the relative amplitude), <italic>τ</italic> the characteristic time-scale of the system (for example a day in a physical context) and <italic>k</italic> the frequency of the oscillation relative to the time-scale <italic>τ</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1 (B)</xref>). We then model the energetic demand placed on the organism by a periodically changing environment as a wave <italic>E</italic>(<italic>t</italic>) = <italic>E<sub>p</sub></italic>(<italic>t</italic>) where <italic>E<sub>p</sub></italic>(<italic>t</italic>) is defined as: <disp-formula id="FD4"><label>(4)</label><mml:math id="M4"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>sin</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>π</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mtext>for</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="P21">For a randomly changing environment, we consider <italic>E</italic>(<italic>t</italic>) as a stochastic process which is either uncorrelated white noise (as used in descriptions of terrestrial environments (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R55">Vasseur and Yodzis, 2004</xref>)), or correlated red noise (as used in descriptions of marine and coastal environments (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R55">Vasseur and Yodzis, 2004</xref>)), also called a random walk.</p><p id="P22">For numerical implementation, for a time interval [0, Γ] of the model, we define a partition 0 = <italic>s</italic><sub>0</sub> <italic>&lt; s</italic><sub>1</sub> <italic>&lt; … &lt; s</italic><sub><italic>k</italic>−1</sub> <italic>&lt; s<sub>k</sub></italic> = Γ so that <italic>D</italic> = <italic>{d<sub>i</sub>}<sub>i∈I</sub></italic>, where <italic>d<sub>i</sub></italic> = [<italic>s<sub>i</sub>, s</italic><sub><italic>i</italic>+1</sub>], is the collection of time subintervals. We then consider <italic>D</italic> to be the time-discrete, finite and bounded domain of the time-continuous series of white and red noise. The range of both types of noise is [0, 2<italic>a</italic>], so that the average value is <italic>a</italic> as for the periodically changing environment <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD4">Eq (4)</xref>.</p><p id="P23">For each <italic>i</italic>, we draw a random number <italic>u<sub>i</sub></italic> that has a uniform distribution in [0, 2<italic>a</italic>], i.e. <italic>u<sub>i</sub></italic> ~ <italic>U</italic>(0, 2<italic>a</italic>). White noise <italic>E<sub>w</sub></italic>(<italic>t</italic>) is then defined as: <disp-formula id="FD5"><label>(5)</label><mml:math id="M5"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>w</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mtext>for</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="P24">To define red noise <italic>E<sub>r</sub></italic>(<italic>t</italic>), we write the accumulation of <italic>u<sub>i</sub></italic> with a step-size <italic>|d<sub>i</sub>|</italic> = <italic>s</italic><sub><italic>i</italic>+1</sub> <italic>− s<sub>i</sub></italic>, and we keep it bounded in [0, 2<italic>a</italic>] as follows: <disp-formula id="FD6"><mml:math id="M6"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>max</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>min</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mo>|</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>|</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula> then we define <italic>E<sub>r</sub></italic>(<italic>t</italic>) as: <disp-formula id="FD7"><label>(6)</label><mml:math id="M7"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mtext>for</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p></sec></sec><sec id="S8"><label>2.2</label><title>Biological parameterisations</title><p id="P25">The specific values of the rates involved in our model vary substantially across species, and across genes in the same species. However, we can connect with biological quantities at a coarse-grained level to interpret our model in an informative way (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">Johnston et al., 2014</xref>).</p><p id="P26">We take characteristic rates measured for the case of yeast <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> as reference for our model. The synthesis rate of gene product is a combination of transcription and translation, the rates of which vary substantially across genes; we will explore orders-of-magnitude ranges in these parameters throughout this study. As first estimates, a transcription rate of 0.12 min<sup><italic>−</italic>1</sup> message RNA molecules (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41">Pelechano et al., 2010</xref>) and a translation rate of 0.43 min<sup><italic>−</italic>1</sup> protein molecules (Siwiak and Zielenkiewicz, l 29) give an overall rate of around 0.1 min<sup><italic>−</italic>1</sup>. Therefore, we choose <italic>T</italic> = 10 min to be the time unit in our model, so that the synthesis rate is set as <italic>λ</italic> = 1<italic>T</italic><sup>−1</sup> for simulations by default (the effect of different synthesis rates are shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figures S10</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S11 in the Supplementary Information</xref>). The average scale of protein half-lives in the cytosol of 43 min (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">Belle et al., 2006</xref>) give <italic>ν<sub>c</sub> ≈</italic> 0.1<italic>T</italic><sup>−1</sup>. Protein half-lives in the mitochondrion vary dramatically across hours and days for different genes, suggesting a possible range of <italic>ν<sub>m</sub> ≈</italic> 0.01 <italic>−</italic> 0.1<italic>T</italic><sup>−1</sup> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">Christiano et al., 2014</xref>). Import rates to the mitochondrion also vary substantially across genes, suggesting <italic>D ≈</italic> 0.1 <italic>−</italic> 10<italic>T</italic><sup>−1</sup> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R51">Schäfer et al., 2022</xref>). The model parameters that we map therefore contain a range of values that correspond to plausible dynamics for real genes. Different eukaryotic species will have different values for these parameters, but the ranges we consider are compatible with observations across kingdoms (for example, Li et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37">2017</xref>)).</p><p id="P27">We set a time window [0, 2 <italic>×</italic> 144] of two days in <italic>T</italic> time units for the numerical simulations. To remove the transient periods determined by the initial conditions (<italic>x<sub>m</sub></italic>(0), <italic>x<sub>c</sub></italic>(0)) = (0, 0) and focus on the equilibrium phases of the system, we use the first day [0, 144] as an equilibration step. Then we take the solutions of the model and compute the respective cost functions <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD3">Eq (3)</xref> only for the last full day, which corresponds to the time window [144, 2 <italic>×</italic> 144].</p><p id="P28">In the periodic environment <italic>E<sub>p</sub></italic>(<italic>t</italic>) <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD4">Eq (4)</xref>, we set the characteristic time-scale <italic>τ</italic> to be a full 24 hours period in <italic>T</italic> units, i.e. <italic>τ</italic> = 144<italic>T</italic> (<italic>τ</italic> = 144<italic>T</italic> = 144 <italic>×</italic> 10 min = 24 hours). So <italic>k</italic> = 1 corresponds to diurnal oscillation (as with day-night cycles), and <italic>k</italic> = 2 to semidiurnal oscillation (as with tides).</p><p id="P29">The wild-type proportion of oDNA <italic>p</italic> is a coarse-grained measure of oDNA integrity in our model. Lower <italic>p</italic> corresponds to more oDNA damage, compromising the expression of functional organelle machinery; <italic>p</italic> = 1 corresponds to perfect oDNA and hence the maximum possible expression capacity. The propensity for oDNA damage in an organism, both within a lifetime and across generations, will act to reduce <italic>p</italic>. Rather than attempting to set this value to match a given biological instance, we will explore the behaviour of the system as it varies. Furthermore, <italic>p</italic> can be pictured as a snapshot value from the ongoing process of oDNA damage accumulation, segregation, and mitigation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31">Johnston, 2019b</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">Guo et al., 2013</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S9"><label>2.3</label><title>Numerical implementation</title><p id="P30">The numerical simulations and visualisations of results were all performed in Python. The model of ordinary differential equations presented in <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD2">Eq (2)</xref> was solved using the numerical integrator scipy.integrate.odeint that uses the method LSODA from the FORTRAN library odepack (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">Hindmarsh, 1983</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R44">Radhakrishnan and Hindmarsh, 1993</xref>). The heatmaps were made using seaborn (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R57">Waskom, 2021</xref>) and the time-lines and phase portraits were made using matplotlib.pyplot (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">Hunter, 2007</xref>). The integral of the cost function <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD3">Eq (3)</xref> was computed using the composite Simpson’s rule using scipy.integrate.simps. Mathematical expressions were implemented using NumPy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">Harris et al., 2020</xref>) and mpmath (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">Johansson et al., 2013</xref>). The code can be found in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/StochasticBiology/Environmental-oDNA-retention.git">https://github.com/StochasticBiology/Environmental-oDNA-retention.git</ext-link>.</p></sec><sec id="S10"><label>2.4</label><title>Bioinformatics</title><p id="P31">The curation of oDNA gene counts follows and builds upon the pipeline for eukaryotic oDNA analysis in (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">Giannakis et al., 2022</xref>). All available complete mtDNA and ptDNA sequences were downloaded from RefSeq (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40">O’Leary et al., 2015</xref>). Gene annotations were systematised with BioPython (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">Cock et al., 2009</xref>) according to a manually-curated list of label substitutions, taken from and validated in (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">Giannakis et al., 2022</xref>). The subset of protein-coding genes in these lists (omitting RNA genes, gene fragments, open reading frames not known to encode a protein, and various other anomalous entries) present in each species’ oDNA was then recorded. The species in the dataset were embedded in a Common Taxonomy Tree (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">Federhen, 2012</xref>) and the members of each basal eukaryotic clade compiled into a corresponding set using R (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43">R Core Team, 2020</xref>), with libraries ggplot2 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R59">Wickham, 2016</xref>), gridExtra (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">Auguie, 2017</xref>), and phytools (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R48">Revell, 2012</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="S11" sec-type="results"><label>3</label><title>Results</title><p id="P32">Our model, described in Methods, pictures the environment as imposing metabolic and bioenergetic demands on the cell, which may be static or vary periodically or randomly over time. This may correspond, for example, to diurnal variation in light levels, temperature, animal activity, and so on; to semidiurnal tidal variation in oxygenation and salinity; or to more rapid variation due to bursts of activity, fluctuating shade, or other conditions. The cell expresses organelle genes to produce gene products in an attempt to supply the required machinery to meet this demand. Genes may be encoded in either the nucleus, in which case their gene products must be imported to the organelle, or in the organelle, in which case the genes are potentially subject to mutational damage. We integrate the absolute difference between supply and demand over a simulated time window to calculate the cost for each compartment <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD3">Eq (3)</xref> for a given parameterisation.</p><p id="P33">There are several parameters in the model corresponding to cell biological and environmental quantities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39">Milo and Phillips, 2015</xref>). Some key parameters are the synthesis of gene product <italic>λ</italic>, the transport <italic>D</italic> and the degradation of gene product in the organelle <italic>ν<sub>m</sub></italic> and in the cytosol <italic>ν<sub>c</sub></italic>. We also consider a measure of oDNA integrity, interpreted as the proportion <italic>p</italic> of wild-type, functional oDNA. Rather than attempt an exhaustive characterisation of the full parameter space in the main text, we focus on several cases which illustrate the more general trends, and support these examples with other results in the <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Information (SI)</xref>. We explore biologically plausible ranges of parameters, with simulation time unit <italic>T</italic> = 10 min setting the scale for other parameters (see Methods), and simulating for a time-scale of a full day after allowing transient behaviours to disappear.</p><sec id="S12"><label>3.1</label><title>Static environments</title><p id="P34">To focus on the influence that the cell biological parameters (see Methods), have in the model, we first look at the case of a static environment <italic>E</italic>(<italic>t</italic>) = <italic>a</italic> for all <italic>t</italic>.</p><p id="P35">In <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Appendix A.2</xref> (SI) we algebraically find the solutions of the system when it is in equilibrium, and from there we can directly compute the instantaneous cost <italic>C<sub>α</sub></italic> for encoding compartment <italic>α</italic> as the absolute difference between the energetic demand <italic>E</italic>(<italic>t</italic>) = <italic>a</italic> and the supply of gene product in the organelle <italic>x<sub>m</sub></italic>(<italic>t</italic>). We look at the ratio between the instantaneous cost for the organelle-encoding strategy (<italic>α</italic> = 0) and the nuclear-encoding strategy (<italic>α</italic> = 1): <disp-formula id="FD8"><mml:math id="M8"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>ν</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>ν</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>ν</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>ν</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>ν</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>ν</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>ν</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="P36">Here, if <italic>C</italic><sub>0</sub><italic>/C</italic><sub>1</sub> &gt; 1, then encoding the gene in the nucleus is the most favourable strategy, and if <italic>C</italic><sub>0</sub><italic>/C</italic><sub>1</sub> &lt; 1, then encoding in the organelle is the most favourable strategy. The first condition <italic>C</italic><sub>0</sub><italic>/C</italic><sub>1</sub> &gt; 1 holds if <italic>D &gt; p</italic>(<italic>D</italic> + <italic>ν<sub>c</sub></italic>), and this is the case when <italic>D</italic> is high (the import to the organelle is fast), <italic>ν<sub>c</sub></italic> is low (gene product is not lost in the cytosol so the import to the organelle is more efficient) and <italic>p</italic> is low (the organelle has a significant load of mutant oDNA that prevents the synthesis of gene product). The second condition <italic>C</italic><sub>0</sub><italic>/C</italic><sub>1</sub> &lt; 1 holds if <italic>D &lt; p</italic>(<italic>D</italic>+<italic>ν<sub>c</sub></italic>), and this is the case when <italic>D</italic> is low (the import to the organelle is slow), <italic>ν<sub>c</sub></italic> is high (a lot of gene product is degraded and therefore not so much is being imported to the organelle) and <italic>p</italic> is high (there is good proportion of wild-type oDNA to synthesise gene product). If we have the special case of no degradation in the organelle <italic>ν<sub>m</sub></italic> = 0, then <italic>C</italic><sub>0</sub><italic>/C</italic><sub>1</sub> = 1, meaning that both strategies are equally favourable. These trends are clearly observable in the numerical results in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2A</xref>, illustrating a moderate level of oDNA damage (<italic>p</italic> = 0.75). Without oDNA damage (<italic>p</italic> = 1), there is never a reason to favour the nuclear compartment, and nuclear-encoded costs at best match (but never drop below) organelle-encoded costs. <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure S2</xref> in the SI explores higher values of <italic>p</italic>.</p><p id="P37">Here and throughout, the parameters of the model provide a way of connecting the theory to specific genes. Gene products with high turnover correspond to a high <italic>ν<sub>m</sub></italic>; long-lived products have a low <italic>ν<sub>m</sub></italic>. Gene products prone to mistargeting (which could include hydrophobic products under the ‘mistargeting’ picture (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">Björkholm et al., 2015</xref>)) have a low <italic>D</italic>; those challenging to import to the organelle (which could include hydrophobic products under the ‘unfolding’ picture (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R56">von Heijne, 1986</xref>)) have a high <italic>ν<sub>c</sub></italic>. A value of <italic>p &lt;</italic> 1 corresponds to the expectation that genes encoded in oDNA will accumulate some level of genetic damage over time; lower <italic>p</italic> corresponds to more damage, while higher <italic>p</italic> corresponds to more robust oDNA maintenance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32">Johnston and Burgstaller, 2019</xref>).</p><p id="P38">Degradation rates play an important role in the model. The degradation rate in the organelle <italic>ν<sub>m</sub></italic> limits the ability of the cell to meet environmental demand: the organelle is prevented from having as much gene product as it needs, and the variable <italic>x<sub>m</sub></italic>(<italic>t</italic>) is always damped with respect to an environmental function <italic>E</italic>(<italic>t</italic>). For low <italic>ν<sub>m</sub></italic> (long-lived gene products), no significant amount of gene product is being lost and the total amount in the organelle is more correctly modulated by the signalling function <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD1">Eq (1)</xref>. For <italic>ν<sub>m</sub></italic> = 0 the system can perfectly satisfy environmental demand (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Appendix A.4 in the SI</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S13"><label>3.2</label><title>Randomly changing environments</title><p id="P39">Here we analyse our model for randomly varying energetic demands (see Methods). The environments behave either like uncorrelated white noise <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD5">Eq (5)</xref> or like correlated red noise <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD7">Eq (6)</xref>. We see in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref> that the plots for static, uncorrelated and correlated noisy environments show very similar patterns, so we can infer that the same principles for static environmental demands discussed in <xref ref-type="sec" rid="S12">Section 3.1</xref> also hold for noisy ones. This is because the system tends to adapt to an average environmental demand (either a constant for uncorrelated noise or a moving average for red noise) and fluctuations around this adapted average challenge the system in similar ways.</p><p id="P40">In <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure S4</xref> in the SI we see that when there is some degradation in the organelle, <italic>ν<sub>m</sub></italic> = 0.5, and no degradation in the cytosol, <italic>ν<sub>c</sub></italic> = 0, for uncorrelated white noise the costs for both encoding compartments are almost identical. For correlated red noise, the cost for the nuclear-encoding compartment is lower. These examples agree with the correspondent points in the heatmaps in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref> for <italic>D</italic> = 0.1 and <italic>D</italic> = 1.</p></sec><sec id="S14"><label>3.3</label><title>Periodically changing environments</title><p id="P41">Next, we consider oscillating environmental demands as defined in <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD4">Eq (4)</xref>. For different frequencies <italic>k</italic> and time-averaged demands <italic>a</italic>, we look at when the amplitude takes a maximal value (<italic>b</italic> = 1), representing higher-magnitude environment oscillations, and when the amplitude is lower (<italic>b</italic> = 0.5), representing an environment closer to the constant case. Qualitatively, the higher the relative amplitude <italic>b</italic> and the frequency <italic>k</italic>, the more dramatically changing the environment is. We see in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref> that encoding the organelle gene in the organelle is much more favourable the more the environment changes, that is, for high amplitude <italic>b</italic> = 1 and every frequency when the transport is slow (<italic>D</italic> = 0.01, corresponding to hard-to-import gene products), and for high frequencies when the transport is faster (<italic>D</italic> = 0.1 and <italic>D</italic> = 1). This agrees with the hypothesis that organisms tend to retain more genes in their oDNA if their environments dramatically and rapidly change, and suggests that those harder to import (possibly including hydrophobic products (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">Björkholm et al., 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R56">von Heijne, 1986</xref>)) will be the most retained.</p><p id="P42">Strikingly, organelle encoding is most strongly favoured at intermediate frequencies <italic>k</italic> of environmental fluctuation, as seen in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>. The specific values of these frequencies depend on the transport rate: for lower transport rates, the peak value for <italic>k</italic> is lower, and for higher transport rates it is higher. Whether this translates to an overall favouring of the organelle compartment also depends on cytoplasmic degradation and oDNA wild-type proportion.</p><p id="P43">On the other side, the nuclear-encoding case is most strongly favourable for a less dynamic environment. We see in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref> that this compartment begins to dominate for lower amplitude <italic>b</italic> = 0.5, and is completely dominant under these parameterisations for a constant environment (<italic>k</italic> = 0) if the proportion of wild-type oDNA <italic>p</italic> is less than 1. For the case when <italic>p</italic> = 1 (perfect oDNA integrity can be retained), we see in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figures S5</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S6</xref> in the SI that the nuclear-encoding case is never favoured, by the reasons described above. Following the trends observed in the static environment, decreased organelle damage <italic>p</italic> = 1 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figures S5</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S6</xref> in the SI), or increased cytoplasmic degradation <italic>ν<sub>c</sub></italic> = 1 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figures S7</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S9</xref> in the SI), has the straightforward effect of shifting the trends in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref> quite uniformly across parameterisations to favour organelle encoding.</p><p id="P44">We can again use the parameterisations of the model to consider predicted gene-to-gene behaviour. As an illustration, consider three gene products: one hydrophobic and challenging to import (with <italic>D</italic> = 0.01), one intermediate (with <italic>D</italic> = 0.1) and a less hydrophobic product with less import difficulty (with <italic>D</italic> = 1). Consider also two sets of environmental conditions, <italic>k</italic> = 4 (intermediate frequency) and <italic>k</italic> = 10 (high frequency) with the same <italic>b</italic>. Under these conditions and the other biologically plausible parameters in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>, for intermediate frequency <italic>k</italic> = 4 only the most hydrophobic product (for <italic>D</italic> = 0.01) is favoured in the organelle with the others (for <italic>D</italic> = 0.01 and <italic>D</italic> = 1) favoured in the nucleus. For <italic>k</italic> = 10 only the most hydrophilic (<italic>D</italic> = 1) will remain in the nucleus. <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure S5</xref> in the SI also supports this picture for different proportions of wild-type oDNA <italic>p</italic>.</p><p id="P45">Lastly, from the algebraic solutions of the model in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Appendix A.4 in the SI</xref>, we can see explicitly how an oscillatory environment challenges the system, as there is an absence of a perfectly synchronised solution <italic>x<sub>m</sub></italic>(<italic>t</italic>) to <italic>E<sub>p</sub></italic>(<italic>t</italic>) <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD4">Eq (4)</xref>. This is because for both organelle-encoding and nuclear-encoding cases the only way the system can reach the time-averaged demand <italic>a</italic> in <italic>E<sub>p</sub></italic>(<italic>t</italic>) is if <italic>ν<sub>m</sub></italic> = 0, but then it cannot enter to decay phase when the environmental wave <italic>E<sub>p</sub></italic>(<italic>t</italic>) goes down. This scenario places the system out-of-phase with respect to the environmental wave, and therefore leads to a high cost. This is seen in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure S1</xref> (vi) in the SI. Moreover, for the organelle-encoding case, the variable <italic>x<sub>m</sub></italic> cannot match the fluctuating environment simultaneously in phase and in amplitude, as discussed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Appendix A.4</xref>. For the nuclear-encoding case, a solution in phase with environmental demand is theoretically possible, as shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Appendix A.4</xref>, but requires unphysical parameter values (either <italic>Dλ, Dν<sub>m</sub></italic> or <italic>ν<sub>m</sub>ν<sub>c</sub></italic> must tend to infinity). This analysis shows that perfect adaptation is not possible with reasonable parameters in biology.</p></sec><sec id="S15"><label>3.4</label><title>Connection with eukaryotic taxa</title><p id="P46">In a periodically changing environment <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD4">Eq (4)</xref>, the frequency <italic>k</italic> gives the number of environmental oscillations per day: corresponding to diurnal oscillation if <italic>k</italic> = 1, or to semidiurnal oscillation if <italic>k</italic> = 2. For several plausible parameterisations of genetic properties (rates of expression, import, and degradation), these <italic>k</italic> values fall in the region where organelle encoding is most favoured. In particular, organelle encoding is strongly favoured in the face of diurnal or semidiurnal oscillation for genes with low <italic>D</italic>, that is, those that are challenging to import to the organelle (perhaps due to hydrophobicity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">Björkholm et al., 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R56">von Heijne, 1986</xref>)). In such cases, we expect species experiencing strong diurnal or semidiurnal variation in their organelle demands to favour organelle encoding of sets of oDNA genes that appear in nuclear DNA in other species.</p><p id="P47">To explore the feasibility of this picture, we extracted the distributions of retained gene counts across all eukaryotes with sequenced organelle DNA (see Methods). Corresponding to our original hypothesis, and the diurnal-semidiurnal predictions of this theory, we asked whether oDNA gene counts in species subjected to such environmental oscillations were higher than those in environments with different (and particularly more limited) dynamics.</p><p id="P48"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5A-B</xref> show the statistics of oDNA gene counts by eukaryotic clade. First, intracellular parasites largely exist inside the highly buffered cells of their host, presented with constant, low demand on their organelles. Correspondingly, they retain very few oDNA genes. This is visible in the mtDNA counts of apicomplexans and subsets of fungi and metazoa. Apicomplexans also possess a plastid-like organelle called the apicoplast, which again contains very few oDNA genes. Free-living fungi often exist on relatively stable nutrient sources like decaying wood or leaf matter (posing few temporal fluctuations in demand), and also retain few mtDNA genes. Plants (within Viridiplantae) are typically subject to diurnal light and temperature changes and, being sessile, cannot move away from other environmental changes, and they retain comparatively many oDNA genes. Sessile, intertidal eukaryotes (including multicellular red and brown algae) face both strong diurnal light fluctuations and semidiurnal tidal variation in oxygen, temperature, and salinity, and they retain the highest plastid DNA (ptDNA) counts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">Giannakis et al., 2022</xref>). There will certainly be other factors influencing where a given gene is encoded, including the evolutionary history of a species and many other features. We here just aim to draw attention to some examples which are compatible with the predictions of our theory.</p><p id="P49">Our theory suggests that the tradeoff between response to environmental demands and maintaining genetic integrity will determine which compartment is favoured for a given gene in a given organism of a specific species. In addition to the different environments described above, different species maintain oDNA integrity to different extents. Plants have lower sequence mutation rates in oDNA than nDNA (although they have pronounced structural diversity in oDNA) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">Johnston, 2019a</xref>), due at least in part for their capacity for oDNA recombination (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">Edwards et al., 2021</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">Chen, 2013</xref>), suggesting that their <italic>p</italic> in our model would be higher and organelle encoding would be further favoured. Metazoa and fungi have high oDNA mutation rates, suggesting a lower <italic>p</italic> and corresponding relative favouring of nuclear encoding.</p></sec></sec><sec id="S16" sec-type="discussion"><label>4</label><title>Discussion</title><p id="P50">Our model describes a link between the environmental dynamics that an organism of a given species faces and the extent to which organelle gene retention is favoured (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5C</xref>). Holding other factors equal, organisms experiencing high-amplitude and/or intermediate-frequency oscillations in environmental demand will favour oDNA encoding of genes more than organisms in less periodic environments. The scale of the rates and values involved mean that this picture could help explain the high oDNA retention counts of organisms in tidal environments and subject to diurnal light oscillations, and the low retention counts in organisms in buffered, stable, or noisy environments. To our knowledge, this is the first theoretical approach attempting to explain these patterns. Of note is the connection between biophysical features governing the cell biological behaviour of gene products and the ability of the cell to respond to changing environments: a connection between the hydrophobicity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R56">von Heijne, 1986</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">Björkholm et al., 2015</xref>) and CoRR (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">Allen and Raven, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">Allen, 2015</xref>) hypotheses, often viewed as competing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">Giannakis et al., 2022</xref>).</p><p id="P51">A natural extension to the work presented throughout this paper is to consider oDNA damage inheritance and buildup in an evolutionary time-scale, instead of analysing the system for shorter, ecological time-scales where the proportion of damaged oDNA 1 <italic>− p</italic> is maintained constant. Another natural target for future work involves the transitions between encoding compartments, as any shift of an oDNA gene to the nucleus will require a transient state in which the gene is encoded in both compartments. Future theoretical work is aimed to address these questions. As with most theories about large-scale evolutionary processes, a direct connection with experimental testing is challenging. It may be possible to experimentally test these ideas further by subjecting otherwise similar organisms that differ in oDNA retention profiles to artificial fluctuating environments and assaying their performance, for example, algae in fluctuating light conditions.</p><p id="P52">We do not (and cannot) claim that this theory explains the full diversity of oDNA retention profiles across eukaryotes: as with parallel gene-specific questions, it is likely that several factors contribute together. However, although the present-day oDNA gene profile of an organism is shaped by many factors over its entire evolutionary history (including serial endosymbiosis events in the case of plastids (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34">Keeling, 2010</xref>)), and not just its present-day situation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27">Janouškovec et al., 2017</xref>), some biological observations do at least qualitatively suggest that the compatibility of gene profiles of modern organisms and their environments does not conflict with our predictions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>). Recent work has shown that the transfer of mtDNA to the nucleus is ongoing in modern humans, estimating that one in every few thousand births experiences a <italic>de novo</italic> transfer of mtDNA material (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R58">Wei et al., 2022</xref>). It is known that transfer of ptDNA to the nucleus occurs frequently even over an individual plant’s lifetime (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R54">Stegemann et al., 2003</xref>). This ever-present potential for gene transfer suggests that modern organisms’ environments may indeed provide some selective advantage to the oDNA retention profiles they have adopted, and that ongoing selective pressures act to shape oDNA in modern eukaryotes.</p><p id="P53">In parallel with this species-specific picture, gene-specific features have been found to rank individual genes from ‘most potential to be retained’ to ‘least potential to be retained’ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">Giannakis et al., 2022</xref>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5C</xref>). Those with most retention potential typically encode the most hydrophobic products (corresponding in our model to a high degradation in the cytosol <italic>ν<sub>c</sub></italic> or slow import of gene product to the organelle <italic>D</italic>, and hence substantial loss in translocation to the organelle), or those most central to the assembly and production of respiratory or photosynthetic complexes (and hence most linked to supplying energetic demands) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">Giannakis et al., 2022</xref>). This last feature is connected via by the CoRR hypothesis to the retention of organelle genes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">Allen, 2015</xref>). Those with least retention potential, by contrast, may experience fewer barriers to translocation and be less essential for fulfilling environmental demands. Taking these pictures together, we can say that species in environments where retention is disfavoured will only retain those gene with highest retention potential, whereas species in environments where retention is more favoured will retain more of the lower-potential genes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5C</xref>). Our model thus connects cell biology, environmental demands, and genetic location to propose how specific combinations of gene and species properties shape the patterns of oDNA retention across species.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="SM"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1"><label>Supplementary Information</label><media xlink:href="EMS155877-supplement-Supplementary_Information.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" id="d47aAdEbB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack id="S17"><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>This project has received funding from the European Research Council (ERC) under the European Union’s Horizon 2020 research and innovation programme (Grant agreement No. 805046 (EvoConBiO) to IGJ). IGJ gratefully acknowledges support from the Peder Sather Center.</p></ack><ref-list><ref id="R1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evolution of mitochondrial gene content: gene loss and transfer to the nucleus</article-title><source>Molecular phylogenetics and evolution</source><year>2003</year><volume>29</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>380</fpage><lpage>395</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Why chloroplasts and mitochondria retain their own genomes and genetic systems: Colocation for redox regulation of gene expression</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source><year>2015</year><volume>112</volume><issue>33</issue><fpage>10231</fpage><lpage>10238</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>WF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Why have organelles retained genomes?</article-title><source>Cell systems</source><year>2016</year><volume>2</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>70</fpage><lpage>72</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Raven</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Free-radical-induced mutation vs redox regulation: costs and benefits of genes in organelles</article-title><source>J Mol Evol</source><year>1996</year><volume>42</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>482</fpage><lpage>492</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><element-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Auguie</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><source>gridExtra: Miscellaneous Functions for “Grid” Graphics R package version 2.3</source><year>2017</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Belle</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanay</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bitincka</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Shamir</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>O’Shea</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quantification of protein half-lives in the budding yeast proteome</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2006</year><month>Aug</month><day>29</day><volume>103</volume><issue>35</issue><fpage>13004</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><comment>p.13004 right column 4th paragraph. ID BioNumbers: 104151</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Björkholm</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Harish</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hagström</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Ernst</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Andersson</surname><given-names>SGE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mitochondrial genomes are retained by selective constraints on protein targeting</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</source><year>2015</year><volume>112</volume><issue>33</issue><fpage>10154</fpage><lpage>10161</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blanchard</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Lynch</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Organellar genes: why do they end up in the nucleus?</article-title><source>Trends in Genetics</source><year>2000</year><volume>16</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>315</fpage><lpage>320</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Burton</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name></person-group><source>Volterra Integral and Differential Equations</source><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name><year>2005</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>XJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mechanism of homologous recombination and implications for aging-related deletions in mitochondrial dna</article-title><source>Microbiology and Molecular Biology Reviews</source><year>2013</year><volume>77</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>476</fpage><lpage>496</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Christiano</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagaraj</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Fröhlich</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Walther</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Global proteome turnover analyses of the yeasts s. cerevisiae and s. pombe</article-title><source>Cell reports</source><year>2014</year><volume>9</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>1959</fpage><lpage>1965</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cock</surname><given-names>PJA</given-names></name><name><surname>Antao</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Chapman</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Dalke</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Friedberg</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamelryck</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kauff</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilczynski</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>de Hoon</surname><given-names>MJL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biopython: freely available Python tools for computational molecular biology and bioinformatics</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2009</year><volume>25</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>1422</fpage><lpage>1423</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coddington</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Levinson</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Theory of Ordinary Differential Equations</chapter-title><source>International series in pure and applied mathematics</source><publisher-name>McGraw-Hill</publisher-name><year>1955</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Daley</surname><given-names>DO</given-names></name><name><surname>Whelan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Why genes persist in organelle genomes</article-title><source>Genome Biology</source><year>2005</year><volume>6</volume><issue>110</issue></element-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Røyrvik</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name><name><surname>Chustecki</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Giannakis</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Glastad</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Radzvilavicius</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>IG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Avoiding organelle mutational meltdown across eukaryotes with or without a germline bottleneck</article-title><source>PLoS biology</source><year>2021</year><volume>19</volume><issue>4</issue><elocation-id>e3001153</elocation-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Federhen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The ncbi taxonomy database</article-title><source>Nucleic acids research</source><year>2012</year><volume>40</volume><issue>Database issue</issue><fpage>D136</fpage><lpage>D143</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Giannakis</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Arrowsmith</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Richards</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Gasparini</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Chustecki</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Røyrvik</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>IG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evolutionary inference across eukaryotes identifies universal features shaping organelle gene retention</article-title><source>Cell Systems</source><year>2022</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>C-I</given-names></name><name><surname>Sheng</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Winther</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Boice</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Shyr</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Very low-level heteroplasmy mtdna variations are inherited in humans</article-title><source>Journal of Genetics and Genomics</source><year>2013</year><volume>40</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>607</fpage><lpage>615</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hadjivasiliou</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Lane</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Seymour</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Pomiankowski</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dynamics of mitochondrial inheritance in the evolution of binary mating types and two sexes</article-title><source>Proceedings of the Royal Society B: Biological Sciences</source><year>2013</year><volume>280</volume><issue>1769</issue><elocation-id>20131920</elocation-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hadjivasiliou</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Pomiankowski</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Seymour</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lane</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Selection for mitonuclear co-adaptation could favour the evolution of two sexes</article-title><source>Proceedings of the Royal Society B: Biological Sciences</source><year>2012</year><volume>279</volume><issue>1734</issue><fpage>1865</fpage><lpage>1872</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Millman</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>van der Walt</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Gommers</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Virtanen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Cournapeau</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Wieser</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Berg</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Array programming with NumPy</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2020</year><volume>585</volume><issue>7825</issue><fpage>357</fpage><lpage>362</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hindmarsh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Odepack, a systematized collection of ode solvers</article-title><source>Scientific Computing</source><year>1983</year><elocation-id>978-0444866073</elocation-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hjort</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldberg</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsaousis</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirt</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name><surname>Embley</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diversity and reductive evolution of mitochondria among microbial eukaryotes</article-title><source>Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society B: Biological Sciences</source><year>2010</year><volume>365</volume><issue>1541</issue><fpage>713</fpage><lpage>727</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hoitzing</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Gammage</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Haute</surname><given-names>LV</given-names></name><name><surname>Minczuk</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>IG</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Energetic costs of cellular and therapeutic control of stochastic mitochondrial dna populations</article-title><source>PLOS Computational Biology</source><year>2019</year><volume>15</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>27</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hunter</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Matplotlib: A 2d graphics environment</article-title><source>Computing in Science &amp; Engineering</source><year>2007</year><volume>9</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>90</fpage><lpage>95</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Itsara</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kennedy</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hewitt</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanchez-Contreras</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Cardozo-Pelaez</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Pallanck</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Oxidative stress is not a major contributor to somatic mitochondrial dna mutations</article-title><source>PLOS Genetics</source><year>2014</year><volume>10</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>13</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Janouškovec</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Tikhonenkov</surname><given-names>DV</given-names></name><name><surname>Burki</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Howe</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name><surname>Rohwer</surname><given-names>FL</given-names></name><name><surname>Mylnikov</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Keeling</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A new lineage of eukaryotes illuminates early mitochondrial genome reduction</article-title><source>Current Biology</source><year>2017</year><volume>27</volume><issue>23</issue><fpage>3717</fpage><lpage>3724</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><element-citation publication-type="web"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Johansson</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>mpmath: a Python library for arbitrary-precision floating-point arithmetic (version 0.18)</source><year>2013</year><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mpmath.org/">http://mpmath.org/</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Rickett</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Explicit tracking of uncertainty increases the power of quantitative rule-of-thumb reasoning in cell biology</article-title><source>Biophysical Journal</source><year>2014</year><volume>107</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>2612</fpage><lpage>2617</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>IG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tension and resolution: Dynamic, evolving populations of organelle genomes within plant cells</article-title><source>Molecular Plant</source><year>2019a</year><volume>12</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>764</fpage><lpage>783</lpage><comment>Plant Systems Biology</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>IG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Varied mechanisms and models for the varying mitochondrial bottleneck</article-title><source>Frontiers in Cell and Developmental Biology</source><year>2019b</year><volume>7</volume></element-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>IG</given-names></name><name><surname>Burgstaller</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evolving mtdna populations within cells</article-title><source>Biochemical Society Transactions</source><year>2019</year><volume>47</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>1367</fpage><lpage>1382</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>IG</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evolutionary inference across eukaryotes identifies specific pressures favoring mitochondrial gene retention</article-title><source>Cell Systems</source><year>2016</year><volume>2</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>101</fpage><lpage>111</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Keeling</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The endosymbiotic origin, diversification and fate of plastids</article-title><source>Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society B: Biological Sciences</source><year>2010</year><volume>365</volume><issue>1541</issue><fpage>729</fpage><lpage>748</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The economics of organellar gene loss and endosymbiotic gene transfer</article-title><source>Genome Biology</source><year>2021</year><volume>22</volume><issue>345</issue></element-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kennedy</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Salk</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmitt</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Loeb</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ultra-sensitive sequencing reveals an age-related increase in somatic mitochondrial mutations that are inconsistent with oxidative damage</article-title><source>PLOS Genetics</source><year>2013</year><volume>9</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>10</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R37"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Fenske</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Trösch</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Pružinská</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Millar</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Changes in specific protein degradation rates in arabidopsis thaliana reveal multiple roles of lon1 in mitochondrial protein homeostasis</article-title><source>The Plant Journal</source><year>2017</year><volume>89</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>458</fpage><lpage>471</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R38"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>WF</given-names></name><name><surname>Garg</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zimorski</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Endosymbiotic theories for eukaryote origin</article-title><source>Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society B</source><year>2015</year><volume>370</volume><issue>1678</issue></element-citation></ref><ref id="R39"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Milo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><source>Cell biology by the numbers</source><publisher-name>Garland Science</publisher-name><year>2015</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R40"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>O’Leary</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Brister</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Ciufo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Haddad</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>McVeigh</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Rajput</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Robbertse</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith-White</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Ako-Adjei</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Astashyn</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Reference sequence (RefSeq) database at NCBI: current status, taxonomic expansion, and functional annotation</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Research</source><year>2015</year><volume>44</volume><issue>D1</issue><fpage>D733</fpage><lpage>D745</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R41"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pelechano</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Chávez</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Pérez-Ortín</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A complete set of nascent transcription rates for yeast genes</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2010</year><month>Nov</month><day>16</day><volume>5</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>5</fpage><comment>left column 2nd paragraph. ID BioNumbers: 106766</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="R42"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Popot</surname><given-names>J-L</given-names></name><name><surname>de Vitry</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>On the microassembly of integral membrane proteins</article-title><source>Annual Review of Biophysics and Biophysical Chemistry</source><year>1990</year><volume>19</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>369</fpage><lpage>403</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2194481</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R43"><element-citation publication-type="book"><collab>R Core Team</collab><source>R: A Language and Environment for Statistical Computing</source><publisher-name>R Foundation for Statistical Computing</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Vienna, Austria</publisher-loc><year>2020</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R44"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Radhakrishnan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hindmarsh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><source>Description and use of lsode, the livermore solver for ordinary differential equations, Technical report</source><publisher-name>Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory</publisher-name><year>1993</year><month>December</month><comment>UCRL-ID-113855</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="R45"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Radzvilavicius</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Layh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Dowling</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>IG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sexually antagonistic evolution of mitochondrial and nuclear linkage</article-title><source>Journal of Evolutionary Biology</source><year>2021</year><volume>34</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>757</fpage><lpage>766</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R46"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Radzvilavicius</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Hadjivasiliou</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Pomiankowski</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lane</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Selection for mitochondrial quality drives evolution of the germline</article-title><source>PLoS Biology</source><year>2016</year><volume>14</volume><issue>12</issue><elocation-id>e2000410</elocation-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R47"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Radzvilavicius</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Lane</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Pomiankowski</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sexual conflict explains the extraordinary diversity of mechanisms regulating mitochondrial inheritance</article-title><source>BMC biology</source><year>2017</year><volume>15</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>12</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R48"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Revell</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>phytools: An R package for phylogenetic comparative biology (and other things)</article-title><source>Methods in Ecology and Evolution</source><year>2012</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>217</fpage><lpage>223</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R49"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roger</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Muñoz-Gómez</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamikawa</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The origin and diversification of mitochondria</article-title><source>Current biology:CB</source><year>2017</year><volume>27</volume><issue>21</issue></element-citation></ref><ref id="R50"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sagan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>On the origin of mitosing cells</article-title><source>Journal of Theoretical Biology</source><year>1967</year><volume>14</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>225</fpage><comment>IN6</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="R51"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schäfer</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bozkurt</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Michaelis</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Klann</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Münch</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Global mitochondrial protein import proteomics reveal distinct regulation by translation and translocation machinery</article-title><source>Molecular cell</source><year>2022</year><volume>82</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>435</fpage><lpage>446</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R52"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Siwiak</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Zielenkiewicz</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A comprehensive, quantitative, and genome-wide model of translation</article-title><source>PLoS Comput Biol</source><year>2010</year><month>Jul</month><day>29</day><volume>6</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>3</fpage><comment>out of 12 table 1. ID BioNumbers: 106218</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="R53"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sloan</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><name><surname>Warren</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Abdel-Ghany</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Chicco</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Havird</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cytonuclear integration and co-evolution</article-title><source>Nature Reviews Genetics</source><year>2018</year><volume>19</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>635</fpage><lpage>648</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R54"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stegemann</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hartmann</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruf</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bock</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>High-frequency gene transfer from the chloroplast genome to the nucleus</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</source><year>2003</year><volume>100</volume><issue>15</issue><fpage>8828</fpage><lpage>8833</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R55"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vasseur</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Yodzis</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The color of environmental noise</article-title><source>Ecology</source><year>2004</year><volume>85</volume><fpage>1146</fpage><lpage>1152</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R56"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>von Heijne</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Why mitochondria need a genome</article-title><source>FEBS Lett</source><year>1986</year><volume>198</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>4</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R57"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Waskom</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>seaborn: statistical data visualization</article-title><source>Journal of Open Source Software</source><year>2021</year><volume>6</volume><issue>60</issue><fpage>3021</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R58"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Schon</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name><surname>Elgar</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Orioli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanguy</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Giess</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Tischkowitz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Caulfield</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Chinnery</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nuclear-embedded mitochondrial dna sequences in 66,083 human genomes</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2022</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>10</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R59"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wickham</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><source>ggplot2: Elegant Graphics for Data Analysis</source><publisher-name>Springer-Verlag</publisher-name><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc><year>2016</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R60"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zaremba-Niedzwiedzka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Caceres</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></name><name><surname>Saw</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Bäckström</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/><name><surname>J</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Asgard archaea illuminate the origin of eukaryotic cellular complexity</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2017</year><volume>541</volume><fpage>353</fpage><lpage>358</lpage></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Model outline.</title><p><bold>(A)</bold> The cell biological processes modelled in gene expression and translocation. A gene encoded in the organelle (<italic>α</italic> = 0) is expressed with rate <italic>λ</italic> from wild-type oDNA, whose proportion is <italic>p</italic>. An organelle gene encoded in the nucleus (<italic>α</italic> = 1) is expressed from nDNA with rate <italic>λ</italic>, and its gene product is imported to the organelle with a transport rate <italic>D</italic>. The labels <italic>x<sub>c</sub></italic> and <italic>x<sub>m</sub></italic> represent the amount of gene product in the cytosol and organelle, respectively, and <italic>ν<sub>c</sub></italic> and <italic>ν<sub>m</sub></italic> are degradation rates in those compartments. <bold>(B)</bold> Environmental supply and demand. The environment places demand on the organelle machinery. For oscillating signals this demand has mean <italic>a</italic>, relative amplitude <italic>b</italic> and frequency <italic>k/τ</italic>. Organelle gene products <italic>x<sub>m</sub></italic> will respond to this demand: following some transient behaviour an oscillation will also occur. An instantaneous cost <italic>C</italic>(<italic>t</italic>) is incurred, being the absolute difference between environmental demand <italic>E</italic>(<italic>t</italic>) and functional machinery supply <italic>x<sub>m</sub></italic>(<italic>t</italic>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS155877-f001"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Cost differences with the interplay of degradation and transport in static and noisy environments.</title><p>Absolute cost difference between nuclear and organelle encoding strategies for a <bold>(A)</bold> static <italic>E</italic>(<italic>t</italic>) = <italic>a</italic>, <bold>(B)</bold> white noise <italic>E<sub>w</sub></italic>(<italic>t</italic>) <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD5">Eq (5)</xref> and <bold>(C)</bold> red noise <italic>E<sub>r</sub></italic>(<italic>t</italic>) <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD7">Eq (6)</xref> environment. The parameter values are synthesis rate <italic>λ</italic> = 1, constant environment <italic>E</italic>(<italic>t</italic>) = <italic>a</italic> = 1 and proportion of wild-type oDNA <italic>p</italic> = 0.75. This proportion <italic>p</italic> influences which compartment is more favourable; results for <italic>p</italic> = 1 and <italic>p</italic> = 0.9 for a static environment are in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure S2 in the SI</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS155877-f002"/></fig><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Cost difference with the interplay between environmental oscillation and cell biological processes.</title><p>Environmental oscillations have frequency <italic>k</italic> per day, amplitude <italic>b</italic> and mean value <italic>a</italic>. Other parameter values are synthesis rate <italic>λ</italic> = 1, degradation in the organelle <italic>ν<sub>m</sub></italic> = 0.5, no degradation in the cytosol <italic>ν<sub>c</sub></italic> = 0 and proportion of wild-type oDNA <italic>p</italic> = 0.75. Different parameterisations show largely the same trends and are explored in the <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Information</xref>: alternative values of <italic>p</italic> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figures S5</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S6</xref>); nonzero degradation in the cytosol <italic>ν<sub>c</sub></italic> = 1 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figures S7</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S9</xref>); higher synthesis rate <italic>λ</italic> = 10 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figures S8</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S11</xref>); and low synthesis rate <italic>λ</italic> = 0.1 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure S10</xref>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS155877-f003"/></fig><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Time behaviour and phase portraits of the system in different examples of periodically changing environments.</title><p>Different rows give different environmental frequencies <italic>k</italic> progressing vertically up <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>: <bold>(A)</bold> <italic>k</italic> = 1; <bold>(B)</bold> <italic>k</italic> = 4; <bold>(C)</bold> <italic>k</italic> = 16. Left column (i) shows time series of environmental demand <italic>E</italic>(<italic>t</italic>) and <italic>x<sub>m</sub></italic>(<italic>t</italic>) for both encoding compartments. Central column (ii) shows demand vs supply traces; departure from the diagonal corresponds to a supply-demand imbalance. Right column (iii) shows time series of accumulated costs. In each case the time series are plotted after equilibration (see Methods). The common parameter values in all cases are a synthesis rate <italic>λ</italic> = 1, a degradation rate in the organelle <italic>ν<sub>m</sub></italic> = 0.5, no degradation in the cytosol <italic>ν<sub>c</sub></italic> = 0, a wild-type proportion of oDNA <italic>p</italic> = 0.75, time-averaged energetic demand <italic>a</italic> = 1 and relative amplitude <italic>b</italic> = 1. In (<italic>i</italic>) the transport is <italic>D</italic> = 0.1 and the frequency <italic>k</italic> = 1, in (<italic>ii</italic>)<italic>D</italic> = 0.1 and <italic>k</italic> = 4 and in (<italic>iii</italic>)<italic>D</italic> = 1 and <italic>k</italic> = 16.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS155877-f004"/></fig><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>Connecting theory to oDNA profiles of extant eukaryotic taxa.</title><p><bold>(A-B)</bold> Protein-coding oDNA gene counts in different eukaryotic clades. (A) mtDNA, (B) ptDNA. The lower points in fungi, metazoa, and viridiplantae (for both organelles) typically correspond to parasitic species, and Apicomplexa are all parasites. <bold>(C)</bold> Summary illustration of the key proposed influences suggested by our model. Both cell biological and environmental features influence which compartment is preferred for encoding a given gene: the figure condenses several degrees of freedom into a single illustrative axis in both cases. At the species level, organisms maintaining high genetic integrity (high <italic>p</italic>; assisted, for example, by developmental bottlenecks and recombination (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">Edwards et al., 2021</xref>)) and subject to strong, intermediate frequency environmental oscillations (high <italic>b</italic>, intermediate <italic>k</italic>; for example, diurnal light or tidal oscillations) retain more genes. At the gene level, genes challenging to import to the organelle (high <italic>ν<sub>c</sub></italic>, low <italic>D</italic>; for example, hydrophobic gene products) and playing a more central role in bioenergetic supply (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">Allen and Martin, 2016</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">Giannakis et al., 2022</xref>) are the more likely to be retained. Transects through the figure give examples of eukaryotic clades and mtDNA genes (generally oDNA-encoded <italic>cytB</italic> and generally nuclear-encoded <italic>sdhA</italic>) corresponding qualitatively to different cases.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS155877-f005"/></fig></floats-group></article>