<!DOCTYPE article
 PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" article-type="preprint"><?all-math-mml yes?><?use-mml?><?origin ukpmcpa?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">bioRxiv</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>bioRxiv : the preprint server for biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub"/></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">EMS156682</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2022.11.04.515239</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="archive">PPR567045</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Low input capture Hi-C (liCHi-C) identifies promoter-enhancer interactions at high-resolution</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Tomás-Daza</surname><given-names>Laureano</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Rovirosa</surname><given-names>Llorenç</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>López-Martí</surname><given-names>Paula</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nieto-Aliseda</surname><given-names>Andrea</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Serra</surname><given-names>François</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Planas-Riverola</surname><given-names>Ainoa</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Molina</surname><given-names>Oscar</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>McDonald</surname><given-names>Rebecca</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ghevaert</surname><given-names>Cedric</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cuatrecasas</surname><given-names>Esther</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>Dolors</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A6">6</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A7">7</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A8">8</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Camós</surname><given-names>Mireia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A9">9</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A10">10</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A11">11</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bueno</surname><given-names>Clara</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Menéndez</surname><given-names>Pablo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A12">12</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Valencia</surname><given-names>Alfonso</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A12">12</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Javierre</surname><given-names>Biola M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A13">13</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Josep Carreras Leukaemia Research Institute, Badalona, Barcelona, Spain</aff><aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Barcelona Supercomputing Center, Barcelona, Barcelona, Spain</aff><aff id="A3"><label>3</label>Wellcome-MRC Cambridge Stem Cell Institute, Cambridge, United Kingdom</aff><aff id="A4"><label>4</label>NHS Blood and Transplant, Cambridge, United Kingdom</aff><aff id="A5"><label>5</label>Pediatric Institute of Rare Diseases, Sant Joan de Déu Hospital, Esplugues de Llobregat, Barcelona, Spain</aff><aff id="A6"><label>6</label>Hospital Clinic, Barcelona, Spain</aff><aff id="A7"><label>7</label>Institute of Biomedical Research August Pi i Sunyer, Barcelona, Spain</aff><aff id="A8"><label>8</label>Cancer Network Biomedical Research Center, Barcelona, Spain</aff><aff id="A9"><label>9</label>Sant Joan de Déu Research Institute, Esplugues de Llobregat, Barcelona, Spain</aff><aff id="A10"><label>10</label>Sant Joan de Déu Hospital, Esplugues de Llobregat, Barcelona, Spain</aff><aff id="A11"><label>11</label>Center for Biomedical Research in the Rare Diseases Network (CIBERER), Carlos III Health Institute, Madrid, Spain</aff><aff id="A12"><label>12</label>Catalan Institution for Research and Advanced Studies (ICREA), Barcelona, Spain</aff><aff id="A13"><label>13</label>Josep Carreras Leukaemia Research Institute and Institute for Health Science Research Germans Trias i Pujol, Badalona, Barcelona, Spain</aff><author-notes><corresp id="CR1"><email>bmjavierre@carrerasresearch.org</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted"><day>06</day><month>11</month><year>2022</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="preprint"><day>05</day><month>11</month><year>2022</year></pub-date><permissions><ali:free_to_read/><license><ali:license_ref>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is licensed under a <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">CC BY-NC 4.0 International license</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p id="P1">Long-range interactions between regulatory elements and promoters are key in gene transcriptional control; however, their study requires large amounts of starting material, which is not compatible with clinical scenarios nor the study of rare cell populations. Here we introduce low input capture Hi-C (liCHi-C) as a cost-effective, flexible method to map and robustly compare promoter interactomes at high resolution. As proof of its broad applicability, we implement liCHi-C to study normal and malignant human hematopoietic hierarchy in clinical samples. We demonstrate that the dynamic promoter architecture identifies developmental trajectories and orchestrates transcriptional transitions during cell-state commitment. Moreover, liCHi-C enables the identification of new disease-relevant cell types, genes and pathways potentially deregulated by non-coding alterations at distal regulatory elements. Finally, we show that liCHi-C can be harnessed to uncover genome-wide structural variants, resolve their breakpoints and infer their pathogenic effects. Collectively, our optimized liCHi-C method expands the study of 3D chromatin organization to unique, low-abundance cell populations, and offers an opportunity to uncover novel factors and regulatory networks involved in disease pathogenesis.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec id="S1" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p id="P2">Enhancers are critical modulators of gene transcription through physical interactions with target promoters that often locate distally in the genome. The physical proximity between enhancers and promoters is ultimately enabled and determined by the three-dimensional folding of the chromatin within the nucleus<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">2</xref></sup>. Although enhancers can be defined through well-characterized features, predicting their target genes at distal locations remains challenging due to the high complexity of studying enhancer-promoter interactions and the large variability according to cell-type and state. This gap of knowledge is particularly problematic for understanding the molecular mechanisms associated with inherited and <italic>de novo</italic> acquired mutations and epimutations involved in common human diseases, which are all highly enriched at regulatory elements<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">4</xref></sup>.</p><p id="P3">To enable the study of genomic regulatory mechanisms underlying disease pathologies at a genome-wide scale, we previously developed the promoter capture Hi-C (PCHi-C) method<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref></sup>. This approach allows systematic identification of the promoter interactome (<italic>i.e</italic>., genomic regions, including distal regulatory regions, in physical proximity with more than 31,000 promoters) independently of the activity status of the interacting regions. This method has allowed us to uncover new aspects of the diversity of transcriptional regulatory factors<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref></sup> and mechanisms in cell differentiation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref></sup> and disease<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref></sup>, and it has broadened our capacity to identify hundreds of potential new disease-candidate genes and/or gene pathways potentially deregulated by non-coding disease-associated variants<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">21</xref></sup>. However, PCHi-C relies on the availability of millions of cells, typically ranging between 30–50 million cells per biological replicate, which prohibits the analysis of rare cell populations such as those commonly obtained in clinical settings.</p><p id="P4">Here, to overcome this limitation, we present liCHi-C, a mini-input method that allows the generation of high-resolution genome-wide promoter interactome maps using very low amounts of starting material. We have validated our new method by benchmarking liCHi-C promoter interactomes against the highest resolution PCHi-C promoter interactomes available to date, demonstrating that the interactomes can be reproducibly interrogated using as low as 50,000 cells of starting material. As a proof of its potential for discovering new insights about gene transcription regulation, we used liCHi-C to study human hematopoiesis i<italic>n vivo</italic> and demonstrate its potential for identifying developmental trajectories and providing mechanistic understanding of transcriptional dynamics along i<italic>n vivo</italic> cell commitment. Furthermore, we show liCHi-C can be applied to investigate molecular links between disease-associated non-coding alterations at distal regulatory elements with their target genes in rare cell populations that cannot be characterized using PCHi-C. Finally, to support the broad applicability of liCHi-C across disease settings, we analyze primary leukemias and identify patient-specific structural genomic alterations and cancer-specific topological features potentially implicated in gene deregulation and disease etiology. All the computational tools to analyze and integrate liCHi-C data are freely available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/JavierreLab/liCHiC">https://github.com/JavierreLab/liCHiC</ext-link>.</p></sec><sec id="S2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="S3"><title>Development and optimization of liCHi-C for low-input samples</title><p id="P5">In order to enable the detection of the promoter interactome using low-input material, we modified the original PCHi-C to minimize losses during the procedure. Specifically, liCHi-C maximizes library complexity by employing a single-tube, modifying reagent concentration and volume, and eliminating or modifying the sequence of some steps (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1a</xref>). Additionally, it reduces by half the time spent on the library preparation. For more details, see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="S11">Methods</xref> section and Extended Data Fig. 1a.</p><p id="P6">To systematically evaluate liCHi-C, we generated libraries from decreasing numbers of human naïve B cells (Supplementary Information <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Table 1</xref>) at controlled ratios and compared these with the most comprehensive PCHi-C data available to date from the exact same cell type that used ~40 million (40M) cells as starting material. Each sample was deep-sequenced and paired-end reads were mapped and filtered using HiCUP pipeline<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">22</xref></sup>. Visual inspection of normalized liCHi-C and PCHi-C contact maps showed a high degree of similarity in topological properties (Extended Data Fig. 1b), and for all experimental conditions (<italic>i.e.,</italic> number of starting cells), the percentage of valid reads (Mean = 58.41%; SD = 5.76%) and the capture efficiency (Mean = 61.29%; SD = 9.15%) were similar between both methods, being 23.58% (SD = 1.59%) of those contacts in <italic>trans</italic> (Extended Data Fig. 1c-e and Supplementary Information <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Table 1</xref>). Unsurprisingly, given the higher need for amplification, the PCR duplicates increased with lower amounts of starting cells, ranging from 86% in 50k cell samples, to 12% of the mapped reads in 40M cell samples. Interaction matrices were also highly reproducible for both methods and different amounts of starting material (stratum-adjusted correlation coefficient (SCC) &gt; 0.90) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1b</xref> and Extended Data Fig. 1f). These data suggest that liCHi-C reliably generates high-quality promoter interactomes, including 31,253 annotated promoters, and can routinely be performed successfully with an input as low as 50k cells. Remarkably, liCHi-C was able to achieve a &gt;10-fold enrichment of read pairs involving promoters when compared with Hi-C using 800 times less of the starting cells (Supplementary Information <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Table 1</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S4"><title>Comparison of liCHi-C with other C-based methods for profiling promoter interactomes</title><p id="P7">To formally compare the performance of liCHi-C to detect promoter interactions, we used the CHiCAGO pipeline<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">23</xref></sup> to call for significant interactions (CHiCAGO score &gt; 5). Distance distribution and nature of interacting fragments were similar across cell number conditions and methods (Extended Data Fig. 2a-c). Specifically, we found a median linear distance between promoters and their interacting regions of 265kb (SD = 30kb), and 89.04% (SD = 3.72%) of these were promoter-to-non-promoter interactions (Extended Data Fig. 2b-c and Supplementary Information <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Table 1</xref>). Principal component analysis (PCA) of CHiCAGO interaction scores across all biological replicates demonstrated that patterns of promoter interactions are highly consistent across biological replicates and group samples according to the number of input cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1c</xref>). To further explore the limits of liCHi-C library complexity we performed hierarchical clustering based on their CHiCAGO interaction scores. We observed that promoter interactomes generated from &gt;100k cells reproduce the ones generated with PCHi-C on 40M cells (Extended Data Fig. 2d). Although promoter interactomes with less than 100k cells showed a different clustering profile, potentially reflecting the reduction of significant interactions due the limited library complexity, these retain cell-type specific and invariant topological features (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1d</xref> and Extended Data Fig 2e-g). Collectively, these results demonstrate the high reproducibility of liCHi-C to profile promoter interactomes at a similar resolution as PCHi-C, and underscore the suitability of the approach to investigate these interactions in cell populations present at relatively low abundance within a sample.</p><p id="P8">In addition, we benchmarked liCHi-C against other existing C-based methods used for detecting the 3D genome topologies of blood lineage, including Low-C<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref></sup>, Hi-C (using a four-cutter<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">25</xref></sup> or a six-cutter<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref></sup> restriction enzyme) and TagHi-C<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">26</xref></sup> (Extended Data Fig 3 and Supplementary Information <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD3">Table 2</xref>). We called chromatin loops in these datasets at a resolution of 5kb, which is similar to the resolution of our liCHi-C data (~4096 bp), using HICCUPS<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27">27</xref></sup>, Mustache<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">28</xref></sup> and HiCExplorer<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">29</xref></sup> loop callers with standard parameters (for more details, see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="S11">Methods</xref> section). Despite the fact that these methods have provided fundamental insights about the role and regulation of spatio-temporal genome architecture on rare cell populations, these methods are very limited with respect to the detection of promoter interactions at restriction fragment resolution (Extended Data Fig. 3a-b and Supplementary Information <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD3">Table 2</xref>). Collectively, these results demonstrate that liCHi-C outperforms other existing C-based methods at genome-wide and promoter-wide detection of potential gene regulatory interactions at high resolution using low-cell numbers.</p></sec><sec id="S5"><title>liCHi-C efficiently captures promoter interactomes across different hematopoietic lineages</title><p id="P9">To assess the capacity of liCHi-C to provide fundamental insight about <italic>in vivo</italic> cell differentiation, we performed high-quality liCHi-C experiments in 9 distinct cellular populations from the human hematopoietic hierarchy (two biological replicates per cell type; 500k cells per replicate), including hematopoietic stem and progenitor cells (HSC), common myeloid progenitors (CMP), common lymphoid B cell progenitors (CLP) and 6 differentiated cell types (Extended Data Fig. 4a-c and Supplementary Information <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Table 1</xref>). As a more comprehensive validation of the liCHi-C method, we first focused on the differentiated cell types for which high quality PCHi-C data is available. Benchmarking of liCHi-C data against PCHi-C data demonstrated high reproducibility between both methods for all profiled cell types (SCC &gt; 0.93) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2a</xref> and Extended Data Fig. 4c). Moreover, promoter interactomes clearly separated cell types independently of the method used (Extended Data Fig. 4f).</p><p id="P10">We then analyzed liCHi-C data in detail. Applying CHiCAGO we identified a median of 134,965 high-confidence promoter interactions (CHiCAGO score &gt; 5) per cell type (Extended Data Fig. 4d-e and Supplementary Information <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Table 1</xref>). A PCA of interaction scores demonstrated that promoter interactomes were highly reproducible and cell-type specific (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2b</xref>). While the first principal component separated cells according to their myeloid or lymphoid linage, the second principal component recapitulated the differentiation potential, allowing altogether to identify both myeloid and lymphoid differentiation trajectories. To decipher these specificities in greater depth we applied Autoclass Bayesian clustering and computed the specificity score of each cluster in each cell type (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2c-d</xref>). Among the 33 clusters, we observed a stem and progenitor-specific cluster (C3), lymphoid-specific clusters (<italic>e.g.,</italic> C10, C13), myeloid-specific clusters (<italic>e.g.</italic>, C25, C27) and cell-type specific clusters (<italic>e.g.,</italic> C4, C7) that contained genes known to be involved in cellular functions important for the given cell types (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2d-g</xref>). These observations were clearly illustrated by the promoter interactomes of <italic>MYB<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">30</xref></sup>,</italic> which encodes for a transcription regulator that plays an essential role in the regulation of lymphoid priming and early B cell development (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2e</xref>), <italic>ITGA2B<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31">31</xref></sup>,</italic> which encodes for the megakaryocyte-specific surface marker CD41 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2f</xref>), and <italic>SARS2<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32">32</xref></sup>,</italic> a housekeeping gene that encodes for the mitochondrial seryl-tRNA synthetase (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2g</xref>). Collectively, this data demonstrates that promoter interactomes are specific to the differentiation trajectories of cell types, and further suggest that the highly dynamic promoter-centric genome architecture recapitulates the developmental history of hematopoietic cell lineages.</p></sec><sec id="S6"><title>Promoter interactomes reshape transcriptional trajectories during <italic>in vivo</italic> cell commitment</title><p id="P11">To validate the ability of liCHi-C to uncover mechanistic insights on transcription regulation, we computationally integrated promoter interactome data with RNA-seq and ChIP-seq data from matched cell types (Extended Data Fig. 5a-c and Supplementary Information <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD4">Table 3</xref>). We distinguish between 2 types of promoter-interacting regions (PIRs): non-promoter PIRs (npPIRs), in which the promoter interacting region does not contain any captured gene promoter, and promoter PIRs (pPIRs), in which the promoter interacting region contains at least a gene promoter. We found high enrichment of histone modifications indicative of active enhancers (<italic>e.g.,</italic> H3K27ac, H3K4me1) and non-coding transcription of regulatory regions (<italic>e.g.,</italic> H3K4me3)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33">33</xref></sup> at distal npPIRs. These enrichments were positively associated with the expression level of linked genes in a cell-type specific manner (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3a</xref>). Conversely, npPIRs of lowly expressed genes tend to be more enriched in repressive histone marks, such as H3K27me3 and H3K9me3, than more highly expressed ones. These enrichment profiles were highly consistent with the ones obtained with PCHi-C data despite the significant difference in the starting cell number (Extended Data Fig. 5d). Collectively, these results, exemplified by the transcriptional regulation of the T cell-specific gene <italic>GATA3<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34">34</xref></sup></italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3b</xref>), the B cell-specific gene <italic>PAX5<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35">35</xref></sup></italic> (Extended Data Fig. 5e), and the HSC-specific gene <italic>CD34</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36">36</xref></sup> (Extended Data Fig. 5f), demonstrate the capacity of liCHi-C to identify distal regulatory elements for each gene in rare cell types, and suggest that promoter-associated regions are enriched in distal regulatory elements that mirror the cell-type specificity of the interacting gene’s expression.</p><p id="P12">We then applied chromatin assortativity analysis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37">37</xref></sup>, which recognizes the preference of a network’s nodes to attach to others that have similar features, to test the potential of liCHi-C to discover proteins or chromatin marks mediating genomic contacts within the nucleus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3c</xref> and Extended Data Fig. 6a). We observed that genomic regions enriched in H3K9me3 histone modification, which have been associated with constitutive heterochromatin and lamina-associated domains, are highly interconnected and may form topological hubs that collaborate with epigenetics to promote gene silencing (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3d</xref> and Extended Data Fig. 6b-d). Collectively, these results illustrate the power of liCHi-C to suggest, after further functional validation, new aspects on the diversity of factors and mechanisms regulating genome architecture.</p></sec><sec id="S7"><title>liCHi-C enables the discovery of disease-relevant cell types and disease-associated genes and pathways</title><p id="P13">Genetic variation, which frequently affects the non-coding genome, occurs at various levels ranging from single-nucleotide variants, such as single-nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs), to larger structural variants (SVs). To test liCHi-C’s ability to uncover novel associations between non-coding SNPs and disease etiology, we integrated summary statistics from thirty-nine genome-wide association studies (GWAS), including seven autoimmune diseases, eight myeloid cell traits, four lymphoid cell traits, nine blood malignancies and eleven traits non-related to the hematopoietic hierarchy (Supplementary Information <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table 4</xref>). Using Blockshifter analysis we showed that PIRs called by liCHi-C in a cell type, independently of whether these are shared or not across cell types, are enriched for genetic variants associated with traits or diseases relevant to the cell type (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4a-b</xref>). For instance, variants associated with final maturation of myeloid cells tend to be more enriched at PIRs in mature myeloid cells. Interestingly, similar enrichment profiles were obtained by liCHi-C and PCHi-C despite the dramatic reduction in starting material (Extended Data Fig. 7a). These data demonstrate that liCHi-C can trace the ontogeny of activity of the non-coding genome in association with pathogenic traits and enables the identification of cell types presumably implicated in disease etiology.</p><p id="P14">We next used the Bayesian prioritization strategy COGS to rank putative disease-associated genes based on GWAS and liCHi-C data. Excluding SNPs at promoter or coding regions, we assigned 24,504 distal non-coding SNPs to potential target genes, which were located at a median genomic distance of 187kb (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4c</xref>). Remarkably, only 19.58% of these were linked to the nearest gene and 38.16% potentially controlled more than one gene. These results highlight the importance of being able to generate data on long-range interactions between promoters and regulatory elements to avoid misleading associations based on proximity in the context of gene regulation and disease.</p><p id="P15">Specifically, using this computational framework on liCHi-C data we prioritized 6,230 candidate genes (with a median of 134 genes per trait/disease at gene-level score &gt; 0.5) and 56 candidate gene pathways according the Reactome Pathway Database<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38">38</xref></sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4d</xref>). These genes were highly similar to those prioritized by PCHi-C using 40M cells (Extended Data Fig. 7b-c). For instance, our data suggested that deregulation of <italic>TLE3,</italic> a gene that encodes for a co-repressor protein that negative regulates canonical <italic>WNT</italic> signaling<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39">39</xref></sup>, could confer susceptibility to lymphocytic leukemia (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4e</xref>). Moreover, it also pointed out ¨activation of BH3-only proteins¨ pathway, which is involved in the canonical mitochondrial apoptosis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40">40</xref></sup>, as being potentially implicated in this type of cancer (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4d</xref>). These and many other examples of expected and unexpected genes and pathways potentially deregulated by non-coding SNPs uncovered in our datasets, warrant follow-up studies to characterize their functional relevance in disease phenotypes. Nonetheless, our results demonstrate the power of liCHi-C to identify potential disease-causative genes and pathways.</p></sec><sec id="S8"><title>liCHi-C can be used to simultaneously diagnose and discover translocations, copy number variations (CNVs) and topological alterations in tumoral samples</title><p id="P16">After demonstrating the capacity of liCHi-C to prioritize non-coding SNPs with potential functional relevance in clinical settings, we sought to investigate SVs affecting larger genomic regions, including translocations and CNVs. Most of the ligation events detected by proximity-ligation methods, such as liCHi-C, occur between sequences in proximity along the linear genome and the frequency of these events decreases logarithmically with the genomic distance that separates them. However, a translocation alters the linear genome and artificially increases the number of ligation events between the juxtaposed regions. Based on this, we reasoned that liCHi-C could detect genome-wide chromosomal translocations, identify the breakpoints and uncover alterations in gene promoter interactions that could shed light on the pathogenic role of SVs. To test this hypothesis, we generated high quality liCHi-C libraries using primary blasts from two pediatric B cell acute lymphoblastic leukemia (B-ALL) samples (500k cells per library) (Supplementary Information <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Table 1</xref> and Extended Data Fig. 8b-e) previously analyzed by routine clinical assays (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5a</xref> and Extended Data Fig. 8a). According to FISH and karyotyping analysis, B-ALL sample 1 carried a balanced translocation between chromosomes 8 and 14, which appeared as ‘butterfly’ blocks of interactions between the translocated chromosomes on the liCHi-C interaction matrix (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5a</xref> top). A closer examination of the interaction directionalities identified the restriction fragments affected by the breakpoints and allowed the reconstruction of the resulting chromosome where the promoter of <italic>MYC</italic> becomes rearranged next to the ¨constant¨ gene cluster of the IgH locus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5b</xref>). Through this focused analysis of promoter interactions, our data suggested that <italic>MYC</italic> expression may be simultaneously controlled by the ¨<italic>MYC</italic> blood enhancer cluster¨ (BENC)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41">41</xref></sup>, located 2Mb downstream, and the IgH-specific enhancer 3’-regulatory region (3’-RR)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42">42</xref></sup>, rearranged 300kb upstream (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5c</xref>). B-ALL sample 2 carried an unbalanced translocation between the same chromosomes that generated single blocks of contacts on the normalized liCHi-C interaction matrix (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5a</xref> bottom). Consequently, the <italic>CEBPD</italic> gene<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43">43</xref></sup> becomes juxtaposed to the IgH locus, which potentially alters its regulatory landscape (Extended DataFig. 8f-g). Collectively, these results demonstrate liCHi-C’s capacity to generate high-quality chromatin conformation maps and regulatory landscapes directly from primary patient tissue samples to detect any type of translocation and surmise the pathogenic effects at a genome-wide scale.</p><p id="P17">In addition to chromosome rearrangements, we tested whether liCHi-C can be used to detect CNVs. Gains or losses of genetic material imply an increase or decrease in the ligation events within the altered regions, respectively. Therefore, we reasoned that CNVs should appear when comparing liCHi-C normalized interaction matrices of cells carrying the CNV against control cells. To test this hypothesis, we focused on the B-ALL sample 2 that, according to the karyotyping analysis, carried a trisomy of chromosome 21 and a partial trisomy affecting the translocated region of the q arm of chromosome 8. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5a</xref> bottom, both trisomies were identified, demonstrating that liCHi-C can be used for genome-wide detection of CNVs and to scan breakpoints from primary patient tissues without the need for a reference.</p><p id="P18">Finally, we tested the ability of liCHi-C to identify disease-specific regulatory 3D chromatin landscapes that may be implicated in disease etiology. To do so, we applied Autoclass Bayesian clustering of liCHi-C significant interactions (CHiCAGO score &gt; 5) called either on B-ALL samples or on the postulated healthy cells of origin of these hematological malignancies (<italic>i.e.,</italic> HSC, CLP and naïve B cells) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5d</xref>). Specificity score analysis of each cluster in each cell type identified promoter interactions specifically acquired (C5-9) or lost (C10-19) in one or both B-ALL samples (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5e</xref>), which included key transcription factors involved in B cell differentiation and function (<italic>e.g., PAX5<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R44">44</xref></sup>, ARID5B<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R45">45</xref></sup>),</italic> well-known tumor suppressor genes (<italic>e.g., BTG1<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R44">44</xref></sup>, IKZF1<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R44">44</xref></sup>)</italic> and protooncogenes (<italic>e.g., MYC<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R46">46</xref></sup>).</italic> For instance, several <italic>HOXA</italic> genes have been associated with normal hematopoiesis and blood malignancies<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R47">47</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R48">48</xref></sup>. According to liCHi-C data, these genes lose connectivity with their enhancers, which could link their transcriptional deregulation with malignant transformation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5f</xref>). Collectively, these results support the broad applicability of liCHi-C to uncover factors and mechanisms involved in disease etiology through simultaneously identifying disease-specific promoter-centered genome topologies and detecting translocations, CNVs, breakpoints and their effects on transcriptional deregulation.</p></sec><sec id="S9"><title>liCHi-C can be customized to improve its resolution</title><p id="P19">liCHi-C resolution is determined by the restriction enzyme used for the library generation and defines the range of significant interactions to be detected. To demonstrate the adaptability of our new method to interrogate promoter interactions at different resolutions we used primary blasts from a third B-ALL sample to generate two high-quality liCHi-C libraries using a six-cutter restriction enzyme (HindIII) and a four-cutter restriction enzyme (MboI) respectively (~250k cells per library) (Supplementary Information <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Table 1</xref> and Extended Data Fig. 8h-k). Patient 3 carried a monosomy of chromosome 7, which was clearly identified as a reduction of reads on the contact matrix generated by both restriction enzymes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6a-b</xref>).</p><p id="P20">liCHi-C libraries generated with MboI detected 1.78 times more significant interactions (Extended Data Fig. 8j), which were characterized by having half of the median linear distance between promoters and their interacting regions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6c</xref>). Indeed, although the shortest significant interaction was similar for both libraries (2574bp for HindIII and 1939 for MboI), the highest frequency of interactions was found at a distance 2.15 times larger for HindIII restriction (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6c</xref>). This data, illustrated by the promoter interactome of the <italic>DDX41</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6d</xref>), a DEAD box RNA helicase associated with B-ALL and other blood malignancies<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R49">49</xref></sup>, demonstrates that the use of a four-cutter restriction enzyme increases the power to detect shortrange interactions and compromises the detection of the long-range ones. Taken together, our results demonstrate liCHi-C capability to provide fundamental and clinical insights about gene-regulatory interactions at different levels of resolution.</p></sec></sec><sec id="S10" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p id="P21">High-throughput chromatin conformation capture methodologies such as Hi-C<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R50">50</xref></sup> have revolutionized our understanding of long-range gene transcriptional control. However, many aspects of its dynamics along <italic>in vivo</italic> differentiation and stimulation, as well as its alteration in disease, remain largely unexplored due to the lack of genome-wide methodologies to study the promoter-centric genome architecture at high resolution with low-input material. Whereas single-cell<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R51">51</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R52">52</xref></sup> or low-input<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R53">53</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R54">54</xref></sup> approaches exist, these generate sparse contact maps with low resolution that do not allow the study of specific chromatin interactomes. More recently, HiChIP<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R55">55</xref></sup> and HiCuT<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R56">56</xref></sup> methods have been developed to study long-range chromatin interactions mediated by a specific protein. Although both technologies are compatible with low-input cell numbers, these rely on the availability of high-quality antibodies that recognize the target protein. Besides, these methods cannot be used to compare chromatin interactomes between conditions in which the binding of the target protein is different, which is very common due to the inherent dynamic nature of chromatin.</p><p id="P22">To overcome these limitations, we have developed liCHi-C, a new mini-input cost-effective method to robustly map and compare promoter interactomes at high resolution in rare cell populations previously unmeasurable. Up to 12 liCHi-C libraries can be generated in 6 days with a total cost of 1500 euros per library (including sequencing cost). Unlike methods that depend on enrichment based on the use of antibodies<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R56">56</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R55">55</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R57">57</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R58">58</xref></sup>, liCHi-C only relies on biotinylated RNAs designed to hybridize against the annotated promoters to ultimately enrich for promoter interactions from a Hi-C library. Thus, it is able to identify long-range contacts of both active and inactive promoters and robustly compare interactomes between any condition. In addition, this capture strategy provides high versatility since any customized capture system from a wide range of coverage can be designed according to the interactome to be studied. For instance, liCHi-C can be easily coupled with capture systems designed to study the interactome of a collection of non-coding alterations or the enhancer interactome. Indeed, it can even be adapted to the study of the interactome of just a few loci as other 3C-based capture methods do<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R59">59</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R60">60</xref></sup>.</p><p id="P23">liCHi-C significantly broadens the capacity for studying organism developments, <italic>in vivo</italic> cell commitment and cellular response to a wide range of external stimuli. As a proof of concept, we have used liCHi-C to study, for the first time, human hematopoietic hierarchy. Our data demonstrates that the promoter interactome can identify the differentiation trajectory. In addition, this suggests a massive dynamic rewiring of the three-dimensional epigenetic landscape parallel to transcriptional decisions during <italic>in vivo</italic> cell commitment.</p><p id="P24">liCHi-C enables the study of primary samples, thus addressing a key limitation of PCHi-C to apply this type of analysis to clinical samples. This new method is especially relevant as most inherited and acquired mutations and epimutations for common human diseases, which largely remain unexplored, are all highly enriched at regulatory elements and cannot be readily modeled in <italic>in vitro</italic> systems. Genetic and epigenetic alterations at distal regulatory elements have the potential to alter the regulatory properties and ultimately lead to quantitative changes in expression of distal target genes with pathological outcomes. As distal regulatory elements and their topological properties are highly dynamic, cell-type specific and state-dependent, it is critical to identify the relevant human cell types for each disease and profile their full repertoire of regulatory elements and target genes. Here, we demonstrate that liCHi-C is able to fulfill this need. Focused on GWAS data we have demonstrated that liCHi-C identifies unexpected etiological associations and exposes new disease-associated genes and pathways.</p><p id="P25">Although we have mostly focused on inherited risk factors, our computational framework can be adapted to study acquired mutations and epimutations at any type of distal regulatory elements (<italic>e.g.</italic>, silencer or primed enhancer), since liCHi-C identifies long-range contacts promoters independently of their activity.</p><p id="P26">How chromatin organization contributes to disease pathogenesis remains largely unexplored. As we have shown, liCHi-C has the potential to contribute to filling this gap of knowledge. Taking malignant neoplasms as a model, we have shown that liCHi-C can be used to discover disease-specific topological alterations in clinical samples and generate hypotheses about genetic factors underlying disease mechanisms. Simultaneously, liCHi-C can uncover SVs at a genomic scale, resolve the positions of their breakpoints and predict their functional effects, including the formation of new regulatory landscapes, in an agnostic manner. Although we focused on the analysis of translocations and duplications associated with cancer, liCHi-C is also able to identify and characterize other types of SVs, such as inversions and deletions in any disease context. In addition, the liCHi-C method holds high potential for disease diagnosis equivalent to other chromosome conformation capture technologies<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R61">61</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R62">62</xref></sup>, since SVs are hallmarks of mental retardation, infertility, developmental disorders and cancer.</p><p id="P27">Despite the broad applicability of our method, there are still several factors to take into consideration. One inherent limitation of liCHi-C is that its resolution is determined by the restriction enzyme used for the library generation. However, as we have demonstrated, it can be increased by replacing the enzyme by another one with greater resolution or exchange it for micrococcal nuclease. In addition, the interpretation of the biological meaning of non-coding alterations purely based on distal chromatin interactions can be challenging. Nevertheless, an integrative analysis of liCHi-C data, gene expression and chromatin states might be indicative of causal relationships, which should be validated with functional assays. Finally, the identification of exact genomic coordinates of the SVs´ breakpoints is not possible unless these map near restriction sites. However, long-range sequencing approaches coupled with liCHi-C can allow to map the SVs at the nucleotide resolution. Besides, this combinatorial approach increases the mapability efficiency of the chromatin contacts at repetitive sequences, which can be target of SVs and other mutations and epimutations. Despite these considerations, our data proves that it is feasible to generate high quality genome-wide promoter interaction maps from low amounts of primary patient material. We anticipate that the robustness and the inherent flexibility for customization make liCHi-C an attractive option that will allow the analysis of spatial genome architecture within reach of personalized clinical diagnostics and development biology.</p></sec><sec id="S11" sec-type="methods" specific-use="web-only"><title>Methods</title><sec id="S12"><title>Cell isolation</title><p id="P28">Naïve B cells (nB), naïve CD4<sup>+</sup> cells (nCD4), naïve CD8<sup>+</sup> cells (nCD8), megakaryocytes (MK), erythroblasts (Ery) and monocytes (Mon) were isolated as described in<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref></sup>. Hematopoietic stem and progenitor cells (HSC; CD34<sup>+</sup>, CD38<sup>-</sup>) common myeloid progenitors (CMP; CD34<sup>+</sup>, CD38<sup>+</sup>, CD33<sup>+</sup>) and common lymphoid B cell progenitors (CLP; CD34<sup>+</sup>, CD38<sup>+</sup>, CD19<sup>+</sup>) were purified by CD34 positive selection (Miltenyi cat. #130-046-703) and fluorescence-activated cell sorting (FACS) from 4 donations (2 per biological replicate) of 15-to 22-week-old human fetal liver and fetal bone marrow as previously described<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R63">63</xref></sup>. Briefly, after CD34<sup>+</sup> selection, positive cells were stained for flow cytometry with the following fluorophore-conjugated monoclonal antibodies, all from BD Biosciences: CD34 PECy7 (cat. #348811), CD38 FITC (cat. #555459), CD19 BV421 (cat. #562440), CD33 APC (cat. #551378) and CD10 PE (cat. #555375). FACS was performed using a BD FACSAria Fusion. B-ALL samples were isolated from bone marrow of pediatric patients after CD19<sup>+</sup> by FACS sorter. All samples were obtained from consent donations of volunteers after approval by the Ethics committee.</p></sec><sec id="S13"><title>Fixation and cell quantification</title><p id="P29">Cells were quantified, resuspended in 1ml of RPMI 1640 culture medium containing 10% FBS and 2% of methanol-free formaldehyde (Thermo Fisher cat. #28908) and incubated in a rocker for 10 minutes at room temperature. Formaldehyde was quenched with glycine to a final concentration of 0.125M. Then, cells were washed with cold 1X PBS. Specific cell numbers were sorted into low-retention 1.5ml tubes (BD FACSJazz sorter, 1.0 Drop Pure sorting mode), pelleted, flash-frozen in dry ice and stored at -80 °C.</p></sec><sec id="S14"><title>liCHi-C method</title><p id="P30">During the whole protocol, low-retention tips and tubes were used to minimize cell loss. Pelleted cells were softly resuspended in 500μl ice cold lysis buffer (10mM Tris-HCl pH 8.0, 10mM NaCl, 0.2% IGEPAL CA-630, 1x cOmplete EDTA-free protease inhibitor cocktail (Merck cat. #11873580001)) and incubated 30 minutes on ice to extract the nuclei. Soft inversions of the tube were performed during the incubation every 5 minutes. Nuclei were centrifuged (1000g and 4°C for 10 min) and 450μl of supernatant was discarded (50μl of supernatant was left in the tube to avoid cell losses). The cell pellet was resuspended in 500μl ice cold 1.25x NEB2 buffer (New England Biolabs cat. #B7002S). After centrifugation (1000g and 4°C for 10 min), 500μl of supernatant was removed.</p><p id="P31">Afterwards, 129ul of 1.25x NEBuffer 2 were added to the low-retention tube to obtain a final volume of 179ul. Then, 5.5μl of 10% SDS (AppliChem cat. #A0676,0250) were laid on the wall of the tube and mixed by inversion. After incubation at 37°C and 950 rpm for 30 minutes, 37.5μl 10% Triton X-100 (AppliChem cat. #A4975,0100) were laid on the wall of the tube, mixed by inversion and incubated at 37°C and 950 rpm for 30 minutes. Chromatin within the nuclei was overnight digested at 37°C and 950rpm after adding 7.5μl of HindIII restriction enzyme at 100U/μl or 37.5μl of MboI restriction enzyme at 25U/μl (New England Biolabs cat. #R0104T or #R0147M). The following day, an extra digestion during one more hour was performed after adding 2.5μl of the HindII enzyme or 12.5 μl of the MboI enzyme.</p><p id="P32">After digestion, MboI enzyme was washed with NEBuffer 2 by centrifuging the sample and removing the supernatant to avoid possible re-digestion of ligated fragments afterwards. Cohesive restriction fragment ends were filled in during 75 minutes at 37°C. To do so, 30μl of master mix composed by 5μl of 5U/μl Klenow polymerase (New England Biolabs cat. #M0210L), 0.75μl of each 10mM dCTP, dGTP and dTTP, and 18.75μl of 0.4mM biotin-14-dATP (Invitrogen #19524-016) were added.</p><p id="P33">In-nucleus ligation of DNA fragments was carried out during 4 hours at 16°C after adding 12.5μl of 1U/μl T4 DNA ligase (Thermo Fisher cat. #15224025), 50μl of 10x ligation buffer (NEB #B0202S), 5μl of 10mg/ml BSA (NEB # B9001S) and 170.5ml of water. Afterwards, DNA ligation products were decrosslinked by adding 30μl of Proteinase K 10mg/ml (Merck cat. #3115879001) and incubating overnight at 65°C. The following day, an extra decrosslink during two more hours was performed after adding 15μl of the Proteinase K enzyme.</p><p id="P34">To purify the decrosslinked DNA ligation products, a single phenol-chloroform-isoamyl alcohol (25:24:1 v/v) purification was carried out followed by ethanol precipitation for 1 hour at -80°C in presence of 30μg Glycoblue (Thermo Fisher cat. #AM9515) as a coprecipitant. DNA ligation products were resuspended in 130μl of nuclease free water and concentration was assessed by fluorimetric quantification using the Qubit dsDNA HS Assay Kit (Thermo Fisher cat. #Q32851).</p><p id="P35">Optional 3C controls assessing the detection of cell-type invariant interactions in the HindIII liCHi-C libraries can be performed by amplifying 50-100ng of the DNA with 37 cycles of PCR amplification (see Supplementary Information <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table 5</xref> for primer information) and running the reactions in a 1.6% agarose gel. Correct fill-in and ligation can also be tested by reamplifying 2.5ul of PCR products 5 more cycles, differentially digesting the product with either HindIII, NheI (Thermo Fisher cat. #ER0975), both enzymes or none and running the product on a 1.6% agarose gel.</p><p id="P36">Biotin removal of the non-ligated ends was skipped. DNA ligation products were sonicated using Covaris M220 focused-ultrasonicator (20% duty factor, 50 peak incident power, 200 cycles per burst, 65 seconds) in 130ul tubes (Covaris cat. #520077). After shearing, DNA ends were repaired by adding 6.5ul of T4 DNA polymerase 3U/μl (New England Biolabs cat. #M0203L), 6.5ul of T4 polynucleotide kinase 10U/μl (New England Biolabs cat. #M0201L) 1.3ul of Klenow polymerase 5U/μl (New England Biolabs cat. #M0210L), 18μl of dNTP mix 2.5mM each and 18μl of 10x ligation buffer (New England Biolabs cat. #B0202S) and incubating for 30 minutes at 20°C.</p><p id="P37">Biotinylated informative DNA ligation products were pulled down using Dynabeads MyOne streptavidin C1 paramagnetic beads (Thermo Fisher cat. #65001). After thorough washing of the ligation products-beads complex and having the sample in 35.7μl of volume, blunt DNA fragments on the beads were adenine-tailed by adding 7μl of Klenow 3'→5' exo- polymerase 5U/μl (New England Biolabs cat. #M0212L), 2.3μl of dATP 10mM and 5 μl NEB2 of 10x NEBuffer 2 and incubating the mixture 30 minutes at 37°C and a further 10 minutes at 65°C to inactivate the enzyme.</p><p id="P38">After thorough washing of the ligation products-beads complex and having the sample in 50μl of 1x ligation buffer, PE Illumina adapters (Supplementary Information <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table 5</xref>) were ligated to the adenine-tailed DNA fragments by adding 1μl of T4 DNA ligase 2000U/μl (New England Biolabs cat. #M0202T) and 4μl of preannealed adaptor mix 15μM and incubating the mixture 2h at room temperature.</p><p id="P39">The bead-bound ligation products were amplified 8-13 cycles by PCR (Supplementary Information <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table 5</xref> for cycle recommendations according to starting cell number) using Phusion high-fidelity PCR master mix with HF buffer (New England Biolabs cat. #M0531L)</p><p id="P40">After recovering the amplified library from the supernatant, size distribution was tailored to 300-800bp by double-sided size selection and purified using CleanNGS SPRI beads (0.4-1 volumes; CleanNA cat. #CNGS-0050). DNA concentration was quantified on an Agilent Tapestation platform using high sensitivity D1000 ScreenTape system and samples were stored at -20°C.</p><p id="P41">Enrichment of promoter-containing ligation products was performed using SureSelectXT Target Enrichment System for the Illumina Platform (Agilent Technologies) as instructed by the manufacturer, and the library was amplified 4 cycles by PCR using Phusion high-fidelity PCR master mix with HF buffer (New England Biolabs cat. #M0531L). Finally, the end product was purified using CleanNGS SPRI beads (0.9 volumes; CleanNA cat. #CNGS-0050) and paired-end sequenced.</p><p id="P42">The fully detailed protocol will be uploaded to Protocol Exchange platform or similar upon acceptance of the manuscript.</p></sec><sec id="S15"><title>Sequencing</title><p id="P43">B-ALL liCHi-C libraries were sequenced by Macrogen Inc using HiseqX 150+150PE platform. The rest of liCHi-C libraries were sequenced by BGI Genomics using DNBseq 100+100PE platform.</p></sec><sec id="S16"><title>B-ALL cytogenetic and FISH analysis</title><p id="P44">Cytogenetic analyses of B-ALL samples were carried out on G-banded chromosomes obtained from 24-hour unstimulated culture. FISH analyses were performed on fixed cell suspensions of the bone marrow using the LSI MYC probe (Metasystems, XL MYC BA) and the LSI IGH probe (Metasystems, XL IGH BA), respectively. Between 200 to 400 interphase nuclei were scored.</p></sec><sec id="S17"><title>liCHi-C processing</title><p id="P45">Paired-end reads were processed using HiCUP (0.8.2)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">22</xref></sup>. First, the genome was computationally digested using the target sequence of the restriction enzyme. Then, the different steps of the HiCUP pipeline were applied to map the reads to the human genome (GRCh38.p13), filter out all the experimental artifacts and remove the duplicated reads and retain only the valid unique paired reads. To assess the capture efficiency, we filtered out those paired reads for which any end overlaps with a captured restriction fragment, retaining only the unique captured valid reads for further analysis. Library statistics for all samples are presented in Supplementary Information <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Table 1</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="S18"><title>liCHi-C interaction calling</title><p id="P46">Interaction confidence scores were computed using the CHiCAGO R package as described in<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R64">64</xref></sup>. In summary, this pipeline implements a statistical model with two components (biological and technical background), together with normalization and multiple testing methods for capture Hi-C data. CHiCAGO analysis was performed in merged samples to increase the sensitivity, after assessing for reproducibility between biological replicates using: i) the stratum adjusted correlation coefficient according to<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R65">65</xref></sup>, averaged over chromosomes, ii) principal component analysis, and iii) hierarchical clustering. The reproducibility-score was also used to compare PCHi-C and liCHi-C libraries of the same cell types. Significant interactions with a CHiCAGO score ≥ 5 were considered as high confidence interactions. Interaction statistics for all samples are presented in Supplementary Information <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Table 1</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="S19"><title>Loop calling using Hi-C, Low-C and TagHi-C</title><p id="P47">We processed Hi-C, TagHi-C and Low-C data with HiCUP<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">22</xref></sup> as detailed above, using the human (GRCh38.p13) and mouse reference genomes (GRCm39). Loop calling was performed with three different methods: HICCUPS<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27">27</xref></sup> (1.22.01), Mustache<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">28</xref></sup> (1.2.7) and HiCExplorer<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">29</xref></sup> (3.7.2). All loop callers were used with default parameters on Knight-Ruiz normalized matrices at 5 kb resolution and a maximum loop distance of 8 Mb. Specific parameters for HICCUPS were: -cpu--ignore_sparsity; for Mustache, the p value threshold was set to 0.05.</p></sec><sec id="S20"><title>Clustering of promoter interactions</title><p id="P48">Interactions were clustered using the Autoclass algorithm and for each cluster a specificity score was computed as described in<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref></sup> using the asinh-transformed CHiCAGO scores. Clustering of cell types was performed using a hierarchical method with average linkage based on Euclidean distances, and principal component analysis was performed using the prcomp function in R. For interaction data handling we used an in-house R package which allows us to compute distance distributions, filter interactions by the presence of histones marks, or generate virtual 4C of specific genes.</p></sec><sec id="S21"><title>ChIP-seq processing</title><p id="P49">Paired-end reads were processed following ENCODE standards. Reads were trimmed using Trim Galore (0.6.5) to remove sequencing adapters, and then mapped using bowtie2 (2.3.2) to the reference genome at PRS (GRCh38.p13) with –very-sensitive parameter. We filtered out low quality reads, reads overlapping the ENCODE blacklist and duplicated reads. Peak calling was performed using macs2 (2.2.7.1) in broad and narrow mode depending on the histone mark using an input sample as control, with default parameters. Bigwig files were generated using the function bamCoverage from deepTools (3.2.1) and scaled based on the background normalization of the samples as described in<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R66">66</xref></sup> before merging the biological replicates together for visualization purposes. All ChIP-seq data analyzed in this article is presented in Supplementary Information <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD4">Table 3</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="S22"><title>Histones mark enrichment at PIRs</title><p id="P50">Enrichment of the different histones mark ChIP-seq in both promoters and npPIRs was performed using a permutation test implemented in GenoMatriXeR<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R67">67</xref></sup>, with 5000 randomizations using the randomizeRegions option. Promoter interactions were classified based on the RPKM expression quartiles of their genes, and the promoters and npPIRs analyzed separately, generating four groups of either promoters or npPIRs from lower expression to higher expression.</p></sec><sec id="S23"><title>Chromatin assortativity</title><p id="P51">Chromatin assortativity was computed for the promoter-pPIR and promoter-npPIR subnetworks separately using ChAseR R package (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://bitbucket.org/eraineri/chaser">https://bitbucket.org/eraineri/chaser</ext-link>) as described in<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37">37</xref></sup>. We validated our results against a set of 1000 randomizations preserving the genomic distances between nodes and the chromosomes distribution of interactions. The abundance of each histone mark on the nodes of the networks was also computed.</p></sec><sec id="S24"><title>Gene ontology and pathways enrichment analysis</title><p id="P52">Gene ontology (GO) enrichment analysis was performed using clusterProfiler R package for the 3 ontologies: molecular functions, biological processes and cellular components. The pathway analysis was done using ReactomePA<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R68">68</xref></sup>. We used the prioritized protein-coding genes by COGS (gene score &gt;= 0.5) to compute enrichment in genes in Reactome pathways, adjusting p values by false discovery rate. In both analyses we used as universe all the genes in the capture design.</p></sec><sec id="S25"><title>Data visualization</title><p id="P53">To visualize the contact matrices, the bam files, containing unique captured valid reads, were transformed into pair files using bam2pairs. Then they were converted into matrices in cool format with a resolution of 1Mb, 250kb and 100kb using cooler<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R69">69</xref></sup> (0.8.11). The visualization of the matrices was done using HiCExplorer<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R70">70</xref></sup>. For the visualization of significant interactions generated by liCHi-C we used the WashU Epigenome Browser<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R71">71</xref></sup> and karyoploteR R package<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R72">72</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="S26"><title>GWAS summary statistics and imputation</title><p id="P54">GWAS summary data was obtained from the NHGRI-EBI GWAS Catalog<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R73">73</xref></sup> and from the UK Biobank - Neale Lab (UK Biobank, <italic>n.d.;</italic> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nealelab.is/uk-biobank">http://www.nealelab.is/uk-biobank</ext-link>), as reported in Supplementary Information <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table 4</xref>. Those datasets that were not in GRCh38 coordinates were converted to it using <italic>liftOver</italic>. To avoid spuriously strong association statistics, we filtered out SNPs with p value &lt; 5·10<sup>-8</sup> for which there were no SNPs in LD (r2 &gt; 0.6 using 1000 genomes EUR cohort as a reference genotype set<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R74">74</xref></sup> or within 50kb with p value &lt; 10<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref></sup>. To increase the power of the GWAS we applied the Poor Man’s Imputation as described in<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref></sup> to the summary statistics described above using as reference genotype set the 1000 Genomes EUR cohort. We used the GRCh38 HapMap Phase II genetic map lifted from GRCh37 coordinates<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R75">75</xref></sup> to define regions with 1cM recombination frequency to be used for the imputation. The MHC region (GRCh38:6:25-35Mb) was excluded from the analysis. Manhattan plots were visualized using the qqman package (0.1.8)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R76">76</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="S27"><title>GWAS enrichment at PIRs</title><p id="P55">Enrichment of SNPs in PIRs was performed using Blockshifter as described in<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref></sup> which considers the correlation between GWAS and PIRs. Blockshifter computes a z-score using a competitive test for each trait and cell type set.</p></sec><sec id="S28"><title>liCHi-C GWAS prioritizing genes</title><p id="P56">Prioritization of relevant genes for each GWAS trait and cell type was performed using the COGS algorithm as described in<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref></sup>. Briefly, this method considers linkage disequilibrium to estimate the posterior probability of each SNP being casual for each trait. Then, these SNPs were used to compute a gene-score for all the genes involved in liCHi-C significant interactions in at least one cell type. This gene-score is composed of 3 components: coding SNPs annotated by VEP (104)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R77">77</xref></sup>; SNPs located in promoter regions; and SNPs overlapping Other-Ends.</p></sec><sec id="S29"><title>SVs analysis</title><p id="P57">Translocations of B-ALL samples were identified using PLIER<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R61">61</xref></sup>. Briefly it compares the genome-wide interactions of a region against a set of random permutations computing a z-score. To detect CNVs, we applied BIC-seq2<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R78">78</xref></sup>, an algorithm that uses Bayesian information criterion-based segmentation on normalized data using naïve B samples as control genome. Visual inspection of both translocations and CNVs was performed by computing the log2ratio between the contact matrices of B-ALL and CLP samples.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="SM"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1"><label>Tomas-Daza L., Rovirosa L. et al _Supplementary Information_Table 4_Primers, adapters and PCR</label><media xlink:href="EMS156682-supplement-Tomas_Daza_L___Rovirosa_L__et_al__Supplementary_Information_Table_4_Primers__adapters_and_PCR.xlsx" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.spreadsheetml.sheet" id="d88aAdEbB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD2"><label>Tomas-Daza L., Rovirosa L. et al _Supplementary Information_Table_1_liCHiC_statistics</label><media xlink:href="EMS156682-supplement-Tomas_Daza_L___Rovirosa_L__et_al__Supplementary_Information_Table_1_liCHiC_statistics.xlsx" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.spreadsheetml.sheet" id="d88aAdEcB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD3"><label>Tomas-Daza L., Rovirosa L. et al _Supplementary Information_Table_2_RNA-seq &amp; ChIP-seq datasets</label><media xlink:href="EMS156682-supplement-Tomas_Daza_L___Rovirosa_L__et_al__Supplementary_Information_Table_2_RNA_seq___ChIP_seq_datasets.xlsx" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.spreadsheetml.sheet" id="d88aAdEdB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD4"><label>Tomas-Daza L., Rovirosa L. et al _Supplementary Information_Table_3_GWAS_datasets</label><media xlink:href="EMS156682-supplement-Tomas_Daza_L___Rovirosa_L__et_al__Supplementary_Information_Table_3_GWAS_datasets.xlsx" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.spreadsheetml.sheet" id="d88aAdEeB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD5"><label>Supplementary Material</label><media xlink:href="EMS156682-supplement-Supplementary_Material.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" id="d88aAdEfB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack id="S30"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank Roberto Malinverni, Oliver S. Burren, Mikhail Spivakov, Vera Pancaldi, Emanuele Raineri, Sven Sewitz and Steven W. Wingett for computational feedback. We gratefully acknowledge the participation of volunteers. We are indebted to the Barcelona Tissue Bank and the Sant Joan de Déu Hospital Biobank integrated in the Spanish Biobank Network of ISCIII for the non-fetal sample and data procurement. The human embryonic and fetal material was provided by the Joint MRC / Wellcome Trust (Grant # MR/006237/1) Human Developmental Biology Resource (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.hdbr.org">http://www.hdbr.org</ext-link>). Finally, we also want to thank Sandra Castillo, Sergi Cuartero, Esteban Ballestar and members of the Javierre Group for critical discussion. This work was supported by FEDER/Spanish Ministry of Science and Innovation (RTI2018-094788-A-I00) and the European Hematology Association (4823998). BMJ is funded by La Caixa Banking Foundation Junior Leader project (LCF/BQ/PI19/11690001), LT-D is funded by the FPI Fellowship (PRE2019-088005), LR is funded by an AGAUR FI fellowship (2019FI-B00017), PL-M is funded by FPU fellowship and OM is funded by an investigator fellowship from Spanish Association against Cancer (INVES211226MOLI). The funder bodies were not involved in the study design, collection, analysis, interpretation of data, the writing of this article or the decision to submit it for publication.</p></ack><sec id="S31" sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p id="P58">All the liCHi-C datasets generated in the present article will be available in EGA. <bold><italic>Accession number will be provided after completing the data upload.</italic></bold></p><sec id="S32" sec-type="data-availability"><title>Code availability</title><p id="P59">All the analyses done in the present article are accessible in the following GitHub repository: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/JavierreLab/liCHiC">https://github.com/JavierreLab/liCHiC</ext-link></p></sec></sec><fn-group><fn id="FN1"><p id="P60"><bold>Institutional Review Board Statement</bold></p><p id="P61">The study was conducted according to the guidelines of the Declaration of Helsinki and approved by the Institutional Review Board of the Clinical Research Ethics Committee of University Hospital Germans Trias i Pujol (REF.CEI: PI-18-205).</p></fn><fn id="FN2" fn-type="con"><p id="P62"><bold>Author contributions</bold></p><p id="P63">BMJ designed research; OM, CG, EC, DC, MC, CB and PM contributed on sample isolation; LR, APR, RM and BMJ performed research; LT-D, PL-M, AN-A, FS analyzed data; BMJ wrote the paper with support of LT-D, LR and PL-M; and all authors provided feedback on the manuscript.</p></fn><fn id="FN3" fn-type="conflict"><p id="P64"><bold>Competing interest</bold></p><p id="P65">No competing interest</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><ref id="R1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zuin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Nonlinear control of transcription through enhancer–promoter interactions</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2022</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41586-022-04570-y</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Amano</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Chromosomal Dynamics at the Shh Locus: Limb Bud-Specific Differential Regulation of Competence and Active Transcription</article-title><source>Dev Cell</source><year>2009</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>47</fpage><lpage>57</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Altshuler</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Daly</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lander</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic Mapping in Human Disease</article-title><source>Science (80- )</source><year>2008</year><volume>322</volume><fpage>881</fpage><lpage>888</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maurano</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Systematic Localization of Common Disease-Associated Variation in Regulatory DNA</article-title><source>Science (80- )</source><year>2012</year><volume>337</volume><fpage>1190</fpage><lpage>1195</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Javierre</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Lineage-Specific Genome Architecture Links Enhancers and Non-coding Disease Variants to Target Gene Promoters</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2016</year><volume>167</volume><fpage>1369</fpage><lpage>1384</lpage><elocation-id>e19</elocation-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schoenfelder</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The pluripotent regulatory circuitry connecting promoters to their long-range interacting elements</article-title><source>Genome Res</source><year>2015</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gr.185272.114</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schoenfelder</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Polycomb repressive complex PRC1 spatially constrains the mouse embryonic stem cell genome</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><year>2015</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>1179</fpage><lpage>1186</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Siersbæk</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Dynamic Rewiring of Promoter-Anchored Chromatin Loops during Adipocyte Differentiation</article-title><source>Mol Cell</source><year>2017</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>420</fpage><lpage>435</lpage><elocation-id>e5</elocation-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rubin</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Barajas</surname></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Lineage-specific dynamic and pre-established enhancer – promoter contacts cooperate in terminal differentiation</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><year>2017</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A compendium of promoter-centered long-range chromatin interactions in the human genome</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><year>2019</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>1442</fpage><lpage>1449</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dryden</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Unbiased analysis of potential targets of breast cancer susceptibility loci by Capture Hi-C</article-title><source>Genome Res</source><year>2014</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gr.175034.114</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McGovern</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Capture Hi-C identifies a novel causal gene, IL20RA, in the pan-autoimmune genetic susceptibility region 6q23</article-title><source>Genome Biol</source><year>2016</year><volume>17</volume><elocation-id>212</elocation-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jäger</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Capture Hi-C identifies the chromatin interactome of colorectal cancer risk loci</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2015</year><volume>6</volume></element-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Choy</surname><given-names>M-K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Promoter interactome of human embryonic stem cell-derived cardiomyocytes connects GWAS regions to cardiac gene networks</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2018</year><volume>9</volume><elocation-id>2526</elocation-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Platelet function is modified by common sequence variation in megakaryocyte super enhancers</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2017</year><volume>8</volume><elocation-id>16058</elocation-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Watt</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genetic perturbation of PU.1 binding and chromatin looping at neutrophil enhancers associates with autoimmune disease</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2021</year><volume>12</volume><elocation-id>2298</elocation-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Burren</surname><given-names>OS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Chromosome contacts in activated T cells identify autoimmune disease candidate genes</article-title><source>Genome Biol</source><year>2017</year><volume>18</volume><elocation-id>165</elocation-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Epigenomics and transcriptomics of systemic sclerosis CD4+ T cells reveal long-range dysregulation of key inflammatory pathways mediated by disease-associated susceptibility loci</article-title><source>Genome Med</source><year>2020</year><volume>12</volume><elocation-id>81</elocation-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miguel-Escalada</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Human pancreatic islet three-dimensional chromatin architecture provides insights into the genetics of type 2 diabetes</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><year>2019</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>1137</fpage><lpage>1148</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Capture Hi-C reveals novel candidate genes and complex long-range interactions with related autoimmune risk loci</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2015</year><volume>6</volume><elocation-id>10069</elocation-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Speedy</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Insight into genetic predisposition to chronic lymphocytic leukemia from integrative epigenomics</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2019</year><volume>10</volume><elocation-id>3615</elocation-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wingett</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>HiCUP: pipeline for mapping and processing Hi-C data [version 1; peer review: 2 approved, 1 approved with reservations]</article-title><source>F1000Research</source><year>2015</year><volume>4</volume></element-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cairns</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>CHiCAGO: robust detection of DNA looping interactions in Capture Hi-C data</article-title><source>Genome Biol</source><year>2016</year><volume>17</volume><elocation-id>127</elocation-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Díaz</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Chromatin conformation analysis of primary patient tissue using a low input Hi-C method</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2018</year><volume>9</volume><elocation-id>4938</elocation-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vilarrasa-Blasi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Dynamics of genome architecture and chromatin function during human B cell differentiation and neoplastic transformation</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2021</year><volume>12</volume><elocation-id>651</elocation-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>tagHi-C Reveals 3D Chromatin Architecture Dynamics during Mouse Hematopoiesis</article-title><source>Cell Rep</source><year>2020</year><volume>32</volume></element-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Durand</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Juicer Provides a One-Click System for Analyzing Loop-Resolution Hi-C Experiments</article-title><source>Cell Syst</source><year>2016</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>95</fpage><lpage>98</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roayaei Ardakany</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gezer</surname><given-names>HT</given-names></name><name><surname>Lonardi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ay</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mustache: multi-scale detection of chromatin loops from Hi-C and Micro-C maps using scale-space representation</article-title><source>Genome Biol</source><year>2020</year><volume>21</volume><elocation-id>256</elocation-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wolff</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Backofen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Grüning</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Loop detection using Hi-C data with HiCExplorer</article-title><source>Gigascience</source><year>2022</year><volume>11</volume><issue>giac061</issue></element-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fahl</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Crittenden</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>Allman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Bender</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>c-Myb is required for pro-B cell differentiation</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><year>2009</year><volume>183</volume><fpage>5582</fpage><lpage>5592</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bray</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Platelet glycoprotein IIb. Chromosomal localization and tissue expression</article-title><source>J Clin Invest</source><year>1987</year><volume>80</volume><fpage>1812</fpage><lpage>1817</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yokogawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Characterization and tRNA Recognition of Mammalian Mitochondrial Seryl-tRNA Synthetase *</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2000</year><volume>275</volume><fpage>19913</fpage><lpage>19920</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Natoli</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Andrau</surname><given-names>J-C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Noncoding Transcription at Enhancers: General Principles and Functional Models</article-title><source>Annu Rev Genet</source><year>2012</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>19</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>I-C</given-names></name><name><surname>Tai</surname><given-names>T-S</given-names></name><name><surname>Pai</surname><given-names>S-Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>GATA3 and the T-cell lineage: essential functions before and after T-helper-2-cell differentiation</article-title><source>Nat Rev Immunol</source><year>2009</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>125</fpage><lpage>135</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cobaleda</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Schebesta</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Delogu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Busslinger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pax5: the guardian of B cell identity and function</article-title><source>Nat Immunol</source><year>2007</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>463</fpage><lpage>470</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A sticky wicket: Defining molecular functions for CD34 in hematopoietic cells</article-title><source>Exp Hematol</source><year>2020</year><volume>86</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>14</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Madrid-Mencía</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Raineri</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>TBN</given-names></name><name><surname>Pancaldi</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Using GARDEN-NET and ChAseR to explore human haematopoietic 3D chromatin interaction networks</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2020</year><volume>48</volume><fpage>4066</fpage><lpage>4080</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fabregat</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The Reactome pathway Knowledgebase</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2016</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>D481</fpage><lpage>D487</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kokabu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Expression of TLE3 by bone marrow stromal cells is regulated by canonical Wnt signaling</article-title><source>FEBS Lett</source><year>2014</year><volume>588</volume><fpage>614</fpage><lpage>619</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bilardi</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Impact of loss of BH3-only proteins on the development and treatment of MLL-fusion gene-driven AML in mice</article-title><source>Cell Death Dis</source><year>2016</year><elocation-id>7</elocation-id><fpage>e2351</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R41"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bahr</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A Myc enhancer cluster regulates normal and leukaemic haematopoietic stem cell hierarchies</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2018</year><volume>553</volume><fpage>515</fpage><lpage>520</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R42"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Sen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Roeder</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Enhancer-promoter communication and transcriptional regulation of Igh</article-title><source>Trends Immunol</source><year>2011</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>532</fpage><lpage>539</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R43"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Akasaka</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Five members of the CEBP transcription factor family are targeted by recurrent IGH translocations in B-cell precursor acute lymphoblastic leukemia (BCP-ALL)</article-title><source>Blood</source><year>2006</year><volume>109</volume><fpage>3451</fpage><lpage>3461</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R44"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scheijen</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Tumor suppressors BTG1 and IKZF1 cooperate during mouse leukemia development and increase relapse risk in B-cell precursor acute lymphoblastic leukemia patients</article-title><source>Haematologica</source><year>2017</year><volume>102</volume><fpage>541</fpage><lpage>551</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R45"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The Role of ARID5B in Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia and Beyond</article-title><source>Front Genet</source><year>2020</year><volume>11</volume><elocation-id>598</elocation-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R46"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Delgado</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>León</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Myc roles in hematopoiesis and leukemia</article-title><source>Genes Cancer</source><year>2010</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>605</fpage><lpage>616</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R47"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name><name><surname>Hess</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Role of HOXA9 in leukemia: dysregulation, cofactors and essential targets</article-title><source>Oncogene</source><year>2016</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>1090</fpage><lpage>1098</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R48"><label>48</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alharbi</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Pettengell</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Pandha</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of HOX genes in normal hematopoiesis and acute leukemia</article-title><source>Leukemia</source><year>2013</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>1000</fpage><lpage>1008</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R49"><label>49</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>WY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A novel bi-alleleic DDX41 mutations in B-cell lymphoblastic leukemia: case report</article-title><source>BMC Med Genomics</source><year>2022</year><volume>15</volume><elocation-id>46</elocation-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R50"><label>50</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lieberman-Aiden</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Comprehensive Mapping of Long-Range Interactions Reveals Folding Principles of the Human Genome</article-title><source>Science (80-.)</source><year>2009</year><volume>326</volume><fpage>289</fpage><lpage>293</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R51"><label>51</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nagano</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Single-cell Hi-C reveals cell-to-cell variability in chromosome structure</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2013</year><volume>502</volume></element-citation></ref><ref id="R52"><label>52</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Xing</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>C-H</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>XS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Three-dimensional genome structures of single diploid human cells</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2018</year><volume>361</volume><fpage>924</fpage><lpage>928</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R53"><label>53</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Allelic reprogramming of 3D chromatin architecture during early mammalian development</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2017</year><volume>547</volume><fpage>232</fpage><lpage>235</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R54"><label>54</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ke</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>3D Chromatin Structures of Mature Gametes and Structural Reprogramming during Mammalian Embryogenesis</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2017</year><volume>170</volume><fpage>367</fpage><lpage>381</lpage><elocation-id>e20</elocation-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R55"><label>55</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mumbach</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>HiChIP: efficient and sensitive analysis of protein-directed genome architecture</article-title><source>Nat Methods</source><year>2016</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>919</fpage><lpage>922</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R56"><label>56</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sati</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>HiCuT: An efficient and low input method to identify protein-directed chromatin interactions</article-title><source>PLoS Genet</source><year>2022</year><volume>18</volume><elocation-id>e1010121</elocation-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R57"><label>57</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Juric</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Abnousi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><source>Proximity Ligation-Assisted ChIP-Seq (PLAC-Seq) BT - Enhancers and Promoters: Methods and Protocols</source><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Borggrefe</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Giaimo</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name></person-group><publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name><publisher-loc>US</publisher-loc><year>2021</year><fpage>181</fpage><lpage>199</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-1-0716-1597-3_10</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R58"><label>58</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fullwood</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>An oestrogen-receptor-α-bound human chromatin interactome</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2009</year><volume>462</volume><fpage>58</fpage><lpage>64</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R59"><label>59</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oudelaar</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Dynamics of the 4D genome during in vivo lineage specification and differentiation</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2020</year><volume>11</volume><elocation-id>2722</elocation-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R60"><label>60</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oudelaar</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>JOJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Downes</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Higgs</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Robust detection of chromosomal interactions from small numbers of cells using low-input Capture-C</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2017</year><volume>45</volume><elocation-id>e184</elocation-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R61"><label>61</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Allahyar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Robust detection of translocations in lymphoma FFPE samples using targeted locus capture-based sequencing</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2021</year><volume>12</volume><elocation-id>3361</elocation-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R62"><label>62</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rickman</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Oncogene-mediated alterations in chromatin conformation</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2012</year><volume>109</volume><fpage>9083</fpage><lpage>9088</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R63"><label>63</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anindita</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Perturbation of fetal liver hematopoietic stem and progenitor cell development by trisomy 21</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci</source><year>2012</year><volume>109</volume><fpage>17579</fpage><lpage>17584</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R64"><label>64</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Freire-Pritchett</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Detecting chromosomal interactions in Capture Hi-C data with CHiCAGO and companion tools</article-title><source>Nat Protoc</source><year>2021</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>4144</fpage><lpage>4176</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R65"><label>65</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>HiCRep: assessing the reproducibility of Hi-C data using a stratum-adjusted correlation coefficient</article-title><source>Genome Res</source><year>2017</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>1939</fpage><lpage>1949</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R66"><label>66</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Torbey</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cooperation, cis-interactions, versatility and evolutionary plasticity of multiple cis-acting elements underlie krox20 hindbrain regulation</article-title><source>PLOS Genet</source><year>2018</year><volume>14</volume><elocation-id>e1007581</elocation-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R67"><label>67</label><element-citation publication-type="other"><collab>RMalinverni</collab><source>RMalinverni/GenoMatriXeR: genoMatriXeR</source><year>2022</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5281/ZENODO.6379726</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R68"><label>68</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>Q-Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>ReactomePA: an R/Bioconductor package for reactome pathway analysis and visualization</article-title><source>Mol BioSyst</source><year>2016</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>477</fpage><lpage>479</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R69"><label>69</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abdennur</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Mirny</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cooler: scalable storage for Hi-C data and other genomically labeled arrays</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2020</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>311</fpage><lpage>316</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R70"><label>70</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ramírez</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>High-resolution TADs reveal DNA sequences underlying genome organization in flies</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2018</year><volume>9</volume><elocation-id>189</elocation-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R71"><label>71</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>WashU Epigenome Browser update 2022</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2022</year><comment>gkac238</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkac238</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R72"><label>72</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Serra</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>karyoploteR: an R/Bioconductor package to plot customizable genomes displaying arbitrary data</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2017</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>3088</fpage><lpage>3090</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R73"><label>73</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Buniello</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The NHGRI-EBI GWAS Catalog of published genome-wide association studies, targeted arrays and summary statistics 2019</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2019</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>D1005</fpage><lpage>D1012</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R74"><label>74</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lowy-Gallego</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Variant calling on the GRCh38 assembly with the data from phase three of the 1000 Genomes Project</article-title><source>Wellcome open Res</source><year>2019</year><volume>4</volume><elocation-id>50</elocation-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R75"><label>75</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Frazer</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A second generation human haplotype map of over 3.1 million SNPs</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2007</year><volume>449</volume><fpage>851</fpage><lpage>861</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R76"><label>76</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>qqman: an R package for visualizing GWAS results using Q-Q and manhattan plotsitle</article-title><source>J Open Source Softw</source><year>2018</year><volume>3</volume><issue>25</issue><elocation-id>731</elocation-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R77"><label>77</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McLaren</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The Ensembl Variant Effect Predictor</article-title><source>Genome Biol</source><year>2016</year><volume>17</volume><elocation-id>122</elocation-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R78"><label>78</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>T-M</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Copy number analysis of wholegenome data using BIC-seq2 and its application to detection of cancer susceptibility variants</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2016</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>6274</fpage><lpage>6286</lpage></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><title>liCHi-C is a robust and reproducible method to study the promoter interactome in low-abundance cell populations.</title><p><bold>a.</bold> Schematic comparison of the PCHi-C vs liCHi-C workflow. Dash-bordered boxes denote removed steps from the original PCHi-C protocol.</p><p><bold>b.</bold> Heatmap displaying stratum adjusted correlation coefficient (SCC) between promoter interactomes of human naïve B cells obtained by liCHi-C and PCHi-C (*) using different cell numbers. Reproducibility between biological replicates and between pairs of merged biological replicates are surrounded by black and grey lines respectively. 1000 (k), million (M).</p><p><bold>c.</bold> Principal Component Analysis of CHiCAGO significant interactions (CHiCAGO scores &gt; 5) of biological replicates detected by liCHi-C and PCHi-C (*) using different cell numbers.</p><p><bold>d.</bold> Top: Interaction matrix at 50kb resolution generated with PCHi-C and 40 million cells. Colored contour plot over the interaction matrix represents gaussian smoothing (alpha=1.2) of the significant CHICAGO interactions detected by liCHi-C data using different numbers of input cells. Bottom: Significant interactions (arcs) detected with liCHi-C and PCHi-C (*) and Hi-C using different numbers of input cells</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS156682-f001"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><title>liCHi-C enables the study of <italic>in vivo</italic> human hematopoiesis.</title><p><bold>a.</bold> Heatmap displaying stratum adjusted correlation coefficient (SCC) between promoter interactomes of merged biological replicates. Hematopoietic stem cell (HSC), common myeloid progenitor (CMP), common B cell lymphoid progenitor (CLP), megakaryocytes (MK), monocytes (Mon), erythroblast (Ery), naïve B cell (nB), naïve CD4<sup>+</sup> cells (nCD4) and naïve CD8<sup>+</sup> cells (nCD8).</p><p><bold>b.</bold> Principal Component Analysis of liCHi-C significant interactions (CHiCAGO scores &gt; 5) from merged biological replicates. Shaded in grey are the predicted differentiation trajectories for both lymphoid and myeloid lineages.</p><p><bold>c.</bold> Heatmap of asinh-transformed CHiCAGO score of significant interactions in at least one cell type clustered using Autoclass algorithm.</p><p><bold>d.</bold> Top: Dendrogram of hierarchical clustering with average linkage based on Euclidean distances of CHiCAGO significant interactions of merged samples. Bottom: Heatmap of cluster specificity score of each Autoclass cluster.</p><p><italic>MYB</italic> (<bold>e.</bold>) <italic>ITGA2B</italic> (<bold>f.</bold>) and <italic>SARS2</italic> (<bold>g.</bold>) promoter-centered interactions (arcs) according to liCHi-C data. Arrows symbolize gene placement and orientation along the genomic window. Green shade depicts the gene promoter.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS156682-f002"/></fig><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><title>liCHi-C identifies enhancer-promoter pairs and proteins involved in chromatin organization.</title><p><bold>a.</bold> Heatmap representing enrichment (expressed in terms of z-scores) of promoters (top) and non-promoter promoter-interacting regions (npPIRs) (bottom) for histone marks. PIRs and promoters were classified by the quartiles level of FPKM expression of the associated gene. Hematopoietic stem cell (HSC), common myeloid progenitor (CMP), common B cell lymphoid progenitor (CLP), megakaryocytes (MK), monocytes (Mon), erythroblast (Ery), naïve B cell (nB), naïve CD4<sup>+</sup> cells (nCD4) and naïve CD8<sup>+</sup> cells (nCD8).</p><p><bold>b.</bold> <italic>GATA3</italic> regulatory landscape in naïve B (top), naïve CD4<sup>+</sup> T (middle) and naïve CD8<sup>+</sup> T (bottom) cells according to histone modifications and liCHi-C data. Green shade depicts the gene promoter, while yellow shades depict putative enhancer regions for that gene in any of these cell types. Arrows symbolize gene placement and orientation along the genomic window.</p><p><bold>c.</bold> Scatterplot plot of chromatin assortativity (ChAs) of 6 histone marks computed for the promoter-pPIR sub-network (x axis) against the promoter-npPIR (y axis) for common myeloid progenitor cells. Dot size depends on the abundancy of each histone mark.</p><p><bold>d.</bold> H3K9me3-centred interaction network (arcs) for common myeloid progenitor cells. Top graph depicts whole chromosome 19, while bottom graph shows a zoom centered on a <italic>ZNF</italic> gene cluster. Arrows symbolize gene placement and orientation along the genomic window.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS156682-f003"/></fig><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><title>liCHi-C enables the discovery of new disease-relevant cell types and disease-associated genes and gene pathways.</title><p><bold>a.</bold> Enrichment of GWAS summary statistics at promoter-interacting regions (PIRs) by cell type. Axes reflect Blockshifter z-scores for two different tissue group comparisons: myeloid versus lymphoid (y axis) and undifferentiated against differentiated cells (x axis). Traits are labeled and colored by category: autoimmune disorder (red), lymphoid trait (yellow), myeloid trait (green), blood cancer (blue) and other (purple). Systolic blood pressure (SBP), diastolic blood pressure (DBP), femoral neck bone mineral density (FNBD), depression (DEP) autism (AUT), low density lipoprotein (LDL), body mass index (BMI), glucose sensitivity (GLC), total cholesterol (TC), triglycerides (TG), type II diabetes (T2D), primary biliary cirrhosis (PBC), type I diabetes (T1D), rheumatoid arthritis (RA), systemic lupus erythematosus (SLE), multiple sclerosis (MS), Crohn’s disease (CD), celiac disease (CD), B cell absolute count (BC), white blood cell count (WBCC), CD4 regulatory T cell absolute count (CD4regC), Naïve CD8<sup>+</sup> T cell absolute count (nCD8C), Hodgkins lymphoma (HL), leukemia (Leu), non-Hodgkins lymphoma_1 (NHL_1:), non-Hodgkins lymphoma_2 (NHL_2), primary lymphoid and hematopoietic malignant neoplasms (PLHMN), lymphoid leukemia (LLC91), chronic lymphocytic leukemia (CLL), lymphoid leukaemia_1 (LL_1), lymphoid leukaemia_2 (LL_2), monocyte count (MC), myeloid white cell count (MWCC), mean corpuscular hemoglobin concentration (MCHC), mean corpuscular hemoglobin (MCH), mean corpuscular volume (MCV), mean platelet volume (MPV), platelet count (PC), red blood cell count (RBCC).</p><p><bold>b.</bold> Heatmap of Blockshifter enrichment z-scores of GWAS summary statistics at promoterinteracting regions (PIRs) by individual cell types using endothelial cells as a control. For each trait, comparisons have been made between each individual cell type against the control endothelial precursors. Green indicates enrichment in the labeled tissue; blue indicates enrichment in the endothelial cell control. Hematopoietic stem cell (HSC), common myeloid progenitor (CMP), common B cell lymphoid progenitor (CLP), megakaryocytes (MK), monocytes (Mon), erythroblasts (Ery), naïve B cell (nB), naïve CD4<sup>+</sup> cells (nCD4) and naïve CD8<sup>+</sup> cells (nCD8).</p><p><bold>c.</bold> Density distribution of the distance between selected SNPs and the transcription start site (TSS) of the nearest protein-coding gene (blue) and the TSS of the gene prioritized by COGS (green). For each GWAS trait, we selected all the significantly associated SNPs (p value &lt; 5·10<sup>-8</sup>) interacting with at least one protein-coding gene prioritized by COGS. Coding SNPs or non-coding SNPs overlapping promoters were excluded. Vertical lines represent median distance.</p><p><bold>d.</bold> Bubble plot of traits with significant enrichment (p-adj &lt; 0.05) in one or more pathways from the Reactome database. Top numbers indicate the total number of genes analyzed for each trait (gene-score &gt; 0.5), bubble size indicates the ratio of test genes to those in the pathway, and blue to yellow corresponds to decreasing adjusted p value for enrichment.</p><p><bold>e.</bold> Example of prioritized gene (<italic>TLE3)</italic> for the trait lymphocytic leukemia (LL_2) in naïve CD4<sup>+</sup> cells. Top: Manhattan plot; grey line indicates the significance cut-off (5·10<sup>-8</sup>). Middle: prioritized SNPs (black dots) at naïve CD4<sup>+</sup> (nCD4) specific enhancer. Bottom: <italic>TLE3</italic> regulatory landscape nCD4 and erythroblasts (Ery). Green shade depicts the gene promoter, while yellow shades depict putative enhancer region for that gene enriched in prioritized non-coding SNPs. Arrows symbolize gene placement and orientation along the genomic window.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS156682-f004"/></fig><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><title>liCHi-C simultaneously detects translocations, copy number variations and topological alterations in tumor samples</title><p><bold>a.</bold> Detection of structural variants using liCHiC data for B cell precursor acute lymphoblastic leukemia (B-ALL) 1 (top) and B-ALL 2 (bottom). Grey matrices on the left represent the log2 ratio between B-ALL and CLP contact matrices at 1Mb resolution across the genome. Black arrows indicate the location of copy number gains. On the top right: matrices at a 250kb resolution of the chromosomes involved in the translocations. On the middle right: zoom-ins of the breakpoint regions and schematic representation of the translocated chromosomes and the location of the FISH probes. On the bottom right: FISH images displaying the translocation.</p><p><bold>b.</bold> Top: Schematic representation of <italic>MYC</italic> and <italic>IgH</italic> genes loci. Bottom: interaction landscape of chromosomes 8 and 14 in common B cell lymphoid progenitors (CLP) and B-ALL 1 sample. Interactions within and between chromosomes are represented over and below the chromosomes respectively.</p><p><bold>c.</bold> Reconstruction of <italic>MYC</italic> promoter interaction landscape on the derivative chromosome in BALL 1. Green shades depict the <italic>MYC</italic> promoter and BENC enhancer from chromosome 8, and the yellow shadow the 3’ RR enhancer from chromosome 14.</p><p><bold>d.</bold> Heatmap of asinh-transformed CHiCAGO score of significant interactions in at least one cell type clustered using Autoclass algorithm. Hematopoietic stem cell (HSC), naïve B cell (nB).</p><p><bold>e.</bold> Heatmap of cluster specificity score of each Autoclass cluster. Clusters containing interactions specific to B-ALL or interactions specifically lost in B-ALL are boxed.</p><p><bold>f.</bold> <italic>HOXA</italic> gene promoter-centered interaction landscape (arcs) in CLP, B-ALL 1 and B-ALL 2 samples. Green shade depicts the <italic>HOXA</italic> gene cluster, while yellow shades depict putative enhancer regions for that gene in any of these cell types. Arrows symbolize gene placement and orientation along the genomic window.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS156682-f005"/></fig><fig id="F6" position="float"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><title>Comparison of liCHi-C libraries at different resolutions.</title><p>Detection of structural variants using liCHi-C data for B cell precursor acute lymphoblastic leukemia (B-ALL) 3 generated using a six-cutter restriction enzyme (HindIII) (<bold>a</bold>) and a four-cutter restriction enzyme (MboI) (<bold>b</bold>). Grey matrices represent the log2 ratio between B-ALL and CLP contact matrices at 1Mb resolution across the genome. Black arrows indicate the location of copy number losses.</p><p><bold>c.</bold> Absolute frequency of interaction according to the genomic distance between interacting regions for liCHi-C libraries generated with MboI (blue) and HindIII (green) digestion respectively. Median and highest absolute frequency of interactions are represented by solid and dashed lines respectively.</p><p><bold>d.</bold> <italic>DDX41</italic> gene promoter-centered interaction landscape (arcs) generated with HindIII (top) and MboI (bottom) respectively. Green shade depicts the <italic>DDX41</italic> gene promoter, while yellow shades depict putative enhancer regions for it. Arrows symbolize gene placement and orientation along the genomic window.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS156682-f006"/></fig></floats-group></article>