<!DOCTYPE article
 PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" article-type="preprint"><?all-math-mml yes?><?use-mml?><?origin ukpmcpa?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">bioRxiv</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>bioRxiv : the preprint server for biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub"/></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">EMS155739</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2022.10.13.512056</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="archive">PPR558008</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="europepmc-category"><subject>Covid-19</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>A pseudovirus system enables deep mutational scanning of the full SARS-CoV-2 spike</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Dadonaite</surname><given-names>Bernadeta</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Crawford</surname><given-names>Katharine H D</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Radford</surname><given-names>Caelan E</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Farrell</surname><given-names>Ariana G</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Timothy C</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hannon</surname><given-names>William W</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Panpan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">5</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A6">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Andrabi</surname><given-names>Raiees</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">5</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A6">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Burton</surname><given-names>Dennis R</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">5</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A6">6</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A7">7</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Lihong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A8">8</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>David D.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A8">8</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A9">9</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A10">10</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Neher</surname><given-names>Richard A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A11">11</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bloom</surname><given-names>Jesse D</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A12">12</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN1">#</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Basic Sciences Division and Computational Biology Program, Fred Hutchinson Cancer Center, Seattle, Washington, 98109, USA</aff><aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Department of Genome Sciences &amp; Medical Scientist Training Program, University of Washington, Seattle, Washington, 98109, USA</aff><aff id="A3"><label>3</label>Molecular and Cellular Biology Graduate Program, University of Washington, and Basic Sciences Division, Fred Hutch Cancer Center, Seattle, Washington, 98109, USA</aff><aff id="A4"><label>4</label>Department of Immunology and Microbiology, The Scripps Research Institute, La Jolla, CA 92037, USA</aff><aff id="A5"><label>5</label>IAVI Neutralizing Antibody Center, The Scripps Research Institute, La Jolla, CA 92037, USA</aff><aff id="A6"><label>6</label>Consortium for HIV/AIDS Vaccine Development (CHAVD), The Scripps Research Institute, La Jolla, CA 92037, USA</aff><aff id="A7"><label>7</label>Ragon Institute of MGH, MIT &amp; Harvard, Cambridge, MA 02139, USA</aff><aff id="A8"><label>8</label>Aaron Diamond AIDS Research Center, Columbia University Vagelos College of Physicians and Surgeons, New York, NY, USA</aff><aff id="A9"><label>9</label>Department of Microbiology and Immunology, Columbia University Vagelos College of Physicians and Surgeons, New York, NY 10032, USA</aff><aff id="A10"><label>10</label>Division of Infectious Diseases, Department of Medicine, Columbia University Vagelos College of Physicians and Surgeons, New York, NY 10032, USA</aff><aff id="A11"><label>11</label>Biozentrum, University of Basel, Basel, Switzerland, Swiss Institute of Bioinformatics, Lausanne, Switzerland</aff><aff id="A12"><label>12</label>Howard Hughes Medical Institute, Seattle, WA, 98195, USA</aff><author-notes><fn id="FN1"><label>#</label><p id="P1">Lead Contact <email>jbloom@fredhutch.org</email></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted"><day>16</day><month>10</month><year>2022</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="preprint"><day>13</day><month>10</month><year>2022</year></pub-date><permissions><ali:free_to_read/><license><ali:license_ref>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is licensed under a <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0 International license</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p id="P2">A major challenge in understanding SARS-CoV-2 evolution is interpreting the antigenic and functional effects of emerging mutations in the viral spike protein. Here we describe a new deep mutational scanning platform based on non-replicative pseudotyped lentiviruses that directly quantifies how large numbers of spike mutations impact antibody neutralization and pseudovirus infection. We demonstrate this new platform by making libraries of the Omicron BA.1 and Delta spikes. These libraries each contain ~7000 distinct amino-acid mutations in the context of up to ~135,000 unique mutation combinations. We use these libraries to map escape mutations from neutralizing antibodies targeting the receptor binding domain, N-terminal domain, and S2 subunit of spike. Overall, this work establishes a high-throughput and safe approach to measure how ~10<sup>5</sup> combinations of mutations affect antibody neutralization and spike-mediated infection. Notably, the platform described here can be extended to the entry proteins of many other viruses.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec id="S1" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p id="P3">The spike protein is the key target of neutralizing antibodies against SARS-CoV-2. Unfortunately, spike has undergone rapid evolution which has eroded the potency of serum neutralization and enabled escape from most monoclonal antibodies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">Cao et al., 2022</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38">Liu et al., 2022</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R67">Wang et al., 2022b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R66">2022a</xref>). Deep mutational scanning experiments can prospectively measure the effects of large numbers of mutations even before they emerge in viral variants, and therefore have been a valuable tool for rapidly interpreting how newly observed mutations in the spike affect antibody binding and protein folding or function (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">Cao et al., 2022</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R58">Starr et al., 2021b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R57">2021a</xref>). The high-throughput nature of deep mutational scanning experiments has also enabled the generation of huge datasets that can inform computational methods for predicting the antigenic properties of possible future viral variants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">Cao et al., 2022</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">Greaney et al., 2022</xref>).</p><p id="P4">However, prior deep mutational scanning of the SARS-CoV-2 spike has been limited to either solely focusing on the receptor-binding domain (RBD) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">Cao et al., 2022</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">Greaney et al., 2021</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R59">Starr et al., 2020</xref>), other subdomains (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R50">Ouyang et al., 2022</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R61">Tan et al., 2022</xref>) or just a small number of mutations across spike (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">Javanmardi et al., 2021</xref>). Furthermore, all previous spike deep mutational scanning experiments have been based on cell-surface display using either yeast (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R60">Starr et al., 2022</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R59">2020</xref>) or mammalian cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">Javanmardi et al., 2021</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R50">Ouyang et al., 2022</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R61">Tan et al., 2022</xref>), and therefore are limited to measuring antibody binding rather than neutralization, despite the fact that neutralization is thought to be a more relevant correlate of protection (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">Feng et al., 2021</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">Gilbert et al., 2022</xref>).</p><p id="P5">Here we describe a new deep mutational scanning platform that directly measures how mutations affect cellular infection and antibody neutralization in the context of the full SARS-CoV-2 spike pseudotyped on non-replicative lentiviral particles. The key innovation behind the platform is a two-step pseudovirus generation protocol that enables creation of large pseudovirus libraries with a link between the lentiviral genotype and the particular spike protein variant on the pseudovirus’s surface. We demonstrate that this new platform can be used to create large genotype-phenotype linked pseudovirus libraries and map how mutations to spike affect both cellular infection and neutralization by antibodies targeting diverse regions of spike, including the RBD, N-terminal domain (NTD), and S2 subunit.</p></sec><sec id="S2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="S3"><title>Producing pseudoviruses with genotype-phenotype link</title><p id="P6">To characterize thousands of mutations in spike glycoprotein, we first established a lentiviral pseudotyping platform that maintains a genotype-phenotype link between the lentiviral genome and the spike variant on the virion’s surface. Lentiviral spike-pseudotyping usually involves transfection of a backbone that carries a reporter gene flanked by the lentiviral long terminal repeats (LTRs), helper plasmids that code for structural and nonstructural genes required for the lentiviral life cycle, and an expression plasmid that codes for the spike variant of interest (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">Crawford et al., 2020</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">Cronin et al., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R45">Naldini et al., 1996</xref>). When these components are transfected into producer cells, virions are formed that carry lentiviral genomes and display spikes on their surface. However, because genome incorporation into a virion does not depend on the expressed spike, there is no link between the virion’s genotype and the phenotype of the spike on its surface. The absence of a genotype-phenotype link is not problematic when only a single spike variant is used for transfection—however, it precludes deep mutational scanning studies that involve studying thousands of variants in a single pooled experiment.</p><p id="P7">To create a lentiviral genotype-phenotype link, we first generated a lentivirus backbone with the following key elements (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1A</xref>): (1) we restored the ability of the lentivirus to transcribe its full genome after integration by repairing the 3’ LTR deletion present in traditional lentivirus vectors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R47">OhAinle et al., 2018</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R74">Zufferey et al., 1998</xref>), (2) we placed spike in the lentivirus backbone under an inducible promoter, (3) we added a second constitutive promoter driving both a fluorescent reporter (ZsGreen) and a puromycin resistance gene.</p><p id="P8">Next, we developed a multi-step protocol that creates a genotype-phenotype link by ensuring that each producer cell only expresses a single variant of spike (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1B</xref>). In the first step of this protocol, we transfect cells with the spike-encoding backbone, a VSV-G expression plasmid, and the necessary helper plasmids. This produces non-genotype-phenotype-linked VSV-G-pseudotyped lentiviruses that we use to infect target cells at low multiplicity of infection, so that most infected cells receive no more than one lentiviral genome. Next we select for cells with integrated lentiviral genomes using puromycin, which yields a population of cells where each cell stores only a single spike variant. The spike is under an inducible promoter, which is only activated by addition of doxycycline. To produce virions, we induce spike expression with doxycycline and transfect the helper plasmids necessary to produce lentiviruses. We validated that this approach can be used to generate genotype-phenotype linked spike-pseudotyped viruses with titers &gt;10<sup>5</sup> transduction units per ml (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure S1A</xref>). We can further increase viral titers by ~5-10 fold by infecting cells in the presence of a putative IFITM3 inhibitor amphotericin B (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35">Lin et al., 2013</xref>), as has been reported previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R52">Peacock et al., 2021</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R71">Zhao et al., 2020</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R72">Zheng et al., 2020</xref>) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure S1B</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S4"><title>Design of mutations in SARS-CoV-2 spike deep mutational scanning library</title><p id="P9">Rather than create deep mutational scanning libraries containing all possible amino-acid mutants of spike, we chose to introduce only mutations that seem likely to arise during natural evolution and yield a functional spike protein. We had two rationales for designing our libraries in this way: (1) it reduces the total number of mutations that need to be included in the library, and (2) it increases the probability that variants with multiple mutations will remain functional by reducing the fraction of mutations that are highly deleterious.</p><p id="P10">Specifically, we included only mutations that have been observed in spike sequences deposited on the GISAID database (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31">Khare et al., 2021</xref>), reasoning that these mutations would represent mostly functional spike proteins. We introduced mutations at a higher frequency when they have emerged in spike independently many times according to the pre-built SARS-CoV-2 phylogenies from UShER (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R63">Turakhia et al., 2021</xref>). Finally, we included every possible amino acid change at sites in spike that are evolving under positive selection (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39">Maher et al., 2022</xref>). We also included deletions at sites where such mutations are observed frequently in natural SARS-CoV-2 evolution. In total, our library design targeted 7,004 mutations in the BA.1 spike and 6,852 mutations in the Delta spike.</p><p id="P11">To introduce these mutations in the spike gene we used a PCR-based mutagenesis method with a primer pool containing the desired mutations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">Bloom, 2014</xref>). Importantly, this method introduces multiple mutations in each spike variant: we targeted ~2 to 3 codon mutations per variant, ensuring the effects of most mutations are measured in multiple genetic backgrounds. The mutated spike genes were then barcoded with 16 random nucleotides placed downstream of the spike-coding sequence (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1A</xref>), and cloned into the lentivirus backbone. As described below, after integration of the libraries into cells, these barcodes can be linked to the full set of mutations in each spike variant to facilitate downstream sequencing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">Hiatt et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40">Matreyek et al., 2018</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S5"><title>Production of pseudotyped BA.1 and Delta spike deep mutational scanning libraries</title><p id="P12">We used the genotype-phenotype linked pseudovirus production strategy in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1B</xref> to make BA.1 and Delta deep mutational scanning libraries. We created three independent BA.1 libraries each containing ~100,000 barcoded variants and two independent Delta libraries each containing ~50,000 barcoded variants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figures 1E</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S2A</xref>; a “barcoded variant” is a spike with a unique nucleotide barcode and some random mutation set; different barcoded variants usually but not always contain different mutations). After integrating the libraries into cells at low multiplicity of infection, we generated VSV-G-pseudotyped lentivirus from these cells by co-transfecting a plasmid expressing VSV-G alongside the other lentiviral helper plasmids (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1B</xref>, top right). The use of VSV-G-pseudotyped virus ensures that we generate infectious lentiviral virions from all integrated backbones regardless of whether they encode a functional spike mutant. We then infected this VSV-G-pseudotyped lentivirus into a new round of cells, and performed long-read PacBio sequencing to link the barcodes to the full set of spike mutations for each variant. We performed the PacBio barcode-mutation linking after integration into cells because recombination of the pseudodiploid lentiviral genome during integration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">Jetzt et al., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R55">Schlub et al., 2010</xref>) means the barcode-mutation pairings may be different in the integrated cells to those in the original lentiviral backbone plasmids (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">Hill et al., 2018</xref>). Importantly, linking barcodes to spike variants allows us to use short-read Illumina sequencing of the barcode to obtain the full spike genotype in all subsequent experiments.</p><p id="P13">Overall, the sequencing revealed that we had successfully introduced ~99% of the targeted mutations in the BA.1 and Delta spike libraries (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figures 1E</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S2B</xref>). The barcoded variants in the BA.1 libraries had on average ~2 codon mutations per spike, while the variants in the Delta libraries had ~3 codon mutations per spike (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figures 1C</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S2C</xref>). The number of mutations per variant is roughly Poisson distributed, so some variants had zero or one mutation, while others had many more (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure S3</xref>).</p><p id="P14">We then generated the actual spike-pseudotyped deep mutational scanning libraries from the variants stored at single copy in the cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1B</xref>, lower right). We calculated a functional score for each variant based on its relative frequency in the spike- versus VSV-G-pseudotyped libraries. Positive functional scores indicate spike variants mediate pseudovirus infection better than the parental spike, whereas negative functional scores indicate worse pseudovirus infection. As expected, spike variants with premature stop codons had highly negative functional scores, while unmutated and synonymously mutated spike variants had functional scores close to zero (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figures 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S2D</xref>). Some variants with nonsynonymous mutations had functional scores close to zero, while others had more negative scores, reflecting the fact that some but not all nonsynonymous mutations are deleterious (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figures 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S2D</xref>; recall that our library design protocol preferentially introduced nonsynonymous mutations expected to yield functional spikes). Variants with multiple nonsynonymous mutations tended to have lower functional scores than variants with just one nonsynonymous mutation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figures 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S2D</xref>), reflecting the cost of accumulating multiple often mildly deleterious mutations.</p></sec><sec id="S6"><title>Use of an absolute standard to measure viral neutralization by deep sequencing</title><p id="P15">Traditional neutralization assays measure the infectivity of a single virus variant at multiple antibody concentrations. Deep sequencing can measure the relative infectivities of many viral variants in pooled infections in the presence of an antibody. However, to convert the relative infectivities measured by deep sequencing into actual neutralization values, it is necessary to have an absolute standard that does not vary in its infectivity as a function of antibody concentration (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3A</xref>). To enable such measurements in our experiments, we added a barcoded VSV-G-pseudotyped virus into our libraries. Importantly, this VSV-G-pseudotyped virus is not neutralized by any of the spike-binding antibodies (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figures 3A</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S4A</xref>), and so the counts for VSV-G barcodes provide an absolute neutralization standard. To calculate the non-neutralized fraction for each viral variant, we simply compute the change in its barcode frequencies relative to the VSV-G standard (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3B</xref>).</p><p id="P16">To validate this approach, we added the VSV-G absolute standard at ~1% of our BA.1 library titers and incubated the virus library with increasing concentrations of the LY-CoV1404 antibody, as schematized in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3B</xref>. We then infected the library into ACE2-expressing target cells overnight, recovered viral genomes, and quantified the abundance of each viral barcode using deep sequencing. As expected, the fraction of VSV-G standard reads increased with antibody concentration because fewer spike variants could still infect in the presence of antibody (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3C</xref>). We then calculated the non-neutralized fraction for each viral variant in our libraries after selection at different concentrations of the antibody. As expected, increasing antibody concentrations led to decreased non-neutralized fraction averaged over variants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3D</xref>). Notably, variants with greater number of substitutions had higher non-neutralized fractions, as expected if some substitutions escape the antibody.</p></sec><sec id="S7"><title>Mapping antibody escape using a full spike deep mutational scanning system</title><p id="P17">To demonstrate that pseudovirus-based deep mutational scanning can map escape from neutralizing antibodies targeting any region of spike, we chose a set of BA.1-neutralizing antibodies that bind distinct regions of spike: RBD-binding LY-CoV1404, NTD-binding 5-7, and S2-binding CC67.105 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">Cerutti et al., 2021</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R68">Westendorf et al., 2022</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R73">Zhou et al., 2022</xref>). Note that LY-CoV1404, also known as bebtelovimab, is one of the few clinically approved antibodies that retains potency against BA.1, BA.2 and other major Omicron lineages (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R66">Wang et al., 2022a</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R68">Westendorf et al., 2022</xref>).</p><p id="P18">We first mapped escape from LY-CoV1404, applying the approach in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3B</xref> to our three independent BA.1 libraries, and performing a technical replicate for one library. We used a biophysical model to decompose the measurements for spike variants in our libraries (some of which are multiply mutated) into escape scores for individual mutations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R69">Yu et al., 2022</xref>). These mutation escape scores correlated well among technical and biological replicates (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4A</xref>). As expected, the key LY-CoV1404 escape sites were in the antibody’s previously described epitope in the RBD (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R68">Westendorf et al., 2022</xref>), which spans sites 439-452 and 498-501 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4B-D</xref> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://dms-vep.github.io/SARS-CoV-2_Omicron_BA.1_spike_DMS_mAbs/LyCoV-1404_escape_plot.html">https://dms-vep.github.io/SARS-CoV-2_Omicron_BA.1_spike_DMS_mAbs/LyCoV-1404_escape_plot.html</ext-link>).</p><p id="P19">However, our deep mutational scanning emphasizes that only some mutations at these sites escape LY-CoV1404 neutralization. For instance, many amino acid mutations at site 446 strongly escape LY-CoV1404, but mutating this site from G (the identity in Wuhan-Hu-1) to S (the identity in BA.1 and BA.2.75) does not have a large effect. This observation emphasizes the somewhat serendipitous nature of the preserved potency of LY-CoV1404. However, this antibody may soon be escaped because sub-variants of BA.5 and BA.2.75 with mutations in the key escape site of K444 are increasingly being detected (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">Cao et al., 2022</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">Chen et al., 2022</xref>).</p><p id="P20">To validate the LY-CoV1404 deep mutational scanning, we cloned a set of mutations in the BA.1 spike with a range of effects in the deep mutational scanning data and performed standard pseudovirus neutralization assays (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4E</xref>). All the tested mutations exhibited neutralization phenotypes consistent with those measured in the deep mutational scanning. Furthermore, the neutralization assay IC50 values correlated well with those predicted by our biophysical model (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R69">Yu et al., 2022</xref>) parameterized by the deep mutational scanning data (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4F</xref>).</p><p id="P21">We also compared the full spike LY-CoV1404 deep mutational scanning measurements to results from our previously described yeast-display system for deep mutational scanning of only the RBD (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R60">Starr et al., 2022</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R59">2020</xref>). The escape scores between the two experimental approaches correlated well (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure S5A</xref>) and both methods identified the same epitope (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure S5B</xref>).</p><p id="P22">To show that we can map escape from non-RBD-targeting antibodies, we next mapped the NTD-targeting 5-7 antibody (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">Cerutti et al., 2021</xref>). This antibody targets an epitope outside the defined antigenic supersite in NTD and is one of the few NTD-targeting antibodies isolated pre-Omicron that still retains some potency against Omicron variants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">Cerutti et al., 2021</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38">Liu et al., 2022</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41">McCallum et al., 2021</xref>). The deep mutational scanning showed that the key escape sites for 5-7 were in a hydrophobic pocket next to the N4 loop (site 172-178) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5A-C</xref> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://dms-vep.github.io/SARS-CoV-2_Omicron_BA.1_spike_DMS_mAbs/NTD_5-7_escape_plot.html">https://dms-vep.github.io/SARS-CoV-2_Omicron_BA.1_spike_DMS_mAbs/NTD_5-7_escape_plot.html</ext-link>), consistent with prior structural characterization of this antibody’s epitope (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">Cerutti et al., 2021</xref>). In addition, deletions in 167-171 ß-sheet, as well as mutations at the base of the adjacent loops such as G103 and V126 also escaped antibody 5-7 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5A-B</xref>). We validated these deep mutational scanning results by performing individual neutralization assays with pseudoviruses containing L176K, S172N and G103F mutations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5D</xref>), all of which had the expected effect of completely escaping neutralization (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5E</xref>).</p><p id="P23">We next applied the full spike deep mutational scanning to S2 stem-helix targeting antibodies CC9.104 and CC67.105, which were isolated using both the SARS-CoV-2 and Middle East Respiratory Syndrome coronavirus (MERS-CoV) spike proteins as baits (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R73">Zhou et al., 2022</xref>). Both CC9.104 and CC67.105 broadly neutralize SARS-related coronaviruses, and CC9.104 also retains some potency against MERS-CoV. As expected, our deep mutational scanning showed that escape sites for both antibodies cluster in the S2 stem-helix region (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6A-E</xref>; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://dms-vep.github.io/SARS-CoV-2_Omicron_BA.1_spike_DMS_mAbs/CC67.105_escape_plot.html">https://dms-vep.github.io/SARS-CoV-2_Omicron_BA.1_spike_DMS_mAbs/CC67.105_escape_plot.html</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://dms-vep.github.io/SARS-CoV-2_Omicron_BA.1_spike_DMS_mAbs/CC9.104_escape_plot.html">https://dms-vep.github.io/SARS-CoV-2_Omicron_BA.1_spike_DMS_mAbs/CC9.104_escape_plot.html</ext-link>). Our data also explain why only CC9.104 neutralizes MERS-CoV. The deep mutational scanning shows that the CC67.105 epitope centers on sites D1146, D1153 and F1156 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figures 6B</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6D</xref>), and consistent with the deep mutational scanning, mutating these sites leads to complete escape in validation neutralization assays (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6G</xref>). By contrast, the deep mutational scanning shows that while CC9.104’s epitope also includes sites D1153 and F1156, mutations at site D1146 cause only modest or no escape (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figures 6C</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6E</xref>), and validation neutralization assays again confirm these deep mutational scanning results (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figures 6G</xref>). Notably, sites D1153 and F1156 are conserved between SARS-CoV-2 and MERS-CoV S2 stem-helix regions, but site D1146 is mutated to isoleucine in MERS-CoV (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6F</xref>). Based on our deep mutational scanning data we expect changes at site D1146 to have significant effects on escape from the CC67.105 antibody but only modest effects on escape from the CC9.104 antibody. While our deep mutational scanning libraries do not include isoleucine at site D1146 (which is found in MERS-CoV), we confirmed that other mutations at D1146 lead to complete escape from CC67.105 and do not substantially impact neutralization by CC9.104 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6G</xref>). Note that site D1163 is also mutated to isoleucine in MERS-CoV and both antibodies show some escape at that site, which may explain why CC9.104’s potency against MERS-CoV is lower than against SARS-CoV-2.</p><p id="P24">The above deep mutational scanning of escape from the S2 antibodies emphasizes the difference between SARS-related coronavirus breadth and resistance to escape in SARS-CoV-2. Both CC9.104 and CC67.105 neutralize many diverse SARS-related coronaviruses, but Omicron sub-variants with mutations that lead to almost complete escape from these antibodies have been detected (e.g. D1153Y in BA.2.46 and BA.2.59). Therefore, even pan-sarbecovirus neutralizing antibodies can be escaped by mutational diversity within SARS-CoV-2, which emphasizes the importance of directly mapping escape mutations in SARS-CoV-2 in addition to assessing breadth across other natural SARS-related coronaviruses.</p><p id="P25">To show that we can perform deep mutational scanning of the spikes from different SARS-CoV-2 strains, we mapped escape from the REGN10933 antibody using Delta spike deep mutational scanning libraries (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure S6A-B</xref>). REGN10933 is a class 1 antibody that directly competes with ACE2 binding, and was part of REGN-COV2 therapeutic cocktail used early in the pandemic but has lost potency against Omicron variants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">Baum et al., 2020</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">Hansen et al., 2020</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38">Liu et al., 2022</xref>). Escape sites for REGN10933 mapped with our deep mutational scanning system overlapped with the antibody binding footprint and included previously described escape mutations (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure S6C</xref>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">Baum et al., 2020</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">Hansen et al., 2020</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R58">Starr et al., 2021b</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S8"><title>Functional effects of mutations on spike-mediated pseudovirus infection</title><p id="P26">Our deep mutational scanning also enables measurement of how mutations affect spike-mediated viral infection in the absence of antibodies. We can make these measurements by computing a functional score for each variant from its relative frequency in infectious spike-pseudotyped lentiviruses generated from our single-copy cell integrated cells versus VSV-G-pseudotyped lentivirus generated from the same cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figures 1B</xref>). Spike variants with negative functional scores are worse at mediating cellular infection than the parental unmutated spike, while variants with positive functional scores are better at mediating infection (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>). To deconvolve the functional scores for the variants (which often contain multiple mutations) into the effects of individual mutations on spike-mediated entry, we used global epistasis models (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R49">Otwinowski et al., 2018</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R54">Sailer and Harms, 2017</xref>).</p><p id="P27">As expected stop-codon mutations to the BA.1 spike were highly deleterious for spike-mediated infection, whereas amino-acid mutations showed a wide range of effects ranging from slightly beneficial to roughly neutral to highly deleterious (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7A</xref>; recall that our library design excludes many of the most deleterious amino-acid mutations). To test whether the mutations measured to have slightly beneficial effects actually improved spike-mediated infection, we chose five mutations that the deep mutational scanning indicated improved infection (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7B</xref>), and generated pseudovirus mutants carrying these mutations. The validation experiments confirmed that all the tested mutations indeed slightly improved spike-mediated infection (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7C</xref>), validating that our deep mutational scanning can identify mutations that increase spike-mediated pseudovirus infection.</p><p id="P28">To examine the relationship between the functional effects of spike mutations in the deep mutational scanning and actual evolution of human SARS-CoV-2, we determined the extent that mutations are enriched or depleted across a phylogenetic tree of all publicly available human SARS-CoV-2 sequences (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R63">Turakhia et al., 2021</xref>). To do this, we calculated the number of independent observations of each mutation on the tree and compared these observed numbers to the expected numbers under neutrality as estimated from four-fold synonymous sites, analyzing only mutations expected to have ≥20 occurrences (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="S10">Methods</xref> for details). Our deep mutational scanning measurements of the effects of mutations on spike-mediated infection were reasonably correlated with the enrichment of mutations among actual sequences (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7D</xref>), indicating our experiments at least partially reflect the functional selection actually shaping spike evolution. We performed a similar analysis for prior spike deep mutational scanning using yeast display of the RBD (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R60">Starr et al., 2022</xref>), or mammalian cell display of the NTD (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R50">Ouyang et al., 2022</xref>) or a region of S2 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R61">Tan et al., 2022</xref>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7D</xref>). Our pseudovirus-based spike deep mutational scanning measurements were more correlated with the enrichment of mutations during actual evolution than any of these prior cell-surface display deep mutational scanning studies, presumably because our experiments mimic the true biological function of spike better than cell-surface display experiments.</p><p id="P29">However, none of the mutations with positive deep mutational scanning functional scores that we validated to improve spike-mediated infection in a pseudovirus context are enriched during actual SARS-CoV-2 evolution (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7D</xref>). We suggest that this is because there is some divergence between the selection pressure in our pseudovirus-based experiments and true natural selection on spike. For instance, mutations at sites P1140 and P1143, which are located at the beginning of the S2 stem-helix, could potentially destabilize the prefusion trimer leading to more rapid cell entry in a pseudovirus context but negatively affect spike stability in the context of actual human transmission. Nonetheless, our functional measurements still provide the most accurate large-scale measurements to date on the effects of mutations to spike, and should be useful for assessing which antibody-escape mutations are well enough tolerated to pose a plausible risk of emerging naturally. We also note that our experiments indicate that there are no further mutations to the BA.1 spike that improve pseudovirus titers to the same extent as the D614G mutation that fixed early in SARS-CoV-2’s evolution in humans (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">Benton et al., 2021</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R53">Plante et al., 2021</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R70">Zhang et al., 2021</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="S9" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p id="P30">We have developed a new deep mutational scanning system for assessing the antigenic and functional effects of mutations in the SARS-CoV-2 spike. This deep mutational scanning system is the first to measure how mutations to the entirety of spike affect cellular infection, and therefore enables the mapping of escape from antibodies targeting any part of the spike. Furthermore, our system directly quantifies how mutations affect antibody neutralization, and we show that these measurements correlate well with traditional pseudovirus neutralization assays. We expect that the ability to directly measure neutralization as opposed to binding will be especially useful when applied to polyclonal sera, since the magnitude of how mutations affect neutralization versus binding can differ in a polyclonal context (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">Bellusci et al., 2022</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">Cao et al., 2022</xref>).</p><p id="P31">Using the new deep mutational scanning system, we have mapped mutations that escape monoclonal antibodies targeting the RBD, NTD, and S2 domains. Although we only characterized a few antibodies here, this work is a first step towards generating similar data for much larger antibody panels. For the RBD, such data has proven valuable for interpreting the antigenic phenotypes of the new SARS-CoV-2 variants constantly emerging in the human population (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">Cao et al., 2022</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">Greaney et al., 2022</xref>). The ability to generate comparable data for other spike domains should enable better antigenic assessment of new variants, which can help inform vaccine design and strain selection (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">DeGrace et al., 2022</xref>). In addition, our work on the S2 antibodies emphasizes the distinction between breadth on natural viruses and potential for escape within SARS-CoV-2: an antibody that cross-neutralizes MERS-CoV and all tested SARS-related viruses is still escaped by mutations already present in some SARS-CoV-2 variants. Therefore, direct prospective mapping of escape mutations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R58">Starr et al., 2021b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R57">2021a</xref>) should be useful for informing development of therapeutic antibodies targeting even regions of spike conserved across most natural viruses.</p><p id="P32">We also used the deep mutational scanning system to measure how mutations in spike affect its ability to mediate pseudovirus infection. These measurements complement existing deep mutational scanning datasets on how spike mutations affect the molecular phenotypes of ACE2 affinity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R60">Starr et al., 2022</xref>), membrane fusion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R61">Tan et al., 2022</xref>), and cell-surface expression (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R50">Ouyang et al., 2022</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R60">Starr et al., 2022</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R61">Tan et al., 2022</xref>). None of these experimental measurements fully reflect how mutations affect actual viral fitness, which is an emergent property of many molecular phenotypes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">Ballal et al., 2020</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">Harms and Thornton, 2013</xref>). However, understanding how mutations affect molecular phenotypes is an important step towards interpreting evolutionary outcomes, and our pseudovirus-based system currently provides the deep mutational scanning measurements that best reflect natural selection on the spike of human SARS-CoV-2.</p><p id="P33">The deep mutational scanning system we describe here can also be straightforwardly extended to any virus with an entry protein amenable to lentiviral pseudotyping. This set of viruses includes other coronaviruses, influenza viruses, filoviruses, arenaviruses, and henipaviruses—all of which have receptor-binding and fusion proteins for which lentiviral pseudotyping provides a safe way to study cellular infection and antibody neutralization without requiring direct work with the actual pathogenic virus (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27">Huang et al., 2020</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32">Khetawat and Broder, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33">Kobinger et al., 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34">Larson et al., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43">Medina et al., 2003</xref>). Deep mutational scanning of the entry proteins of all these viruses could provide valuable information for antigenic surveillance and vaccine design, since these proteins are the dominant target of neutralizing antibodies. However, we note that data generated by such a system could in principle be used to inform introduction of gain-of-function mutations into actual potential pandemic viral pathogens. We therefore suggest that advances in the high-throughput characterization of mutations to viral proteins should be coupled with thoughtful limits on any downstream experiments with actual replicating viruses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">Inglesby et al., 2022</xref>) to ensure that safely generated information is used to benefit public health without creating new risks.</p></sec><sec id="S10" sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec id="S11"><title>Design of lentiviral backbone and spike gene nucleotide sequence optimization</title><p id="P34">The structure of lentiviral backbone is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1A</xref>. The plasmid map of the lentivirus backbone containing BA.1 spike is at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/dms-vep/SARS-CoV-2_Omicron_BA.1_spike_DMS_mAbs/blob/main/library_design/reference_sequences/3282_pH2rU3_ForInd_Omicron_sinobiological_BA.1_B11529_Spiked21_T7_CMV_ZsGT2APurR.gb">https://github.com/dms-vep/SARS-CoV-2_Omicron_BA.1_spike_DMS_mAbs/blob/main/library_design/reference_sequences/3282_pH2rU3_ForInd_Omicron_sinobiological_BA.1_B11529_Spiked21_T7_CMV_ZsGT2APurR.gb</ext-link> and the map for the Delta spike-containing backbone is at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/dms-vep/SARS-CoV-2_Delta_spike_DMS_REGN10933/blob/main/library_design/reference_sequences/pH2rU3_ForInd_sinobiolo_gical_617.2_Spiked21_CMV_ZsGT2APurR.gb">https://github.com/dms-vep/SARS-CoV-2_Delta_spike_DMS_REGN10933/blob/main/library_design/reference_sequences/pH2rU3_ForInd_sinobiolo_gical_617.2_Spiked21_CMV_ZsGT2APurR.gb</ext-link>. Note our BA.1 spike includes the EPE insertion after position 214 (Wuhan-Hu-1 numbering). The vector is based on a pHAGE2 lentiviral backbone in which we repaired the 3’ LTR sequence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R47">OhAinle et al., 2018</xref>), which allows us to re-rescue the pseudovirus from the cells in which lentiviral backbones have been integrated. The lentiviral backbone is non-replicative unless helper plasmids (Gag/Pol (NR-52517), Tat1b (NR-52518), and Rev1b (NR-52519)) are also transfected into the cells containing this backbone. Expression of the spike gene in the lentivirus backbone is driven both by inducible TRE3G promoter and by Tat1b. TRE3G promoter is activated by addition of doxycycline in the presence of the reverse tetracycline transactivator (rtTA), which is endogenously expressed in HEK-293T-rtTA cells. The spike gene has been codon optimized and lacks 21 amino acids in its cytoplasmic tail. The cytoplasmic tail deletion has been previously shown to significantly increase pseudovirus titers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">Crawford et al., 2021</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">Havranek et al., 2020</xref>). For spike sequence codon optimization we tested a large panel of optimized sequences and found that virus titers can vary between codon optimizations by as much as 100-fold. While we did observe some titer differences when virus was generated from just transfection reactions using lentiviral backbones and helper plasmids, these differences were even more noticeable when virus was generated from cells with integrated spike-carrying lentiviral backbones. Of the tested codon optimizations we found that the sequence optimized spike from SinoBiological (VG40609-UT) gave by far the best virus titers; we therefore based all variant sequences on the original SinoBiological optimization. In addition to the inducible promoter and spike gene, the backbone also has a CMV promoter that drives expression of the ZsGreen gene linked by a T2A linker to the puromycin resistance gene. ZsGreen is used as a reporter gene to detect pseudovirus infection and the puromycin resistance gene is used as a selection marker for cells with successfully integrated lentiviral backbones.</p></sec><sec id="S12"><title>Design of spike mutations to include in BA.1 and Delta full spike deep mutational scanning libraries</title><p id="P35">We aimed to create a library with mutations that would result in mostly functional spike proteins and include the mutations likely to be important for the antigenic evolution of spike. To this end, for BA.1 and Delta deep mutational scanning libraries we included the following types mutations: (1) mutations (nonsynonymous changes and deletions) observed in spike sequences deposited on GISAID database, (2) mutations that reoccur in spike phylogeny independently multiple times, (3) all possible amino acid changes at sites in spike that show positive selection. Specifically for the BA.1 library, we also included all possible amino acid changes for sites that are mutated in the BA.1 spike relative to Wuhan-Hu-1.</p><p id="P36">The following criteria were used to select the above described mutations for BA.1 library: nonsynonymous mutations need to be present in GISAID database &gt;16 times, deletions need to occur in the NTD and be observed on GISAID database &gt;300 times, nonsynonymous mutations need to reoccur on spike phylogenetic tree independently at least 21 times. To get all spike mutations observed in GISAID deposited sequences we used a CoVsurver curated spike amino acid frequency table (with sequences deposited up to January-31-2022) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31">Khare et al., 2021</xref>). To get independently recurring spike mutation counts we used pre-built SARS-CoV-2 phylogenies from UShER (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R63">Turakhia et al., 2021</xref>). Information on sites in spike undergoing positive selection was taken from taken from table here <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/spond/SARS-CoV-2-variation/master/windowed-sites-fel-2021-07.csv">https://raw.githubusercontent.com/spond/SARS-CoV-2-variation/master/windowed-sites-fel-2021-07.csv</ext-link> which was built using methods described in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39">Maher et al. (2022)</xref>. The full list of mutations included in the BA.1 library can be found at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/dms-vep/SARS-CoV-2_Omicron_BA.1_spike_DMS_mAbs/blob/main/library_design/results/aggregated_mutations.csv">https://github.com/dms-vep/SARS-CoV-2_Omicron_BA.1_spike_DMS_mAbs/blob/main/library_design/results/aggregated_mutations.csv</ext-link>.</p><p id="P37">The following criteria were used to select the above described mutations for the Delta library: nonsynonymous mutations and deletions need to be observed on GISAID database more than once and nonsynonymous mutations need to reoccur on spike phylogenetic tree independently more than 7 times. To get all spike mutations observed in GISAID deposited sequences we aligned all spike sequences deposited on GISAID up to July-26-2021 and extracted mutation frequency counts. Independently recurring spike mutations and positively selected sites were identified as described for BA.1 library above. The full list of mutations included in the Delta library can be found at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/dms-vep/SARS-CoV-2_Delta_spike_DMS_REGN10933/blob/main/library_design/results/aggregated_mutations.csv">https://github.com/dms-vep/SARS-CoV-2_Delta_spike_DMS_REGN10933/blob/main/library_design/results/aggregated_mutations.csv</ext-link>.</p></sec><sec id="S13"><title>Design of primers for BA.1 and Delta spike mutagenesis</title><p id="P38">For each set of mutations described in the section above we designed separate primer pools: (1) a pool of primers for observed mutations, (2) a pool of primers for recurrent mutations, (3) a pool of primers for positive selection site mutations, and (4) a pool of primers that would cover changes at multiple positive selection sites if those positive selection sites are close enough to each other so that the primers in the pool (3) would overlap. For the BA.1 library we also designed primers that would introduce multiple amino acid deletions at recurrent deletion regions described in (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42">McCarthy et al., 2021</xref>) and included them in the observed mutation primer pool. Also for the BA.1 library, the set of primers that cover all possible amino acid changes at the sites already mutated in BA.1 was pooled with the positive selection site primer pool.</p><p id="P39">All primer pools were ordered from Integrated DNA Technologies as oPools. Scripts for designing the BA.1 library primer pools and the resulting oPools that were ordered are at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/dms-vep/SARS-CoV-2_Omicron_BA.1_spike_DMS_mAbs/tree/main/library_design">https://github.com/dms-vep/SARS-CoV-2_Omicron_BA.1_spike_DMS_mAbs/tree/main/library_design</ext-link> and scripts for designing the Delta library primer pools are at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/dms-vep/SARS-CoV-2_Delta_spike_DMS_REGN10933/tree/main/library_design">https://github.com/dms-vep/SARS-CoV-2_Delta_spike_DMS_REGN10933/tree/main/library_design</ext-link>.</p></sec><sec id="S14"><title>Design of full-spike deep mutational scanning plasmid libraries</title><p id="P40">Making of the plasmid libraries for deep mutational scanning required the following three steps (1) mutagenesis of the spike gene, (2) barcoding of the mutagenised spike sequence, and (3) cloning of the mutagenised and barcoded spike into the lentiviral backbone-carrying plasmid.</p><p id="P41">Spike mutagenesis was carried out by first amplifying BA.1 or Delta spike gene sequence from a plasmid carrying lentiviral backbone with a codon optimized spike sequence (see section ‘Design of lentiviral backbone and spike gene nucleotide sequence optimization’ for plasmid maps). Spike sequence was amplified using ‘Spike amplification’ primers from <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 1</xref> with the following PCR conditions: 1.5 μl of 10μM forward primer, 1.5 μl of 10 μM reverse primer, 10 ng of amplified spike gene template, 25 μl of KOD polymerase (KOD Hot Start Master Mix, Sigma-Aldrich, Cat. No. 71842), and water for the final volume of 50 μl. PCR cycling conditions were as follows: <list list-type="order" id="L1"><list-item><p id="P42">95°C for 2 min</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P43">95°C for 20 s</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P44">62°C for 15 s</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P45">70°C for 2 min (return to step 2 for another 19x cycles)</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P46">Hold at 4°C</p></list-item></list>
</p><p id="P47">Amplified spike sequence was first gel-purified using NucleoSpin Gel and PCR Clean-up kit (Takara, Cat. No. 740609.5) and then further purified using Ampure XP beads (Beckman Coulter, Cat. No. A63881) at 1:2.6 sample to bead ratio.</p><p id="P48">Next the purified spike template was used in mutagenesis PCR using protocol described previously in (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">Bloom, 2014</xref>) with a few modifications (see also <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/jbloomlab/CodonTilingPrimers">https://github.com/jbloomlab/CodonTilingPrimers</ext-link> for general background on this protocol). Forward and reverse primers for mutagenesis PCR were pooled into separate pools at 1 : 2 : 2 : 0.2 per primer molar ratio between observed primer pool : recurrent primer pool : positive selection primer pool : paired positive selection primer pool. The pooling ratios are determined by the fact that recurrent and positively selected sites may be more antigenically and structurally important for spike. Two independent mutagenesis reactions were performed for each spike creating two independent biological library replicates (which means that they will have a unique set of barcodes and a unique set of mutation combinations in spike). For BA.1 libraries we performed two rounds of mutagenesis with the first round consisting of 8 mutagenic PCR cycles followed by the second round of 10 mutagenic PCR cycles. For Delta libraries one biological replicate consisted of a single round of 10 mutagenic PCR cycles and the second biological replicate consisted one round of 8 and another round of 10 mutagenic PCR cycles. Each mutagenesis PCR reaction was divided into forward and reverse reactions based on whether the reaction used the forward or reverse pool of mutagenesis primers. The PCR conditions for mutagenesis were as follows: 1.5 μl of 5 μM of forward or reverse mutagenesis primer pool, 1.5 μl of 5 μM of forward or reverse ‘Spike amplification and joining PCR’ primer (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">supplementary table 1</xref>), 1.5 μl of 3 ng/μl linearised spike template, 4 μl of water, and 15 μl of KOD. The PCR cycling conditions were as follows: <list list-type="order" id="L2"><list-item><p id="P49">95°C, 2 min</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P50">95°C, 20 s</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P51">70°C, 1 s</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P52">54°C, 20 s, cooling at 0.5°C/s</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P53">70°C, 100 s (return to step 2 for the number of cycles described above)</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P54">4°C, hold</p></list-item></list>
</p><p id="P55">Between each mutagenic PCR round 20 cycles of joining PCR were performed. For joining PCR we used 4 μl each of 1:4 diluted forward and reverse mutagenesis reactions, 1.5 μL each of forward and reverse joining primers (see ‘Spike amplification and joining PCR’ primers in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">supplementary table 1</xref>), 4 μl of water, and 15 μl of KOD. PCR cycling conditions were identical to the mutagenesis PCR conditions. Joined PCR mutagenesis products were gel and Ampure XP purified after each joining reaction.</p><p id="P56">After the spike sequence was mutagenised we performed a barcoding PCR that appended a random 16 nucleotide barcode sequence downstream of the spike gene stop codon. We chose 16 nucleotide barcodes as it allows for a total of 4<sup>16</sup> unique barcoded variants, which is much greater diversity of barcodes than the final size of our deep mutational scanning plasmid libraries and therefore limits potential barcodes dulications. For barcoding ‘Spike barcoding’ primers from <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">supplementary table 1</xref> were used with the following PCR conditions 1.5 μl of 10μM forward primer, 1.5 μl of 10 μM reverse primer, 30 ng of the mutagenised spike gene template, 25 μl of KOD polymerase, and water for final volume of 50 μl. PCR cycling conditions were as follows: <list list-type="order" id="L3"><list-item><p id="P57">95°C, 2 min</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P58">95°C, 20 s</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P59">70°C, 1 s</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P60">55.5°C, 20 s, cooling at 0.5°C/s</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P61">70°C, 2 min (return to step 2 for another 9x cycles)</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P62">4°C hold</p></list-item></list>
</p><p id="P63">The mutagenised and barcoded spike was then cloned into lentiviral backbone-containing plasmid. First, we digested a lentiviral backbone containing plasmid using Mlul and Xbal restriction sites. The map of plasmid used for vector digestion is at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/dms-vep/SARS-CoV-2_Omicron_BA.1_spike_DMS_mAbs/blob/main/library_design/reference_sequences/other_plasmid_maps_f_or_library_design/3137_pH2rU3_Forlnd_mCherry_CMV_ZsGT2APurR.gb">https://github.com/dms-vep/SARS-CoV-2_Omicron_BA.1_spike_DMS_mAbs/blob/main/library_design/reference_sequences/other_plasmid_maps_f_or_library_design/3137_pH2rU3_Forlnd_mCherry_CMV_ZsGT2APurR.gb</ext-link>. Digested vector was gel and Ampure XP purified. We then used 1:3 insert to vector ratio in a 1 hour Hifi assembly reaction using NEBuilder HiFi DNA Assembly kit (NEB, Cat. No. E2621). After the HiFi assembly, we Ampure XP purified the reaction and eluted it in 20 μl of water (note that elution in water as opposed to elution buffer enhances the subsequent electroporation efficiency). We used 1 μl of the purified HiFi product to transform 20 μl of 10-beta electrocompetent <italic>E. coli</italic> cells (NEB, C3020K). We performed 10 electroporation reactions to get a final count of &gt; 2 million CFUs per library and plated transformed cells out on LB+ampicillin plates. We aim to make plasmid library from a much greater number of CFUs than the number of variants in our final virus libraries to minimize barcode duplication, as explained in the next section. About 16 hours after transformation bacterial colonies were scraped using liquid LB+ampicillin and plasmid stocks were prepared using QIAGEN HiSpeed Plasmid Maxi Kit (Cat. No. 12662). The final structure of the lentiviral genome with mutagenised spike cloned into it is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1A</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="S15"><title>Production of cell-stored spike deep mutational scanning libraries</title><p id="P64">Production of cell-stored deep mutational scanning libraries required the following steps: (1) production of VSV-G-pseudotyped lentivirus, (2) infection of rtTA-expressing cells with VSV-G-pseudotyped virus, and (3) selection for transduced cells. These steps are illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1B</xref>.</p><p id="P65">To generate VSV-G-pseudotyped virus for each library we plated 0.5 million HEK-293T cells per well in eight wells of two 6-well tissue culture dishes. Note we aim to produce VSV-G-pseudotyped virus stocks that have a greater number of infectious particles than the number of colonies scraped for plasmid libraries in order to not introduce any bottleneck on barcodes at this stage. The next day we transfected 0.25 μg of each helper plasmid (Gag/Pol, Tat1b, and Rev1b), 0.25 μg of VSV-G expression plasmid (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/jbloomlab/SARS-CoV-2-BA.1_Spike_DMS_validations/blob/main/plasmid_maps/29_HDM_VSV_G.gb">https://github.com/jbloomlab/SARS-CoV-2-BA.1_Spike_DMS_validations/blob/main/plasmid_maps/29_HDM_VSV_G.gb</ext-link>) and 1 μg of mutagenised and barcoded spike containing lentiviral vector (described in the section above). Transfections were done using BioT reagent (Bioland Scientific, Cat. No. B01-02) according to the manufacturer’s instructions. 48 hours post transfection supernatants from each well were pooled, filtered through a surfactant-free cellulose acetate 0.45 μm syringe filter (Corning, Cat. No. 431220), and stored at −80°C. VSV-G-pseudotyped viruses were titrated as described in (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">Crawford et al., 2020</xref>).</p><p id="P66">Next we infected HEK-293T-rtTA cells with the generated VSV-G-pseudotyped virus. The number of infectious virus units used in these infections allowed us to bottleneck the library size at the desired final variant number. For BA.1 libraries we attempted to bottleneck libraries at 100,000 variants and for Delta libraries we bottlenecked the libraries at 50,000 variants. Notably, we used a substantially lower number of variants to infect cells compared to the possible diversity of variants in our plasmid libraries. This allows us to limit any potential duplication of barcodes between different variants due to recombination in the lentivirus genome (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">Hill et al., 2018</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">Jetzt et al., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R55">Schlub et al., 2010</xref>). Note for BA.1, libraries Lib-1 and Lib-2 originate from the same mutagenised lentiviral backbone plasmid stock but independent VSV-G virus infections and Lib-3 originates from independent mutagenised plasmid library stock. For Delta libraries Lib-1 and Lib-2 are both from independent mutagenised spike plasmid stocks. Infections were performed at MOI &lt; 0.01 (in order to ensure that only a single spike variant is integrated in each cell), which was verified 48 hours after infection using fluorescence-activated cell sorting by detecting ZsGreen expression from the lentiviral backbone. After MOI was verified, we expanded cells for another 48 hours and then started puromycin selections to select for cells with successfully integrated lentivirus genomes. Selection was done using 0.75 μg/ml of puromycin with a fresh change of puromycin-containing D10 (see ‘Cell lines’ section below) every 48 hours. Selections were terminated when visual inspection using a fluorescent microscope indicated that all cells express ZsGreen (approximately 6-8 days). After puromycin selection was finished we expanded cells for another 48 hours in fresh D10 and froze cell aliquots in tetracycline-free FBS (Gemini Bio, Cat. No. 100-800) containing 10% DMSO. Frozen cell aliquots were stored in liquid nitrogen long-term.</p></sec><sec id="S16"><title>Generation of spike and VSV-G-pseudotyped viruses from cell-stored spike deep mutational scanning libraries</title><p id="P67">To generate spike-pseudotyped viruses from cell-stored deep mutational scanning libraries we plated 100 million library-containing cells per 5-layer flask (Corning Falcon 875cm<sup>2</sup> Rectangular Straight Neck Cell Culture Multi-Flask, Cat. No. 353144) in 150 ml of D10 without phenol red supplemented with 1 μg/ml for doxycycline (which allows to induce spike expression ahead of pseudovirus production). 24 hours after plating we transfected cells with 50 μg of each helper plasmid (Gag/Pol, Tat1b, Rev1b) using BioT reagent according to manufacturer’s instructions. 48 hours post transfection cell supernatant was collected and filtered through a 0.45 μm SFCA Nalgene 500mL Rapid-Flow filter unit (Cat. No. 09-740-44B). Filtered supernatant was then concentrated by spinning at 4°C 3000 rcf for 30 min using Pierce Protein Concentrator (ThermoFisher, 88537). Virus aliquots were stored long-term at -80°C. Titers for concentrated spike-pseudotyped libraries titrated on HEK-293T-ACE2 cells ranged between 0.5×10<sup>6</sup> - 2×10<sup>6</sup> transcription units per ml.</p><p id="P68">To generate VSV-G-pseudotyped viruses (for functional selection and long-read PacBio sequencing) from cell-stored deep mutational scanning libraries we plated 60 million library-containing cells per 3-layer flask (Corning Falcon 525cm<sup>2</sup> Rectangular Straight Neck Cell Culture Multi-Flask, 353143) in 90 ml of D10 without phenol red (note we do not add doxycycline in this case). 24 hours after plating we transfected cells with 30 μg of each of the helper plasmid (Gag/Pol, Tat1b, Rev1b) and 18.75 μg of VSV-G expression plasmid using BioT reagent according to manufacturer’s instructions. 32-36 hours post transfection cell culture supernatant was collected and filtered through a 0.45 μm SFCA Nalgene filter unit. Filtered supernatant was then concentrated by spinning at 4°C 3000 rcf for 30 min using Pierce Protein Concentrator. Virus aliquots were stored long-term at -80°C. Titers for concentrated VSV-G-pseudotyped libraries titrated on HEK-293T-ACE2 cells ranged between 10×10<sup>6</sup> - 30×10<sup>6</sup> transcription units per ml.</p></sec><sec id="S17"><title>Long-read PacBio sequencing of barcoded spike variants in deep mutational scanning libraries</title><p id="P69">Long-read PacBio sequencing was used to acquire reads spanning the spike and the random 16 nucleotide barcode sequences. To prepare amplicons for PacBio sequencing we infected 1 million HEK-293T cells with ~30 million VSV-G-pseudotyped lentiviruses carrying the deep mutational scanning libraries. This number of viruses is significantly greater than the expected number of variants in the library, which allows us to achieve high variant coverage, avoid bottleneck of barcode diversity and correct for any potential PCR or sequencing errors. 12-15 hours after infection cells were trypsinized, washed with PBS and non-integrated lentiviral genomes were recovered using QIAprep Spin Miniprep Kit (Cat. No. 27106X4) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">Dingens et al., 2018</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">Haddox et al., 2016</xref>). We use non-integrated viral genomes as our sequencing templates because they are the more abundant forms of the lentiviral genome than the integrated proviruses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">Chun et al., 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R51">Pang et al., 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R56">Sharkey et al., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R64">Van Maele et al., 2003</xref>). Elution volume for the miniprep was adjusted to 144 μl. Next we performed two rounds of PCR to amplify the region in the lentivirus genome spanning the spike and the random 16 nucleotide barcode. In the first round of PCR we use primers containing single nucleotide tags, which allow us to later detect strand exchange that may occur during PCR amplification. To limit strand exchange during PCR (which would disrupt barcode/spike variant linkage) we also minimize the number of PCR cycles performed and do multiple PCR reactions per sample (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36">Liu et al., 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R48">Omelina et al., 2019</xref>). Each sample was split into eight PCR reactions, four of which use ‘tag_1’ forward and reverse primers and four of which use ‘tag_2’ forward and reverse primers from the ‘Spike gene amplification for PacBio long-read sequencing’ primer set in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplemental Table 1</xref>. PCR reaction conditions were as follows: 1 μl of forward primer, 1 μl of reverse primer, 20 μl of KOD, and 18 μl of sample. PCR cycling conditions for round 1 PCR were as follows: <list list-type="order" id="L4"><list-item><p id="P70">95°C for 2 min</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P71">95°C for 20 s</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P72">70°C for 1 s</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P73">60°C for 10 s (ramp 0.5°C/s)</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P74">70°C for 2.5 min (go to 2 for another 7 cycles)</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P75">70°C for 5 min</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P76">4°C hold</p></list-item></list>
</p><p id="P77">After the first PCR round we pooled all reactions for each sample and purified them using Ampure XP beads with 1:0.8 beads to sample ratio and the PCR product was eluted in 84 μl of elution buffer. Eluted PCR product was divided into four PCR tubes and the second round of PCR was performed using ‘RND2’ forward and reverse primers from the ‘Spike gene amplification for PacBio long-read sequencing’ primer set in the <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplemental Table 1</xref>. PCR reaction conditions were as follows: 2 μl of forward primer, 2 μl of reverse primer, 25 μl of KOD, and 21 μl of purified sample. PCR cycling conditions were the same as for the round 1 PCR for a total of 10 PCR cycles. PCR reactions for each sample were pooled, purified using Ampure XP beads with 1:0.8 beads to sample ratio, and eluted in 27 μl of elution buffer. Barcodes were attached to each sample using sample SMRTbell prep kit 3.0 before multiplexing. Multiplexed SMRTbell libraries were then bound to polymerase using Sequel II Binding Kit 3.2 and sequenced with PacBio Sequel IIe sequencer with a 20-hour movie collection time.</p></sec><sec id="S18"><title>Antibody escape mapping using full spike deep mutational scanning libraries</title><p id="P78">For antibody escape mapping we used between 4-15 times more infectious virions than the estimated total number of barcodes in a deep mutational scanning library. Using significantly more infectious virions relative to the number of variants per library avoids bottlenecking by having multiple copies of each variant. Note that we expect there to be several fold more lentiviral genomes per selection experiment than the amount of infectious units used because we are recovering the non-integrated viral genomes for sequencing, which are more abundant than integrated proviral DNA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">Chun et al., 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R51">Pang et al., 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R56">Sharkey et al., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R64">Van Maele et al., 2003</xref>) on which our library virus titers are based. For each antibody escape mapping experiment we made a master mix of library spike-pseudotyped virus mixed with VSV-G pseudotyped neutralization standard (described below). Neutralization standard was added at 1-2% of the total virus titer used in the experiment. Virus master mix was then aliquoted into eppendorf tubes to which either different mounts of antibody or no antibody was added. For LY-CoV1404, CC9.104 and CC67.105 antibodies we performed selection experiments at 3 concentrations, starting with IC<sub>99</sub> concentration predetermined using standard pseudovirus neutralization assay and then increasing this concentration 4 fold and 16 fold. We start with IC<sub>99</sub> concentration intending that around 1% of the library will be able to escape antibody selection. We use additional concentrations as it helps us to cover a greater dynamic concentration range in cases where the exact IC<sub>99</sub> value is difficult to determine. Also, the use of multiple concentrations enables more precise mutation-escape predictions by the biophysical model used to decompose single-mutation effects (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R69">Yu et al., 2022</xref>). For LY-CoV1404 starting concentration was 0.654 μg/ml, for CC9.104 - 68 μg/ml, for CC67.105 - 52.5 μg/ml. For the REGN10933 we started at IC<sub>99.5</sub> at 0.146 μg/ml and also increased that concentration by 4 fold and 16 fold. For the NTD 5-7 antibody, which does not fully neutralize the virus, we started with &gt;IC96 concentration at 150 μg/ml and then increased that concentration by 2 fold. Virus was mixed with the antibody by inverting tubes several times, spun down at 300 g, and incubated at 37°C for 1 h. After incubation virus and antibody mix or no antibody control were used to infect approximately 0.5 million target cells, which were plated a day before in D10 supplemented with 2.5 μg/ml of amphotericin B (Sigma, Cat. No. A2942) (which increases viral titers as shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure S1B</xref>). The target cell line for different antibodies is determined by whether an antibody is able to neutralize pseudovirus on that cell line. We have previously described this phenomena in (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">Farrell et al., 2022</xref>) where we show that non-ACE2 competing antibodies do not fully neutralize pseudovirus on ACE2 overexpressing cells. While testing antibodies for the current study we also noticed that some S2-targeting antibodies are also not affected by ACE2 overexpression. Therefore, for LY-CoV1404, CC9.104 and CC67.105 antibodies we used HEK-293T-ACE2 as target cells but for NTD-targeting 5-7 antibody we used HEK-293T-ACE2-medium cells. For REGN10933 we used HEK-293T-ACE2-TMPRSS2 as target cells, because TMPRSS2 overexpression increases Delta pseudovirus titers. 12-15 hours after infection cells were trypsinized, washed with PBS and non-integrated lentiviral genomes were recovered using QIAprep Spin Miniprep Kit and eluted in 21 μl of Qiagen elution buffer. Barcode reads for each sample were then prepared for Illumina sequencing using a method described in ‘Barcode amplicon preparation for Illumina sequencing’ section below.</p></sec><sec id="S19"><title>Functional selections using full spike deep mutational scanning libraries</title><p id="P79">To perform functional spike selections we infected 1 million HEK-293T-ACE2 cells with 1-2 millions of the spike or VSV-G-pseudotyped viruses produced from deep mutational scanning library carrying cells (described earlier). As for antibody selections, the amount of virus used is greater than the number of variants in each library which limits potential bottlenecking of the library barcodes. 12-15 hours after infection cells were trypsinized, washed with PBS and non-integrated lentiviral genomes were recovered using QIAprep Spin Miniprep Kit. Barcode reads for each sample were then prepared for Illumina sequencing using methods described in ‘Barcode amplicon preparation for Illumina sequencing’ section below.</p></sec><sec id="S20"><title>Barcode amplicon preparation for Illumina sequencing</title><p id="P80">To prepare barcode reads for Illumina sequencing we performed two rounds of PCR. In the first round of PCR we used primers that align to Illumina Truseq Read 1 primer site located directly upstream of the barcode in the lentiviral backbone and a primer annealing downstream of the barcode containing an overhand with Illumina Truseq Read 2 sequence (see ‘Illumina barcode sequencing 1st round PCR primers’ in the <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplemental Table 1</xref>). Conditions for the first round PCR were as follows: 1 μl of 10uM forward primer, 1 μl of 10uM reverse primer, 26 μl of KOD, and 24 μl of miniprepped sample DNA. PCR cycling conditions for round 1 PCR were as follows: <list list-type="order" id="L5"><list-item><p id="P81">95°C for 2 min</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P82">95°C for 20 s</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P83">70°C fro 1 s</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P84">58°C for 10 s, cooling at 0.5°C per s</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P85">70°C 20 s (return to step 2 for another 27 cycles)</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P86">4°C hold</p></list-item></list>
</p><p id="P87">PCR reactions were purified with Ampure XP beads using 1:3 sample to beads ratio and eluted in 37 μl of Qiagen elution buffer. Second round of PCR used primers primer annealing to the Illumina Truseq Read 1 primer site with P5 Illumina adapter overhang and reverse primers from the PerkinElmer NextFlex DNA Barcode adaptor set, which anneal to Truseq Read 2 site and contain P7 Illumina adapter and i7 sample index. Conditions for the second round PCR were as follows: 1.5 μl of 10uM universal primer, 1.5 μl of 10uM indexing primer, 25 μl of KOD, and 20 ng of first round PCR product. PCR cycling conditions were the same as the first round PCR for a total of 20 cycles. After the second PCR round all samples were pooled at desired ratios and gel and Ampure XP bead purified. Barcode amplicons were sequenced using NextSeq 2000 with either P2 or P3 reagent kits.</p></sec><sec id="S21"><title>Production of barcoded neutralization standard</title><p id="P88">To make the neutralization standard that we add into our deep mutational scanning libraries we used the same general barcodinging approach as described above for the deep mutational scanning plasmid library generation with a few important differences. The lentiviral backbone used for the neutralization standard consists of TRE3G inducible mCherry protein and CMV promoter driven ZsGreen. The plasmid map of the template backbone is at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/dms-vep/SARS-CoV-2_Omicron_BA.1_spike_DMS_mAbs/blob/main/library_design/reference_sequences/other_plasmid_maps_for_library_design/2871_pH2rU3_ForInd_mCherry_CMV_ZsG_NoBC_cloningvector.gb">https://github.com/dms-vep/SARS-CoV-2_Omicron_BA.1_spike_DMS_mAbs/blob/main/library_design/reference_sequences/other_plasmid_maps_for_library_design/2871_pH2rU3_ForInd_mCherry_CMV_ZsG_NoBC_cloningvector.gb</ext-link>. Note this backbone does not encode any viral glycoproteins and to rescue VSV-G-pseudotyped virus we provide VSV-G expression plasmid in <italic>trans</italic>. We amplified mCherry plasmid from the lentiviral template and barcoded it in two independent PCR reactions using 2 sets of primers containing 4 unique barcodes (see ‘Neutralization standard barcoding primers’ in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">supplementary table 1</xref>). Importantly, the unique barcodes were balanced so that there is a unique nucleotide at each position of the 16-nucleotide barcode between each of the four barcoding primers in a PCR reaction. Furthermore, the 8 barcoding primers are unique to the neutralization standard and are not present in any of our deep mutational scanning libraries. The PCR for barcoding was done the same way as described for deep mutational scanning plasmid library production and both PCR reactions were pooled together before HIfi assembly into the lentiviral backbone. VSV-G-pseudotyped lentiviral particles were then produced as described above (Production of cell-stored spike deep mutational scanning libraries) for the spike libraries, except using this mCherry-containing barcoded backbone as the lentiviral backbone. This VSV-G-pseudotyped virus was then used to infect HEK-293T-rtTA cells at low MOI. Successfully transduced HEK-293T-rtTA were then selected by flow activated fluorescence sorting based on ZsGreen expression and expanded. We then generated VSV-G-pseudotyped neutralization standard by tranfecting helper plasmids and VSV-G expression plasmid in the same way as described for deep mutational scanning library virus rescues. Note, that we use the neutralization standard generated from the integrated cells as opposed to the original transfection in order to prevent lentiviral backbone-containing plasmid contamination of the virus stocks that can occur when viruses are produced from transfections.</p></sec><sec id="S22"><title>Validation of deep mutational scanning by pseudovirus titration and neutralization</title><p id="P89">Spike genes carrying desired mutations were cloned by performing PCR reactions with partially overlapping desired mutation-containing primers followed by HiFi assembly. HDM_omicron_B11529_IDTDNA plasmid was used as the template for PCR. The map of the plasmid can be found at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/jbloomlab/SARS-CoV-2-BA.1_Spike_DMS_validations/blob/main/plasmid_maps/3277_HDM_omicron_B11529_IDTDNA.gb">https://github.com/jbloomlab/SARS-CoV-2-BA.1_Spike_DMS_validations/blob/main/plasmid_maps/3277_HDM_omicron_B11529_IDTDNA.gb</ext-link>. All plasmid sequences were verified using full plasmid sequencing by Primordium. Mutated spike plasmids or VSV-G expression plasmid were then used to generate and titrate pseudoviruses as described in (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">Crawford et al., 2020</xref>) except that the backbone used for virus generation was pHAGE6_Luciferase_IRES_ZsGreen and which also only required Gag/Pol helper plasmid for virus rescues. Note, for the spike variants cloned to validate functional selections we performed three replicate virus rescues for each variant and each rescue was done using an independent plasmid preparation for that spike variant.</p><p id="P90">BA.1 spike variants rescued for funcional selection validation were titrated on HEK-293T-ACE2 and Delta spike variants were titrated on HEK-293T-ACE2-TMPRSS2 cells. We performed duplicate serial dilutions using supernatants collected from the virus rescues and measured luciferase expression at each dilution using Bright-Glo Luciferase Assay System (Promega, E2610). Virus titers were calculated as relative light units (RLU) per μl for each dilution and taking the average RLU/μl values across dilutions within a linear range. For spike variants used to validate antibody escape experiments virus titration was performed in the same way using the same target cells as the neutralization assays were performed in (see below).</p><p id="P91">For pseudovirus neutralization 12.5 thousand target cells were plated into poly-L-lysine coated, black-walled, 96-well plates (Greiner 655930) in D10 supplemented with 2.5 μg/ml of amphotericin B. For neutralization assays using LY-CoV1404, CC9.104 or CC67.105 antibodies we used HEK-293T-ACE2 as target cells, for REGN10933 we used HEK-293T-ACE2-TMPRSS2 as target cells, and for NTD 5-7 mAb we used HEK-293T-ACE2-medium as target cells. The use of different cell lines for each antibody is determined by the ability of that antibody to neutralize the virus on that cell line as described previously. Next day we prepared replicate serial dilutions for each antibody. Starting concentration for each antibody was as follows: LY-CoV1404 – 4 μg/ml, CC9.104 and CC67.105 – 300 μg/ml, 5-7 – 96 μg/ml, REGN10933 – 6 μg/ml. Serial dilutions were then mixed with pseudovirus and incubated for 1 h at 37°C. After incubation the virus-antibody mix was transferred onto the target cells. 48-55 h after infection Bright-Glo Luciferase Assay System (Promega, E2610) was used to measure luciferase activity. Fraction infectivity for each antibody dilution was calculated by subtracting background readings and dividing RLU values in the presence of antibody by RLU values in the absence of it. Neutralization curves were then plotted by fitting a Hill curve to fraction infectivity values using neutcurve software (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://jbloomlab.github.io/neutcurve/">https://jbloomlab.github.io/neutcurve/</ext-link>, version 0.5.7). Neutcurve package was also used to extract target IC<sub>x</sub> values from the fitted neutralization curves.</p><p id="P92">Code for plotting virus titers and neutralization curves from this paper can be found at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/jbloomlab/SARS-CoV-2-BA.1">https://github.com/jbloomlab/SARS-CoV-2-BA.1</ext-link> Spike DMS validations.</p></sec><sec id="S23"><title>Cell lines</title><p id="P93">HEK-293T were acquired from ATCC (CRL3216), HEK-293T-ACE2 cells are described in (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">Crawford et al., 2020</xref>), generation and characterization of HEK-293T-ACE2-medium cells is described in (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">Farrell et al., 2022</xref>) (referred to ‘medium’ cells in the reference), generation of HEK-293T-rtTA cells is described below. All cells were grown in D10 media (Dulbecco’s Modified Eagle Medium with 10% heat-inactivated fetal bovine serum, 2 mM l-glutamine, 100 U/mL penicillin, and 100 μg/mL streptomycin). For antibody selection experiments D10 was made with phenol-free DMEM (Corning DMEM With 4.5g/L Glucose, Sodium Pyruvate; Without L-Glutamine, Phenol Red from Fisher, Cat. No. MT17205CV). For experiments with HEK-293T-rtTA cells D10 was made with tetracycline-free FBS (Gemini Bio, Cat. No. 100-800) to avoid any expression of spike unless doxycycline is added.</p><p id="P94">To produce HEK-293T-rtTA expressing cells (used for storing deep mutational scanning libraries and required for TRE3G promoter activation) we first generated VSV-G-pseudotyped lentivirus carrying rtTA gene. To produce this virus we transfected 0.5 million HEK-293T cells with 0.25 μg of each helper plasmid (Gag/Pol, Tat1b, Rev1b), 0.25 μg of VSV-G expression plasmid and 1 μg of lentiviral backbone carrying plasmid into which rtTA has been cloned (plasmid map <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/dms-vep/SARS-CoV-2_Omicron_BA.1_spike_DMS_mAbs/blob/main/library_design/reference_sequences/other_plasmid_maps_for_library_design/2850_pHAGE2_EF1a_TetOn_IRES_mCherry.gb">https://github.com/dms-vep/SARS-CoV-2_Omicron_BA.1_spike_DMS_mAbs/blob/main/library_design/reference_sequences/other_plasmid_maps_for_library_design/2850_pHAGE2_EF1a_TetOn_IRES_mCherry.gb</ext-link>). Note this lentiviral backbone is selfinactivating and therefore would not be produced and packaged into lentiviral particles upon helper plasmid transfection. 48 hours after transfection virus-containing cell supernatant was collected and filtered through a surfactant-free cellulose acetate 0.45 μm syringe filter. 5μl of the virus was used to infect 0.5 million low passage HEK-293T cells. 48 hours post infection single cell clones were sorted into a 96-well plate using BD Aria II cell sorter with 610/20 filter in PE-Texas Red channel. Single clones were expanded and tested for ability to produce high virus titers. High virus titers are essential for performing deep mutational scanning experiments on a practical experimental scale and we found that individual cell clones can vary significantly in the virus titers they can produce. Clonal cell population producing the highest virus titers was selected for expansion, frozen down in 10% DMSO and 20% FBS D10 media, and stored long-term in liquid nitrogen freezer.</p></sec><sec id="S24"><title>Antibodies</title><p id="P95">LY-CoV1404 antibody was cloned and produced by GensScript. Variable domain sequences were taken from previously published antibody structure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R68">Westendorf et al., 2022</xref>). LY-CoV1404 variable regions were cloned with IgG1 heavy chain and human IgL2 constant regions, expressed in mammalian cells and purified using IgG-binding columns. S2 antibodies were produced as described previously in (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R73">Zhou et al., 2022</xref>). 5-7 antibody was produced as described previously in (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37">Liu et al., 2020</xref>)</p></sec></sec><sec id="S25"><title>Computational Analysis and Data Availability</title><sec id="S26"><title>Overview of data analysis pipeline</title><p id="P96">To analyze the deep mutational scanning data, we created a modular analysis pipeline. At the core of this pipeline is a set of common steps that are expected to be shared across analysis of many different datasets. We implemented this set of common steps in a standalone GitHub repository named <italic>dms-vep-pipeline</italic> that is publicly available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/dms-vep/dms-vep-pipeline">https://github.com/dms-vep/dms-vep-pipeline</ext-link> and is designed to be included in project-specific analyses as a git submodule. The <italic>dms-vep-pipeline</italic> consists of a series of Snakemake (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R44">Mölder et al., 2021</xref>) rules that run Python scripts or Jupyter notebooks, and specifies a conda environment that provides details on the software used for the analysis. For this paper, we used version 1.01 of the <italic>dms</italic>-<italic>vep-pipeline</italic>.</p><p id="P97">For each specific project (in this case, deep mutational scanning of the BA.1 and Delta spikes) we created a separate GitHub repository that included <italic>dms-vep-pipeline</italic> as a submodule. The repository for BA.1 is publicly available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/dms-vep/SARS-CoV-2_Omicron">https://github.com/dms-vep/SARS-CoV-2_Omicron</ext-link> BA.1 spike DMS mAbsand the repository for Delta is at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/dms-vep/SARS-CoV-2_Delta_spike_DMS_REGN10933">https://github.com/dms-vep/SARS-CoV-2_Delta_spike_DMS_REGN10933</ext-link> Note how each repository has a configuration file (the <italic>config.yaml</italic> file), project-specific input data (the <italic>data</italic> subdirectory), and a top-level Snakemake file (the <italic>Snakefile)</italic> that runs the analysis. The output of running the pipeline is placed in a results subdirectory, although only key results files are tracked in the GitHub repository since many of them are very large. The pipeline also generates HTML rendering of the key analysis notebooks and result plots, which are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://dms-vep.github.io/SARS-CoV-2_Omicron_BA.1_spike_DMS_mAbs_for_BA.1">https://dms-vep.github.io/SARS-CoV-2_Omicron_BA.1_spike_DMS_mAbs_for_BA.1</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://dms-vep.github.io/SARS-CoV-2_Delta_spike_DMS_REGN10933">https://dms-vep.github.io/SARS-CoV-2_Delta_spike_DMS_REGN10933</ext-link> for Delta. Looking at these websites is the easiest way to understand the analysis. Note that many of the plots are interactive charts created with Altair (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R65">VanderPlas et al., 2018</xref>), and we encourage readers to use the interactive features to better explore the data.</p></sec><sec id="S27"><title>Analysis of PacBio data to link barcodes to spike mutations</title><p id="P98">To link each barcode to its spike variant, we used <italic>alignparse</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">Crawford and Bloom, 2019</xref>) to process the PacBio CCSs to determine the barcode and spike mutations for each CCS.</p><p id="P99">We performed several quality control steps. First we examined the synonymous tags introduced at the end of each amplicon during the library preparation to identify CCSs with discordant tags indicative of strand exchange during library preparation: typically &lt;2% of CCSs had discordant tags, indicating a low rate of strand exchange. CCSs with identified strand exchange or out of frame indels were discarded. Next, we computed the empirical accuracy of the CCSs by examining how often CCSs with the same barcode reported the same spike sequence (the exact method used to compute the empirical accuracy is implemented here: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://jbloomlab.github.io/alignparse/alignparse.consensus.html#alignparse.consensus.empirical_accuracy">https://jbloomlab.github.io/alignparse/alignparse.consensus.html#alignparse.consensus.empirical_accuracy</ext-link>). The empirical accuracies were between 0.65 and 0.75, indicating that fraction of CCSs correctly report the actual mutations. The inaccuracies are due to a combination of sequencing errors, reverse transcription errors, PCR strand exchange, and occasional actual association of the same barcode with different variants in different cells (which can especially arise if the complexity of the initial virus library integrated into cells at single copy is not much higher than the complexity of the final cell library).</p><p id="P100">We then built consensus sequences for each barcode with at least three CCSs, using the method implemented at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://jbloomlab.github.io/alignparse/alignparse.consensus.html#alignparse.consensus.simple_mutconsens_us">https://jbloomlab.github.io/alignparse/alignparse.consensus.html#alignparse.consensus.simple_mutconsens_us</ext-link> with <italic>max_minor_sub_frac</italic> and <italic>max_minor_indel_frac</italic> both set to 0.2. This approach of requiring multiple concordant CCSs to call a consensus is expected to lead to higher accuracy in the final barcode / spike variant linking, and will generally discard barcodes that are not uniquely linked to a single spike variant.</p><p id="P101">Files containing the final barcode / variant lookup tables and the analysis notebooks with resulting quality control plots are linked to the main HTML pages in the documentation for the BA.1 and Delta experiments as provided in the <italic>Processed data</italic> section below.</p></sec><sec id="S28"><title>Analysis of Illumina data to count barcodes for each variant in each experiment</title><p id="P102">For each experiment, we processed the Illumina barcode sequencing with the parser implemented at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://jbloomlab.github.io/dms_variants/dms_variants.illuminabarcodeparser.html">https://jbloomlab.github.io/dms_variants/dms_variants.illuminabarcodeparser.html</ext-link> to determine the counts of each variant in each condition. Barcoded variants were only retained for subsequent analysis if their “pre-selection” counts (no-antibody selection for antibody escape experiments, VSV-G-pseudotyped infections for functional selections) met some minimal count threshold specified in the <italic>config.yaml</italic> file of the GitHub repos for the BA.1 and Delta spikes. This thresholding removes variants that are expected to have substantial noise due to low counts. Note that a caveat that should be kept in mind is that the actual key bottleneck is expected to usually occur at the stage of infection with the virus library rather than sequencing, since the barcodes are generally sequenced to a depth that greatly exceeds the complexity of the libraries used for the infections. Therefore, although variants with low counts are expected to have more noise, the counts do not enable a quantitative estimate of the actual bottleneck size experienced by each variant.</p><p id="P103">Files containing the barcode counts and the analysis notebook with resulting quality control plots are linked to the main HTML pages in the documentation for the BA.1 and Delta experiments as provided in the <italic>Processed data</italic> section below.</p></sec><sec id="S29"><title>Computing functional effects of mutations in deep mutational scanning</title><p id="P104">To estimate the functional effects of individual mutations, we first computed functional scores for each variant from the counts in the VSV-G-pseudotyped library infection (which should not impose any selection on the spike) versus the spike-pseudotyped library infected into ACE2 expressing target cells. The functional score for variant <italic>v</italic> is defined as <italic>log<sub>2</sub></italic> ([n<sup>v</sup><sub>post</sub> / <italic>n<sup>wt</sup><sub>post</sub></italic>]/[<italic>n<sup>v</sup><sub>pre</sub></italic> / <italic>n<sup>wt</sup><sub>pre</sub></italic>]) where <italic>n<sup>v</sup><sub>post</sub></italic> is the count of variant <italic>v</italic> in the post-selection (spike-pseudotyped) infection, <italic>n<sup>v</sup><sub>pre</sub></italic> is the count of variant <italic>v</italic> in the pre-selection (VSV-G-pseudotyped) infection, and <italic>n<sup>wt</sup><sub>post</sub></italic> and <italic>n<sup>wt</sup><sub>post</sub></italic> are the counts of all unmutated (wildtype) variants in each condition. Negative functional scores indicate a spike variant is worse at mediating infection than the unmutated spike, and positive functional scores indicate a variant is better at mediating infection than the unmutated spike. The distributions of these functional scores are plotted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>.</p><p id="P105">To deconvolve the functional scores for all spike variants (which often contain multiple mutations) into estimates of the effects of individual amino-acid mutations, we fit global epistasis models (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R49">Otwinowski et al., 2018</xref>) to the variant functional scores, using the models implemented at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://jbloomlab.github.io/dms_variants/dms_variants.globalepistasis.html">https://jbloomlab.github.io/dms_variants/dms_variants.globalepistasis.html</ext-link> with the Gaussian likelihood function. This fitting estimates how each mutation affects an underlying latent phenotype, as well as the shape of the global epistasis function relating the latent phenotype to the observed functional score. We also then re-transform the inferred effect of each mutation on this latent phenotype through the global epistasis function to estimate its effect on the observed phenotype. This approach provides a way to deconvolve the information in the multi-mutant variants to more accurately estimate the effects of mutations under the assumptions of a global epistasis model (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R49">Otwinowski et al., 2018</xref>). For final reporting, we then took the average (median) of the estimated functional effect of each mutation across all the replicates and libraries for each different spike (BA.1 or Delta). In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref> of this paper we report the functional effects on the observed (rather than latent) phenotype, as that is a more relevant measure of its expected impact on spike-mediated infection.</p><p id="P106">Files containing the effects of mutations on both the latent and observed phenotypes for both individual replicates/libraries and averages across them, the analysis notebooks with relevant quality control plots, and interactive plots summarizing the final estimates are linked to the main HTML pages in the documentation for the BA.1 and Delta experiments as provided in the <italic>Processed data</italic> section below.</p><p id="P107">For the figures in this paper and the default view of the interactive plots described in the <italic>Processed data</italic> section below, we only include mutations seen in at least three distinct variants (averaged across libraries).</p></sec><sec id="S30"><title>Computing antibody escape by mutations</title><p id="P108">For the antibody selections, we computed the non-neutralized fraction (probability of escape) <italic>p<sub>v</sub></italic>(<italic>c</italic>) for each variant <italic>v</italic> at each antibody concentration <italic>c</italic> for a given antibody as <italic>p<sub>v</sub></italic>(<italic>c</italic>) = <italic>(n<sub>v</sub><sup>c</sup>/S<sup>c</sup>)/(n<sub>v</sub></italic><sup>0</sup>/<italic>S</italic><sup>0</sup>) where <italic>n<sub>v</sub><sup>c</sup></italic> is the count of variant <italic>v</italic> at antibody concentration <italic>c</italic>, <italic>n<sub>v</sub></italic><sup>0</sup> is the count of variant <italic>v</italic> in the no-antibody control, <italic>S<sup>c</sup></italic> is the total counts of the neutralization standard at antibody concentration <italic>c</italic>, and <italic>S</italic><sup>0</sup> is the total concentration of the neutralization standard in the no-antibody control. These values should in principle fall between 0 (variant is totally neutralized by antibody) and 1 (variant is not neutralized by antibody), and in practice we clip any values measured as &gt;1 to a value of 1.</p><p id="P109">To deconvolve mutation-level escape values from the measured <italic>p<sub>v</sub>(c)</italic> values for the variants (which often contain multiple mutations) at multiple concentrations, we used the approach implemented in <italic>polyclonal</italic> software package (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://jbloomlab.github.io/polyclonal/">https://jbloomlab.github.io/polyclonal/</ext-link>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R69">Yu et al., 2022</xref>), constraining the fits to a single epitope (since we are only analyzing monoclonal antibodies). This analysis yields a mutation-level escape score for each observed variant (the <italic>β<sub>m,e</sub></italic> values in the nomenclature of the <italic>polyclonal</italic> package) which will be zero for mutations that have no effect on antibody escape, and &gt;0 for mutations that mediate antibody escape. These are the values plotted in the heat maps shown in the antibody escape figures in this paper; the line plots show site-level summaries of these values (eg, the sum of the escape values at each site). Note that the <italic>polyclonal</italic> models (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R69">Yu et al., 2022</xref>) can use the escape values inferred from the deep mutational scanning to predict the non-neutralized fraction for arbitrary mutants, and we correlated those measurements with the IC50 values measured by standard neutralization assays in the antibody escape figures in this paper. For all antibodies we had replicate measurements (multiple libraries, and in some cases technical replicates of the same library), and the final reported values are the average (median) across these replicates.</p><p id="P110">Files containing the escape values for both individual replicates/libraries and averages across them, the analysis notebooks with relevant quality control plots, and interactive plots summarizing the final estimates are linked to the main HTML pages in the documentation for the BA.1 and Delta experiments as provided in the <italic>Processed data</italic> section below.</p><p id="P111">For the figures in this paper and the default view of the interactive plots described in the <italic>Processed data</italic> section below, we only include mutations seen in at least three distinct variants (averaged across libraries), and with a functional effect of at least −1.38 (for Omicron BA.1) or at least −1.47 (for Delta).</p></sec><sec id="S31"><title>Comparison of deep mutational scanning data to enrichment of mutations during actual human SARS-CoV-2 evolution</title><p id="P112">In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref>, we compare the functional effects of mutations measured in deep mutational scanning to the enrichment of mutations in actual human SARS-CoV-2 evolution compared that expected given the underlying viral mutation rate. The computation of the “expected” versus actual observed mutation counts is performed by the code at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/jbloomlab/SARS2-mut-rates/tree/25204ea0c868c4c86d0cc16bd5f203b1_b0607868">https://github.com/jbloomlab/SARS2-mut-rates/tree/25204ea0c868c4c86d0cc16bd5f203b1_b0607868</ext-link>
</p><p id="P113">The approach for calculating the enrichment of observed versus expected mutations is inspired by the strategy used in (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R46">Neher, 2022</xref>). Briefly, we downloaded the pre-built UShER tree of all publicly available SARS-CoV-2 sequences (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R63">Turakhia et al., 2021</xref>) as of Sept-26-2022 from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://hgdownload.soe.ucsc.edu/goldenPath/wuhCor1/UShER_SARS-CoV-2/2022/09/26/public-2022-09-26.all.masked.nextclade.pangolin.pb.gz">http://hgdownload.soe.ucsc.edu/goldenPath/wuhCor1/UShER_SARS-CoV-2/2022/09/26/public-2022-09-26.all.masked.nextclade.pangolin.pb.gz</ext-link>. We then used matUtils (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R63">Turakhia et al., 2021</xref>) to separate the tree by the pre-annotated Nextstrain clades, and extract the number of unique <bold><italic>occurrences</italic></bold> of each nucleotide mutation along the tree branches for each clade. Note that we are counting unique occurrences of each mutation along the tree (number of branches with a mutation), not the number of observations of the mutation in the final set of aligned mutations. This is an important distinction, as a mutation could be common in the final aligned sequences even if it only had one or a few occurrences. In counting these occurrences, we ignored mutations on any branch with more than four nucleotide mutations, or more than one nucleotide mutation to either the Wuhan-Hu-1 reference sequence or the founder sequence for that clade, as taken from (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R46">Neher, 2022</xref>). The reason for excluding mutations on branches with high numbers of mutations as these can often indicate problematic sequences; the reason for excluding mutations on branches with multiple reversions to reference is that sometimes sequences with missing coverage have identities automatically called to reference. After tabulating these mutation counts, we ignored any mutations that are reversions from the clade founder to the Wuhan-Hu-1 reference or reversions of these, a set of sites known to be subject to sequencing errors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R62">Turakhia et al., 2020</xref>), or were at sites with unusually high mutation rates (see sites manually specified in the config.yaml file at the GitHub repo listed above). Overall, this process provided a list of the counts of nucleotide mutations for each Nextstrain clade after filtering branches and mutations/sites expected to be affected by various possible errors.</p><p id="P114">We then calculated the relative rates of each type of the 12 possible nucleotide mutations at four-fold synonymous third codon positions by counting the mutation at such positions in each Nextstrain clade, and then normalizing the fraction of these positions that had each nucleotide identity at each site, retaining only Nextstrain clades with at least 5000 such mutation counts. We then calculated for each clade the expected number of counts of each nucleotide mutation based on these rates and the actual counts at the four-fold synonymous sites. The result of these calculations is how many times we expect to observe each nucleotide mutation if all sites are under the same constraint as the four-fold synonymous sites. Next, we aggregated the expected and observed counts across all Nextstrain clades, and also across all nucleotide mutations that encoded for the same amino-acid mutation to get expected and observed counts for amino-acid mutations, and only retained amino-acid mutations with at least 20 expected counts. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7D</xref> plots the log base 2 of the expected versus observed counts after adding a pseudocount of 0.5.</p><p id="P115">We compared these counts to deep mutational scanning data from our study and several other spike deep mutational scanning studies as described in the main text. The tabulated deep mutational scanning measurements and the enrichments of mutations in actual SARS-CoV-2 evolution are at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/dms-vep/SARS-CoV-2_Omicron_BA.1_spike_DMS_mAbs/blob/main/results/compare_muteffects/natural_enrichment_vs_dms.csv">https://github.com/dms-vep/SARS-CoV-2_Omicron_BA.1_spike_DMS_mAbs/blob/main/results/compare_muteffects/natural_enrichment_vs_dms.csv</ext-link></p></sec><sec id="S32"><title>Processed data</title><p id="P116">The key results from the analysis are stored in the results subdirectory of the GitHub repos for BA.1 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/dms-vep/SARS-CoV-2_Omicron_BA.1_spike_DMS_mAbs">https://github.com/dms-vep/SARS-CoV-2_Omicron_BA.1_spike_DMS_mAbs</ext-link>) and Delta (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/dms-vep/SARS-CoV-2_Delta_spike_DMS_REGN10933">https://github.com/dms-vep/SARS-CoV-2_Delta_spike_DMS_REGN10933</ext-link>). The easiest way to navigate these results are via the HTML documentation at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://dms-vep.github.io/SARS-CoV-2_Omicron_BA.1_spike_DMS_mAbs">https://dms-vep.github.io/SARS-CoV-2_Omicron_BA.1_spike_DMS_mAbs</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://dms-vep.github.io/SARS-CoV-2_Delta_spike_DMS_REGN10933">https://dms-vep.github.io/SARS-CoV-2_Delta_spike_DMS_REGN10933</ext-link> These pages contain links to the key data files, as well as interactive heat maps of the functional effects of mutations and the effects of mutations on antibody escape. Note that these plots are interactive, and allow you to filter by certain regions of the protein, the number of variants in which a mutation is seen, the maximum magnitude of an effect at a given site, and other relevant parameters.</p><p id="P117">In the final output files, mutations are numbered in reference-based (Wuhan-Hu-1) spike numbering. The GitHub repos contain files that convert sequential numbering of the BA.1 and Delta spike to reference based numbering.</p></sec><sec id="S33"><title>Raw sequencing data</title><p id="P118">The raw PacBio and Illumina sequencing data have been deposited on the NCBI’s Sequence Read Archive with BioProject number PRJNA888402 for the Omicron BA.1 data and PRJNA889020 for the Delta data. The PacBio sequencing linking variants to barcodes can be found under BioSample accessions SAMN31220980 for Omicron BA.1 and SAMN31230634 for Delta. The Illumina barcode sequencing can be found under BioSample accessions SAMN31216920 for Omicron BA.1 and SAMN31230628 for Delta.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="SM"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1"><label>Supplementary Material</label><media xlink:href="EMS155739-supplement-Supplementary_Material.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" id="d126aAdFbB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack id="S34"><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>We thank Michael Emerman for scientific advice and Kenneth A Matreyek for providing HEK-293T-ACE2-medium cell line. This work was supported in part by the NIH/NIAID under grant R01AI141707 and contract 75N93021C00015 to JDB. This work was supported in part by a Gates Foundation grant INV-004949 to JDB. JDB is an Investigator of the Howard Hughes Medical Institute. KHDC was supported by NIH/NIAID grant F30AI149928. BD was funded in part by EMBO under grant ALTF 81-2020. CER was supported by the Viral Pathogenesis and Evolution training grant T32 AI083203. TCY was supported by the CMB training grant T32 GM007270 and the NSF graduate research fellowship DGE-2140004. DRB was supported by NIAID grant UM1 AI44462 and Bill and Melinda Gates Foundation grants OPP1170236 and INV-004923.</p></ack><fn-group><fn id="FN2" fn-type="conflict"><p id="P119"><bold>Competing interests</bold></p><p id="P120">JDB is on the scientific advisory board of Apriori Bio and Oncorus, and has recently consulted on topics related to viral evolution for Moderna and Merck. JDB, KHDC, and CER receive royalty payments as inventors on Fred Hutch licensed patents related to viral deep mutational scanning. JDB, KHDC, CER and BD are inventors on a pending patent application relating to the viral deep mutational scanning system described in this paper. RB is a consultant for IAVI, Adagio, Adimab, Mabloc, VosBio, Nonigenex, and Radiant. DDH is a co-founder of TaiMed Biologics and RenBio, consultant to WuXi Biologics and Brii Biosciences, and board director for Vicarious Surgical. The other authors declare no competing interests.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><ref id="R1"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ballal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Malliaris</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Morozov</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Molecular Phenotypes as Key Intermediates in Mapping Genotypes to Fitness</chapter-title><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Pontarotti</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><source>Evolutionary Biology—A Transdisciplinary Approach</source><publisher-name>Springer International Publishing</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Cham</publisher-loc><year>2020</year><fpage>15</fpage><lpage>40</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-3-030-57246-4_2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baum</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Fulton</surname><given-names>BO</given-names></name><name><surname>Wloga</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Copin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Pascal</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name><surname>Russo</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Giordano</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lanza</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Negron</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Ni</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Antibody cocktail to SARS-CoV-2 spike protein prevents rapid mutational escape seen with individual antibodies</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2020</year><elocation-id>eabd0831</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.abd0831</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bellusci</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Grubbs</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Zahra</surname><given-names>FT</given-names></name><name><surname>Forgacs</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Golding</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Khurana</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antibody affinity and cross-variant neutralization of SARS-CoV-2 Omicron BA.1, BA.2 and BA.3 following third mRNA vaccination</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2022</year><volume>13</volume><elocation-id>4617</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-022-32298-w</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Benton</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wrobel</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Roustan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Borg</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosenthal</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name><name><surname>Skehel</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Gamblin</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effect of the D614G substitution on the structure of the spike glycoprotein of SARS-CoV-2</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci</source><year>2021</year><volume>118</volume><elocation-id>e2022586118</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.2022586118</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bloom</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An Experimentally Determined Evolutionary Model Dramatically Improves Phylogenetic Fit</article-title><source>Mol Biol Evol</source><year>2014</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>1956</fpage><lpage>1978</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/molbev/msu173</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Jian</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Yisimayi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>An</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Yao</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Imprinted SARS-CoV-2 humoral immunity induces converging Omicron RBD evolution</article-title><year>2022</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2022.09.15.507787</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cerutti</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Nair</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Katsamba</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name><surname>Bahna</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Reddem</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Neutralizing antibody 5-7 defines a distinct site of vulnerability in SARS-CoV-2 spike N-terminal domain</article-title><source>Cell Rep</source><year>2021</year><volume>37</volume><elocation-id>109928</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.celrep.2021.109928</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Nadeau</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yared</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Voinov</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Roemer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Stadler</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>CoV-Spectrum: analysis of globally shared SARS-CoV-2 data to identify and characterize new variants</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2022</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>1735</fpage><lpage>1737</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btab856</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chun</surname><given-names>T-W</given-names></name><name><surname>Carruth</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Finzi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>DiGiuseppe</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hermankova</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Chadwick</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Margolick</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Quinn</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuo</surname><given-names>Y-H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Quantification of latent tissue reservoirs and total body viral load in HIV-1 infection</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1997</year><volume>387</volume><fpage>183</fpage><lpage>188</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/387183a0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crawford</surname><given-names>KHD</given-names></name><name><surname>Bloom</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>alignparse: A Python package for parsing complex features from high-throughput long-read sequencing</article-title><source>J Open Source Softw</source><year>2019</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>1915</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21105/joss.01915</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crawford</surname><given-names>KHD</given-names></name><name><surname>Dingens</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Eguia</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolf</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilcox</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Logue</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Shuey</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Casto</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Fiala</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Wrenn</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Pettie</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Dynamics of Neutralizing Antibody Titers in the Months After Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome Coronavirus 2 Infection</article-title><source>J Infect Dis</source><year>2021</year><volume>223</volume><fpage>197</fpage><lpage>205</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/infdis/jiaa618</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crawford</surname><given-names>KHD</given-names></name><name><surname>Eguia</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Dingens</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Loes</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name><name><surname>Malone</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolf</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name><name><surname>Tortorici</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Veesler</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pettie</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Protocol and Reagents for Pseudotyping Lentiviral Particles with SARS-CoV-2 Spike Protein for Neutralization Assays</article-title><source>Viruses</source><year>2020</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>513</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/v12050513</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cronin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X-Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Reiser</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Altering the Tropism of Lentiviral Vectors through Pseudotyping</article-title><source>Curr Gene Ther</source><year>2005</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>387</fpage><lpage>398</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>DeGrace</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghedin</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Frieman</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Krammer</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Grifoni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Alisoltani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Alter</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Amara</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name><surname>Baric</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Barouch</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Bloom</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Defining the risk of SARS-CoV-2 variants on immune protection</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2022</year><volume>605</volume><fpage>640</fpage><lpage>652</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41586-022-04690-5</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dingens</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Acharya</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Haddox</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name><name><surname>Rawi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Chuang</surname><given-names>G-Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Mascola</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Carragher</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Potter</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Complete functional mapping of infection- and vaccine-elicited antibodies against the fusion peptide of HIV</article-title><source>PLOS Pathog</source><year>2018</year><volume>14</volume><elocation-id>e1007159</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/iournal.ppat.1007159</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Farrell</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Dadonaite</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Greaney</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Eguia</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Loes</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name><name><surname>Franko</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><name><surname>Logue</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Carreño</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Abbad</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name><name><surname>Matreyek</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Receptor-Binding Domain (RBD) Antibodies Contribute More to SARS-CoV-2 Neutralization When Target Cells Express High Levels of ACE2</article-title><source>Viruses</source><year>2022</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>2061</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/v14092061</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Sayal</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Aley</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name><name><surname>Bibi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Dold</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Fuskova</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gilbert</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirsch</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Humphries</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Correlates of protection against symptomatic and asymptomatic SARS-CoV-2 infection</article-title><source>Nat Med</source><year>2021</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>2032</fpage><lpage>2040</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41591-021-01540-1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gilbert</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name><name><surname>Montefiori</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>McDermott</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Fong</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Benkeser</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Houchens</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Martins</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Jayashankar</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Castellino</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Immune correlates analysis of the mRNA-1273 COVID-19 vaccine efficacy clinical trial</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2022</year><volume>375</volume><fpage>43</fpage><lpage>50</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.abm3425</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Greaney</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Starr</surname><given-names>TN</given-names></name><name><surname>Barnes</surname><given-names>CO</given-names></name><name><surname>Weisblum</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Caskey</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaebler</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Agudelo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Finkin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Mapping mutations to the SARS-CoV-2 RBD that escape binding by different classes of antibodies</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2021</year><volume>12</volume><elocation-id>4196</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-021-24435-8</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Greaney</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Starr</surname><given-names>TN</given-names></name><name><surname>Bloom</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An antibody-escape estimator for mutations to the SARS-CoV-2 receptor-binding domain</article-title><source>Virus Evol</source><year>2022</year><volume>8</volume><elocation-id>veac021</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ve/veac021</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haddox</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name><name><surname>Dingens</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Bloom</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Experimental Estimation of the Effects of All Amino-Acid Mutations to HIV’s Envelope Protein on Viral Replication in Cell Culture</article-title><source>PLOS Pathog</source><year>2016</year><volume>12</volume><elocation-id>e1006114</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1006114</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Baum</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pascal</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name><surname>Russo</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Giordano</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wloga</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Fulton</surname><given-names>BO</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Koon</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Studies in humanized mice and convalescent humans yield a SARS-CoV-2 antibody cocktail</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2020</year><volume>369</volume><fpage>1010</fpage><lpage>1014</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.abd0827</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harms</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Thornton</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evolutionary biochemistry: revealing the historical and physical causes of protein properties</article-title><source>Nat Rev Genet</source><year>2013</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>559</fpage><lpage>571</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrg3540</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Havranek</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name><surname>Jimenez</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Acciani</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Lay Mendoza</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Reyes Ballista</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Diaz</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Brindley</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>SARS-CoV-2 Spike Alterations Enhance Pseudoparticle Titers and Replication-Competent VSV-SARS-CoV-2 Virus</article-title><source>Viruses</source><year>2020</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>1465</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/v12121465</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hiatt</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Patwardhan</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Shendure</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Parallel, tag-directed assembly of locally derived short sequence reads</article-title><source>Nat Methods</source><year>2010</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>119</fpage><lpage>122</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.1416</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>McFaline-Figueroa</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Starita</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Gasperini</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Matreyek</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Packer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Shendure</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Trapnell</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>On the design of CRISPR-based single-cell molecular screens</article-title><source>Nat Methods</source><year>2018</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>271</fpage><lpage>274</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.4604</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>S-W</given-names></name><name><surname>Tai</surname><given-names>C-H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hsu</surname><given-names>Y-M</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Hung</surname><given-names>S-J</given-names></name><name><surname>Chai</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y-F</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J-R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assessing the application of a pseudovirus system for emerging SARS-CoV-2 and re-emerging avian influenza virus H5 subtypes in vaccine development</article-title><source>Biomed J</source><year>2020</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>375</fpage><lpage>387</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bj.2020.06.003</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><element-citation publication-type="web"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Inglesby</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Bloom</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Brownstein</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Burke</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Cicero</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Correa</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>del Rio</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Diggans</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Esvelt</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>Recommendations to Strengthen the US Government’s Enhanced Potential Pandemic Pathogen Framework and Dual Use Research of Concern Policies</source><year>2022</year><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.centerforhealthsecurity.org/news/center-news/pdfs/220629-RecstostrengthenUSGePPPandDURCPolicies.pdf">https://www.centerforhealthsecurity.org/news/center-news/pdfs/220629-RecstostrengthenUSGePPPandDURCPolicies.pdf</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Javanmardi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Chou</surname><given-names>C-W</given-names></name><name><surname>Terrace</surname><given-names>CI</given-names></name><name><surname>Annapareddy</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaoud</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Lutgens</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zorkic</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Horton</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Gardner</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name><name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Rapid characterization of spike variants via mammalian cell surface display</article-title><source>Mol Cell</source><year>2021</year><volume>81</volume><fpage>5099</fpage><lpage>5111</lpage><elocation-id>e8</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molcel.2021.11.024</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jetzt</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Klarmann</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ron</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Preston</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name><name><surname>Dougherty</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>High Rate of Recombination throughout the Human Immunodeficiency Virus Type 1 Genome</article-title><source>J Virol</source><year>2000</year><volume>74</volume><fpage>1234</fpage><lpage>1240</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khare</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gurry</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Freitas</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Schultz</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bach</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Diallo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Akite</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>TC Lee</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Yeo</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><collab>Core Curation Team, G.</collab><etal/></person-group><article-title>GISAID’s Role in Pandemic Response</article-title><source>China CDC Wkly</source><year>2021</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>1049</fpage><lpage>1051</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.46234/ccdcw2021.255</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khetawat</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Broder</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A Functional Henipavirus Envelope Glycoprotein Pseudotyped Lentivirus Assay System</article-title><source>Virol J</source><year>2010</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>312</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1743-422X-7-312</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kobinger</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name><name><surname>Weiner</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Q-C</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Filovirus-pseudotyped lentiviral vector can efficiently and stably transduce airway epithelia in vivo</article-title><source>Nat Biotechnol</source><year>2001</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>225</fpage><lpage>230</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/85664</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Larson</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Hosack</surname><given-names>VT</given-names></name><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Bolken</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name><name><surname>Hruby</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Amberg</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of a Broad-Spectrum Arenavirus Entry Inhibitor</article-title><source>J Virol</source><year>2008</year><volume>82</volume><fpage>10768</fpage><lpage>10775</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JVI.00941-08</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>T-Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Chin</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Everitt</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Clare</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Perreira</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Savidis</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Aker</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>John</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Sarlah</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Carreira</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Elledge</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Amphotericin B Increases Influenza A Virus Infection by Preventing IFITM3-Mediated Restriction</article-title><source>Cell Rep</source><year>2013</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>895</fpage><lpage>908</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.celrep.2013.10.033</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Zuo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhuang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Extensive Recombination Due to Heteroduplexes Generates Large Amounts of Artificial Gene Fragments during PCR</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2014</year><volume>9</volume><elocation-id>e106658</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0106658</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R37"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Nair</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Rapp</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>JF-W</given-names></name><name><surname>Sahi</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Figueroa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>XV</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Potent neutralizing antibodies against multiple epitopes on SARS-CoV-2 spike</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2020</year><volume>584</volume><fpage>450</fpage><lpage>456</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41586-020-2571-7</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R38"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Lihong</given-names></name><name><surname>Iketani</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>JF-W</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Liyuan</given-names></name><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Yiming</given-names></name><name><surname>Nair</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Striking antibody evasion manifested by the Omicron variant of SARS-CoV-2</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2022</year><volume>602</volume><fpage>676</fpage><lpage>681</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41586-021-04388-0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R39"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maher</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Bartha</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Weaver</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>di Iulio</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferri</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Soriaga</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Lempp</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hie</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name><name><surname>Bryson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Predicting the mutational drivers of future SARS-CoV-2 variants of concern</article-title><source>Sci Transl Med</source><year>2022</year><volume>14</volume><elocation-id>eabk3445</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/scitranslmed.abk3445</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R40"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Matreyek</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Starita</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Stephany</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Chiasson</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>VE</given-names></name><name><surname>Kircher</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Khechaduri</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Dines</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name><name><surname>Hause</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhatia</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Multiplex Assessment of Protein Variant Abundance by Massively Parallel Sequencing</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><year>2018</year><volume>50</volume><fpage>874</fpage><lpage>882</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41588-018-0122-z</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R41"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McCallum</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>De Marco</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lempp</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name><name><surname>Tortorici</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Pinto</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Walls</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Beltramello</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Zatta</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Zepeda</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>N-terminal domain antigenic mapping reveals a site of vulnerability for SARS-CoV-2</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2021</year><volume>184</volume><fpage>2332</fpage><lpage>2347</lpage><elocation-id>e16</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2021.03.028</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R42"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McCarthy</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name><surname>Rennick</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Nambulli</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Robinson-McCarthy</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name><name><surname>Bain</surname><given-names>WG</given-names></name><name><surname>Haidar</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Duprex</surname><given-names>WP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Recurrent deletions in the SARS-CoV-2 spike glycoprotein drive antibody escape</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2021</year><volume>371</volume><fpage>1139</fpage><lpage>1142</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.abf6950</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R43"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Medina</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Kobinger</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name><name><surname>Rux</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gasmi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Looney</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bates</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lentiviral vectors pseudotyped with minimal filovirus envelopes increased gene transfer in murine lung</article-title><source>Mol Ther</source><year>2003</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>777</fpage><lpage>789</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ymthe.2003.07.003</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R44"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mölder</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Jablonski</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name><name><surname>Letcher</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Tomkins-Tinch</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Sochat</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Forster</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Twardziok</surname><given-names>SO</given-names></name><name><surname>Kanitz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilm</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Sustainable data analysis with Snakemake</article-title><year>2021</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.12688/f1000research.29032.2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R45"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Naldini</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Blömer</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Gallay</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Ory</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Mulligan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Gage</surname><given-names>FH</given-names></name><name><surname>Verma</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name><name><surname>Trono</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In Vivo Gene Delivery and Stable Transduction of Nondividing Cells by a Lentiviral Vector</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1996</year><volume>272</volume><fpage>263</fpage><lpage>267</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.272.5259.263</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R46"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Neher</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Contributions of adaptation and purifying selection to SARS-CoV-2 evolution</article-title><year>2022</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2022.08.22.504731</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R47"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>OhAinle</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Helms</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Vermeire</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Roesch</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Humes</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Basom</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Delrow</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Overbaugh</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Emerman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A virus-packageable CRISPR screen identifies host factors mediating interferon inhibition of HIV</article-title><source>eLife</source><year>2018</year><volume>7</volume><elocation-id>e39823</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.39823</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R48"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Omelina</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name><surname>Ivankin</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name><name><surname>Letiagina</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Pindyurin</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Optimized PCR conditions minimizing the formation of chimeric DNA molecules from MPRA plasmid libraries</article-title><source>BMC Genomics</source><year>2019</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>536</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12864-019-5847-2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R49"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Otwinowski</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>McCandlish</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Plotkin</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inferring the shape of global epistasis</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci</source><year>2018</year><volume>115</volume><fpage>e7550</fpage><lpage>E7558</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1804015115</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R50"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ouyang</surname><given-names>WO</given-names></name><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>TJC</given-names></name><name><surname>Lei</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Kieffer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Andrabi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Matreyek</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Probing the biophysical constraints of SARS-CoV-2 spike N-terminal domain using deep mutational scanning</article-title><year>2022</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2022.06.20.496903</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R51"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Koyanagi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Miles</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wiley</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Vinters</surname><given-names>HV</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>ISY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>High levels of unintegrated HIV-1 DNA in brain tissue of AIDS dementia patients</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1990</year><volume>343</volume><fpage>85</fpage><lpage>89</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/343085a0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R52"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peacock</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldhill</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Baillon</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Frise</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Swann</surname><given-names>OC</given-names></name><name><surname>Kugathasan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Penn</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanchez-David</surname><given-names>RY</given-names></name><name><surname>Braga</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The furin cleavage site in the SARS-CoV-2 spike protein is required for transmission in ferrets</article-title><source>Nat Microbiol</source><year>2021</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>899</fpage><lpage>909</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41564-021-00908-w</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R53"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Plante</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lokugamage</surname><given-names>KG</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Muruato</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Fontes-Garfias</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Mirchandani</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Spike mutation D614G alters SARS-CoV-2 fitness</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2021</year><volume>592</volume><fpage>116</fpage><lpage>121</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41586-020-2895-3</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R54"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sailer</surname><given-names>ZR</given-names></name><name><surname>Harms</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Detecting High-Order Epistasis in Nonlinear Genotype-Phenotype Maps</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>2017</year><volume>205</volume><fpage>1079</fpage><lpage>1088</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1534/genetics.116.195214</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R55"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schlub</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name><name><surname>Smyth</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name><surname>Grimm</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Mak</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Davenport</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Accurately Measuring Recombination between Closely Related HIV-1 Genomes</article-title><source>PLOS Comput Biol</source><year>2010</year><volume>6</volume><elocation-id>e1000766</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000766</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R56"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sharkey</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Teo</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Greenough</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharova</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Luzuriaga</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Sullivan</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Bucy</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name><surname>Kostrikis</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name><name><surname>Haase</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Veryard</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Davaro</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Persistence of episomal HIV-1 infection intermediates in patients on highly active anti-retroviral therapy</article-title><source>Nat Med</source><year>2000</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>76</fpage><lpage>81</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/71569</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R57"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Starr</surname><given-names>TN</given-names></name><name><surname>Czudnochowski</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Zatta</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>Y-J</given-names></name><name><surname>Addetia</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pinto</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Beltramello</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hernandez</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Greaney</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Marzi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>SARS-CoV-2 RBD antibodies that maximize breadth and resistance to escape</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2021a</year><volume>597</volume><fpage>97</fpage><lpage>102</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41586-021-03807-6</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R58"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Starr</surname><given-names>TN</given-names></name><name><surname>Greaney</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Addetia</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hannon</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name><name><surname>Choudhary</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Dingens</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>JZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bloom</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prospective mapping of viral mutations that escape antibodies used to treat COVID-19</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2021b</year><volume>371</volume><fpage>850</fpage><lpage>854</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.abf9302</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R59"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Starr</surname><given-names>TN</given-names></name><name><surname>Greaney</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hilton</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Ellis</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Crawford</surname><given-names>KHD</given-names></name><name><surname>Dingens</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Navarro</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bowen</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Tortorici</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Walls</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>King</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Deep Mutational Scanning of SARS-CoV-2 Receptor Binding Domain Reveals Constraints on Folding and ACE2 Binding</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2020</year><volume>182</volume><fpage>1295</fpage><lpage>1310</lpage><elocation-id>e20</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2020.08.012</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R60"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Starr</surname><given-names>TN</given-names></name><name><surname>Greaney</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Walls</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Hannon</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name><name><surname>Veesler</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Bloom</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Deep mutational scans for ACE2 binding, RBD expression, and antibody escape in the SARS-CoV-2 Omicron BA.1 and BA.2 receptor-binding domains</article-title><year>2022</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2022.09.20.508745</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R61"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>TJC</given-names></name><name><surname>Mou</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Lei</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Ouyang</surname><given-names>WO</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Andrabi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kieffer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Matreyek</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>High-throughput identification of prefusion-stabilizing mutations in SARS-CoV-2 spike</article-title><year>2022</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2022.09.24.509341</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R62"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Turakhia</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Maio</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name><name><surname>Thornlow</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Gozashti</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Lanfear</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Hinrichs</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Fernandes</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Borges</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Slodkowicz</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Weilguny</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Stability of SARS-CoV-2 phylogenies</article-title><source>PLOS Genet</source><year>2020</year><volume>16</volume><elocation-id>e1009175</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1009175</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R63"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Turakhia</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Thornlow</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Hinrichs</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>De Maio</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Gozashti</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Lanfear</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Haussler</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Corbett-Detig</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ultrafast Sample placement on Existing tRees (UShER) enables real-time phylogenetics for the SARS-CoV-2 pandemic</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><year>2021</year><volume>53</volume><fpage>809</fpage><lpage>816</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41588-021-00862-7</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R64"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van Maele</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>De Rijck</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>De Clercq</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Debyser</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Impact of the Central Polypurine Tract on the Kinetics of Human Immunodeficiency Virus Type 1 Vector Transduction</article-title><source>J Virol</source><year>2003</year><volume>77</volume><fpage>4685</fpage><lpage>4694</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JVI.77.8.4685-4694.2003</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R65"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>VanderPlas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Granger</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name><name><surname>Heer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Moritz</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Wongsuphasawat</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Satyanarayan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lees</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Timofeev</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Welsh</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Sievert</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Altair: Interactive Statistical Visualizations for Python</article-title><source>J Open Source Softw</source><year>2018</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>1057</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21105/joss.01057</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R66"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Iketani</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nair</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohri</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bowen</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Antibody evasion by SARS-CoV-2 Omicron subvariants BA.2.12.1, BA.4 and BA.5</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2022a</year><volume>608</volume><fpage>603</fpage><lpage>608</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41586-022-05053-w</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R67"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Iketani</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Yeh</surname><given-names>AY</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sheng</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antigenic characterization of the SARS-CoV-2 Omicron subvariant BA.2.75</article-title><source>Cell Host Microbe</source><year>2022b</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chom.2022.09.002</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R68"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Westendorf</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Žentelis</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Vaillancourt</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Wiggin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lovett</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>van der Lee</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Hendle</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Pustilnik</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sauder</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>LY-CoV1404 (bebtelovimab) potently neutralizes SARS-CoV-2 variants</article-title><year>2022</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2021.04.30.442182</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R69"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name><name><surname>Thornton</surname><given-names>ZT</given-names></name><name><surname>Hannon</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name><name><surname>DeWitt</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name><name><surname>Radford</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsen</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bloom</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A biophysical model of viral escape from polyclonal antibodies</article-title><year>2022</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2022.09.17.508366</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R70"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Sterling</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Rits-Volloch</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Woosley</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Structural impact on SARS-CoV-2 spike protein by D614G substitution</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2021</year><volume>372</volume><fpage>525</fpage><lpage>530</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.abf2303</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R71"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>J-T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>LY6E Restricts Entry of Human Coronaviruses, Including Currently Pandemic SARS-CoV-2</article-title><source>J Virol</source><year>2020</year><volume>94</volume><fpage>e00562</fpage><lpage>20</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JVI.00562-20</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R72"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>J-T</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bat SARS-Like WIV1 coronavirus uses the ACE2 of multiple animal species as receptor and evades IFITM3 restriction via TMPRSS2 activation of membrane fusion</article-title><source>Emerg Microbes Infect</source><year>2020</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>1567</fpage><lpage>1579</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/22221751.2020.1787797</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R73"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Beutler</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Tse</surname><given-names>LV</given-names></name><name><surname>Martinez</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Schäfer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Anzanello</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Yong</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Dueker</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Broadly neutralizing anti-S2 antibodies protect against all three human betacoronaviruses that cause severe disease</article-title><year>2022</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2022.03.04.479488</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R74"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zufferey</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Dull</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Mandel</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bukovsky</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Quiroz</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Naldini</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Trono</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Self-Inactivating Lentivirus Vector for Safe and Efficient In Vivo Gene Delivery</article-title><source>J Virol</source><year>1998</year><volume>72</volume><fpage>9873</fpage><lpage>9880</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JVI.72.12.9873-9880.1998</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Deep mutational scanning platform for spike</title><p><bold>(A)</bold> Lentivirus backbone used for deep mutational scanning. The backbone contains functional lentiviral 5’ and 3’ long terminal repeat (LTR) regions. The spike gene is under an inducible tet response element 3rd generation (TRE3G) promoter, and there is a 16 nucleotide barcode (BC) downstream of the stop codon. A CMV promoter drives expression of reporter ZsGreen gene that is linked to a puromycin resistance gene (PuR) via a T2A linker. The backbone also contains a woodchuck hepatitis virus posttranscriptional regulatory element (WPRE), Rev response element (RRE), and a central polypurine tract (cPPT). <bold>(B)</bold> Approach for creating genotype-phenotype linked lentivirus libraries. HEK-293T cells are transfected with spike-carrying lentivirus backbone, VSV-G expression plasmid and lentiviral helper plasmids to generate VSV-G-pseudotyped lentiviruses. These viruses are used to transduce reverse tetracycline-controlled transactivator (rtTA) expressing HEK-293T cells at low multiplicity of infection (MOI), and successfully transduced cells are selected using puromycin. Selected cells can be transfected with helper plasmids and a VSV-G expression plasmid to produce VSV-G-pseudotyped viruses carrying all genomes present in the deep mutational library or selected cells can be induced with doxycycline (dox) to express spike and transfected with only the helper plasmids to generate spike-pseudotyped lentiviruses that have a genotype-phenotype link. <bold>(C)</bold> Average number of mutations per barcoded spike in BA.1 libraries. <bold>(D)</bold> Total number of barcoded variants in each BA.1 library. <bold>(E)</bold> The coverage of intended mutations across all BA.1 libraries.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS155739-f001"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Some types of mutations tend to impair spike-mediated pseudovirus infection</title><p>For each barcoded spike variant, we compute a functional score that reflects how well that spike mediates pseudovirus infection relative to the unmutated spike: negative scores indicate impaired infection, positive scores indicate improved infection. The plots show the distribution of functional scores across all variants in each of the three BA.1 libraries for different categories of variants, with each distribution colored by the mean functional score for that variant type.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS155739-f002"/></fig><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>A VSV-G standard enables measurement of absolute neutralization by deep sequencing.</title><p id="P121"><bold>(A)</bold> Neutralization assay demonstrating that BA.1-spike-pseudotyped lentivirus is neutralized by antibody LY-CoV1404, but the VSV-G-pseudotyped neutralization standard is not. <bold>(B)</bold> Use of the VSV-G standard to measure absolute neutralization. Deep mutational scanning libraries are mixed with VSV-G neutralization standard. The virus mixture is incubated with a no-antibody control or increasing antibody concentrations and infected into ACE2-expressing 293T cells. After ~12 hours viral genomes are recovered, barcodes are sequenced, and absolute neutralization of each variant is computed by comparing its barcode counts to those from the VSV-G standard. <bold>(C)</bold> Fraction of barcodes derived from the VSV-G neutralization standard in infections with increasing LY-CoV1404 concentrations. <bold>(D)</bold> BA.1 deep mutational scanning library non-neutralized fractions averaged across variants with different numbers of amino-acid mutations at differentLY-CoV1404 concentrations.Note panels C and D use a symlog scale.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS155739-f003"/></fig><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Antibody LY-CoV1404 escape mapping</title><p><bold>(A)</bold> Correlation of mutation escape scores between technical replicates (BA1 Lib-1.1 and BA1 Lib-1.2) and biological replicates (BA1 Lib-1, BA1 Lib-2, BA1 Lib-3). <bold>(B)</bold> Total escape scores at each site in the BA.1 spike, and a zoomed-in plot showing the key escape sites. Sites of mutations chosen for validation experiments are labeled on the x-axis. <bold>(C)</bold> Heatmap of mutation escape scores at key sites. Residues marked with X are the wild-type amino acids in BA.1. Amino acids not present in our libraries are shown in gray. An interactive heatmap for the entirety of spike is at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://dms-vep.github.io/SARS-CoV-2_Omicron_BA.1_spike_DMS_mAbs/LyCoV-1404_escape_plot.html">https://dms-vep.github.io/SARS-CoV-2_Omicron_BA.1_spike_DMS_mAbs/LyCoV-1404_escape_plot.html</ext-link> <bold>(D)</bold> Surface representation of spike coloured by sum of escape scores at that site. LY-CoV1404 antibody is in yellow. Only the antibody-bound protomer is coloured. PDB IDs 7MMO and 6XM4 were aligned to make this structure. <bold>(E)</bold> Validation pseudovirus neutralization assays of the indicated BA.1 spike mutants against the LY-CoV1404 antibody. <bold>(F)</bold> Correlation between predicted IC50 values from deep mutational scanning (DMS) data versus the IC50 values measured in the validation assays in panel (E). The points are colored as in panel (E). Lower bound indicates that the antibody did not neutralize at the highest concentration tested in the validation neutralization assay. Site numbering in all plots is based on the Wuhan-Hu-1 sequence.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS155739-f004"/></fig><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>Antibody 5-7 escape mapping.</title><p><bold>(A)</bold> Total escape scores for each site in the BA.1 spike and a zoomed-in plot showing the key escape sites. <bold>(B)</bold> Heatmap of mutation escape scores at key sites. Residues marked with X are the wild-type amino acids in BA.1. Amino acids not present in our libraries are shown in gray. An interactive version of this plot for the entirety of spike is at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://dms-vep.github.io/SARS-CoV-2_Omicron_BA.1_spike_DMS_mAbs/NTD_5-7_escape_plot.html">https://dms-vep.github.io/SARS-CoV-2_Omicron_BA.1_spike_DMS_mAbs/NTD_5-7_escape_plot.html</ext-link> <bold>(C)</bold> Surface representation of spike coloured by the sum of escape scores at that site. Antibody 5-7 is shown in yellow in the inset. PDB ID: 7RW2. <bold>(D)</bold> Validation pseudovirus neutralization assays of the indicated BA.1 spike mutants against antibody 5-7. <bold>(E)</bold> Correlation between predicted IC50 values from deep mutational scanning (DMS) data versus the IC50 values measured in the validation assays in (F). Lower bound indicates that the antibody did not neutralize at the highest concentration tested in the validation neutralization assay. Site numbering in all plots is based on the Wuhan-Hu-1 sequence.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS155739-f005"/></fig><fig id="F6" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title>Antibody CC9.104 and CC67.105 escape mapping</title><p><bold>(A-B)</bold> Total escape scores for each site in the BA.1 spike for the CC9.104 (A) and CC67.105 (B) antibodies. <bold>(C-D)</bold> Escape heatmaps for the S2 stem-helix (sites 1146-1163) for CC9.104 (C) and CC67.105 (D) antibodies. Residues marked with X are the wild-type amino acids in BA.1 sequence. Amino acids that are not present in our libraries are shown in gray. Interactive heatmaps for the entirety of spike are at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://dms-vep.github.io/SARS-CoV-2_Omicron_BA.1_spike_DMS_mAbs/CC67.105_escape_plot.html">https://dms-vep.github.io/SARS-CoV-2_Omicron_BA.1_spike_DMS_mAbs/CC67.105_escape_plot.html</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://dms-vep.github.io/SARS-CoV-2_Omicron_BA.1_spike_DMS_mAbs/CC9.104_escape_plot.html">https://dms-vep.github.io/SARS-CoV-2_Omicron_BA.1_spike_DMS_mAbs/CC9.104_escape_plot.html</ext-link> <bold>(E)</bold> Surface representation of spike coloured by the sum of escape scores at that site for CC9.104 (left) and CC67.105 (right) antibodies. Site 1163 is not resolved in the structure. PDB ID: 6XR8. <bold>(F)</bold> Alignment of SARS-CoV-2 and MERS-CoV spikes at sites 1146-1163. <bold>(G)</bold> Validation pseudovirus neutralization assay for CC9.104 (left) and CC67.105 (right) antibodies with BA.1 spike carrying the indicated mutations. <bold>(H)</bold> Correlation between predicted IC50 values from deep mutational scanning (DMS) data versus the IC50 values measured in the validation assays in (G). Lower bound indicates that the antibody did not neutralize at the highest concentration tested in the validation neutralization assay. Site numbering in all plots is based on the Wuhan-Hu-1 sequence.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS155739-f006"/></fig><fig id="F7" position="float"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><title>Functional effects of mutations on spike-mediated pseudovirus infection</title><p><bold>(A)</bold> Distribution of functional effects of mutations in BA.1 deep mutational scanning libraries. Negative values indicate mutations are deleterious for viral entry. The stop codon mutation with a neutral functional effect of ~0 is at the last codon of the spike used in our experiments. <bold>(B)</bold> Heatmap showing functional effects at sites of mutations with beneficial functional effects that were chosen for validation assays in C. An interactive version of this heatmap for the entire spike is at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://dms-vep.github.io/SARS-CoV-2_Omicron_BA.1_spike_DMS_mAbs/muteffects_observed_heatmap.html">https://dms-vep.github.io/SARS-CoV-2_Omicron_BA.1_spike_DMS_mAbs/muteffects_observed_heatmap.html</ext-link> <bold>(C)</bold> Fold change in virus entry titer for spike mutants relative to unmutated spike. There are three points for each mutant, reflecting triplicate measurements. <bold>(D)</bold> Correlation between enrichment of mutations during actual evolution of human SARS-CoV-2 and functional effects from our lentivirus-based deep mutational scanning or previous RBD expression or ACE2 affinity for yeast-based deep mutational scanning (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R60">Starr et al., 2022</xref>), and S2 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R61">Tan et al., 2022</xref>) or NTD (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R50">Ouyang et al., 2022</xref>) expression for mammalian display-based deep mutational scanning. Interactive plots that enable mouseovers and show correlations among experiments are at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://dms-vep.github.io/SARS-CoV-2_Omicron_BA.1_spike_DMS_mAbs/natural_enrichment_vs_dms.html">https://dms-vep.github.io/SARS-CoV-2_Omicron_BA.1_spike_DMS_mAbs/natural_enrichment_vs_dms.html</ext-link></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS155739-f007"/></fig></floats-group></article>