<!DOCTYPE article
 PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" article-type="preprint"><?all-math-mml yes?><?use-mml?><?origin ukpmcpa?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">bioRxiv</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>bioRxiv : the preprint server for biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub"/></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">EMS158923</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2022.12.20.521155</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="archive">PPR586663</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>CircPrime: a web-based platform for design of specific circular RNA primers</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Sharko</surname><given-names>Fedor</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Rbbani</surname><given-names>Golam</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Siriyappagouder</surname><given-names>Prabhugouda</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Raeymaekers</surname><given-names>Joost A.M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Galindo-Villegas</surname><given-names>Jorge</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nedoluzhko</surname><given-names>Artem</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">5</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CR1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fernandes</surname><given-names>Jorge M.O.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CR1">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Research Center of Biotechnology of the Russian Academy of Sciences, Leninsky prospect 33/2, 119071, Moscow, Russia</aff><aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Limited liability company ELGENE, Malaya Kalitnikovskaya 16, 109029, Moscow, Russia</aff><aff id="A3"><label>3</label>National Research Center "Kurchatov Institute", 1st Akademika Kurchatova Square, 123182, Moscow, Russia</aff><aff id="A4"><label>4</label>Nord University, Universitetsalléen 11, 8049, Bodø, Norway</aff><aff id="A5"><label>5</label>European University at Saint Petersburg, 6/1A Gagarinskaya st., 191187, Saint Petersburg, Russia</aff><author-notes><corresp id="CR1">
<label>*</label>Corresponding authors: Dr. Artem Nedoluzhko, Paleogenomics laboratory, European University at Saint Petersburg, Saint Petersburg, Russia. <email>nedoluzhko@gmail.com</email>; Prof. Jorge M. O. Fernandes, Faculty of Biosciences and Aquaculture, Nord University, PB 1490. 8049 Bod, Norway. <email>jorge.m.fernandes@nord.no</email>
</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted"><day>23</day><month>12</month><year>2022</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="preprint"><day>20</day><month>12</month><year>2022</year></pub-date><permissions><ali:free_to_read/><license><ali:license_ref>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is licensed under a <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">CC BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec id="S1"><title>Background</title><p id="P1">Circular RNAs (circRNAs) are covalently closed-loop RNAs with critical regulatory roles in cells. The tenth of thousands of circRNAs have been unveiled due to the recent advances in high throughput RNA sequencing technologies and bioinformatic tools development. At the same time, polymerase chain reaction (PCR) cross-validation for circRNAs predicted by bioinformatic tools remains an essential part of any circRNA study before publication.</p></sec><sec id="S2"><title>Results</title><p id="P2">Here, we present the CircPrime web-based platform, providing a user-friendly solution for DNA primer design and thermocycling conditions for circRNA identification with routine PCR methods.</p></sec><sec id="S3"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="P3">User-friendly CircPrime web platform (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://circprime.elgene.net/">http://circprime.elgene.net/</ext-link>) works with outputs of the most popular bioinformatic predictors of circRNAs to design specific circular RNA primers. CircPrime works with circRNA coordinates and any reference genome from the National Center for Biotechnology Information database (NCBI).</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Circular RNAs</kwd><kwd>RNA-sequencing</kwd><kwd>circRNAs</kwd><kwd>primer design</kwd><kwd>RT-PCR</kwd><kwd>qPCR</kwd><kwd>validation</kwd><kwd>PCR</kwd><kwd>web platform</kwd><kwd>prediction</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="S4" sec-type="intro"><title>Background</title><p id="P4">In recent years, there is a marked increase in the number of circular RNA (circRNA)-related studies (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>). CircRNAs have become a main focus of non-coding RNA biology research because they affect many genetic regulatory networks. These covalently closed-loop RNA molecules are an integral part of the cell regulome and interact with RNA-binding proteins. They can modulate microRNA expression and indirectly affect gene expression. In addition, some of them contain exon parts and can thus translate into proteins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">Kristensen, et al., 2019</xref>).</p><p id="P5">Modern sequencing technologies make it now possible to identify hundreds of circRNAs that may be used as biomarkers and therapeutic targets in different applied researches (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">Nedoluzhko, et al., 2020;</xref> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">Rbbani, et al., 2021</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">Verduci, et al., 2021</xref>). However, <italic>in silico</italic> prediction of circRNAs leads to numerous false-positives (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">Hansen, et al., 2016</xref>), as well as inconsistencies among different bioinformatic pipelines (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">Nedoluzhko, et al., 2020</xref>). As a result, cross-checking and validation of circRNAs is an essential component of any circRNA study (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">Das, et al., 2022</xref>).</p><p id="P6">Reverse transcription PCR (RT-PCR) and quantitative PCR (qPCR) are considered the gold standard for identification of circRNA expression in cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">Das, et al., 2022</xref>). At the same time, primer design for the circRNAs validation differs from the design for the their linear host genes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">Vromman, et al., 2022</xref>). To date, only a few tools have been published that allow the development of primers for validation of circRNAs. At the same time, they require additional software to be installed in different operating systems – CircPrimer (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">Zhong, et al., 2018</xref>), CircPrimer2.0 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">Zhong and Feng, 2022</xref>) and circtools (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">Jakobi, et al., 2019</xref>), or work as a web tool with already known circRNAs of model organisms, namely human (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">Dudekula, et al., 2016</xref>) or novel circRNAs for limited number of animal species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">Vromman, et al., 2022</xref>). Here, to overcome these previous constraints and facilitate the circRNA studies by presenting the user-friendly CircPrime web platform (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://circprime.elgene.net/">http://circprime.elgene.net/</ext-link>), which works with outputs of the most popular bioinformatic predictors of circRNAs, such as CIRI2 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">Gao, et al., 2018</xref>), KNIFE (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">Szabo, et al., 2015</xref>), CIRCexplorer2 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">Zhang, et al., 2016</xref>), find_circ (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">Memczak, et al., 2013</xref>), circRNA_finder (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">Westholm, et al., 2014</xref>), DCC (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">Cheng, et al., 2016</xref>), mapsplice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">Wang, et al., 2010</xref>) and common BED files. Importantly, CircPrime is also suitable for non-model organisms that have reference genome assemblies in the National Center for Biotechnology Information database (NCBI).</p></sec><sec id="S5"><title>Implementation</title><p id="P7">To date, there are several methods for PCR-based identification of different circRNAs types (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2A</xref>). One of them is rolling circle amplification (RCA). This method avoids deep RNA sequencing and bioinformatic analysis, but is only capable of identifying a limited number of circRNA types (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">Boss and Arenz, 2020</xref>). The other most commonly used method assumes a longer workflow, which comprises circRNA enrichment, circRNA-library construction, deep sequencing, circRNA prediction, and finally RT-PCR/qPCR validation of bioinformatically predicted circRNAs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">Shi, et al., 2022</xref>). PCR primers for this validation are designed to target the circRNA fragment overlapping a junction (back-splice) site of a specific circRNA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2A</xref>).</p><p id="P8">We developed CircPrime, as a streamlined pipeline in Python 3 and web platform, which makes use of output files from the most popular circRNAs <italic>in silico</italic> predictors. The CircPrime script implemented into the web platform currently contains the four main modules shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2B</xref> and works under the parameters presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>.</p><p id="P9">After the first step, which includes BED file uploading, CircPrime generates FASTA files using circRNA coordinates and reference genome from the NCBI. Then CircPrime extracts junction regions from the uploaded BED file and develops primer sets with the recommended melting temperature (Tm) for each circRNA in the list (up to 100) using Primer3 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2B</xref>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">Koressaar and Remm, 2007;</xref> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">Untergasser, et al., 2012</xref>). An example of the CircPrime output is presented as <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary Dataset 2</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="S6" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><p id="P10">The novel CircPrime web-based platform was evaluated to design primer sets for RT-PCR validation of circRNA expression in the muscle transcriptome of a teleost, the Nile tilapia (<italic>Oreochromis niloticus</italic>). Successfully, we showed that CircPrime significantly simplifies the primer design process for bioinformatically predicted circRNAs without the need to upload a reference genome of the organism studied.</p><p id="P11">In this study, we successfully applied circRNAs list predicted by CIRI2 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">Gao, et al., 2018</xref>) and CircPrime web platform to design circRNA primer pairs and validate their RT-PCR efficiency using total RNA extract from the Nile tilapia skeletal muscle tissue (see details in Supplementary Material). We expect that this bioinformatic tool will play a relevant role on varied studies describing circRNAs expression and their possible functionality. CircPrime is applicable both on model and non-model organisms, including even those with a poor genome assembly and annotation.</p></sec><sec id="S7" sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="P12">Herein, we present a Circprime web platform (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://circprime.elgene.net/">http://circprime.elgene.net/</ext-link>) for PCR primer design and PCR conditions development for validation of circRNAs predicted based on RNA-sequencing data using different types of bioinformatics tools. We expect that this web tool will be convenient for users who intend to analyze the expression of circRNAs in animal and plant transcriptomes.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="SM"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1"><label>Supplementary Dataset 1</label><media xlink:href="EMS158923-supplement-Supplementary_Dataset_1.xlsx" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.spreadsheetml.sheet" id="d36aAdEbB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD2"><label>Supplementary Dataset 2</label><media xlink:href="EMS158923-supplement-Supplementary_Dataset_2.txt" mimetype="text" mime-subtype="plain; charset=utf-8" id="d36aAdEcB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD3"><label>Supplementary Material</label><media xlink:href="EMS158923-supplement-Supplementary_Material.docx" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document" id="d36aAdEdB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack id="S8"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>Not applicable</p><sec id="S9"><title>Funding</title><p>This study has received funding from the European Research Council (ERC) under the European Union’s Horizon 2020 research and innovation programme (grant agreement no 683210) and from the Research Council of Norway under the Toppforsk programme (grant agreement no 250548/F20). Fedor Sharko was partly supported by the state task of the Federal Research Center of Biotechnology RAS.</p></sec></ack><sec id="S10" sec-type="data-availability"><title>Availability and requirements</title><p id="P13">Project name: CircPrime</p><p id="P14">Project home page: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://circprime.elgene.net/">http://circprime.elgene.net/</ext-link></p><p id="P15">Operating system(s): Platform independent</p><p id="P16">Programming language: Python 3.10</p><p id="P17">Other requirements: None</p><p id="P18">License: GNU GPL Version 3</p></sec><sec id="S11" sec-type="data-availability"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p id="P19">The user-friendly CircPrime tool for circular RNA primer development is written in Python 3 and implemented on a web-based platform. It is freely available online at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://circprime.elgene.net/">http://circprime.elgene.net/</ext-link>. The RNA-seq dataset generated and analysed during the current study is available in the GEO (NCBI) repository, under the accession number PRJNA826285</p></sec><glossary><title>List of abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term><italic>PCR</italic></term><def><p>Polymerase chain reaction</p></def></def-item><def-item><term><italic>CircRNA</italic></term><def><p>Circular RNA</p></def></def-item><def-item><term><italic>RT-PCR</italic></term><def><p>Reverse transcription PCR</p></def></def-item><def-item><term><italic>qPCR</italic></term><def><p>Quantitative PCR</p></def></def-item><def-item><term><italic>NCBI</italic></term><def><p>National Center for Biotechnology Information database</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RCA</term><def><p>Rolling circle amplification</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><fn-group><title>Declarations</title><fn id="FN1"><p id="P20">Any restrictions to use by non-academics: no license needed</p></fn><fn id="FN2"><p id="P21">Ethics approval and consent to participate: This research was approved by the Nord University (Bodø, Norway) ethical committee. The experimental procedures involving animals were performed in accordance with the regulation and instructions of the Norwegian Animal Research Authority (FOTS ID 1042). All procedures involving animals were conducted according to the EU Directive 2010/63 on the use of animals for scientific purposes.</p></fn><fn id="FN3"><p id="P22">Consent for publication: Not applicable</p></fn><fn id="FN4" fn-type="conflict"><p id="P23">Competing interests: The authors declare there are no competing interests.</p></fn><fn id="FN5" fn-type="con"><p id="P24">Author's contributions: F.S. – wrote tool script and implemented it on a web-based platform, wrote and approved the final draft; G.R. – performed the experiments, prepared figures and/or tables, and approved the final draft; P.S. - performed the experiments, prepared figures and/or tables, and approved the final draft; J.R. – conceived and designed the experiments and approved the final draft; J.G. – conceived and designed the experiments and approved the final draft; A.N. – conceived and designed the experiments, performed the experiments, analyzed the data, prepared figures and/or tables, authored or reviewed drafts of the paper, and approved the final draft. J.M.O.F. – conceived and designed the experiments, authored or reviewed drafts of the paper, approved the final draft, administrated project and acquisited funding.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><ref id="R1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boss</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Arenz</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A Fast and Easy Method for Specific Detection of Circular RNA by Rolling-Circle Amplification</article-title><source>Chembiochem</source><year>2020</year><volume>21</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>793</fpage><lpage>796</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7154740</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31584239</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cbic.201900514</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Metge</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Dieterich</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Specific identification and quantification of circular RNAs from sequencing data</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2016</year><volume>32</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>1094</fpage><lpage>1096</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26556385</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Das</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Das</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Panda</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Validation of Circular RNAs by PCR</chapter-title><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Basu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><source>PCR Primer Design</source><publisher-name>Springer US</publisher-name><publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc><year>2022</year><fpage>103</fpage><lpage>114</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dudekula</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>CircInteractome: A web tool for exploring circular RNAs and their interacting proteins and microRNAs</article-title><source>RNA Biol</source><year>2016</year><volume>13</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>34</fpage><lpage>42</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4829301</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26669964</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/15476286.2015.1128065</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Circular RNA identification based on multiple seed matching</article-title><source>Brief Bioinform</source><year>2018</year><volume>19</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>803</fpage><lpage>810</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28334140</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>TB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Comparison of circular RNA prediction tools</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2016</year><volume>44</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>e58</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4824091</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26657634</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkv1458</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jakobi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Uvarovskii</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Dieterich</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>circtools-a one-stop software solution for circular RNA research</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2019</year><volume>35</volume><issue>13</issue><fpage>2326</fpage><lpage>2328</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6596886</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30462173</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/bty948</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koressaar</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Remm</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Enhancements and modifications of primer design program Primer3</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2007</year><volume>23</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>1289</fpage><lpage>1291</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17379693</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kristensen</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The biogenesis, biology and characterization of circular RNAs</article-title><source>Nat Rev Genet</source><year>2019</year><volume>20</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>675</fpage><lpage>691</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31395983</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Memczak</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Circular RNAs are a large class of animal RNAs with regulatory potency</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2013</year><volume>495</volume><issue>7441</issue><fpage>333</fpage><lpage>338</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23446348</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nedoluzhko</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The Biomarker and Therapeutic Potential of Circular Rnas in Schizophrenia</article-title><source>Cells</source><year>2020</year><volume>9</volume><issue>10</issue><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7601372</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33020462</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/cells9102238</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nedoluzhko</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>CircParser: a novel streamlined pipeline for circular RNA structure and host gene prediction in non-model organisms</article-title><source>PeerJ</source><year>2020</year><volume>8</volume><elocation-id>e8757</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7081776</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32211235</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.8757</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rbbani</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Function of Circular RNAs in Fish and Their Potential Application as Biomarkers</article-title><source>Int J Mol Sci</source><year>2021</year><volume>22</volume><issue>13</issue><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8268770</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34281172</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms22137119</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Comparative analysis of circular RNA enrichment methods</article-title><source>RNA Biol</source><year>2022</year><volume>19</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>55</fpage><lpage>67</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8786342</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34895057</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/15476286.2021.2012632</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Szabo</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Statistically based splicing detection reveals neural enrichment and tissue-specific induction of circular RNA during human fetal development</article-title><source>Genome Biology</source><year>2015</year><volume>16</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>126</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4506483</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26076956</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13059-015-0690-5</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Untergasser</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Primer3--new capabilities and interfaces</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2012</year><volume>40</volume><issue>15</issue><fpage>e115</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3424584</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22730293</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gks596</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Verduci</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>CircRNAs: role in human diseases and potential use as biomarkers</article-title><source>Cell Death &amp; Disease</source><year>2021</year><volume>12</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>468</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8113373</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33976116</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41419-021-03743-3</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vromman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>CIRCprimerXL: Convenient and High-Throughput PCR Primer Design for Circular RNA Quantification</article-title><source>Front Bioinform</source><year>2022</year><volume>2</volume><elocation-id>834655</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9580850</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36304334</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fbinf.2022.834655</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>MapSplice: accurate mapping of RNA-seq reads for splice junction discovery</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2010</year><volume>38</volume><issue>18</issue><fpage>e178</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2952873</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20802226</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkq622</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Westholm</surname><given-names>JO</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genome-wide analysis of drosophila circular RNAs reveals their structural and sequence properties and age-dependent neural accumulation</article-title><source>Cell Rep</source><year>2014</year><volume>9</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>1966</fpage><lpage>1980</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4279448</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25544350</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.celrep.2014.10.062</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>XO</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Diverse alternative back-splicing and alternative splicing landscape of circular RNAs</article-title><source>Genome Res</source><year>2016</year><volume>26</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>1277</fpage><lpage>1287</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5052039</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27365365</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gr.202895.115</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>CircPrimer 2.0: a software for annotating circRNAs and predicting translation potential of circRNAs</article-title><source>BMC Bioinformatics</source><year>2022</year><volume>23</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>215</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9169404</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35668371</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12859-022-04705-y</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>CircPrimer: a software for annotating circRNAs and determining the specificity of circRNA primers</article-title><source>BMC Bioinformatics</source><year>2018</year><volume>19</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>292</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6090782</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30075703</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12859-018-2304-1</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Exponential increase in the number of publications mentioning “circRNA” in their title.</title><p>X-axis shows years from 2014 until 2021; Y-axis represents the number of publications. Source: Web of Science, accessed 6 October 2022.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS158923-f001"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>An overview of the CircPrime pipeline.</title><p>(A) Types of possible variants for primer design for circular RNA validation. (B) The main steps of CircPrime pipeline and tools combined in it.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS158923-f002"/></fig><table-wrap id="T1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Required and default parameters for CircPrime usage.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="rows"><thead><tr><th align="center" valign="top">CircPrime parameter</th><th align="center" valign="top">Parameter description</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center" valign="top">CircRNA BED file</td><td align="center" valign="top">Required</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top">Shift range left</td><td align="center" valign="top">Default 150 nucleotides</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top">Shift range right</td><td align="center" valign="top">Default 150 nucleotides</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top">Optimum length of a primer</td><td align="center" valign="top">Default 19 nucleotides</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top">Minimum acceptable length of a primer</td><td align="center" valign="top">Default 15 nucleotides</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top">Maximum acceptable length of a primer</td><td align="center" valign="top">Default 20 nucleotides</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top">PCR product size</td><td align="center" valign="top">Default 150-200 nucleotides</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top">Optimum melting temperature for a primer</td><td align="center" valign="top">in Celsius</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top">Minimum acceptable melting temperature for a primer</td><td align="center" valign="top">in Celsius</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top">Maximum acceptable melting temperature for a primer</td><td align="center" valign="top">in Celsius</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top">Number of primer sets</td><td align="center" valign="top">Default 4 sets</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></floats-group></article>