<!DOCTYPE article
 PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" article-type="preprint"><?all-math-mml yes?><?use-mml?><?origin ukpmcpa?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">bioRxiv</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>bioRxiv : the preprint server for biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub"/></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">EMS145419</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2021.11.01.466724</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="archive">PPR415046</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Multiplexed Single-Molecule Epigenetic Analysis of Plasma-Isolated Nucleosomes for Cancer Diagnostics</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Fedyuk</surname><given-names>Vadim</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Erez</surname><given-names>Nir</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Furth</surname><given-names>Noa</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Beresh</surname><given-names>Olga</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Andreishcheva</surname><given-names>Ekaterina</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shinde</surname><given-names>Abhijeet</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>Daniel</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zakai</surname><given-names>Barak Bar</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mavor</surname><given-names>Yael</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Peretz</surname><given-names>Tamar</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hubert</surname><given-names>Ayala</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>Jonathan E</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Salah</surname><given-names>Azzam</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Temper</surname><given-names>Mark</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Grinshpun</surname><given-names>Albert</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Maoz</surname><given-names>Myriam</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zick</surname><given-names>Aviad</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ron</surname><given-names>Guy</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shema</surname><given-names>Efrat</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CR1">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Department of Biological Regulation, Weizmann Institute of Science, Rehovot 76100, Israel</aff><aff id="A2"><label>2</label>SeqLL Inc., Woburn, MA 01801, USA</aff><aff id="A3"><label>3</label>Department of Surgery A, Kaplan Medical Center, Rehovot, Israel</aff><aff id="A4"><label>4</label>Sharett Institute of Oncology, Hebrew University - Hadassah Medical Center, Jerusalem, Israel</aff><aff id="A5"><label>5</label>Racah Institute of Physics, Hebrew University, Jerusalem 91904, Israel</aff><author-notes><corresp id="CR1">
<label>*</label>Corresponding author: <email>Efrat.shema@weizmann.ac.il</email>.</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted"><day>27</day><month>05</month><year>2022</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="preprint"><day>26</day><month>05</month><year>2022</year></pub-date><permissions><ali:free_to_read/><license><ali:license_ref>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is licensed under a <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">CC BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p id="P1">The analysis of cell-free DNA (cfDNA) in plasma represents a rapidly advancing field in medicine, providing information on pathological processes in the body. Blood cfDNA is in the form of nucleosomes, which maintain their tissue- and cancer-specific epigenetic state. We developed EPINUC, a single-molecule multi-parametric assay to comprehensively profile the <underline>E</underline>pigenetics of <underline>P</underline>lasma <underline>I</underline>solated <underline>Nuc</underline>leosomes, DNA methylation and cancer-specific protein biomarkers. Our system allows high-resolution detection of six active and repressive histone modifications, their ratios and combinatorial patterns, on millions of individual nucleosomes by single-molecule imaging. In addition, it provides sensitive and quantitative data on plasma proteins, including detection of non-secreted tumor-specific proteins such as mutant p53. Applying this analysis to a cohort of plasma samples detected colorectal cancer at high accuracy and sensitivity, even at early stages. Finally, combining EPINUC with direct single-molecule DNA sequencing revealed the tissue-of-origin of colorectal, pancreatic, lung and breast tumors. EPINUC provides multi-layered clinical-relevant information from limited liquid biopsy material, establishing a novel approach for cancer diagnostics.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><p id="P2">Non-invasive liquid biopsy methods, based on the analysis of cfDNA, potentiate a new generation of diagnostic approaches. The cfDNA that circulates in the plasma and serum of healthy individuals originates predominantly from death of normal blood cells<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref></sup>. In cancer patients, however, a fraction of cfDNA is tumor-derived, termed circulating tumor DNA (ctDNA). ctDNA-based sequence analysis has been shown to reveal tumor-specific genetic alterations and provide the means for non-invasive molecular profiling of tumors<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">3</xref></sup>. Despite encouraging data, these approaches are limited, as they require genetic differences (i.e. mutations) in order to distinguish between the normal and tumor DNA. Liquid biopsy approaches based on analysis of non-genetic features have emerged recently, most prominently methodologies that utilize tissue- and cancer-specific DNA methylation, as well as differential fragmentation patterns of cfDNA<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">8</xref></sup>.</p><p id="P3">cfDNA in the plasma appears predominantly in the form of nucleosomes (cfNucleosomes), the basic unit of chromatin that consists of ~150 base pairs of DNA wrapped around the octamer of core histone proteins. Histones are extensively modified by covalent attachment of various chemical groups, forming combinatorial epigenetic patterns that are unique to each tissue, and provide information on gene expression and regulatory elements within cells<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref></sup>. There is evidence that cfNucleosomes retain at least some of their epigenetic modifications, and a recent study applied Chromatin Immunoprecipitation and sequencing (ChIP-seq) to identify certain marks<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref></sup>. Moreover, deep sequencing of cfDNA revealed nucleosome occupancy patterns correlating with the tissue of origin<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref></sup>. While these approaches provide the first glimpse into the rich epigenetic information present in plasma that has so far remained mostly inaccessible, they have major limitations. Mainly, they require large amounts of input material, have a limited dynamic range (ChIP-seq), or are costly and require deep sequencing. Most importantly, these methodologies have limited output and sensitivity, as they usually measure a single layer of information (i.e. DNA methylation OR a single histone modification OR nucleosome occupancy, etc.). Thus, high-resolution approaches that integrate information from multiple parameters spanning different types of analytes are required.</p><p id="P4">Colorectal Cancer (CRC) is the third most common cancer worldwide, causing approximately 700,000 deaths every year<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref></sup>. Early metastatic seeding has been recently demonstrated in CRC<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">20</xref></sup>, underlining the necessity to develop better diagnostic tools to improve patient outcome. In this study, we developed a single-molecule-based liquid biopsy approach, to analyze multiple parameters from less than 1 ml of plasma sample and demonstrated its value for CRC diagnosis. We coined the technology “EPINUC” for Epigenetics of Plasma Isolated Nucleosomes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1a</xref>). The technology builds on our recent development of a single-molecule system to image combinatorial histone modifications by Total Internal Reflection (TIRF) microscopy<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">21</xref></sup>. TIRF provides a powerful means for detecting single fluorescent molecules that are within ~100 nm of a solid surface; a light source creates an evanescent wave that decays exponentially in intensity, thus eliminating background fluorescence from outside the focal plane. To capture nucleosomes from plasma, we developed high-efficiency enzymatic reactions to fluorescently tag and polyadenylate nucleosomes (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD5">Supplementary Fig.1a-e</xref>, <xref ref-type="sec" rid="S1">Methods</xref>). Tailed, intact nucleosomes were then immobilized on a PEGylated surface via hybridization, and the status of their post-translational modifications (PTMs) was recorded by TIRF imaging with fluorescently tagged antibodies, verifying minimal spectral overlap (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1b</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD5">Supplementary Fig. 1f,g</xref>). Binding and dissociation of antibodies to target PTMs was imaged over 90 minutes, leveraging the TIRF narrow excitation range. Integration of binding events assured maximal detection of modified histones (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1c</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD5">Supplementary Fig. 2a</xref>).</p><p id="P5">EPINUC relies on direct counting of single-molecules in a population, yielding data amenable to absolute quantification and comparisons between samples. Each antibody was verified for specificity and linearity of binding with a panel of recombinant modified nucleosomes, yielding six antibodies that passed the quality control criteria (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD5">Supplementary Fig. 2b-d</xref>). These antibodies target the tri-methylations on histone H3 lysine 9 (H3K9me3) and lysine 27 (H3K27me3), associated with gene silencing and heterochromatin, as well as antibodies targeting marks associated with active transcription: tri-methylation of histone H3 on lysine 4 (H3K4me3) and lysine 36 (H3K36me3), and acetylation on lysine 9 (H3K9ac). In addition, our panel includes an antibody targeting mono-methylation of histone H3 on lysine 4 (H3K4me1), a mark associated with enhancers<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">23</xref></sup>.</p><p id="P6">Nucleosomes from each plasma sample were tagged with Cy3 (green), and imaged with three pairwise combinations of antibodies labeled with AF488 (cyan) or AF647 (red). Thus, we obtained multi-parametric data for six histone PTMs, comprising of the percentage of modified nucleosomes in each sample, the ratio between various histone modifications, and the percentage of nucleosomes that harbor a combinatorial pattern of two modifications (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1d-f</xref>). Repeated measurements of the same plasma samples produced highly similar results, attesting to the quantitative nature of this technology (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD5">Supplementary Fig.3</xref>). To the best of our knowledge, EPINUC is the only technology that enables counting of multiple histone PTMs, as well as combinatorially-modified nucleosomes, at a single-molecule precision, from low volume plasma sample (&lt;1ml).</p><p id="P7">To extend the number of analytes measured beyond histone PTMs, we exploited the single-molecule system for quantification of protein biomarkers. We modulated surface chemistry to contain PEG-streptavidin, allowing anchoring of biotin-conjugated antibodies that target plasma proteins. Following incubation with plasma, bound proteins are imaged by fluorescent detection antibodies. Multiplexed simultaneous detection of three biomarkers is achieved through the use of distinct fluorophores (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2a</xref>). We imaged two proteins known to increase in plasma of CRC patients: Carcinoembryonic antigen (CEA), a canonical biomarker measured routinely by clinicians<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref></sup>, and Tissue inhibitor of metalloproteinase-1 (TIMP-1), a glycoprotein reported to have diagnostic value in screening for CRC<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">25</xref></sup>. In addition, we measured the mammalian sterile 20-like kinase 1 (MST1), an inhibitor of cell proliferation that decreases in CRC patients<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">26</xref></sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2b</xref>). We verified linear detection and specificity using cell-culture systems and knockdown experiments (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2c,d</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD5">Supplementary Fig. 4</xref>).</p><p id="P8">Counting of single molecules confers high sensitivity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27">27</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">28</xref></sup>, thus we explored whether we could also quantify non-secreted tumor-specific plasma proteins that are undetectable by conventional technologies. We focused on the tumor suppressor p53, which is frequently mutated in CRC; p53 mutations lead to its stabilization and accumulation in tumor cells<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">29</xref></sup>. We captured p53 from plasma and applied simultaneous detection with two distinct antibodies; an antibody targeting both the wild type and mutant forms of p53, or another antibody specifically targeting the mutant conformation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2e</xref>). Time-lapse imaging enabled the accumulation of p53 signal, overcoming the transient binding dynamics of the detection antibodies (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2f</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD5">Supplementary Fig. 4d</xref>). Indeed, we observed higher levels of total and mutant p53 in the plasma of CRC patients with confirmed p53 mutations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2g</xref>), establishing our system’s capabilities in specific detection of mutant proteins that originate directly from tumor cells.</p><p id="P9">DNA methylation is often deregulated in cancer, and specifically in colorectal cancer<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">30</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31">31</xref></sup>. We therefore aimed to combine our analysis with quantitative single-molecule detection of DNA methylation levels in plasma. We incubated Methyl-CpG-binding domain protein 2 (MBD2-biotin), which specifically binds to methylated DNA<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32">32</xref></sup>, with fluorescently labeled plasma cfDNA. Bound complexes were anchored to the surface and imaged (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2h</xref>). Of note, bound DNA molecules may harbor one or more methylation sites. Specificity and sensitivity were validated using synthetic methylated/unmethylated DNA, as well as DNA from cells treated with the DNA methyl transferase (DNMT) inhibitor 5-Aza-2’-deoxycytidine (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2i</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD5">Supplementary Fig. 5a-c</xref>). Finally, we verified detection of cfDNA methylation levels from plasma of CRC and healthy subjects (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2j</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD5">Supplementary Fig. 5d</xref>).</p><p id="P10">We applied EPINUC to generate high-dimensional data, comprising of the three layers of information; histone PTMs, DNA methylation and protein biomarkers, from 33 plasma samples of healthy subjects and 46 samples taken from 40 late stage CRC patients (stages III-IV; six patients were sampled twice at different times during cancer progression and treatment). CRC samples were obtained from patients prior to surgery or from patients that underwent surgical resection procedure and chemotherapy. In accordance with its use in clinical diagnostics<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref></sup>, single-molecule counting of CEA showed higher levels in CRC patients (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3a</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD5">Supplementary Fig. 6a,b</xref>), and a reduction in patients after resection. Interestingly, high CEA levels were also observed in a few healthy individuals, generating a ‘false positive’ signal (for example, samples 6, 9 and 19, marked by * in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD5">Supplementary Fig. 6a</xref>). Simultaneous probing of MST1, an anti-proliferative factor, allowed us to derive the CEA/MST1 ratio, resulting in better classification of samples and highlighting an advantage of combinatorial biomarker detection (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3b,c</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD5">Supplementary Fig. 6a</xref>). Of note, plasma from CRC patients following resection exhibited altered CEA/MST1 ratio compared to non-resected patients, showing higher similarity to healthy individuals (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3a,b</xref>). This demonstrates the potential applicability of our technology to monitor treatment, while underlying the need to collect additional information from each sample to allow correct sample classification.</p><p id="P11">EPINUC also provides quantitative measurements of the total number of cfNucleosomes, six histone PTMs, their pairwise combinations and ratios per plasma sample (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). In agreement with the literature, CRC patients had higher cfNucleosomes in their plasma compared to healthy controls<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33">33</xref></sup> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD5">Supplementary Fig. 6c</xref>). While most epigenetic parameters did not change, several showed significant differences: CRC patients had higher levels of H3K27me3-, H3K9me3-, H3K9ac- and H3K4me1-modified nucleosomes, and higher ratio of H3K9ac to H3K4me1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3d</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD5">Supplementary Fig. 6c,d</xref>). Interestingly, the combinatorial pattern of H3K9me3+H3K36me3-modified nucleosomes decreased in CRC, concomitant with an increase in ‘bivalent’ nucleosomes marked by H3K4me3+H3K27me3 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3d</xref>). As bivalent chromatin is strongly implicated in many types of cancers<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34">34</xref></sup>, this result further confirms the diagnostic value of single-molecule quantification of combinatorial histone marks. DNA methylation was reduced in CRC samples, in agreement with previous studies<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35">35</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36">36</xref></sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3e</xref>).</p><p id="P12">The identification of epigenetic and biomarkers alterations in late stage CRC motivated us to apply EPINUC to 17 plasma samples from individuals diagnosed with early stage CRC (stages I,II). As in the later stage, the levels of DNA methylation, CEA and CEA/MST1 ratio significantly differed in early stage cancer patients versus healthy (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3f</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD5">Supplementary Fig. 6e</xref>). Interestingly, TIMP1, whose levels did not alter between our cohort of healthy an late stage CRC, was elevated at the early stage (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD5">Supplementary Fig. 6e,f</xref>). This might be due to chemotherapy treatment administrated to most of the late stage CRC patients, which was reported to downregulate TIMP1 levels<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37">37</xref></sup>. On the contrary, early stage CRC patients did not receive chemotherapy, and indeed showed elevated TIMP1, rendering it a significant biomarker only for early stage. Of note, plasma from stages I,II CRC patients also showed elevated levels of H3K27me3- and H3K9me3-modified nucleosomes, as seen in the late stage (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3f</xref>). Interestingly, we did not observe increased levels of cfNucleosomes in early stage CRC, likely due to the low tumor burden (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD5">Supplementary Fig. 6e</xref>). While the levels of H3K9ac- and H3K4me1-modified nucleosomes did not differ significantly from the healthy group, the combinatorial pattern of H3K4me1 and H3K9ac was lower in early CRC patients compared to healthy (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3f</xref>). These results indicate various epigenetic alterations already occurring at early stage CRC.</p><p id="P13">As proof-of-concept that EPINUC could be generalized and applied to study diverse types of cancers, we obtained and analyzed 10 plasma samples from patients diagnosed with pancreatic ductal adenocarcinoma (PDAC), a devastating disease with poor prognosis and rising incidence<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38">38</xref></sup>. The data revealed multiple epigenetic parameters, as well as protein biomarkers, which differ significantly from healthy subjects (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD5">Supplementary Fig. 7a</xref>). Interestingly, PDAC patients showed very high levels of H3K4me3- and H3K27me3-modified nucleosomes, compared to both groups of healthy and CRC patients (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD5">Supplementary Fig. 7a,b</xref>). Moreover, the percentage of bivalent nucleosomes marked by both of these modifications was surprisingly high, clearly differentiating these samples from plasmas obtained from CRC patients. Finally, as opposed to CRC, in PDAC we did not observe a significant change in H3K9me3-modified nucleosomes. Additional parameters that were altered in CRC compared to healthy, such as the combination of H3K9me3+H3K36me3 and the ratio of H3K9ac to H3K4me1, were not affected in patients diagnosed with PDAC (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD5">Supplementary Fig. 7c</xref>). Overall, while the number of samples analyzed is limited, the data suggests cancer-type specific alterations to various epigenetic parameters. Finally, we calculated the predictive score of each parameter alone to discriminate between the healthy, the distinct groups of CRC patients, and PDAC patients (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3g</xref>, <xref ref-type="sec" rid="S1">Methods</xref>). These results highlight EPINUC’s capabilities in providing multiplexed single-molecule measurements of protein biomarkers, epigenetic modifications and their combinations for cancer diagnostics.</p><p id="P14">To visualize the distribution of samples across the most significant and predictive parameters, we performed Principal Component Analysis (PCA). The PCA showed spatial separation between the groups, with the early stage CRC samples positioned in between the healthy and the late-stage CRC, potentially reflecting a transition stage (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3h</xref>). While samples from healthy individuals formed a tight cluster, the cancer samples showed greater variability, likely due to inherent heterogeneity between tumors. CRC patients who underwent resection also exhibited a high heterogeneity; interestingly, patients who received both primary tumor resection and metastectomy were positioned closer to the healthy group (samples 4118, 4211, 4050 and 4493). Strikingly, the PDAC samples clustered separately from the CRC samples, pointing to the power of EPINUC in differentiating cancer types solely based on multiplexed measurements of epigenetic parameters.</p><p id="P15">A few CRC patients in our cohort were sampled twice along the course of the study, allowing us to examine the projection of samples taken from the same individual in the PCA plot (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3h</xref>, marked in *, #, and †). Sample 4090 was collected two months following sample 4075 from a CRC patient who underwent tumor resection and extensive treatments. Unfortunately, her condition did not improve and she passed away a month later; indeed the later sample projects further from healthy on both principle components. A similar trend can be seen for samples 3488 and 4059, taken 6.5 months apart. These results highlight the potential of EPINUC to monitor patients’ positive or negative response to treatment, and the power of collecting multiple layers of information from each sample.</p><p id="P16">Finally, in order to integrate all measurements and fine-tune the discrimination between healthy and CRC samples, we employed machine-learning classification (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4a</xref>, <xref ref-type="sec" rid="S1">Methods</xref>). The best predictive model displayed high diagnostic potential by generating a 0.96 AUC [95% confidence interval (CI) 0.945 - 0.975], and sensitivity of 92% [95% CI 89.3 − 94.7] at 85% specificity [95% CI 80.2 − 89.8] and 92% precision [95% CI 89.7 − 94.3], outperforming predictive models relying solely on protein biomarkers, protein biomarkers coupled with DNA methylation, or protein biomarkers coupled with histone PTMs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4a</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD5">Supplementary Fig. 8a</xref>). Intriguingly, this high discrimination power is achieved without including DNA sequencing. This is mainly due to the combination of multiple parameters spanning various cellular pathways into a single assay, and the high accuracy of the single-molecule technology that allows for digital counting of molecules.</p><p id="P17">We hypothesized that introducing a sequencing feature for samples that were classified as cancerous by the machine-learning algorithm would provide yet another layer of specificity and sensitivity. As different tissues vary in their epigenetic modifications, it may allow detection of the tissue-of-origin of the circulating nucleosomes, thus revealing the origin of the cancer. To that end, we coupled the epigenetic analysis with single-molecule DNA sequencing<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">21</xref></sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4b</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD5">Supplementary Fig. 8b</xref>). Briefly, following detection of histone PTMs on cfNucleosomes, the histone proteins are evicted, and the DNA is subjected to repeated cycles of sequencing-by-synthesis using an automated fluidics system. Each cycle consists of incorporation of A, C, T or G by DNA polymerase and imaging; following 120 cycles, the data is integrated to build a strand that can be aligned to the genome, corresponding to the position of the modified nucleosome.</p><p id="P18">As proof-of-concept, we applied EPINUC followed by sequencing (EPINUC-seq) to three plasma samples of late stage CRC probed for H3K4me3, H3K27me3 or H3K9ac (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4c,d</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD5">Supplementary Fig. 8c-e</xref>). Single-molecule mapped reads, corresponding to modified nucleosomes, were intersected with unique antibody peak signatures generated from ENCODE ChIP-seq data for various tissues and primary cell lines, followed by bootstrapping simulations to calculate significance (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD5">Supplementary Fig. 8c</xref>, <xref ref-type="sec" rid="S1">Methods</xref>). Reinforcing our hypothesis, we found that plasma samples showed significant overlap with colon-specific H3K4me3, H3K27me3 and H3K9ac peaks, indicating colon as the main tissue-of-origin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4c,d</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD5">Supplementary Fig. 8c-e</xref>). Moreover, comparing our data to a recent ChIP-seq study of H3K4me3 in plasma showed significant overlap with profiles obtained from CRC patients<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref></sup>, but not with healthy plasma (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4e</xref>). H3K27me3 mapped reads showed a broader pattern compared to H3K4me3 and H3K9ac, overlapping with peaks corresponding to hematopoietic lineage as well as colon. Interestingly, for CRC patients 4044 and 3821 we also observed a significant overlap with liver-specific H3K27me3 and H3K9ac peaks, in agreement with clinical data indicating these patients had liver metastases. This is consistent with recent studies reporting liver damage and release of liver-specific DNA due to tumor cells metastasizing to the liver<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39">39</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40">40</xref></sup>. Yet, the liver signal may also originate from chemotherapy-induced liver damage<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41">41</xref></sup>. Validating our EPINUC-seq approach for tissue-of-origin detection, analysis of plasma samples from PDAC, lung and breast cancer patients revealed pancreas, lung and breast tissues as the main contributors, respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4f</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD5">Supplementary Fig. 8f,g</xref>).</p><p id="P19">Finally, we combined a complementary single-molecule approach to identify the tumor tissue-of-origin, by single-molecule profiling of the DNA modification 5-Hydroxymethylcytosine (5hmC). 5hmC is known to play important roles in gene regulation and cancer<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42">42</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43">43</xref></sup>. We captured 5hmC-enriched DNA from plasma as previously described<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R44">44</xref></sup>, followed by single-molecule DNA sequencing (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD5">Supplementary Fig. 9a</xref>, <xref ref-type="sec" rid="S1">Methods</xref>). In agreement with previous reports<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R45">45</xref></sup>, we found 5hmC in cfDNA to be enriched at gene bodies and promoter proximal regions (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD5">Supplementary Fig. 9b</xref>), which are also known to be marked with H3K36me3. Thus, we generated unique 5hmC read signatures for healthy and CRC samples, and examined their overlap with H3K36me3 peak signatures from various tissues and primary cell lines (<xref ref-type="sec" rid="S1">Methods</xref>). Similar to sequencing of the histone marks (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4d</xref>), analysis of 5hmC in the plasma of the same patient showed highly significant overlap with the colon-specific profile, validating this strategy for identification of the tumor tissue-of-origin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4g</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD5">Supplementary Fig. 9c</xref>). We next aimed to explore whether we can correlate the 5hmC signatures with gene expression data from primary CRC tumors. Thus, we generated a list of genes found to be associated with 5hmc signal for each group of healthy and CRC patients. Interestingly, the expression levels of these CRC-specific genes (identified based on the 5hmc signal) was significantly higher in CRC tumors versus the expression levels of the group of healthy-specific genes (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD5">Supplementary Fig. 9d</xref>). Finally, we showed correct identification of colon origin also for early stage CRC patients, and identification of pancreas origin for the patient diagnosed with PDAC (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4h</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD5">Supplementary Fig. 9e,f</xref>).</p><p id="P20">Our work establishes EPINUC as a novel liquid biopsy approach that analyzes multiple histone and DNA modifications, as well as protein biomarkers, at single-molecule precision. EPINUC distinguishes between CRC patients to healthy individuals at high specificity and sensitivity. We showed that this multi-parametric approach is suitable also for detection of early stage patients, although expanding the analysis to a larger cohort is needed. The main challenges with analyzing plasma nucleosomes are (1) their minute amount- in 1 ml of plasma there are ~1000 genome copies<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R46">46</xref></sup>; (2) The plasma is highly dense with additional proteins, rendering enzymatic or binding approaches to capture nucleosomes difficult; (3) There is high variability between different individuals, stressing the need for quantitative methodologies to allow comparison between samples; and (4) Multi-parametric data is needed to achieve high specificity and confidence in detection. Our EPINUC approach addresses these challenges by enabling single-molecule combinatorial detection of epigenetic marks, DNA sequencing and protein biomarkers from limited input material. For quantification of global DNA methylation levels, several alternative approaches have been developed<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R47">47</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R48">48</xref></sup>. The methylation status of repeat elements in the genome, measured by bisulfite conversion followed by PCR, is frequently used as proxy for global genomic methylation. Yet, it is uncertain to what extent this method provides accurate representation of global DNA methylation in diverse biological and pathological conditions. Alternative approaches utilize mass spectrometry to quantify methylated versus unmethylated cytosine; while these methods are quantitative and accurate, they require relatively high amounts of DNA. Our approach complements these methodologies by providing quantitative single-molecule measurements of global DNA methylation, which is independent on chemical conversion and is not limited to analysis of specific genomic regions, and requires very low input material.</p><p id="P21">In addition to the unique epigenetic analysis, the single-molecule system outperforms the classical ELISA assay for measuring protein biomarkers. ELISA is of relatively low sensitivity and is therefore limited to proteins that are present at high levels, has lower dynamic range in quantifying proteins, and is not amenable to multiplexed detection of several proteins<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27">27</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">28</xref></sup>. We showed that the single-molecule system is capable of detecting the mutant form of p53, which is a non-secreted protein that originates directly from the tumor cells. The main advantages of the single-molecule imaging system is its unique ability to follow binding of antibodies over time, thus allowing for accumulation of signal. Interestingly, the accumulation kinetics for each antibody is highly reproducible across different experiments, likely representing the antibody’s affinity and avidity to its target epitope. Importantly, the system is straightforward to adapt for detection of additional proteins, thus increasing sensitivity and enabling disease-specific biomarkers analysis.</p><p id="P22">EPINUC is built on the idea that integration of multiple parameters would provide specific diagnosis, which is independent on DNA sequencing. Indeed, we show that the few pancreatic cancer samples tested within this study cluster separately from CRC patients, despite the heterogeneity within each group. This would potentially render the EPINUC approach fast and inexpensive, paving the way to a mass screening method for a variety of cancers. Moreover, the integration of multiple parameters may overcome potential confounding effects generating heterogeneity in the cohort, such as chemotherapy treatments administrated to some of the patients, or varied composition of blood cells between individuals. Expanding the protein biomarkers panel to include cancer-type specific indicators may be instrumental in allowing differential diagnosis, independent of sequencing data. Nevertheless, further studies, analyzing larger cohorts of patients, are needed to test whether this technology can differentiate between various cancer types based solely on the epigenetic and biomarker profiles. Such studies may also provide insights on whether the epigenetic differences detected by EPINUC originate solely from the tumor cells, or may represent, at least in part, epigenetic alterations occurring in non-cancer cells in the tumor microenvironment, or generated by chemotherapy or other treatments. Importantly, we showed that the combination of EPINUC with single-molecule DNA sequencing provides unequivocal evidence of the tumor tissue-of-origin, thus further elucidating the type of cancer of each individual. In future studies, it would be of special interest to apply EPINUC-seq to cancer of unknown primary, potentially identifying its origin. Further efforts in clinical use of EPINUC would require a system that offers streamlined sample workflow, integrated instrumentation, and robust data processing pipelines and interpretation algorithms. EPINUC technology greatly expands the already burgeoning field of liquid biopsies and has the potential to be applicable for early detection of cancer and monitoring.</p><sec id="S1" sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec id="S2" sec-type="subjects"><title>Patients</title><p id="P23">All clinical studies were approved by the local ethics committees (Helsinki applications 091-2020 and 0198-14-HM0). Informed consent was obtained from all individuals before blood sampling.</p></sec><sec id="S3"><title>Plasma collection</title><p id="P24">Blood samples were collected in VACUETTE K3 EDTA tubes and transferred immediately to ice. Next, blood was centrifuged (10 minutes, 1,500g, 4°C) and the supernatant was transferred to a fresh 50-ml tubes and centrifuged again (10 minutes, 3,000g, 4°C). The supernatant was collected and used as plasma for all experiments. Plasma was analyzed fresh or flash-frozen and stored at −80°C for future analysis.</p></sec><sec id="S4"><title>Cell-free nucleosomes (cfNucleosomes) preparation for single-molecule imaging</title><p id="P25">Tagging and tailing of cfNucleosomes was carried out as following: 20 μl of plasma or 5X (DDW diluted) concentrated apoptotic medium was incubated at 37°C for 1 hour with the following reaction mixture: 10 μl 10X Green Buffer (Enzymatics, B0120), 416 μM CoCl2 (Enzymatics, B0220), 1:60 PI (SIGMA, P8340), 83.3 nM fluorescently labeled dATP (Jena Bioscience, NU-1611-Cy3/Cy5), 83.3 μM dATP (Thermo Fisher Scientific, R0181), 5 μl of Klenow Fragment (3′→5′ exo-, NEB, M0212S) 3μl of T4 Polynucleotide Kinase (NEB, M0201L) and 4 μl of Terminal deoxynucleotidyl transferase (TdT, Enzymatics, P7070L). Following incubation, samples were inactivated by immediate transfer to ice. For nucleosome sequencing, 1.67 μl of ddATP was added (SIGMA, GE27-2051-01).</p></sec><sec id="S5"><title>Plasma cell-free DNA (cfDNA) isolation and fluorescent labeling</title><p id="P26">cfDNA was extracted from 4 ml of healthy human blood plasma, or from 0.5 ml of plasma from CRC patients, using the Mag-Bind cfDNA Kit (Omega Bio-Tek, M3298-01). For optimized yield, protocol was modified by increasing elution time to 20 minutes on a thermomixer, at 1,600 rpm, in 15 μl elution buffer at room temperature. Sample concentration was measured using Qubit Fluorometer (Thermo Fisher Scientific). For fluorescent labeling of plasma isolated DNA, 10 μl of cfDNA was incubated at 37°C for 1 hour with the following reaction mixture: NEBuffer™ 2 (NEB, B7202), 0.25 mM MnCl2 (SIGMA, M1787), 33 μM fluorescently labeled dATP (Jena Bioscience, NU-1611-Cy3), 1.5 μl of Klenow Fragment (3′→5′ exo-, NEB, M0212S) and 1.5 μl of T4 Polynucleotide Kinase (NEB, M0201L). Following incubation, samples were inactivated by addition of EDTA (Invitrogen, 15575-038) at a final concentration of 20mM. Next, DNA was purified by AMPure SPRI beads (Beckman Coulter, A63881), and quantified by Qubit (Thermo Fisher Scientific).</p></sec><sec id="S6"><title>Cell culture and apoptosis</title><p id="P27">Cell lines were maintained at 37°C with 5% CO2. HEK-293 cells were cultured in 150 cm plates (10×10<sup>6</sup> cells in 20 ml of media) in DMEM supplemented with 10% FBS and 1% P/S, and passaged every week. For induction of apoptosis, 6 μM of Staurosporine (STS, Holland-Moran, 62996-74-1.25) was added to medium of confluent cells. 72 hours later, medium was collected and immediately processed. To verify fragment sizes along with nucleosome labeling, 10 ul of the nucleosomes and 10ul of AMPure extracted DNA (either directly from concentrated medium or after the tagging and tailing reaction), were loaded on High Sensitivity D1000 ScreenTapes (Agilent, 5067-5584) and 6% TBE gel (ThermoFisher Scientific, EC62655BOX), and imaged with 4200 TapeStation (Agilent) or Typhoon imager (Amersham Biosciences), respectively. Apoptotic medium cfNucleosomes were concentrated and recovered using Centricon Plus-70 centrifugation filteres (Merck, UFC710008) according to the manufacture protocol. PI was supplemented 1:100 following concentration.</p></sec><sec id="S7"><title>Surface preparation for single-molecule imaging</title><p id="P28">PEGylated-Biotin and PEGylated-poly T coated microscope slides were prepared based on the protocol described by Chandradoss et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R49">49</xref></sup>. Ibidi glass coverslips (25 mm x 75 mm, IBIDI, IBD-10812) were cleaned with (1) MilliQ H2O (3X washes, 5 minutes sonication, 3X washes); (2) 2% Alconox (SIGMA, 242985) (20 min sonication followed by 5X washes with MilliQ H2O); and (3) 100% Acetone (20 min sonication followed by 3X washes with MilliQ H2O). Slides were further cleaned and functionalized (Hydroxylated) by incubation in 1 M KOH (SIGMA, 484016) solution for 20 minutes while sonicated, followed by 3X washes with MilliQ H2O. Slides were sonicated twice for 10 minutes in 100% HPLC ethanol (J.T baker 8462-25) prior to applying amino-silanization chemistry. Next, slides were incubated for 24 minutes in a mixture of 3% 3-Aminopropyltriethoxysilane (ACROS Organics, 430941000) and 5% acetic acid in HPLC EtOH, with 1 minute sonication in the middle. Slides were then washed with HPLC EtOH (3X) and MilliQ H2O (3X) and dried with N2. Surface functionalization along with first passivation step was performed by applying mPEG: PEGylated-Biotin/PEG-Azide solution [20 mg PEGylated-Biotin (Laysan, Biotin-PEG-SVA-5000), 180 mg mPEG (Laysan, MPEG-SVA-5000) or 20 mg PEG-Azide (JenKem, A5088), 180 mg mPEG (Laysan, MPEG-SVA-5000)] dissolved in 1560 ul 0.1 M Sodium Bicarbonate (SIGMA, S6297) and degassed (centrifugation at 1 minute at 16,000<italic>g</italic>). Next, 140 μl of solution was applied on one surface, followed by immediate assembly of another surface on top. Each pair of assembled surfaces were incubated overnight in a dark humid environment.</p><p id="P29">For PEGylated-Biotin surfaces: At the next day, surfaces were washed with MilliQ H2O and dried with N2 followed by a second passivation step. MS(PEG)4 (ThermoFisher Scientific, TS-22341) was diluted in 0.1 M of sodium bicarbonate to a final concentration of 11.7 mg/ml and applied on one surface, followed by the assembly of another surface on top. Each pair of assembled surfaces were incubated overnight in dark humid environment. The next day, surfaces were disassembled, washed with MilliQ H2O and dried with nitrogen. After nitrogen flush, surfaces were stored in -20°C.</p><p id="P30">For PEGylated-poly T surfaces, following PEG-Azide coating, surfaces were washed with MilliQ H2O and dried with N2. To enable anchoring of dT50 to surface via click chemistry, 10 μM of 5’heyxynyl-dT50 (IDT) were mixed with 2 mM of CuSO4 (SIGMA, C1297) and DDW. Next, 100 μl of the mixture was applied on one surface, followed by immediate assembly of another surface on top. Each pair of assembled surfaces was incubated overnight in a dark humid environment. In the next day, a second passivation step [MS(PEG)4] was carried out, similarly to PEGylated-Biotin preparation. Surfaces were stored in -20°C post nitrogen flush in a similar fashion.</p></sec><sec id="S8"><title>Antibody labeling</title><p id="P31">Capture and detection antibodies were labeled using Biotin conjugation kit (Abcam, ab201796) and Alexa flour antibody labeling kits (Thermo Fisher Scientific, A20181/ A10237/A20186) according to the manufacture protocol. Labeled antibodies were purified by size exclusion chromatography using Bio-Spin 6 columns (Bio-Rad, 7326200) followed by measurement of protein concertation using <italic>Nanodrop</italic> 2000 at 260 nm.</p></sec><sec id="S9"><title>TIMP-1 siRNA transfections</title><p id="P32">siRNA transfection was performed using INTERFERin (Polyplus, 409-10) according to the manufacturer’s protocol. Briefly, cells were plated in 6-well plates (1.5 × 10<sup>5</sup> in 2.5 ml per well) overnight, and the 200 μl of transfection complex was added directly to medium, at final concentration of 25 nM of siRNA. RNA and protein samples were isolated from cells 72 hours after transfection. The following siRNA was used: SMARTpool: ON-TARGETplus Human TIMP1 siRNA (L-011792-00-0005, Dharmacon). For single-molecule imaging, medium was collected from plates, followed by centrifugation at max speed in 4°C and collection of supernatant to separate proteins from cell debris. Protein concentration was determined by Pierce™ BCA Protein Assay (Thermo Fisher Scientific, 23225), followed by addition (1:100) of protease inhibitor cocktail (PI, SIGMA, P8340).</p></sec><sec id="S10"><title>Synthetic DNA preparation for DNA methylation assay</title><p id="P33">DNA fragments were generated by conventional PCR (primer sites underlined) supplementing the reaction with either methylated (NEB, N0356S) or un-methylated cytosine (Thermo Fisher Scientific, R0181), followed by purification with AMPure SPRI beads. The size (~200 bp) was chosen to mimic the size of mono-nucleosomal DNA fragments previously identified in blood plasma<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R50">50</xref></sup>. Fragment labeling, purification and quantification was performed as described for plasma cfDNA.</p><p id="P34">Sequence:</p><p id="P35"><underline>CATCAATGTATCTTATCATGTCTG</underline>TATACCGTCGACCTCTAGCTAGAGCTTGGCGT AATCATGGTCATAGCTGTTTCCTGTGTGAAATTGTTATCCGCTCACAATTCCACAC AACATACGAGCCGGAAGCATAAAGTGTAAAGCCTGGGGTGC<underline>CTAATGAGTGAGCTAACTCACA</underline></p></sec><sec id="S11"><title>5-Aza-2-Deoxycytidine Treatment</title><p id="P36">HEK-293 cells were plated in 150 cm plates (10×10<sup>6</sup> cells in 20 ml of media) overnight, then treated with 1 uM of 5-Aza-2-deoxycytidine (5 −Aza, SIGMA, A3656) or PBS for 4 days. Next, 5×10<sup>6</sup> cells were collected and washed with PBS supplemented with PI (1:100), followed by centrifugation at 3000 rpm for 3 minutes. Cell pellet was resuspended with 1 ml of 0.05% Igepal (SIGMA, I8896) diluted in PBS (supplemented with PI as mentioned above) and centrifuged again at 3000 rpm for 3 minutes. Next, the pellet was resuspended in Lysis buffer [100 mM Tris-HCl pH 7.5 (Gibco, 115567-027), 300 mM NaCl (J.T Baker, 7647145), 2% Triton® X-100 (SIGMA, 9002 93-1), 0.2% sodium deoxycholate (SIGMA, D6750), 10 mM CaCl2 (SIGMA, 21115)] supplemented with PI and Micrococcal Nuclease (ThermoFisher Scientific, 88216). The reaction mixture was incubated at 37°C for 10 minutes and then inactivated by addition of EGTA at a final concentration of 20mM. Then, lysate was centrifuged for 10 minutes at max speed and supernatant was transferred to a new tube. DNA extraction, fluorescent labeling and quantification was performed as described for plasma cfDNA.</p></sec><sec id="S12"><title>Single-molecule imaging</title><p id="P37">PEGylated-Biotin and PEGylated-poly T coated coverslips were assembled into an Ibidi flowcell (Sticky Slide VI hydrophobic, IBIDI, IBD-80608) generating a six lane flowcell, which enables imaging of six different samples or various combinations of antibodies on a single surface. For PEGylated-Biotin flowcells, Streptavidin (SIGMA, S4762) was added to a final concentration of 0.2 mg/ml followed by 10 minutes incubation and washing with imaging buffer [IMB: 12 mM HEPES pH 8 (Thermo Fisher Scientific, 15630056), 40 mM TRIS pH 7.5 (Gibco, 115567-027) 60 mM KCL (SIGMA, 60142), 0.32 mM EDTA (Invitrogen, 15575-038), 3 mM MgCl2 (SIGMA, 63069), 10% glycerol (Bio-Lab, 56815), 0.1 mg/ml BSA (SIGMA, A7906) and 0.02% Igepal (SIGMA, I8896)]. For time-lapse imaging experiments (Histone PTMs, p53), prior to sample application, TetraSpeck beads (ThermoFisher Scientific, T7279) diluted in PBS were added and incubated on surface for at least 10 minutes to allow correction for stage drift in image analysis. Imaging was performed on a total internal reflection (TIRF) microscope manufactured by Nikon (ECLIPSE Ti2-E LU-N4 TIRF) with CFI Apochromat TIRF 60X Objective lens and TRF49904, TRF49909, and TRF89902 filter cubes (CHROMA) for the 488, 561, and 647 lasers, respectively. Images were taken with 1.5X magnification setting resulting in FOV of 148x148um, using ANDOR ZYLA 4.2 PLUS camera. At least 50 FOVs were imaged per lane.</p></sec></sec><sec id="S13"><title>Histone PTMs analysis</title><p id="P38">PEGylated-poly T coated coverslips were assembled as described and further passivated with 5% BSA (Merck, A7906) for 30 minutes followed by wash with IMB. Next, plasma sample containing tailed and fluorescently labeled cfNucleosomes was incubated with antibodies (diluted 1:60) for 30 minutes at room temperature (RT), to allow formation of antibody-cfNucleosomes complexes. Next, samples were loaded on the surface and incubated for 15 minutes to allow hybridization. Flowcell was washed (X3) with IMB, followed by time lapse imaging every 15 minutes, with the three laser channels, across all positions (50 Fields of View (FOVs, 148μm<sup>2</sup>) per experiment). Removing antibodies from the surface (to achieve multiplexed PTM profiling) can be achieved either by multiple washes, or simply by using a reducing agent (TCEP) that disrupts the disulfide bonds between the heavy and light chains of antibodies but maintains nucleosomes intact.</p></sec><sec id="S14"><title>Protein biomarkers analysis</title><p id="P39">Single-molecule analysis of protein biomarkers requires the use of different capture and detection antibodies that would bind to different epitopes on the target protein. This would allow capture of target protein to the surface, while exposing a different epitope for the binding of the detection antibody. Thus, the methodology relies on the availability of two distinct antibodies for each target protein. The specific antibodies we used for each protein biomarker are listed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary Table 2</xref>.</p><p id="P40">PEGylated-Biotin coated coverslips were assembled and coated with streptavidin. Biotinylated antibodies were incubated on surface in IMB2 [10 mM MES pH 6.5 (Boston Bioproducts Inc, NC9904354), 60 mM KCL, 0.32 mM EDTA, 3 mM MgCl2, 10% glycerol, 0.1 mg/ml BSA and 0.02% Igepal] for 30 minutes, followed by wash with IMB2. Next, plasma sample was added to flowcell and incubated on surface for 30 minutes, followed by washes (3X) with IMB2, to allow binding of target proteins. Fluorescently labeled antibodies (detection antibodies) were introduced to the surface for 60 minutes, washed with IMB2, and imaged.</p></sec><sec id="S15"><title>Global DNA methylation analysis</title><p id="P41">PEGylated-Biotin coated coverslips were assembled and coated with streptavidin. 2 μl of MBD2-Biotin (Thermo Fisher Scientific, A11148) was incubated with 8 μl of Cy3 labeled cfDNA fragments for 30 minutes, to allow MBD2-Biotin binding to methylated DNA. Next, the reaction mixture was immobilized on the surface and incubated for 10 minutes, followed by TIRF imaging.</p></sec><sec id="S16"><title>DNA Hydroxymethylation analysis</title><p id="P42">cfDNA was incubated in 25 μl reaction mixture containing 50 mM HEPES buffer (pH 8), 25 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 60 μM UDP-6-N<sub>3</sub>-Glc (Jena Bioscience, CLK-076Motif) and 12.5 U T4 beta-glucosyltransferase (Thermo Fisher Scientific, EO0831) for 2 hours at 37°C. Next, 5 μl DBCO-S-S-biotin (Click Chemistry Tools, 10 mM stock in DMSO) was directly added to the reaction mixture and incubated overnight at 37°C. DNA was cleaned using Oligo Clean &amp; Concentrator (Zymo, D4060), and immobilized on a PEGylated-Biotin streptavidin coated surface, followed by imaging.</p></sec><sec id="S17"><title>Single-molecule DNA sequencing</title><p id="P43">For single-molecule DNA sequencing of cfNucleosomes, PEGylated-poly T surface was blocked with BSA as described above. Poly-A tailed FluoSpheres (described below) along with TetraSpeck beads and cfNucleosomes were applied to the surface. PTMs of plasma cfNucleosomes were imaged over time for 169 FOV, as described above. Then flowcell was washed with Wash A buffer [150 mM HEPES (KOH, pH 7.0), 1×SSC, 0.1% SDS] and Wash B buffer [150 mM HEPES (KOH, pH 7.0), 150 mM NaCl] to evict histones and antibodies. During single-molecule sequencing, temperature was maintained at 37°C by UNO-T stage top incubator (Okolab), and Luer adapter was used to connect the flowcell to IDEX 1/4-28 flat bottom fittings connecting to 1/16" OD tubing. Sequencing was performed as described previously, using Helicos True Single Molecule Sequencing (tSMS) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://seqll.com/">http://seqll.com/</ext-link>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R51">51</xref></sup>, by repurposing a microfluidics system used in the HeliScope single molecule sequencer to deliver tSMS chemistry to the flowcell (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD5">Supplementary Fig. 10</xref>). A similar setup was previously used to enable single molecule sequencing<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R52">52</xref></sup>.</p><p id="P44">The microfluidics system features the storage compartment for tSMS chemistry reagents, connected to a set of syringe pumps and mixing valves that deliver tSMS chemistry to the attached flowcell. During sequencing, imaging on microscope and chemistry on microfluidics system was automatically controlled by using μManager (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://micro-manager.org/">https://micro-manager.org/</ext-link>) software with custom scripts to enable tSMS sequencing-by-synthesis method.</p><p id="P45">FluoSpheres preparation: FluoSpheres (Carboxylate-Modified Microspheres, Thermo Fisher Scientific, F8789) were conjugated to dA50-amine (IDT), tailed as previously described, and hybridized to the surface to serve as reference points for stage drift correction during alignment of sequencing images.</p><sec id="S18"><title>Single-Molecule Hydroxymethylation sequencing</title><p id="P46">2.5 ng of plasma cfDNA was added to a 25 μl solution containing 50 mM HEPES buffer (pH 8), 25 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 60 μM UDP-6-N<sub>3</sub>-Glc (Jena Bioscience, CLK-076) and 12.5 U T4 beta-glucosyltransferase (Thermo Fisher Scientific, EO0831), and incubated for 2 hours at 37°C. Next, 5 μl DBCO-S-S-biotin (Click Chemistry Tools, 10 mM stock in DMSO) was directly added to the reaction mixture and incubated overnight at 37°C. For 5hmC DNA pulldown, samples were incubated at RT with 15 μl of Streptavidin beads (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Dy-11205D) for 1 hour, followed by 3 washes with 1X wash buffer, and elution in 20 μl of 125 mM TCEP (Thermo Fisher Scientific, TS-77720). 5hmC eluted DNA was poly-adenylated and sequenced on a PEGylated-poly T surface as described above. Metagene profile was generated using ngs.plot.</p></sec><sec id="S19"><title>Image analysis</title><p id="P47">Image analysis was performed with the open-source software Cell Profiler (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cellprofiler.org/">http://www.cellprofiler.org/</ext-link>). Image analysis pipelines are available upon request. Briefly, time-lapse images of antibody binding events and TetraSpeck beads are aligned, stacked and summed to one image. Antibody spots can be differentiated from TetraSpeck beads spots based on spot size and intensity. Summed antibodies images are aligned with cfNucleosomes images to count colocalization events.</p></sec><sec id="S20"><title>Predictive Power Score (PPS)</title><p id="P48">PPS analysis on the data was conducted using a previously published algorithm (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/8080labs/ppscore">https://github.com/8080labs/ppscore</ext-link>). Briefly, by calculating a cross-validated decisions tree (repeated [10K] 4-fold cross-validation) for the target variable (e.g., diagnosis) using only one of the markers, it is possible to determine which of the markers in the datasets contributes most to the target variable. The PPS is normalized to the most common assignment in order to provide a baseline for comparison. Using the PPS rather than a simple correlation measure allows us to account for non-linear effects and provides an alternative formulation for correlation which also treats categorical variables (e.g., diagnosis, or disease state − see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD3">Supplementary Table 3</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S21"><title>Machine learning model for sample classification</title><p id="P49">For sample binary classification, various machine-learning algorithms were trained on the features that showed significant differences between healthy and CRC (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3c,d,e</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD5">Supplementary Fig. 6b,c</xref>), and evaluated for their performance using a four-fold cross-validation across all samples. The best predictive performance was achieved by a Logistic Regression classifier. To improve classifier performance, we conducted additional feature selection by training the classifier on all possible feature combinations out of the significant features aforementioned. Evaluating the resulting Area Under the Curve (AUC) values of repeated (500 iterations) four-fold cross-validation for each combination revealed an optimal cumulative performance of a five feature combination: H3K27me3/Nuc, H3K9me3/Nuc, CEA, CEA/MST1, and global DNA methylation. To evaluate the classifier overall performance using the selected features, we performed repeated (10K) 4-fold cross-validation across all samples. For each iteration the sensitivity, specificity, accuracy, precision, negative predictive value and the AUC value were calculated and averaged over all iterations. R caret and RWeka packages were used for machine-learning modeling.</p></sec><sec id="S22"><title>Tissue and plasma signatures</title><p id="P50">We downloaded and combined two independent <italic>Homo sapiens</italic> based ChIP-seq tracks for each tissue from the Encyclopedia of DNA Elements (ENCODE, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD4">Supplementary Table 4</xref>). To generate a unique antibody peak profile for a given tissue, we discarded peaks found to overlap with at least one of the other eight tissues tested, retaining only tissue specific peaks. Of note, brain H3K36me3 peaks were available only for embryonic tissue, therefore were replaced with spleen tissue H3K36me3 peaks. Similarly, heart H3K9ac peaks were available only for embryonic tissue, therefore were replaced with skeletal muscle tissue H3K9ac peaks. To generate unique plasma H3K4me3 ChIP-seq peaks, we obtained data from healthy (H) and CRC (C) plasma (n=3 for each) produced by Sadeh et. al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref></sup> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD4">Supplementary Table 4</xref>). For each group, reads were intersected and only shared reads across all samples were kept for further analysis. Non-overlapping reads between the overlapping healthy and overlapping CRC reads were defined as the unique plasma signature.</p><p id="P51"><underline>Bootstrapping simulation to analyze single-molecule reads overlap with various tissues Overlap</underline> significance was assessed as following: First, single-molecule sequenced plasma antibody aligned reads were extended by 100bp from each side to resemble nucleosome length. Then, for each chromosome, we randomly selected a number of 230bp-long DNA segments that is equivalent to the number of antibody positive plasma reads for this chromosome. Random reads were intersected with each unique tissue/plasma signature and overlapping events were recorded. These bootstrapping simulations were iterated 10K times for each tissue for a given antibody to generate a distribution of overlap by chance. Finally, single-molecule sequenced plasma antibody reads were intersected with all tissue signatures, and contrasted against the corresponding distribution of random overlap for that tissue to evaluate overlap significance (two tailed z-test or Wilcoxon rank sum test). Signature and overlap analysis were performed using an in-house R script (EPINUC-overlap), where minimal overlap was defined as 1bp overlap. The accession numbers for the ENCODE chip-seq datasets are summarized in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD4">Supplementary Table 4</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="S23"><title>5hmC gene signature expression in CRC</title><p id="P52">To explore the correlation between 5hmC signatures and gene expression in CRC, we generated annotated gene lists for healthy and CRC plasma (n=3 for each) enriched for 5hmC DNA sequenced reads via Clusterpofiler R package. Next, for each group, genes were intersected and only shared genes across all samples within each group were kept for further analysis. Then, in order to generate unique 5hmC gene signature for each group, both datasets were intersected and overlapping genes were discarded. Each unique 5hmC gene signature was intersected with RNA expression datasets of CRC primary tumors, obtained from the cBioportal database (TCGA, Firehose Legacy). Finally, both unique 5hmC gene signatures were compared by their logarithmic mean expression levels (two samples, Welch’s t-test).</p></sec><sec id="S24"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="P53">All statistical analysis was conducted using the statistical programming language R. Multiple comparison (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD5">Supplementary Fig. 6d</xref>) was calculated using Asymptotic K-Sample Brown-Mood Median Test.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="SM"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1"><label>Supplementary table 1</label><media xlink:href="EMS145419-supplement-Supplementary_table_1.xlsx" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.spreadsheetml.sheet" id="d36aAdABbB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD2"><label>Supplementary table 2</label><media xlink:href="EMS145419-supplement-Supplementary_table_2.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" id="d36aAdABcB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD3"><label>Supplementary table 3</label><media xlink:href="EMS145419-supplement-Supplementary_table_3.csv" mimetype="text" mime-subtype="csv; charset=utf-8" id="d36aAdABdB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD4"><label>Supplementary table 4</label><media xlink:href="EMS145419-supplement-Supplementary_table_4.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" id="d36aAdABeB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD5"><label>Supplementary Figures</label><media xlink:href="EMS145419-supplement-Supplementary_Figures.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" id="d36aAdABfB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack id="S25"><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>We thank Dr. R. Rozenzweing, Dr. O. Fasust, Mr. M. Maurer, and Ms. R. Irwin for their contribution in establishing a protocol for Methyl-CpG-binding domain protein 2 labeling. We thank Lior Segev for his help with writing and integrating the μManager scripts for performing EPINUC-Seq. We are grateful for the important comments made by I. Ulitsky while reading the manuscript.</p><sec id="S26"><title>Funding</title><p>E.S. is an incumbent of the Lisa and Jeffrey Aronin Family Career Development chair. This research was supported by grants from the European Research Council (ERC801655, ERC_PoC_963863), Emerson Collective, The Israeli Science Foundation (1881/19), The German-Israeli Foundation for Scientific Research and Development and Minerva.</p></sec></ack><sec id="S27" sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data and materials availability</title><p id="P54">All data is available in the main text or the <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">supplementary materials</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="S28" sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p id="P55">Datasets generated and analyzed during this study are summarized in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD4">Supplementary Table 4</xref>, BED files of plasma sequenced reads are available upon request.</p></sec><sec id="S29" sec-type="data-availability"><title>Code availability</title><p id="P56">Code for performing overlap analysis is available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/Vadim-Fed/EPINUC-overlap">https://github.com/Vadim-Fed/EPINUC-overlap</ext-link>.</p></sec><fn-group><fn id="FN1" fn-type="con"><p id="P57"><bold>Author contributions:</bold> V.F, N.E, and E.S designed the study and wrote the manuscript. V.F and N.E performed the experiments and analyzed the data. N.F and O.B assisted in the experiments, G.R assisted with data analysis. B.B.Z, Y.M, T.P, A.H, J.E.C, A.S, M.T, A.G, M.M and A.Z collected the plasma samples of early and late stage CRC patients. D.J, A.S, K.A contributed to the development of single-nucleosomes imaging technology and sequencing experiments described in this study.</p></fn><fn id="FN2" fn-type="conflict"><p id="P58"><bold>Competing interests:</bold> Authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><ref id="R1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wan</surname><given-names>JCM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Liquid biopsies come of age: Towards implementation of circulating tumour DNA</article-title><source>Nat Rev Cancer</source><year>2017</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>223</fpage><lpage>238</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bronkhorst</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ungerer</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Holdenrieder</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The emerging role of cell-free DNA as a molecular marker for cancer management</article-title><source>Biomol Detect Quantif</source><year>2019</year><volume>17</volume><elocation-id>100087</elocation-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heitzer</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Haque</surname><given-names>IS</given-names></name><name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>CES</given-names></name><name><surname>Speicher</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Current and future perspectives of liquid biopsies in genomics-driven oncology</article-title><source>Nat Rev Genet</source><year>2019</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>71</fpage><lpage>88</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lo</surname><given-names>YMD</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>DSC</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Chiu</surname><given-names>RWK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Epigenetics, fragmentomics, and topology of cell-free DNA in liquid biopsies</article-title><source>Science (80-.)</source><year>2021</year><volume>372</volume></element-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Circulating tumour DNA methylation markers for diagnosis and prognosis of hepatocellular carcinoma</article-title><source>Nat Mater</source><year>2017</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>1155</fpage><lpage>1162</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moss</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Comprehensive human cell-type methylation atlas reveals origins of circulating cell-free DNA in health and disease</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2018</year><volume>9</volume><elocation-id>5068</elocation-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>CancerLocator: Non-invasive cancer diagnosis and tissue-of-origin prediction using methylation profiles of cell-free DNA</article-title><source>Genome Biol</source><year>2017</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>12</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Sensitive tumour detection and classification using plasma cell-free DNA methylomes</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2018</year><volume>563</volume><fpage>579</fpage><lpage>583</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reinberg</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Vales</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chromatin domains rich in inheritance only certain histone posttranslational modifications qualify as being epigenetic</article-title><source>Science (80-.)</source><year>2018</year><volume>361</volume><fpage>33</fpage><lpage>34</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shema</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Bernstein</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name><name><surname>Buenrostro</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Single-cell and single-molecule epigenomics to uncover genome regulation at unprecedented resolution</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><year>2019</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>19</fpage><lpage>25</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Allis</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Jenuwein</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The molecular hallmarks of epigenetic control</article-title><source>Nat Rev Genet</source><year>2016</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>487</fpage><lpage>500</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mancarella</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Plass</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Epigenetic signatures in cancer: proper controls, current challenges and the potential for clinical translation</article-title><source>Genome Med</source><year>2021</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><comment>2021 131</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sadeh</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>ChIP-seq of plasma cell-free nucleosomes identifies gene expression programs of the cells of origin</article-title><source>Nat Biotechnol</source><year>2021</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>586</fpage><lpage>598</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gezer</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Histone methylation marks on circulating nucleosomes as novel blood-based biomarker in colorectal cancer</article-title><source>Int J Mol Sci</source><year>2015</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>29654</fpage><lpage>29662</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van den Ackerveken</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A novel proteomics approach to epigenetic profiling of circulating nucleosomes</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2021</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>12</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Snyder</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Kircher</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Daza</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Shendure</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cell-free DNA Comprises an in Vivo Nucleosome Footprint that Informs Its Tissues-Of-Origin</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2016</year><volume>164</volume><fpage>57</fpage><lpage>68</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ulz</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Inferring expressed genes by whole-genome sequencing of plasma DNA</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><year>2016</year><volume>48</volume><fpage>1273</fpage><lpage>1278</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Orientation-aware plasma cell-free DNA fragmentation analysis in open chromatin regions informs tissue of origin</article-title><source>Genome Res</source><year>2019</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>418</fpage><lpage>427</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ferlay</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cancer incidence and mortality worldwide: Sources, methods and major patterns in GLOBOCAN 2012</article-title><source>Int J Cancer</source><year>2015</year><volume>136</volume><fpage>E359</fpage><lpage>E386</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Quantitative evidence for early metastatic seeding in colorectal cancer</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><year>2019</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>1113</fpage><lpage>1122</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shema</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Single-molecule decoding of combinatorially modified nucleosomes</article-title><source>Science (80-)</source><year>2016</year><volume>352</volume><fpage>717</fpage><lpage>721</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heintzman</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Distinct and predictive chromatin signatures of transcriptional promoters and enhancers in the human genome</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><year>2007</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>311</fpage><lpage>318</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barski</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>High-Resolution Profiling of Histone Methylations in the Human Genome</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2007</year><volume>129</volume><fpage>823</fpage><lpage>837</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tiernan</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Carcinoembryonic antigen is the preferred biomarker for in vivo colorectal cancer targeting</article-title><source>Br J Cancer</source><year>2013</year><volume>108</volume><fpage>662</fpage><lpage>667</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>TIMP-1 is a novel serum biomarker for the diagnosis of colorectal cancer: A meta-analysis</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2018</year><volume>13</volume><elocation-id>e0207039</elocation-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Identification of MST1 as a potential early detection biomarker for colorectal cancer through a proteomic approach</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2017</year><volume>7</volume></element-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mandal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Direct Kinetic Fingerprinting for High-Accuracy Single-Molecule Counting of Diverse Disease Biomarkers</article-title><source>Acc Chem Res</source><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.accounts.0c00621</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Furth</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Unified platform for genetic and serological detection of COVID-19 with single-molecule technology</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2021</year><volume>16</volume><elocation-id>e0255096</elocation-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nakayama</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Oshima</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mutant p53 in colon cancer</article-title><source>J Mol Cell Biol</source><year>2019</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>267</fpage><lpage>276</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Hernández-Illán</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Moreira</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Balaguer</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Goel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Epigenetics of colorectal cancer: biomarker and therapeutic potential</article-title><source>Nat Rev Gastroenterol Hepatol</source><year>2020</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>111</fpage><lpage>130</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dawson</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The cancer epigenome: Concepts, challenges, and therapeutic opportunities</article-title><source>Science(80-)</source><year>2017</year><volume>355</volume><issue>6330</issue><fpage>1147</fpage><lpage>1152</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Emerging molecular and biological functions of MBD2, a reader of DNA methylation</article-title><source>Front Genet</source><year>2016</year><volume>7</volume></element-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bettegowda</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Detection of circulating tumor DNA in early- and late-stage human malignancies</article-title><source>Sci Transl Med</source><year>2014</year><volume>6</volume><elocation-id>224ra24</elocation-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Curry</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Magnani</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilhelm-Benartzi</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Borley</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Poised epigenetic states and acquired drug resistance in cancer</article-title><source>Nat Rev Cancer</source><year>2014</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>747</fpage><lpage>753</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kerachian</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Crosstalk between DNA methylation and gene expression in colorectal cancer, a potential plasma biomarker for tracing this tumor</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2020</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>113</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>King</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A cross-sectional study of global DNA methylation and risk of colorectal adenoma</article-title><source>BMC Cancer</source><year>2014</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>9</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Frederiksen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Plasma TIMP-1 levels and treatment outcome in patients treated with XELOX for metastatic colorectal cancer</article-title><source>Ann Oncol</source><year>2011</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>369</fpage><lpage>375</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Garrido-Laguna</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Hidalgo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pancreatic cancer: from state-of-the-art treatments to promising novel therapies</article-title><source>Nat Rev Clin Oncol</source><year>2015</year><volume>126</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>319</fpage><lpage>334</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lubotzky</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Liquid biopsy reveals collateral tissue damage in cancer</article-title><source>JCI Insight</source><year>2022</year><volume>7</volume></element-citation></ref><ref id="R40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gai</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Liver- and Colon-Specific DNA Methylation Markers in Plasma for Investigation of Colorectal Cancers with or without Liver Metastases</article-title><source>Clin Chem</source><year>2018</year><volume>64</volume><fpage>1239</fpage><lpage>1249</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R41"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tannapfel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Reinacher-Schick</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>[Chemotherapy associated hepatotoxicity in the treatment of advanced colorectal cancer (CRC)]</article-title><source>Z Gastroenterol</source><year>2008</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>435</fpage><lpage>440</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R42"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>5-Hydroxymethylcytosine signatures in circulating cell-free DNA as diagnostic biomarkers for human cancers</article-title><source>Cell Res</source><year>2017</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>1243</fpage><lpage>1257</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R43"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lio</surname><given-names>CWJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuita</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dysregulation of the TET family of epigenetic regulators in lymphoid and myeloid malignancies</article-title><source>Blood</source><year>2019</year><volume>134</volume><fpage>1487</fpage><lpage>1497</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R44"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Tet-mediated covalent labelling of 5-methylcytosine for its genome-wide detection and sequencing</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2013</year><volume>4</volume></element-citation></ref><ref id="R45"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>CX</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>5-Hydroxymethylcytosine signatures in cell-free DNA provide information about tumor types and stages</article-title><source>Cell Res</source><year>2017</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>1231</fpage><lpage>1242</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R46"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Newman</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Integrated digital error suppression for improved detection of circulating tumor DNA</article-title><source>Nat Biotechnol</source><year>2016</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>547</fpage><lpage>555</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R47"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lisanti</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Comparison of Methods for Quantification of Global DNA Methylation in Human Cells and Tissues</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2013</year><volume>8</volume><elocation-id>79044</elocation-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R48"><label>48</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bock</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Quantitative comparison of DNA methylation assays for biomarker development and clinical applications</article-title><source>Nat Biotechnol</source><year>2016</year><volume>347</volume><issue>34</issue><fpage>726</fpage><lpage>737</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R49"><label>49</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chandradoss</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Surface passivation for single-molecule protein studies</article-title><source>J Vis Exp</source><year>2014</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3791/50549</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R50"><label>50</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fleischhacker</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Circulating nucleic acids (CNAs) and cancer-A survey</article-title><source>Biochim Biophys Acta - Rev Cancer</source><year>2007</year><volume>1775</volume><fpage>181</fpage><lpage>232</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R51"><label>51</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Single-Molecule DNA Sequencing of a Viral Genome</article-title><source>Science(80-)</source><year>2008</year><volume>320</volume><fpage>106</fpage><lpage>109</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R52"><label>52</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Systematic detection of m6A-modified transcripts at single-molecule and single-cell resolution</article-title><source>Cell Reports Methods</source><year>2021</year><volume>1</volume><elocation-id>100061</elocation-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Fig.1</label><caption><title>EPINUC decodes the combinatorial epigenetic states of plasma cell-free nucleosomes.</title><p><bold>a,</bold> Experimental scheme: (1) Sample preparation procedure of cfNucleosomes is carried out in one-step and consists of two enzymatic processes: repair of DNA ends by Klenow polymerase, and addition of a poly A tail by Terminal Transferase (TdT). The reaction contains a mixture of natural dATPs and fluorescently labeled dATPs (Cy3-dATP) to label nucleosomes. (2) cfNucleosmes are captured on a PEGylated-poly T surface via dA:dT hybridization. Immobilized nucleosomes are incubated with fluorescently labeled antibodies targeting different histone modifications. (3) TIRF microscopy is applied to record nucleosome positions and generate time-lapse imaging of antibodies’ binding events. <bold>b,</bold> Representative images of plasma-derived cfNucleosomes and the corresponding H3K4me3 and H3K27me3 signal (numbers within images represent counted spots). Each spot corresponds to a single nucleosome. Nucleosomes anchor to the surface specifically via hybridization, as evident from the lack of signal when tailed with dTTP (Poly-dT) rather than dATP (Poly-dA). <bold>c,</bold> Representative images of antibodies’ binding and dissociation events over time from individual target molecules (marked by red/yellow circles). <bold>d,e,f</bold> Example for quantification and representative images of the various parameters measured by EPINUC in plasma samples from one healthy subject and one CRC patient. Zoomed-in image segments of entire field of view (148μm<sup>2</sup>). <bold>d,</bold> The percentage of cfNucleosomes (green spots, Cy3) that are modified by H3K27me3 (cyan spots, AF488). Red arrows indicate co-localization events. Scale bar = 1μm <bold>e,</bold> Ratio between H3K4me3 (red, AF647) and H3K27me3 (cyan) antibodies. White arrows indicate antibody spots, blue arrows indicate TetraSpeck beads that are used for alignment. Scale bar = 5μm. <bold>f,</bold> cfNucleosomes marked by the combinatorial pattern of both H3K27me3 and H3K4me3. Red arrows indicate co-localization events of H3K27me3 only, yellow arrow indicates a combinatorially modified nucleosome. Scale bar = 1μm.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS145419-f001"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Fig.2</label><caption><title>Multiplexed single-molecule detection of cancer-associated protein biomarkers, mutant p53 and DNA methylation.</title><p><bold>a,</bold> Experimental scheme: biotinylated capture antibodies targeting distinct proteins are anchored to a PEG-streptavidin surface. Plasma proteins are captured on surface, followed by detection with fluorescently labeled antibodies and TIRF imaging. Multiplexed detection of up to three proteins is achieved by labeling antibodies with different fluorophores. Each spot represents a single protein bound on the surface. <bold>b,</bold> Representative TIRF images of selected CRC biomarkers measured simultaneously for each plasma sample: CEA (red), MST1 (cyan) and TIMP-l(green). Images reveal distinct biomarkers profiles for healthy and CRC. <bold>c,</bold> Representative TIRF images depicting α-CEA antibody binding events (spots) over serial plasma dilutions. <bold>d,</bold> Regression analysis of the number of spots as a function of plasma concentration highlights the linearity of detection. Data is presented as the mean +/- s.d. of 50 FOVs for each concentration. <bold>e,f,g</bold> Single-molecule detection of p53 in the plasma of healthy and CRC patients with known p53 mutations. <bold>e,</bold> Representative TIRF images. Detection is carried out simultaneously with antibodies targeting all p53 (red) and with antibodies that are specific to the mutant p53 conformation (green). Large diameter spots correspond to TetraSpeck beads used for alignment. <bold>f,</bold> p53 signal accumulation over time in late stage CRC and healthy plasma. Data is presented as the mean +/- s.d. of 50 FOVs for each time point. <bold>g,</bold> Total and mutant p53 levels in plasma show significantly higher levels in CRC patients versus healthy individuals (n=6 for each group). Box plots limits: 25−75% quantiles, middle: median, upper (lower) whisker to the largest (smallest) value no further than 1.5× interquartile range from the hinge. P values were calculated by Wilcoxon rank sum exact test. *** P value &lt; 0.001. <bold>h,</bold> Experimental scheme for single-molecule imaging of global DNA methylation: MBD2-biotin is incubated with Cy3-labeled (green) DNA, and binds specifically to methylated DNA molecules. Next, biotin-MBD-meDNA complexes are immobilized on a PEG-streptavidin surface, followed by TIRF imaging. Each spot represents a single bound complex, number of spots correspond to the level of DNA methylation in plasma. <bold>i,</bold> Representative TIRF images of DNA methylation in HEK293 cells treated with 5-Aza-2’-deoxycytidine, demonstrating significant reduction in methylation compared to control cells. <bold>j,</bold> Representative TIRF images of global cfDNA methylation levels in the plasma of CRC and healthy subjects, showing lower DNA methylation levels in CRC. For all images, numbers within images represent counted spots.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS145419-f002"/></fig><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Fig.3</label><caption><title>EPINUC reveals significant epigenetic and biomarkers alterations in the plasma of CRC patients.</title><p><bold>a,</bold> Representative TIRF images depict changes in protein biomarker levels in the plasma of healthy, CRC patient, and CRC following tumor resection. Numbers within images represent counted spots. <bold>b,</bold> CEA/MST1 normalized levels in the plasma of CRC patients and healthy individuals. Each bar represents a subject; data is presented as the mean +/- s.d. of 50 fields of view per sample. *1-3 correspond to healthy samples 19, 6, and 9, respectively. Sample 4445 (CRC, red) is denoted by *. <bold>c,</bold> Box plot representation of the data in B (healthy = 33, CRC = 46). Box plots limits: 25−75% quantiles, middle: median, upper (lower) whisker to the largest (smallest) value no further than 1.5× interquartile range from the hinge. P values were calculated by Welch’s t-test. *** P value &lt; 0.001. <bold>d,</bold> Histone PTMs, ratios and combinations (as indicated on the graphs) that significantly differ between healthy and CRC late stage samples (healthy = 33, CRC = 46). P values were calculated by Welch’s t-test. * P value &lt; 0.05 ** P value &lt; 0.01. *** P value &lt; 0.001. <bold>e,</bold> Global DNA methylation levels, measured as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2J</xref>, in the same cohort as (d). <bold>f,</bold> EPINUC measurements (Histone PTMs, DNA methylation and protein biomarkers) that significantly differ between healthy and early stage CRC patients (healthy = 33, early CRC = 17). P values were calculated by Wilcoxon rank sum exact test. * P value &lt; 0.05 ** P value &lt; 0.01. *** P value &lt; 0.001. <bold>g,</bold> Individual parameters predictive power score (PPS) analysis for the various subgroups (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="S1">Methods</xref>). Color scale represents PPS value. <bold>h,</bold> Principal Component Analysis (PCA) with input parameters of H3K27me3/Nuc, H3K4me3 &amp; H3K27me3, CEA/MST1 and CEA. Sample groups are color-coded as indicated, each dot represents a plasma sample. Ellipse represents 95% confidence interval for the barycenter of each group.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS145419-f003"/></fig><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Fig.4</label><caption><title>EPINUC differentiates healthy versus CRC patients and informs the tumor tissue-of-origin.</title><p><bold>a,</bold> ROC curves discriminate between healthy (n=33) and all CRC samples (n=63) using a logistic regression model. The area under the curve (AUC) is shown for protein biomarkers only (Proteins; CEA + CEA/MST1, black line), protein biomarkers in combination with global DNA methylation levels (Proteins + Methylation, purple line), protein biomarkers with histone PTMs (Proteins + PTMs, blue line) and the complete dataset generated by EPINUC (Proteins + Methylation + PTMs, Red line). Gray diagonal line indicates expected curve for random classification. <bold>b,</bold> Experimental scheme for EPINUC-seq. Histone PTMs are decoded as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1A</xref>. Next, histones are evicted by increasing salt concentration, retaining DNA strands at identical positions. Single-molecule DNA sequencing-by-synthesis is performed by cycles of incorporation of fluorescently labeled nucleotides and TIRF imaging<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">21</xref></sup>. Images represent four sequencing cycles, showing incorporation of cytosine (C), thymine (T), adenosine (A) and Guanine (G). For each x,y coordinate on the surface, sequence data is analyzed and integrated with the initial images that registered histone PTMs, revealing the modification state of the corresponding nucleosome. <bold>c,</bold> Single-molecule reads of H3K27me3 (blue) from a CRC patient overlap with ChIP−seq profile of H3K27me3 in the colon, but not the other indicated tissues. BM=bone marrow. <bold>d,</bold> EPINUC-seq analysis of plasma from stage IV CRC patient (patient 4044). Tissues and primary cell lines ranked by overlap significance with single-molecule plasma H3K4me3 (top) or H3K27me3 (bottom) positive reads. Black line corresponds to P value of 0.05. P values were determined by Z-test. <bold>e,</bold> Overlap significance of H3K4me3 single-molecule reads with ChIP-seq data<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref></sup> performed in the plasma of healthy and CRC patients. <bold>f,</bold> EPINUC-seq analysis of plasma from stage IV PDAC patient (patient 2974). Tissues and primary cell lines ranked by overlap significance with single-molecule H3K27me3 (Left) or H3K4me3 (Right) positive reads. <bold>g,h,</bold> Overlap significance of tissues and primary cell lines unique H3K36me3 profiles with single-molecule 5hmC reads from healthy versus late stage CRC <bold>(g)</bold> or early stage CRC <bold>(h),</bold> calculated as in (e). Black line corresponds to P value of 0.05. P values were determined by Z-test.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS145419-f004"/></fig></floats-group></article>