<!DOCTYPE article
 PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" article-type="preprint"><?all-math-mml yes?><?use-mml?><?origin ukpmcpa?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">bioRxiv</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>bioRxiv : the preprint server for biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub"/></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">EMS141183</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2021.12.17.473140</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="archive">PPR434811</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="europepmc-category"><subject>Covid-19</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Human genetic variants associated with COVID-19 severity are enriched in immune and epithelium regulatory networks</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>Zhanying</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>Xianwen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Duren</surname><given-names>Zhana</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Yong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">5</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A6">6</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CR1">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1"><label>1</label>CEMS, NCMIS, HCMS, MDIS, Academy of Mathematics and Systems Science, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Beijing 100190, China</aff><aff id="A2"><label>2</label>School of Mathematics, University of Chinese Academy of Sciences, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Beijing, China</aff><aff id="A3"><label>3</label>School of Life Sciences, Peking University, Beijing 100871, China</aff><aff id="A4"><label>4</label>Center for Human Genetics and Department of Genetics and Biochemistry, Clemson University, Greenwood, SC, 29646, USA</aff><aff id="A5"><label>5</label>Center for Excellence in Animal Evolution and Genetics, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Kunming 650223, China</aff><aff id="A6"><label>6</label>Key Laboratory of Systems Biology, Hangzhou Institute for Advanced Study, University of Chinese Academy of Sciences, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Hangzhou, 330106,China</aff><author-notes><corresp id="CR1"><label>*</label>Corresponding authors: <email>ywang@amss.ac.cn</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted"><day>07</day><month>02</month><year>2022</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="preprint"><day>21</day><month>12</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><permissions><ali:free_to_read/><license><ali:license_ref>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is licensed under a <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">CC BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p id="P1">Human genetic variants can influence the severity of symptoms being infected with SARS-COV-2. Several genome-wide association studies have identified human genomic risk SNPs associated with COVID-19 severity. However, the causal tissues or cell types of COVID-19 severity are uncertain and candidate genes associated with these human risk SNPs were investigated in genomic proximity instead of their functional cellular contexts. Here, we compiled regulatory networks of 77 human contexts and revealed those risk SNPs’ enriched cellular contexts and associated transcript factors, regulatory elements, and target genes. Twenty-one human contexts were identified and grouped into two categories: immune cells and epithelium cells. We further aggregated the regulatory networks of immune cells, epithelium cells, and immune-epithelium crosstalk and investigated their association with risk SNPs’ regulation. Two genomic clusters, chemokine receptors cluster and OAS cluster, showed the strongest association with COVID-19 severity and different regulations in immune and epithelium contexts. Our findings were supported by analysis on both microarray and whole genome sequencing based GWAS summary statistics.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec id="S1" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p id="P2">Coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) is an infectious disease caused by the SARS-CoV-2 virus. Most people infected with the virus will experience mild to moderate respiratory illness and recover without requiring special treatment. However, some people will become seriously ill and require medical attention. Scientists from all over the world have made great efforts to understand the genetic mechanism of COVID-19 severity, which may lead to efficient prevention stratagem and effective cure. Genome-wide association analysis (GWAS) has been the ideal option to find human genetic variants associated with severity phenotypes. Recently, applying GWAS to phenotypes of COVID-19, such as infection and severe respiratory symptoms, has helped us identify some risk loci associated with COVID-19. For example, the “The Severe COVID-19 GWAS Group” conducted a GWAS involving 1,980 patients with severe COVID-19 symptoms and detected SNPrsll385942 at locus 3p21.31 and rs657l52 at locus 9q34.2<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref></sup>. Erola P C. <italic>et al</italic>. used GWAS to study 2,244 critically ill COVID-19 patients from 208 UK intensive care units (ICUs) and found rs10735079 on 12q24.13 in a gene cluster encoding antiviral restriction enzyme activators (<italic>OAS1</italic>, <italic>OAS2</italic>, <italic>OAS3</italic>), rs2109069 on 19p13.2 near the gene <italic>TYK2</italic>, rs2109069 on 19p13.3 within <italic>DPP9</italic>, and rs2236757 on 21q22.1 in the interferon receptor gene <italic>IFNAR2<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">2</xref></sup></italic>. “The COVID-19 Host Genetics Initiative” conducted several GWAS, including “very severe respiratory confirmed COVID” and “hospitalized COVID”, and also found many potential loci<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">3</xref></sup>. These identified human risk loci allowed us to further understand the underlying mechanism of COVID-19 severity.</p><p id="P3">Interpreting these COVID-19 associated human genetic variants remains challenging since most genetic variants were located in the non-coding regulatory region with high linkage disequilibrium<sup>4-6</sup> and were functional in time- and space-specific contexts<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref></sup>. This implies that we must elucidate these genetic variants in the proper cellular contexts. Several works have been done to uncover the regulatory mechanism of genetic variants. For example, FUMA<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">8</xref></sup> and GREAT<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref></sup> used the routine way to link SNPs to the nearby genes. SMR<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref></sup> and Sherlock<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref></sup> utilized the expression information to find causal SNP affecting gene regulation. However, these methods didn’t consider either the direct cisregulation or the regulatory effects in biological network. Recently, we developed a method, PECA, to infer context specific regulatory network with paired expression and chromatin accessibility data from diverse cellular context<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref></sup> and then extended to PECA2 to reconstruct regulatory network for a single sample<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref></sup>. The reconstructed regulatory networks have been successfully applied to reveal critical regulations for time course data<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref></sup>. We noticed that the availability of the public available paired expression and chromatin accessibility data, such as ENCODE and ROADMAP, ensured the diversity in tissue source of the cells and the germ layer lineage representation. This allows us to run PECA2 to systematically construct a regulatory network atlas of 77 human contexts, which served as a valuable resource for genetic variants interpretation in multi-cellular contexts.</p><p id="P4">Here, we utilized these 77 regulatory networks to interpret the SNPs associated with COVID-19 severity. We found the relevant tissues of COVID-19 severity were categorized into two main cell types: immune cells and epithelium cells. Then in these two cell type categories, we illustrated the detailed SNP associated regulations: SNP located in regulatory elements (REs), their upstream transcription factors (TFs), and their downstream target genes (TGs). We found that two gene clusters (chemokine receptors and OAS cluster) showed different regulation patterns in two cell type categories. Our COVID-19 severity associated regulatory network will be promising to serve as a valuable perspective to study COVID-19.</p></sec><sec id="S2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="S3"><label>1</label><title>Human genetic variants of COVID-19 severity are enriched in immune and epithelium cells</title><p id="P5">We first collected paired expression and chromatin accessibility data from 76 human contexts and constructed a human regulatory network atlas. The samples covered all three germ layers, such as frontal cortex (ectoderm), primary T cells (mesoderm), and upper lobe of left lung (endoderm). With each sample’s paired expression and chromatin accessibility data as input, we used PECA2 model<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref></sup> to construct regulatory network for each context (<xref ref-type="sec" rid="S9">Methods</xref>). The basic unit of regulatory network is TF-REs-TG triplet and each triplet denotes that a TF binds on the REs and regulates a nearly TG.</p><p id="P6">We also included the regulatory network of cranial neural crest cells<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref></sup> (CNCC), a migratory cell population in early human craniofacial development, into our regulatory network atlas. Then we applied these regulatory networks of 77 human contexts to interpret genetic variants of COVID-19 severity.</p><p id="P7">We fetched the 542 SNPs with significant associations (P≤ 5 × 10<sup>-8</sup>) with “very severe respiratory confirmed COVID” (“A2_ALL” study in “The COVID-19 Host Genetics Initiatives”). To evaluate the relevance between SNPs and 77 human contexts, the fold enrichment (FE) score of these 542 SNPs in RE sets of 77 human contexts were calculated (<xref ref-type="sec" rid="S9">Methods</xref>). We set the threshold of FE score 3.0 and found that 21 contexts were relevant to COVID-19 severity, such as “primary monocytes” and “upper lobe of left lung” (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1A</xref>). Furthermore, these 21 contexts could be classified into two categories. The first category was immune cells, including 10 cell types: “Primary monocytes”, “Primary B cells”, “Jurkat”, “GM12878”, “Primary natural killer cells”, “CD4 primary cells”, “Fetal thymus”, “Primary T cells”, “CD8 primary Cells”, and “Hematopoietic multipotent progenitor cell”. The second category was epithelium cells and consisted of 11 cell types: “Vagina”, “Omental fat pad”, “Gastric”, “Upper lobe of left lung”, “Lower leg skin”, “Esophagus squamous epithelium”, “Esophagus muscularis mucosa”, “Fetal spleen”, “Subcutaneous adipose tissue”, “Spleen”, and “T47D”.</p><p id="P8">We further extracted sub-network that was associated with SNPs of COVID-19 severity in every relevant context (<xref ref-type="sec" rid="S9">Methods</xref>). For example, “Primary monocytes” was one of the immune cell types. And 12 SNPs were located in the 8 REs in regulatory network of “Primary monocytes” (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1B</xref>). These REs were predicted to regulate 9 TGs, such as <italic>CCR1</italic> and <italic>FYCO1</italic>. <italic>CCR1</italic> played a key role in T-cell-mediated respiratory inflammation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref></sup>. These REs were bound by immunity associated TFs, such as <italic>CEBPB</italic>/<italic>D</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">20</xref></sup> and <italic>FLI1</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">21</xref></sup>. On the other hand, “Upper lobe of left lung” was one of the epithelium cell type (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1C</xref>), and 8 REs were associated with 14 SNPs of COVID-19 severity and regulated 5 TGs, such as <italic>CCR1</italic> and <italic>OAS1</italic>. Polymorphisms of <italic>OAS1</italic> have been reported to affect susceptibility to a variety of viral diseases<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">23</xref></sup>CEBPD<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref></sup> and ETS2<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">25</xref></sup>.</p><p id="P9">In summary, we built a regulatory network atlas of 77 human contexts and leveraged their regulatory elements to reveal relevant contexts to human genetic variants of COVID-19 severity. Two categories of cell types were found: the first was epithelium cells and may be involved with susceptibility to viral diseases; the other category was immune cells and possibly linked to severity after being infected with disease. The relevance to two categories of cell types were reproduced by more recent GWAS with a larger cohort from HGI (Figure S1).</p></sec><sec id="S4"><label>2</label><title>Construction of SNP associated regulatory network of immune and epithelium cells</title><p id="P10">To further understand SNPs’ function in two categories of cell types, we constructed COVID-19 severity associated regulatory networks in immune cells and epithelium cells respectively. Briefly, we pooled the SNPs associated networks of 10 immune cell types into a COVID-19 severity associated regulatory network of immune cells. Similarly, we pooled the SNPs associated regulatory network of 11 epithelium cell types into a COVID-19 severity associated regulatory network of epithelium cells (<xref ref-type="sec" rid="S9">Methods</xref>).</p><p id="P11">In COVID-19 severity associated immune regulatory network, there were totally 17 TFs, 25 REs and 15 TGs associated with 38 SNPs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2A</xref>). This sub-regulatory network was highly associated with immune functions. For example, <italic>TCF3/7/12</italic> were important upstream TFs in regulatory network of immune cells and played vital roles during T-cell development<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27">27</xref></sup>. <italic>IRF1/3/4</italic> were critical TFs in the cellular differentiation of hematopoietic cells and in the regulation of gene expression in response to pathogen-derived danger signals<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">28</xref></sup>. <italic>CCR5</italic> was downstream TGs in this regulatory network, and it encoded a protein on the surface of white blood cells that is involved in the immune system<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">29</xref></sup>. We found that 2 TGs (<italic>CCR5</italic>, <italic>CXCR6</italic>) of the 15 immune TGs were also differentially expressed in blood samples of fatal COVID-19 patients<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">30</xref></sup> (<italic>P</italic> ≤ 0.014), which supported that our reconstructed sub-regulatory networks of immune cells were significantly associated with severity of COVID-19. In COVID-19 severity associated epithelium regulatory network, there were totally 16 TFs, 24 REs and 10 TGs associated with 42 SNPs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2B</xref>). This SNP associated regulatory network was involved with the functions of epithelium cells. For example, <italic>ETS2</italic>, which was core TF in regulatory network of epithelium cells, could promote epithelial-to- mesenchymal transition in renal fibrosis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">25</xref></sup>. <italic>ELF3</italic> was also essential for mesenchymal to epithelial transition<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31">31</xref></sup>. <italic>NBEAL2</italic> was a TG in epithelium regulatory network and the <italic>Nbeal2-deficient</italic> mice exhibited impaired development of functional granulation tissue due to severely reduced differentiation of myofibroblasts in the model of excisional skin wound repair<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32">32</xref></sup>. These literature evidence showed that our reconstructed SNP associated regulatory networks were promising to reveal COVID-19 severity associated regulations in immune and epithelium cells.</p><p id="P12">We further overlapped our SNP associated regulatory network with eQTL dataset. Our SNP associated regulatory network revealed the link between SNPs and genes by SNP’s location in REs.</p><p id="P13">For example, SNP “12:113364332:A:G” was located in RE “chr12:113364318-113364636” and “chr12:113364318-113364636” regulated <italic>OAS1</italic>, which gave the association between SNP</p><p id="P14">“ 12:113364332:A:G” and gene <italic>OSA1</italic>. In this way, we totally obtained 91 SNP-TG association from immune and epithelium regulatory networks. Then we collected significant variants-gene association of 49 tissues from GTEx v8. We found that our SNP-TG associations were highly reproducible by eQTL variants-gene association. First, there were 78 (85.7%) SNP-TG associations could be validated as an eQTL variant-gene association in at least one tissue. On the other hand, when we ranked the 49 tissues by the overlapping number of eQTL with our SNP-TG association, we found that the top ranked tissues were also immune and epithelium cell types (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>). For example, “esophagus mucosa”, which was one of epithelium cell types, ranked first among 49 tissues. There were some other tissues that were related to epithelium cells, such as “Cells Cultured fibroblasts”, “Skin Not Sun Exposed Suprapubic”, “Spleen”, “Skin Sun Exposed Lower leg”, “Lung”. And there were also immune tissues among the top ranked tissue, such as “Artery Tibial” and “Whole Blood”. To check if our SNP-TG associations were causally responsible for COVID-19 severity, we conducted colocalization analysis with GWAS summary statistics of COVID-19 severity and eQTL form GTEx by SMR<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref></sup>. We obtained 57 SNP-TG pairs in 49 tissues and found that 2 of our 91 SNP-TG association were validated by the colocalization analysis, which was significantly overlapped (<italic>P</italic> = 1 × 10<sup>-7</sup>). These two SNP-TG association were related to <italic>OAS3</italic>, revealing that “12:113376320:C:T” and “12:113375983:T:C” might causally regulate expression of <italic>OAS3</italic> and influenced severity of COVID-19 symptoms. These results showed that our COVID-19 severity associated regulatory network could be supported by independent eQTL dataset.</p><p id="P15">In summary, we have constructed COVID-19 severity associated regulatory network of immune cells and epithelium cells. These two regulatory networks were tightly linked to immune and epithelium functions and could be validated by eQTL of immune and epithelium tissues in GTEx.</p></sec><sec id="S5"><label>3</label><title>Associating two cell types’ regulatory networks revealed shared regulatory structure</title><p id="P16">After reconstructing and validating the regulatory networks of immune and epithelium cells, we next compared these two cell types to find conservation and divergence. We first compared the TFs, TGs, REs, and SNPs in the regulatory networks of immune and epithelium cells. For TFs, 7 TFs were shared by two cell types, such as <italic>ETS1</italic> and <italic>IRF1</italic>. There were 10 immune-specific TFs (such as <italic>TCF7</italic> and <italic>ELF1</italic>) and 9 epithelium-specific TFs (such as <italic>ETS2</italic> and <italic>KLF4</italic>). There were also 8 overlapped TGs (such as <italic>CCR1</italic>, <italic>FYCO1</italic>), 7 immune-specific TGs (such as <italic>CCR5</italic> and <italic>LZTFL1</italic>) and 2 epithelium-specific TGs (<italic>MATK</italic> and <italic>NBEAL2</italic>). For SNPs and REs, about half of them in immune regulatory network were shared by epithelium regulatory network (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>).</p><p id="P17">We found that the regulatory network could be clustered into four clusters according to their location and this clustering was shared between immune and epithelium cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2A, B</xref>). The first cluster was on chromosome 3. This cluster was involved with regulation of <italic>CCR1/2/5/9, CXCR6, FYCO1, LIMD1, LZTFL1, SACM1L, XCR1</italic> in immune cells and <italic>CCR1/2/5/9</italic>, <italic>CXCR6</italic>, <italic>NBEAL2</italic> in epithelium cells. The second cluster was located in chromosome 12 and involved with regulation of <italic>OAS1/2/3</italic> in both immune and epithelium cells. The third cluster was in chromosome 19. In immune cells, this cluster was associated with <italic>ARRDC5</italic> and in epithelium cells, it was associated with <italic>MATK</italic>. The last cluster was in chromosome 21 and linked to <italic>IFNAR2</italic> in two cell types. These four genetic variants associated regulatory clusters may exert genetic influence on infection and severity of COVID-19.</p><p id="P18">In the regulatory network of two cell types, we found two classes of upstream TFs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2A, B</xref>). The first class of TFs regulated most of the four regulatory clusters. For example, in regulatory network of immune cells, <italic>ETS1, TCF3</italic> and <italic>GATA3</italic> were involved with at least three regulatory clusters. And for the epithelium cells, <italic>ETS1, ETS2</italic>, and <italic>PITX1</italic> were classified into this class. Contrary to the broad regulation of the first class, the second class of TFs was only responsible for a small part of regulatory network. For example, in immune regulatory network, <italic>CEBPD, CEBPB, TCF7</italic>, <italic>FOS</italic>, <italic>JUNB</italic>, <italic>JUN</italic>, <italic>ELF1</italic> were only regulate REs in chromosome 3 regulatory cluster. And <italic>IRF3</italic>, <italic>IRF4</italic>, and <italic>MYC</italic> only responsible for regulations in chromosome 12 regulatory cluster. In the epithelium regulatory network, <italic>CEBPD</italic>, <italic>JUNB</italic>, <italic>IRF1</italic>, <italic>ID1</italic>, <italic>RORA</italic>, <italic>MYC</italic>, and <italic>KLF4</italic> were only involved with the regulatory of chromosome 3 regulatory cluster. <italic>ID2</italic>, <italic>IRF3</italic>, <italic>AHR</italic>, <italic>STAT2</italic>, <italic>ELF3</italic> was associated with the chromosome 12 regulatory cluster.</p><p id="P19">Through the comparison of two cell types’ regulatory networks, we found these two cell types shared many TFs, TGs, REs, and SNPs. The regulatory structure (four regulatory clusters based on location and two classes of upstream TFs) were conserved in two cell types. Despite the shared regulatory structure, there were also many cell-type-specific TFs, TGs, REs, and SNPs.</p></sec><sec id="S6"><label>4</label><title>Chromosome 3 and 12 clusters showed distinct regulatory program in immune and epithelium cells</title><p id="P20">From the above analysis of regulatory structure, we noticed that there are two relatively denser clusters in immune and epithelium regulatory: chromosome 3 and chromosome 12 clusters,indicating that they may play an essential role in COVID-19 severity. Here we focused on these two regulatory clusters.</p><p id="P21">For regulatory cluster in chromosome 12, these regulatory programs were mainly involved with <italic>OAS</italic> cluster (<italic>OAS1/2/3</italic>) in ten immune cell types and nine epithelium cell types. These <italic>OAS</italic> cluster was closely associated with immune and epithelium functions. For example, <italic>OAS1</italic> polymorphisms played potential roles in respiratory infection from human bronchial epithelial cells<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">23</xref></sup>. The <italic>OAS2</italic> protein is a well-known innate immune activated antiviral enzyme catalyzing synthesis of 2’-5’- oligoadenylate for RNase L activation and inhibition of viral propagation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33">33</xref></sup>. We found that the REs of this cluster in different cell types were mainly distributed around the promoter of <italic>OAS3</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5A</xref>) and there were many COVID-19 severity associated SNPs within these REs, which was consistent among immune and epithelium cell types. To add additional evidence of regulation in this area, we collected previously published promoter-capture Hi-C (PCHi-C) data of primary blood cell types<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34">34</xref></sup>. We used the PCHi-C interactions that have CHiCAGO scores ≥ 5 in at least one analyzed cell type and found there was a loop between promoter of <italic>OAS3</italic> and promoter of <italic>OAS2</italic>. This observation induced a hypothesis that the REs around the promoter of <italic>OAS3</italic> were cis- regulatory elements of <italic>OAS2</italic> in immune cells. To validate this hypothesis, we first checked the REs regulating the three OAS genes in 10 immune cell types and found that all 15 REs were predicted to regulate <italic>OAS2</italic>, 13 REs were predicted to regulate <italic>OAS1</italic> and only 7 REs were predicted to regulate <italic>OAS3</italic>, which revealed that more evidence supported that REs in this locus regulated <italic>OAS2</italic>. Then we checked the expression of three <italic>OAS</italic> genes and found <italic>OAS2’s</italic> expression was the highest among <italic>OAS</italic> cluster in immune cell types (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5B</xref>). We also computed the averaged correlation between the openness score of REs in <italic>OAS3’s</italic> promoter and expression of three OAS genes across 148 samples of human (<bold>Table S1</bold>). The result showed that the accessibility of these REs was more correlated to expression of <italic>OAS2</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5C</xref>). In summary, these evidence of PCHi-C loop, regulatory network, expression data, and RE-TG correlation indicated that in immune cells, the REs around <italic>OAS3’s</italic> promoter were more likely to regulate <italic>OAS2</italic>.</p><p id="P22">For regulatory cluster in chromosome 3, these regulatory programs were mainly involved with chemokine receptor (<italic>CCR1/2/5/9, CXCR6</italic>, and <italic>XCR1</italic>) in eight immune cell types and eight epithelium cell types. In literature, there were many reports that these chemokine receptors were associated with the function of both immune and epithelium cells<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">29</xref></sup>. We found five main regulatory areas that were associated with SNPs and regulated these chemokine receptors (we name them as LOC1-LOC5, <bold>Figure 6A</bold>). Some of these REs’ regulation was shared by two cell types. For example, LOC3 were predicted to regulate <italic>CCR1</italic> in both immune and epithelium cells. And there was also a PCHi-C loop between LOC3 and <italic>CCR1</italic>. The other LOCs’ regulatory programs were different. For example, LOC1 and LOC2 were immune-specific REs and regulated <italic>CCR9</italic> and <italic>CXCR6</italic>. While REs in LOC4 were shared by two cell types, they were predicted to regulate <italic>CCR5</italic> in immune cells but regulate <italic>CCR1</italic> in epithelium cells. LOC4 and <italic>CCR5</italic> were also contacted by a PCHi-C loop in blood cells. Similar to LOC4, LOC5 regulated <italic>CCR2/5</italic> in immune cells but only regulate <italic>CCR2</italic> in epithelium. The expression of these chemokine receptors supported the regulation above: <italic>CCR1/2/5/9</italic> and <italic>CXCR6</italic> were relatively high expressed in immune cells but only <italic>CCR1</italic> and <italic>CCR2</italic> were expressed in epithelium cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6B</xref>). We also checked the RE-TG correlation and found the above regulations were also supported. LOC1 showed the highest correlation with <italic>CCR9</italic>.</p><p id="P23">LOC2 were more correlated with <italic>CXCR6</italic> and <italic>CCR9</italic>. LOC3 was most associated with <italic>CCR1</italic>. LOC4 showed higher correlation with <italic>CCR1</italic> and <italic>CCR5</italic>. And LOC5 was correlated with <italic>CCR5</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6C</xref>).</p><p id="P24">Taken together, we found some shared and distinct regulatory programs in immune and epithelium by detailed study of two main COVID-19 severity associated regulatory cluster on chromosome 3 and 12. These conserved and divergent regulations may give biological insights about how virus infected human through epithelium cells and how human defensed SARS-COV-2 with our immune system.</p></sec><sec id="S7"><label>5</label><title>Analyzing whole genome sequencing based GWAS summary statistics reproduced relevant immune and epithelium cells and refined the regulatory networks</title><p id="P25">Microarray genotyping based genome-wide association studies (GWAS) have been the most common approach for identifying disease associations across the whole genome and can interrogate over 4 million markers per sample. Whole-genome sequencing provides a comprehensive base-bybase method for interrogating the 3.2 billion bases of the human genome. Higher resolution GWAS summary statistics hold the promise to reveal richer and more accurate genetic variants. We noticed that Kousathanas <italic>et al</italic>. used whole genome sequencing data (WGS) of a larger cohort to conduct GWAS analysis and found 1,322 SNPs (P≤ 5 × 10<sup>-8</sup>) with significant association with severity with COVID-19<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35">35</xref></sup>. We then used this independent data to validate and refine our relevant contexts and regulatory networks.</p><p id="P26">We first conducted the SNP enrichment analysis on these 1,322 significant SNPs to find relevant contexts. Eighteen cellular contexts obtained FE score ≥3.0 and were grouped into two categories: immune cells such as “Primary monocytes”, “CD4 primary cells” and epithelium cells such as “Upper lobe of left lung”. This results faithfully reproduced our results in microarray genotyping based GWAS data that human genetic variants of COVID-19 severity were enriched in immune and epithelium cells. Furthermore, this WGS genotyping based GWAS also revealed that immune cells were more associated with severity of COVID-19 that epithelium cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7A</xref>). Next, we sought to refine our regulatory networks of immune and epithelium cells with the overlapped SNPs of the WGS based GWAS and previous microarray based GWAS. We found that among the 38 SNPs of the previous reconstructed regulatory network of immune cells, 25 SNPs were reproducible in the WGS based GWAS. These 25 SNPs formed a regulatory network of immune cell, which include 12 TGs such as <italic>CCR1/2/5/9</italic>, 14 TFs such as <italic>FLI1, JUNB, CEBPD</italic>, and 20 REs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7B</xref>). And for epithelium cells, we found that among the 42 SNPs of the previous reconstructed regulatory network, 22 SNPs were also significant in the WGS based GWAS. These 22 SNPs gave a regulatory network of epithelium cell, which include 6 TGs such as <italic>CCR1/2, FYCO1</italic>, 14 TFs such as <italic>ETS1/2, KLF4</italic>, and 16 REs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7C</xref>).</p><p id="P27">In summary, we conducted regulatory network analysis with a recent published WGS based GWAS and validated our findings that human genetic variants of COVID-19 severity were enriched in immune and epithelium cells. We also used the reproducible SNPs to obtain refined regulatory networks of immune and epithelium cells.</p></sec></sec><sec id="S8" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p id="P28">The COVID-19 pandemic has influenced human’s life all over the world. Scientists made their efforts to gain more understanding of pathology of COVID-19 and to find effective cure. GWAS is a powerful tool to discover suspicious loci for interesting traits. By profiling phenotype and genotype of COVID-19 infected people, the “COVID-19 host genetics initiative” had conducted GWAS analysis with more and more power<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36">36</xref></sup>. Through these GWAS, many risk loci that may be associated with COVID-19 infection and severity were found. Following these discoveries, we used regulatory network atlas to interpret these risk loci and sought to gain biological insights of COVID-19.</p><p id="P29">First, we found that COVID-19 severity associated SNPs were mainly enriched in two types of human contexts: immune cells and epithelium cells. We used another GWAS of COVID-19 severity with larger cohort (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.covid19hg.org/results/r6/">https://www.covid19hg.org/results/r6/</ext-link>) to show that the association with immune cells and epithelium cells were quite reproducible (Figure S1). We then reconstructed the COVID-19 severity associated regulatory network in the two major contexts. The COVID-19 severity associated regulatory networks were validated by recently published RNA-seq data of COVID-19 patients and eQTL from GTEx. And further analysis revealed regulatory structure of COVID-19 associated regulatory networks: the four regulatory clusters and two classes of upstream TFs. The regulatory structure showed both conservation and divergence between two of cell types. Then we focused on two important regulatory clusters (OAS cluster and chemokine receptor cluster) and revealed the causal genes and differential regulation between two cell types. Finally, analysis on a recent WGS based GWAS with a larger cohort validated the two COVID-19 severity’s relevant cell types and refined the associated regulatory networks.</p><p id="P30">Several factors hindered the post-GWAS analysis of COVID-19. First of all, one more powerful GWAS with larger cohort is in need for such a complex trait. In this paper, the GWAS only detected 542 SNPs that significantly associated with COVID-19’s symptoms, which is not comparative to normal phenotype, such as height or BMI. Some efforts have been made to improve the power of GWAS. For example, the most recent GWAS conducted by “COVID-19 host genetics initiative” has included more than 8,000 very severe respiratory confirmed cases into analysis. On the other hand, a more comprehensive regulatory network atlas is promising for better understanding of COVID-19 severity. Although our current regulatory network atlas has covered many tissues, it is still far from complete and is limited in cell type resolution. As the symptoms of COVID-19 are involved with many organs, a more comprehensive regulatory network atlas, even at cell type level from single cell multi-omics data, will interpret more genetic variants associated with COVID-19.</p></sec><sec id="S9" sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec id="S10"><title>Construction of regulatory network from paired expression and chromatin accessibility data</title><p id="P31">We utilized PECA2 to infer genome-wide and context-specific regulatory networks based on gene expression and chromatin accessibility data in that context<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref></sup>. Given paired RNA-seq and ATAC-seq data for a sample, PECA2 hypothesized that TF regulated the downstream TG by binding at REs. The regulatory strength of a transcription factor (TF) on a target gene (TG) was quantified by the trans-regulation score, which was calculated by integrating information from multiple regulatory elements (REs) that may mediate the activity of the TF to regulate the TG. A prior TF-TG correlation across external public data from ENCODE database was included in the trans-regulation score definition to distinguish the TFs sharing the same binding motif (i.e., TFs from the same family).</p><p id="P32">We collected paired expression and chromatin accessibility data of 76 human tissues or cell lines(<bold>Table S2</bold>) and applied PECA2 to these data to obtain regulatory networks of 76 human contexts. Furthermore, we recently constructed high-quality regulatory network of cranial neural crest<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref></sup> and we included it into our analysis to form regulatory network atlas of 77 human contexts.</p></sec><sec id="S11"><title>Fold enrichment score of SNPs in given region set</title><p id="P33">Given a group of SNPs and a RE set, we defined the fold enrichment (FE) score as follows, <disp-formula id="FD1"><mml:math id="M1"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="P34">Where <italic>P<sub>r</sub></italic> was the number of SNPs in REs. <italic>L<sub>r</sub></italic> was the length of the REs. <italic>P</italic> was the total number of SNPs. <italic>L</italic> was the genome length.</p><p id="P35">We calculated the <italic>FE</italic> score of 542 SNPs of COVID-19 severity in RE sets of 77 human contexts and used a criterion of <italic>FE</italic> ≥ 3 to find 21 contexts that associated with COVID-19 severity. The FE score was also computed in the 1,322 SNPs of a recent GWAS. Under the same threshold, 18 contexts were found to be relevant to severity of COVID-19.</p></sec><sec id="S12"><title>Extraction of SNPs associated regulatory network in given tissue and two categories</title><p id="P36">Given a tissue, we check every RE in its regulatory network, if there was at least one SNP that was located in this RE, we extracted this RE and its upstream TFs and downstream TGs. We linked the SNPs in RE and this RE with edges and the SNPs, REs, TFs, TGs formed a SNP-associated regulatory network in a given tissue.</p><p id="P37">For 11 tissues of immune cells, we union the SNPs, REs, TFs, TGs. We assigned an edge to SNP-RE if it existed in at least one tissue’s SNP associated regulatory network, assigned an edge to TF-RE if it existed in at least one tissue’s SNP associated regulatory network, assigned an edge to RE-TG if it existed in at least one tissue’s SNP associated regulatory network. After the union and edge assignment, we constructed a regulatory network of immune cells. The regulatory network of epithelium cells was constructed with the same procedure.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack id="S13"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We acknowledge funding from the Strategic Priority Research Program of the Chinese Academy of Sciences (XDPB17), National Key Research and Development Program of China (2020YFA0712402), and the National Natural Science Foundation of China (grants 12025107,11871463, 61621003, 11688101). The Genotype-Tissue Expression (GTEx) Project was supported by the Common Fund of the Office of the Director of the National Institutes of Health, and by NCI, NHGRI, NHLBI, NIDA, NIMH, and NINDS. The data used for the analyses described in this manuscript were obtained fromthe GTEx Portal under dbGaP accession number phs000424.v8.p2 on 12/09/2020.</p></ack><sec id="S14" sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p id="P38">The GWAS summary statistics of COVID-19 severity (“A2_ALL” study) was download at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.covid19hg.org/results/r4/">https://www.covid19hg.org/results/r4/</ext-link>. The GWAS summary statistics from WGS data were download at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://genomicc.org/data/">https://genomicc.org/data/</ext-link>. The constructed regulatory network atlas was freely available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/AMSSwanglab">https://github.com/AMSSwanglab</ext-link>. The eQTL dataset was download at the GTEx portal <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.gtexportal.org/home/datasets">https://www.gtexportal.org/home/datasets</ext-link>. The collected paired expression and chromatin accessibility data was summarized in Table S1 and Table S2.</p></sec><fn-group><fn id="FN1" fn-type="conflict"><p id="P39"><bold>Declaration of interests</bold></p><p id="P40">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><ref id="R1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Severe Covid GG</collab><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genomewide Association Study of Severe Covid-19 with Respiratory Failure</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2020</year><volume>383</volume><fpage>1522</fpage><lpage>1534</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pairo-Castineira</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genetic mechanisms of critical illness in Covid-19</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2020</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>Initiative C-HG</collab><article-title>The COVID-19 Host Genetics Initiative, a global initiative to elucidate the role of host genetic factors in susceptibility and severity of the SARS-CoV-2 virus pandemic</article-title><source>Eur J Hum Genet</source><year>2020</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>715</fpage><lpage>718</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Wijmenga</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Withoff</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>From genome-wide association studies to disease mechanisms: celiac disease as a model for autoimmune diseases</article-title><source>Seminars in Immunopathology</source><year>2012</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>567</fpage><lpage>580</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smemo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Obesity-associated variants within FTO form long-range functional connections with IRX3</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2014</year><volume>507</volume><fpage>371</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Claussnitzer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>FTO Obesity Variant Circuitry and Adipocyte Browning in Humans</article-title><source>New England Journal of Medicine</source><year>2015</year><volume>373</volume><fpage>895</fpage><lpage>907</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Andersson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>An atlas of active enhancers across human cell types and tissues</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2014</year><volume>507</volume><fpage>455</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Taskesen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>van Bochoven</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Posthuma</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Functional mapping and annotation of genetic associations with FUMA</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2017</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>1826</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McLean</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>GREAT improves functional interpretation of cis-regulatory regions</article-title><source>Nat Biotechnol</source><year>2010</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>495</fpage><lpage>501</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Integration of summary data from GWAS and eQTL studies predicts complex trait gene targets</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><year>2016</year><volume>48</volume><fpage>481</fpage><lpage>7</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Sherlock: detecting gene-disease associations by matching patterns of expression QTL and GWAS</article-title><source>Am J Hum Genet</source><year>2013</year><volume>92</volume><fpage>667</fpage><lpage>80</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Duren</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Modeling gene regulation from paired expression and chromatin accessibility data</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2017</year><volume>114</volume><fpage>E4914</fpage><lpage>E4923</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Duren</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Xin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Time course regulatory analysis based on paired expression and chromatin accessibility data</article-title><source>Genome Res</source><year>2020</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>622</fpage><lpage>634</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Chromatin accessibility landscape and regulatory network of high-altitude hypoxia adaptation</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2020</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>4928</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>ZY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>hReg-CNCC reconstructs a regulatory network in human cranial neural crest cells and annotates variants in a developmental context</article-title><source>Communications Biology</source><year>2021</year><volume>4</volume></element-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schaller</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kallal</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name><surname>Lukacs</surname><given-names>NW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A key role for CC chemokine receptor 1 in T-cell-mediated respiratory inflammation</article-title><source>Am J Pathol</source><year>2008</year><volume>172</volume><fpage>386</fpage><lpage>94</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kinoshita</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Akira</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kishimoto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A member of the C/EBP family, NF-IL6 beta, forms a heterodimer and transcriptionally synergizes with NF-IL6</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>1992</year><volume>89</volume><fpage>1473</fpage><lpage>6</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chinery</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Brockman</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Dransfield</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name><name><surname>Coffey</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antioxidant-induced nuclear translocation of CCAAT/enhancer-binding protein beta. A critical role for protein kinase A-mediated phosphorylation of Ser299</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1997</year><volume>272</volume><fpage>30356</fpage><lpage>61</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>MEKK1 plays a critical role in activating the transcription factor C/EBP-beta-dependent gene expression in response to IFN-gamma</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2002</year><volume>99</volume><fpage>7945</fpage><lpage>50</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pless</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>G9a-mediated lysine methylation alters the function of CCAAT/enhancer-binding protein-beta</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2008</year><volume>283</volume><fpage>26357</fpage><lpage>63</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Characterization of the relationship between FLI1 and immune infiltrate level in tumour immune microenvironment for breast cancer</article-title><source>Journal of Cellular and Molecular Medicine</source><year>2020</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>5501</fpage><lpage>5514</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Burgner</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Jamieson</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Blackwell</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic susceptibility to infectious diseases: big is beautiful, but will bigger be even better?</article-title><source>Lancet Infectious Diseases</source><year>2006</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>653</fpage><lpage>663</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Noguchi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Differential effects of a common splice site polymorphism on the generation of OAS1 variants in human bronchial epithelial cells</article-title><source>Hum Immunol</source><year>2013</year><volume>74</volume><fpage>395</fpage><lpage>401</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cassel</surname><given-names>TN</given-names></name><name><surname>Nord</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>C/EBP transcription factors in the lung epithelium</article-title><source>Am J Physiol Lung Cell Mol Physiol</source><year>2003</year><volume>285</volume><elocation-id>L773-81</elocation-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kabbout</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>ETS2 mediated tumor suppressive function and MET oncogene inhibition in human non-small cell lung cancer</article-title><source>Clin Cancer Res</source><year>2013</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>3383</fpage><lpage>95</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Staal</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Clevers</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tcf/Lef transcription factors during T-cell development: unique and overlapping functions</article-title><source>Hematol J</source><year>2000</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>3</fpage><lpage>6</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>TCF-1-Centered Transcriptional Network Drives an Effector versus Exhausted CD8 T Cell-Fate Decision</article-title><source>Immunity</source><year>2019</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>840</fpage><lpage>855</lpage><elocation-id>e5</elocation-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tamura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Yanai</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Savitsky</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Taniguchi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The IRF family transcription factors in immunity and oncogenesis</article-title><source>Annu Rev Immunol</source><year>2008</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>535</fpage><lpage>84</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jiao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Recent Advances Targeting CCR5 for Cancer and Its Role in Immuno-Oncology</article-title><source>Cancer Res</source><year>2019</year><volume>79</volume><fpage>4801</fpage><lpage>4807</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wargodsky</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>C</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name><surname>LaFleur</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamane</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Benjenk</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>RNA Sequencing in COVID-19 patients identifies neutrophil activation biomarkers as a promising diagnostic platform for infections</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2022</year><volume>17</volume><elocation-id>e0261679</elocation-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sengez</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The Transcription Factor Elf3 Is Essential for a Successful Mesenchymal to Epithelial Transition</article-title><source>Cells</source><year>2019</year><volume>8</volume></element-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Deppermann</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Gray platelet syndrome and defective thrombo-inflammation in Nbeal2-deficient mice</article-title><source>J Clin Invest</source><year>2013</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mozzi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>OASes and STING: adaptive evolution in concert</article-title><source>Genome Biol Evol</source><year>2015</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>1016</fpage><lpage>32</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Javierre</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Lineage-Specific Genome Architecture Links Enhancers and Non-coding Disease Variants to Target Gene Promoters</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2016</year><volume>167</volume><fpage>1369</fpage><lpage>1384</lpage><elocation-id>e19</elocation-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kousathanas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Whole genome sequencing reveals host factors underlying critical Covid-19</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2022</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pairo-Castineira</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genetic mechanisms of critical illness in COVID-19</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2021</year><volume>591</volume><fpage>92</fpage><lpage>98</lpage></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>(A). 21 COVID-19 severity relevant contexts ranked by fold enrichment (FE) scores. Red: immune cells. Blue: epithelium cells. (B). COVID-19 SNP associated regulatory of “Primary monocytes”, which is an immune cell type. (C). COVID-19 SNP associated regulatory of “Upper lobe of left lung”, which is an epithelium cell type.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS141183-f001"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>(A). COVID-19 severity associated regulatory network of immune cells. (B). COVID-19 severity associated regulatory network of epithelium cells.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS141183-f002"/></fig><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Overlapping of SNP-TGs inferred from our regulatory networks with eQTL of 49 tissues in GTEx. The tissues are ranked by the number of eQTL overlaps.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS141183-f003"/></fig><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Overlapping of SNP, RE, TF, TG between immune regulatory network and epithelium regulatory network.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS141183-f004"/></fig><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>(A). SNPs, REs and PCHi-C loop associated with <italic>OAS1/2/3</italic>. The RE tracks consisted of 11 immune cell types and 9 epithelium cell types. PCHi-C loops were from blood samples. The number labels around the RE were indicator of RE's target genes. (B). Expression of <italic>OAS1/2/3</italic> in immune and epithelium cells. (C). Correlations between accessibility of REs and expression of <italic>OAS1/2/3</italic>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS141183-f005"/></fig><fig id="F6" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>(A).SNPs, REs and PCHi-C loop associated with chemokine receptors. The RE tracks consisted of 11 immune cell types and 9 epithelium cell types. PCHi-C loops were from blood samples. The labels around REs were indicator of TGs: C1-CCR1, C2-CCR2, C5-CCR5, C6-CXCR6, C9-CCR9, X1-XCR1. (B). Expression of chemokine receptors in immune and epithelium cells. (C). Correlations between accessibility of REs and expression of chemokine receptors.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS141183-f006"/></fig><fig id="F7" position="float"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p>(A). Analyzing whole genome sequencing based GWAS summary statistics revealed 18 COVID-19 severity relevant contexts, which are ranked by fold enrichment (FE) scores. Red: immune cells. Blue: epithelium cells. (B). Refined COVID-19 severity associated immune regulatory network. (C). Refined COVID-19 severity associated epithelium regulatory network.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS141183-f007"/></fig></floats-group></article>