<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="preprint">
<?all-math-mml yes?>
<?use-mml?>
<?origin ukpmcpa?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">bioRxiv</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>bioRxiv : the preprint server for biology</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub"/>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">EMS140407</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2021.11.26.470043</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="archive">PPR426191</article-id>
<article-version article-version-type="publisher-id">1</article-version>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>A recombinant SARS-CoV-2 RBD antigen expressed in insect cells elicits immunogenicity and confirms safety in animal models</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Choque-Guevara</surname>
<given-names>Ricardo</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Poma-Acevedo</surname>
<given-names>Astrid</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Montesinos-Millán</surname>
<given-names>Ricardo</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Rios-Matos</surname>
<given-names>Dora</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Gutiérrez-Manchay</surname>
<given-names>Kristel</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Montalvan</surname>
<given-names>Angela</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Quiñones-Garcia</surname>
<given-names>Stefany</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>de Grecia Cauti-Mendoza</surname>
<given-names>Maria</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Agurto-Arteaga</surname>
<given-names>Andres</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ramirez-Ortiz</surname>
<given-names>Ingrid</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Criollo-Orozco</surname>
<given-names>Manuel</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Huaccachi-Gonzales</surname>
<given-names>Edison</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lázaro</surname>
<given-names>Yomara K. Romero</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Perez-Martinez</surname>
<given-names>Norma</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Isasi-Rivas</surname>
<given-names>Gisela</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Sernaque-Aguilar</surname>
<given-names>Yacory</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Villanueva-Pérez</surname>
<given-names>Doris</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Vallejos-Sánchez</surname>
<given-names>Katherine</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Fernández-Sánchez</surname>
<given-names>Manolo</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Guevara</surname>
<given-names>Luis</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Fernández-Díaz</surname>
<given-names>Manolo</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zimic</surname>
<given-names>Mirko</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CR1">*</xref>
<on-behalf-of>COVID-19 Working Group in Perú</on-behalf-of>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="A1">
<label>1</label>Laboratorios de investigación y desarrollo, FARVET SAC, Chincha, Ica, Perú</aff>
<aff id="A2">
<label>2</label>Laboratorio de Bioinformática, Biología Molecular y Desarrollos Tecnológicos. Laboratorios de Investigación y Desarrollo. Facultad de Ciencias y Filosofía. Universidad Peruana Cayetano Heredia, Lima, Peru</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="CR1">
<label>*</label>Corresponding author, <email>mirko.zimic@upch.pe</email>(MZ)</corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted">
<day>01</day>
<month>12</month>
<year>2021</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="preprint">
<day>30</day>
<month>11</month>
<year>2021</year>
</pub-date>
<permissions>
<ali:free_to_read/>
<license>
<ali:license_ref>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
<license-p>This work is licensed under a <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">CC BY-NC 4.0 International license</ext-link>.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p id="P1">COVID-19 pandemic has accelerated the development of vaccines against its etiologic agent, SARS-CoV-2. However, the emergence of new variants of the virus requires new immunization strategies in addition to the current vaccines approved for human administration. In the present report, the immunological and safety evaluation in mice and hamsters of a subunit vaccine based on the RBD sub-domain with two adjuvants of oil origin is described.</p>
<p id="P2">The RBD protein was expressed in insect cells and purified by chromatography until &gt;95% purity. The protein was shown to have the appropriate folding as determined by ELISA and flow cytometry binding assays to its receptor, as well as by its detection by hamster immune anti-S1 sera under non-reducing conditions.</p>
<p id="P3">In immunization assays in mice and hamsters, the purified RBD formulated with adjuvants based on oil-water emulsifications and squalene was able to stimulate specific neutralizing antibodies and confirm the secretion of IFN-γ after stimulating spleen cells with the purified RBD. The vaccine candidate was shown to be safe, as demonstrated by the histopathological analysis in lungs, liver and kidney. These results demonstrate the potential of the purified RBD administered with adjuvants through an intramuscular route, to be evaluated in a challenge against SARS-CoV-2 and determine its ability to confer protection against infection.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>RBD</kwd>
<kwd>vaccine</kwd>
<kwd>SARS-CoV-2</kwd>
<kwd>COVID-19</kwd>
<kwd>squalene</kwd>
<kwd>adjuvant</kwd>
<kwd>recombinant protein</kwd>
<kwd>SF9</kwd>
<kwd>baculovirus</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="S1" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p id="P4">In December 2019, a phylogenetically related SARS-CoV virus, later identified as SARS-CoV-2, caused an outbreak of atypical pneumonia in Wuhan. This virus is associated with a high rate of transmission, the appearance of symptoms such as fever and respiratory difficulties leads later to pulmonary and systemic failure with an exacerbated inflammatory condition that can lead to death [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref>]. The high transmission and mortality, coupled with the lack of effective treatment, justify the urgent development of vaccine candidates.</p>
<p id="P5">SARS-CoV-2 recognizes the Angiotensin Converting Enzyme-2 (ACE-2), which belongs to the surface of several types of human cells. The glycosylated Spike (S) protein gives the virus the ability to bind to the cell membrane and then fuse for the entry of viral RNA. The Spike protein has the S1 domain, and at its most distal end has a receptor binding sub-domain (RBD) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">2</xref>]. The RBD is responsible for the binding of the virus to the ACE-2 receptor of host cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">4</xref>]. The amino acid sequences of RBD protein are being subjected to a positive selective pressure, which is conferring greater affinity to the ACE-2 receptor, this is due to the change in the structural conformation of ACE-2 binding [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref>]. An important mechanism of neutralization is the blockade of ACE-2 binding to the virus, so candidate vaccines based on the RBD domain induce a strong immune response, generating a remarkable humoral and cellular response [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">8</xref>]. Several vaccine candidates use the baculovirus expression system. Researchers widely use this system due to its easy manipulation and the ability to produce complex proteins with suitable glycosylation patterns [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref>]. Currently, human and veterinary vaccines produced in this system are widely commercialized [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>]. Additionally, to the successful production of some large-scale vaccine candidates for clinical trials [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref>]. However, these vaccines require appropriate adjuvants to stimulate a strong immune response.</p>
<p id="P6">There are several types of adjuvants on the market, which have an immunogenic effect when inoculated in animals and humans: those that are based on Alum [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">3</xref>], as well as emulsions based on mineral oils or non-mineral [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref>], which are the most widely used and approved for use in humans [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref>]. Alum-based adjuvants are not highly effective in stimulating the cellular immune response of either Th1 or Th2 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref>]. These adjuvants require improvements in their concentration and the type of aluminum used to generate a cellular-type immune response; however, these could cause necrosis or tissue damage in the inoculation area [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref>]. This has led to the use of emulsions based on squalene-in-water, which come in formulations according to the interface where they are prepared: oil-in-water (O/W), which are microdroplets of oil in the aqueous phase together with the antigen; and water-in-oil (W O), microdroplets of water containing the antigen, in an oily phase [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref>].</p>
<p id="P7">In the present study, purified RBD administered through an intramuscular route with two different oil adjuvants was evaluated for immunogenicity and safety in mice and hamsters.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S2" sec-type="materials | methods">
<title>Material and methods</title>
<sec id="S3">
<title>Animals</title>
<p id="P8">This study used thirty-five female albino mice (<italic>Mus musculus</italic>) strain BALB/c of 5-8 weeks-old and 5 female Golden Syrian hamsters (<italic>Mesocricetus auratus</italic>) of 8-10 weeks-old obtained from the Universidad peruana Cayetano Heredia (UPCH) and the Instituto Nacional de Salud (INS-Peru), respectively.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S4">
<title>Adjuvants</title>
<p id="P9">An oil-in-water (ESSAI 1849101) hereinafter defined as A1, and modified adjuvant resulting from a mix of water-in-oil adjuvant and squalene, hereinafter defined as A3 were used.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S5">
<title>Ethics statement</title>
<p id="P10">The use of animals was aligned to ethical protocols approved by the Bioethics Committee of the Universidad Nacional Hermilio Valdizán and the animal’s ethical Committee at the Universidad Peruana Cayetano Heredia, registered as approval certificates of Research Project No. 1, 2, and 10 and E011-06-20, respectively.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="S6">
<title>Recombinant RBD expression in Sf9 cells</title>
<sec id="S7">
<title>Recombinant baculovirus generation</title>
<p id="P11">The amino acid sequence of the SARS-CoV-2 spike protein was obtained from the SARS-CoV-2 reference genome Wuhan-Hu-1 (Genbank accession number: NC_045512.2). For the design of RBD construct, the Pro330-Ser530 region was selected. The sequence was optimized for expression in insect cells, the gp67 secretion signal peptide was added at the N-terminal and a 10xHis-tag in the C-terminal region. The resulting sequence was chemically synthesized by (GenScript Laboratories, USA) and cloned at the EcoRI/HindIII sites of pFastBac1 (Thermo Fisher Scientific, USA) under the control of the polyhedrin promoter and upstream of the SV40 polyadenylation sequence. Transformation of competent DH10BAC cells and transfection of Sf9 cells were performed with the Bac-to-Bac technology following the manufacturer’s instructions (Thermo Fisher Scientific, USA).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S8">
<title>Propagation of baculovirus and expression of RBD in Sf9 insect cells culture</title>
<p id="P12">The recombinant baculovirus was amplified in Sf9 cells (Thermo Fisher Scientific, USA) to a density of 2 x 10<sup>6</sup> cells/mL in ExCell 420 medium (Sigma Aldrich, USA) supplemented with 5% fetal bovine serum (Gibco, USA). Cultures were infected at a multiplicity of infection (MOI) of 0.4. At 48 hours post infection (hpi), cultures were centrifuged at 4500 rpm for 15 minutes. The supernatants were collected and titrated by plaque assay. Viral stocks were stored at 4°C until use.</p>
<p id="P13">For protein production, 7 L of Sf9 cell culture at a density of 2 x 10<sup>6</sup> cells/mL were infected with the baculovirus at a MOI of 3 using a Biostat B plus bioreactor (Sartorius, Germany). The following conditions were maintained during the culture period: temperature at 28°C, pH at 6.2, 50% dissolved oxygen (DO) with an oxygen flow rate of 0.1 vvm via micro sparger and agitation at 150 rpm. At 48 hours post-infection, the cultures were centrifuged at 4500 rpm for 15 minutes and the supernatant was filtered through a 0.22 μm membrane.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="S9">
<title>Recombinant RBD purification</title>
<sec id="S10">
<title>Tangential filtering</title>
<p id="P14">Tangential filtration was conducted on a Hydrosart cassette (Sartorius, Germany) with 5 KDa of nominal molecular weight cutoff (MWCO) was used in a SARTOFLOW Advanced (Sartorius, Germany) tangential flow system. The supernatant was retained and concentrated to a volume of 2 L. Subsequently, the retentate was diafiltered into a saline phosphate buffer (PBS) at pH 6.3 and concentrated again to a volume of 1 L, filtered as filtered through 0.22 μM membrane and stored at 4°C until use.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S11">
<title>Affinity chromatography</title>
<p id="P15">As a first step, an immobilized metal affinity chromatography (IMAC) was performed using a HisTrap Excel column (1.6 x 2.5 cm) on an AKTA Pure 25L system (Cytiva, Sweden). Desalting and buffer exchange were performed on a Hiprep 26/10 desalting column (Cytiva, Sweden) using PBS pH 7.4 throughout the elution phase. The desalted protein was concentrated on an Amicon 10,000 MWCO (Merck, Germany) and filtered through a 0.22 μM membrane.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S12">
<title>Size exclusion chromatography</title>
<p id="P16">As a second step, a size exclusion chromatography was performed on a Superdex 200 increase 10/300 GL column (Cytiva, Sweden) using PBS pH 7.4 during the entire process. Protein fractions were collected and analyzed by SDS-PAGE under reducing conditions and Western blot using a commercial anti-His monoclonal antibody. The pool of selected fractions was concentrated using an Amicon 10,000 MWCO (Merck, Germany) and filtered through a 0.22 μM membrane The concentration of purified RBD was determined using the Bradford assay (Merck, Germany).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="S13">
<title>Recombinant RBD characterization in vitro</title>
<sec id="S14">
<title>RBD binding to human ACE-2</title>
<p id="P17">A 96-well plate was coated overnight at 4°C with 100 μL of a recombinant human ACE-2 fused to a Fc fragment (GenScript Laboratories, USA) at 1 μg/mL in carbonate buffer (pH 9.6). The plate was blocked with 3% skimmed milk for 1 hour at room temperature and then washed five times with PBS 0.05% Tween 20 (PBS-T). Serial dilutions (1:2) of purified RBD were performed in PBS, starting from 2 μg/mL and ending to 1.9 ng/mL. Dilutions were added to the wells and incubated for 2 hours at 37°C. Five washing steps with PBS-T were performed, 100 μL of rabbit IgG polyclonal anti-spike antibody (SinoBiological, China) was added to the wells (1:5000) in 1% skimmed milk and incubated for 1 hour at 37°C. The plate was washed five times with PBS-T. Then, 100 μL of anti-rabbit IgG HRP conjugated (GenScript, USA) (1:30,000) in 1% skimmed milk was added to the wells. The plates were incubated at 37°C for 1 hour. Finally, the plates were washed with PBS-T five times, and 100 μL of TMB (Sigma Aldrich, USA) were added to the wells and incubated for 15 minutes at room temperature. The reaction was stopped with 50 μL of 2N sulfuric acid and the absorbance at 450 nm was read with an Epoch 2 microplate reader (Biotek, USA).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S15">
<title>RBD binding to Vero-E6 cells</title>
<p id="P18">Vero-E6 cells (Cod. CRL-1586™, ATCC®, USA), which were previously cultured in DMEM/F12 (HyClone, USA) + 10% fetal bovine serum (FBS) (HyClone, USA), were harvested and washed with DPBS with 5% FBS (FACS buffer). Approximately 10<sup>6</sup> cells were blocked with FACS buffer and 5% of normal mouse serum (Abcam, USA) for 30 min at 37°C. Then, the cells were incubated with the purified RBD (8 μg/mL) for 2 h at 37□C. To remove the excess of RBD not attached to Vero E6, the cells were washed with FACS buffer twice. After that, the mix was marked with rabbit monoclonal antibody anti-SARS-CoV-2 S1 (1:200) (Sino Biological, China) as the primary antibody for 1 h at 37°C, followed by the addition of the secondary goat anti-rabbit IgG antibody conjugated with Alexa Fluor 488 (1:200) (Abcam, USA). Finally, cells were acquired by the BD FACSCanto™ II flow cytometer (BD Biosciences, USA). The data was analyzed using the software FlowJo v.10.6 (BD Biosciences, USA), and the graphics were generated with GraphPad Prism 8.0.1. For the interpretation of results, the percentage of positive cells indicates of binding of RBD to Vero E6 cells.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S16">
<title>RBD recognition by immunized sera</title>
<p id="P19">Purified RBD was loaded at 0.2 μg/well and electrophoretically separated by SDS-PAGE under non-reducing conditions and transferred to nitrocellulose membranes using an e-blot device (GenScript Laboratories, USA). The membranes were blocked with 5% (w/v) non-fat milk in PBS with 0.1% of Tween 20 at pH 7.4 and incubated overnight at room temperature. Then, membranes were washed three times for 5 minutes each with Tris-buffered saline containing 0.1% (v/v) Tween 20 (TBS-T) and incubated for two hours at room temperature with serum of a hamster immunized with a New Castle disease virus expressing the S1 sub-unit of SARS-CoV-2 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref>] (1:250) in 5% non-fat milk. After three washes with TBS-T, anti-Hamster IgG antibody conjugated to HRP (Abcam, USA) was added to the membrane at 1:5000 dilution in 5% non-fat milk and incubated for two hours at room temperature. Finally, the membranes were washed three times with TBST-0.1%, incubated with luminol (Azure Biosystems, USA) as a substrate and revealed with a CCD camera (Azure Biosystems, USA).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="S17">
<title>Immunization and samples collection in mice</title>
<p id="P20">Female BALB/c mice (18-25g) were immunized intramuscularly (i.m.) with 20 and 50 μg/mice of purified RBD mixed with 50 μL of A1 or A3 (1:1, 100 μL final volume). Two boosters were administered at 15 and 30 days post-immunization (DPI) with the same dose (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). As a control, mice were immunized with PBS mixed with A1 or A3, an unvaccinated group was maintained during the experiment. Serum of each animal was collected on 0, 15, 30 and 45 DPI by low-speed centrifugation of blood at 2500 rpm for 5 minutes. All animals were euthanized at 45 DPI and organs (lung, liver and kidney) were collected for histopathological analysis.</p>
<p id="P21">
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>. Mice immunization flow chart. Mice were immunized by the intramuscular route using a prime-boost regimen with a booster on days 15 and 30. Seven groups of mice were included: group 1 (20 μg RBD/A1, n=5), group 2 (50 μg RBD/A1, n=5), group 3 (20 μg RBD/A3, n=5), group 4 (50 μg RBD/A3, n=5), group 5 (only A1 n=5), group 6 (only A3 n=5) and group 7 (no immunization).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S18">
<title>Immunization and samples collection in hamsters</title>
<p id="P22">Five Golden Syrian hamsters were immunized intramuscularly, each one with 30 μg of purified RBD mixed with oil adjuvant A3 (1:1) (which had the best adjuvant tested in mice) in a final volume 100 μL (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig 2</xref>). Five animals received only adjuvant A3 and were considered as the group. At 15 DPI, all groups received a booster at the same dose. Hamsters were bled at 0, 15 and 30 DPI to evaluate the specific and neutralizing antibody (nAbs) titers. Serum from each sample was obtained by centrifugation of blood at 2500 rpm for 5 minutes.</p>
<p id="P23">
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>. Hamster immunization flow chart. Hamsters were immunized by the intramuscular route with 30 μg of purified RBD in adjuvant A3 using a prime-boost regimen with a booster on day 15.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S19">
<title>Evaluation of humoral immunity</title>
<sec id="S20">
<title>Detection of specific antibodies by ELISA</title>
<p id="P24">Nunc MaxiSorp 96-well flat bottom plates (Sigma-Aldrich, USA) were coated with 100 μL of SARS-CoV-2 RBD (1 μg/mL) (GenScript, USA) in carbonate bicarbonate buffer (pH 9.6) and incubated at 4°C overnight. The next day, the wells were washed six times with PBS containing 0.05% (v/v) Tween-20 (PBS-T) and blocked with 3% (w/v) Difco Skim Milk (BD Biosciences, USA) in PBS-T for 2 h in agitation at RT. The plates were then washed six times with PBS-T. Then, 100 μL of each collected serum sample diluted 1:100 with 1% (w/v) Difco Skim Milk (BD Biosciences, USA) was added to each plate for 1 h at 37°C. The wells were washed six times with PBS-T and incubated with 100 μL (1:10000) of Goat Anti Mouse IgG (Genscript, USA) or Anti Hamster IgG (Abcam, USA) conjugated to HRP diluted in 1% Difco Skim Milk in PBS-T for 1h at 37°C. The plates were washed six times and were incubated with 100 μL of TMB for 15 min at RT. Finally, the reaction was stopped by adding 50 μL per well of 2 N H2SO4, and the plates were read at 450 nm using an Epoch 2 microplate reader (Biotek, USA). The negative control was obtained from serum samples of the control group.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S21">
<title>Detection of neutralizing antibodies</title>
<p id="P25">Hamster serum samples were processed to assess neutralizing antibodies (nAbs) titers against SARS-CoV-2 at 0, 15, and 30 days post immunization. All Neutralization assays were performed with the surrogate virus neutralization test (sVNT) (GenScript, USA), following the manufacturer’s instructions. Plates were read for absorbance at 450 nm using an Epoch 2 microplate reader (Biotek, USA). The optical density results were converted into percentage of inhibition, by the formula provided by the manufacturer. The positive and negative cut-off points for the detection of SARS-CoV-2 nAbs were set as follows: positive, if percentage of inhibition ≥ 30% (neutralizing antibody detected) and negative, if percentage of inhibition &lt;30% (neutralizing antibody not detectable).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="S22">
<title>Evaluation of cellular immunity</title>
<sec id="S23">
<title>Extraction of mononuclear cells from mouse spleen</title>
<p id="P26">The mice vaccinated with the purified RBD and the control group (adjuvant only) were euthanized at 45 days post immunization, and spleens were removed. aseptically. The organs were transferred to Petri dishes with 5 mL cold RPMI medium (Sigma Aldrich, USA) and two pieces of 41 μm nylon net (Merck, USA), where the organ was disrupted using a 3 mL syringe plunger. The cell suspension was filtered and placed in a centrifuge tube containing 2 mL of Histopaque® 1077 (Sigma Aldrich, USA). The samples were centrifuged at 300 x g for 30 minutes without brake. The buffy coat containing mononuclear cells was removed, placed in cold RPMI medium, and washed twice. Cells were resuspended in 1 mL of complete RPMI medium and counted by hemocytometer. Cells were resuspended in fetal bovine serum (HyClone, USA) with 10% dimethyl sulfoxide (Sigma Aldrich, USA) and frozen in liquid nitrogen until use.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S24">
<title>ELISPOT for IFN-γ secretion in spleen mononuclear cells</title>
<p id="P27">Mononuclear cells were cultured in 96-well plates with a PVDF membrane, previously coated with anti-mouse IFN-γ (clone RMMG-1, Merck, USA) and blocked with 1% bovine serum albumin (BSA) (Sigma Aldrich, USA). Cells were stimulated with the purified RBD (4 μg/mL) for 24 hours at 37°C at 5% CO<sub>2</sub>. Concanavalin A (Sigma Aldrich, USA) was used as a positive control. The cells were removed by successive washes with water and PBS with 0.1% Tween. The wells were incubated with biotinylated anti-mouse IFN-γ (clone R4-6A2, Biolegend, USA) for 16 hours at 4° C. After washing, the wells were incubated with streptavidin-alkaline phosphatase (SAP) (Sigma Aldrich, USA) for one hour at room temperature. After washing, the chromogen-substrate, NBT/BCIP (Abcam, USA), was added. The spots formed were counted with an AID EliSpot plate reader (Advanced Imaging Devices, v. 7.0, Germany).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S25">
<title>Intracellular labeling of cellular immune response cytokines</title>
<p id="P28">The mononuclear cells were stimulated with or without purified RBD (8 μg/mL) for 21 hours at 37° C at 5% CO2 hours, in the last 5 hours of culture a protein transport inhibitor Brefeldin A (1μL/mL) was added (BD Biosciences, USA). Cells were fixed using the BD Cytofix/Cytoperm® kit (BD Biosciences, USA) following the manufacturer’s instructions, and then labeled with conjugated antibodies to surface antigens (PerCP-Cy®5.5 anti-mouse CD3, FITC anti-mouse CD4, APC-Cy®7 mouse anti-CD8, all from BD Biosciences, USA; LIVE/DEAD™ Fixable Yellow Dead Cell Stain, Invitrogen, USA) and intracellular cytokines (PE anti-mouse IFN-γ, PE-Cy®7 anti-mouse TNF-α, APC anti-mouse IL-2, all from BD Biosciences, USA). The labeled cells were acquired with the BD FACSCanto™ II flow cytometer and analyzed with the program FlowJo v.10.6.2 (BD Biosciences).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S26">
<title>Immunophenotype of spleen mononuclear cells</title>
<p id="P29">Mononuclear cells were directly labeled with conjugated antibodies to surface antigens (PerCP-Cy®5.5 anti-mouse CD3, clone, FITC anti-mouse CD4, APC-Cy®7 anti-mouse CD8, for T lymphocyte phenotype, all from BD Biosciences, USA; LIVE/DEAD™ Fixable Yellow Dead Cell Stain, for cell viability, cat. No. L34959, invitrogen, USA). These cells were acquired with the BD FACSCanto™ II flow cytometer, and the analysis was performed with the program FlowJo v 10.6.2 (BD Biosciences).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S27">
<title>Histopathological analysis</title>
<p id="P30">For safety analysis, organs were obtained from euthanized mice at 45 days post immunization and fixed with 10% buffered formalin for 48 hours. Then. organs were reduced and placed in a container for 24 hours with buffered formalin. The containers with the organs were passed to an automatic tissue processor (Microm brand) conducting the following processes: dehydration, diaphanating, rinsing, and impregnation; within an average of 8 hours. Organs included in paraffin were sectioned to a thickness of 5 microns (Microtome Leica RM2245) and placed in a flotation solution in a water bath and then fixed on a slide sheet, dried in the stove at 37°C for 1 to 2 hours. The staining was done with the Hematoxylin and Eosin staining method (H&amp;E). Samples were mounted in a microscope slide with Canada Balm (glue) and dryed at 37°C for 12 to 24 hours, for further labeling. The colored slides with H&amp;E were taken and analyzed under an AxioCam MRc5 camera and AxioScope.A1 microscope (Carl Zeiss, Germany) at 20x magnification by a board-certified veterinary pathologist.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S28">
<title>Statistical analysis</title>
<p id="P31">All quantitative data were analyzed using GraphPad Prism version 6.1 (GraphPad Software, San Diego, CA, USA). Student t-test was used to evaluate cellular immunity. For EC50 estimation, a regression model of four parameter logistic curve (4PL) was used. Two-way ANOVA analysis was performed to determine significant difference in ELISA results. A 5% statistical significance was considered in all cases.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="S29" sec-type="results">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="S30">
<title>Recombinant SARS-CoV-2 RBD production</title>
<p id="P32">Recombinant RBD was expressed and secreted into the extracellular medium by infected Sf-9 cells. A single band of ~28KDa was detected by western blot using Anti-his and Anti-spike antibodies (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig 3B</xref>). In bioreactor conditions, the highest protein expression level was observed at 68 hours post-infection. After the purification processes, a productivity level of 0.8 mg/mL of RBD was obtained at a purity level &gt; 90% (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig 3C</xref>).</p>
<p id="P33">
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>. RBD expression and purification. (A) Design of the expression cassette integrated into the recombinant baculovirus. (B) Detection of RBD from infected culture supernatants using an anti-His (left) and anti-spike (right) antibody. Bv-WT: Wild type baculovirus; Bv-RBD: RBD expressing baculovirus. (C) SDS-PAGE of purified RBD after the affinity chromatography purification step (Lane 1) and size exclusion chromatography (Lane 2).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S31">
<title>Recombinant SARS-CoV-2 RBD characterization</title>
<p id="P34">To determine the correct conformational state of RBD, ACE-2 receptor binding assays were performed. ACE-2 binding dependent on RBD concentration was observed, with a half maximal effective concentration (EC50) of 46.8 ng/mL (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig 4A</xref>). Similarly, through flow cytometry, bounded RBD to Vero E6 cell surface at different concentrations, with a 60% binding level (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig 4C</xref>). Based on the main fluorescence intensity (MFI), the difference between the cells treated with purified RBD and those treated with FACS buffer as a negative control was significant. On the other hand, commercially available recombinant RBD was used as a positive control. Although its binding was slightly higher than RBD (78%), the difference was not statistically significant. This trend was observed in all the concentrations evaluated.</p>
<p id="P35">The importance of disulfide bonds for the correct folding of the RBD sub-domain is known. Therefore, an additional way to verify the correct folding of the recombinant RBD was evaluating its detection under reducing and non-reducing conditions using a serum from a hamster immunized with a New Castle Disease virus (NDV) expressing the S1 Domain [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref>] (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig 4B</xref>). In this way, by Western blot RBD could be detected by the serum only under non-reducing conditions, demonstrating that it conserves the folding of the RBD sub-domain occurring in the Spike protein.</p>
<p id="P36">
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>. RBD binding and folding characterization in vitro. (A) Dose dependent curve of RBD binding to human ACE-2 by ELISA, dashed lines represent the EC50 value. Dots and error bars represent the mean value of three independent experiments and the standard deviation, respectively. (B) Disulfide bond dependent recognition of RBD by hamsters immunized serum by western blot. Lane1: RBD under non-reducing conditions; Lane 2: RBD under reducing conditions. (C) RBD binding to Vero E6 cell surface. The binding values are represented as the percentage of cells bound to RBD (left diagram) and the Mean Fluorescence Intensity (MFI) of each group was evaluated (right diagram). Two repetitions were performed per group, except in the FACS buffer group. Student <italic>t</italic>-test was used to compare the MFI values. ns: not significant (P&gt;0.05); **: significant (P&lt;0.01).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S32">
<title>Humoral Immunity</title>
<p id="P37">Specific antibodies were detected in both groups immunized with each adjuvant. In group A1, antibody levels with both doses of FAR-RBD were similar at 15 and 30 days after immunization. However, after the second booster, there was a slight decrease in the antibodies detected in the sub-group immunized with 20 μg of RBD, while those immunized with 50 μg increased slightly. Regarding group A3, it was observed that the antibodies generated were higher in the dose of 50 μg at all times of evaluation. Moreover, at 45-day post-immunization the antibodies detected remained at the same level prior to the second booster. In addition, group A3 generated higher levels of antibodies at 15 days post-immunization compared to group A1. Control groups immunized with each adjuvant had baseline reactivities throughout the evaluation time (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig 5</xref>).</p>
<p id="P38">
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>. Detection of specific antibodies against RBD in mice. Immunized mice were bled at 0, 15, 30 and 45 days post immunization. All sera were isolated by low-speed centrifugation. Serum samples were processed to detect specific antibodies against SARS-CoV-2 RBD protein using indirect ELISA assay. (A) Group immunized with RBD mixed with adjuvant 1 and (B) Group immunized with RBD mixed with adjuvant 3. Two-way ANOVA and post-hoc Tukey’s test were performed. **: P&lt;0.01</p>
<p id="P39">Since with adjuvant 3 the maximum levels of antibodies were obtained with a single boost and in less time, this adjuvant was used to immunize the hamsters. In this way, a significant increase in specific antibody levels was observed from day 15 post-immunization until day 30 in all the individuals tested (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig 6A</xref>). The neutralization assays using the surrogate virus neutralization test (sVNT) detected neutralizing antibodies only at day 30 post-immunization, where the sera from hamsters vaccinated showed a mean percentage of inhibition of the RBD-ACE2 union above 30%. Sera of the control group remained below 30% and did not show neutralizing antibodies (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig 6B</xref>).</p>
<p id="P40">
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>. Detection of specific antibodies against RBD and neutralizing antibodies in hamsters. (A) Immunized hamsters were bled at 0, 15 and 30 days post immunization. Serum samples were processed to detect specific antibodies against SARS-CoV-2 RBD protein using indirect ELISA assay. (B) Serum samples were processed to evaluate the neutralizing antibody titers against SARS-CoV-2 using sVNT. The cut-off for positive/negative neutralizing antibodies in the sample was 30% of inhibition of RBD binding to ACE-2. Two-way ANOVA and post-hoc Tukey’s test were performed. **: P&lt;0.01. ****: P&lt;0.0001.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S33">
<title>Cellular immunity</title>
<p id="P41">The cellular immunity stimulated by the purified RBD in mice was evaluated on day 45 after the first immunization. The percentage of CD4+ and CD8+ T cells is observed for each adjuvant evaluated. For adjuvant A1, the percentage of CD4+ and CD8+ T cells increased proportional to the dose of RBD administered (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig 7A</xref>). For adjuvant A3, the percentage of cells decreased when the dose of RBD was increased. Although the differences were not significant for all groups compared with the control group. When reviewing the production of Th1-type cytokines (IFN-γ, TNF-α and IL-2) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig 7C</xref>), the increase in CD8+ T cells secreting IFN-γ (for A1 and A3), TNF-α (for A1 and A3) and IL-2 (for A1 and A3) decreased according to the administered dose of RBD. Regarding the secretion of IFN-γ in splenocytes stimulated with purified RBD using the ELISPOT technique (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig 7B</xref>), the adjuvant A3 stimulated a greater number of cells directly proportional to the administered dose.</p>
<p id="P42">
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref>. Evaluation of cellular immunity in mice vaccinated with purified RBD. Mice were immunized with 20 and 50 μg of RBD using two different adjuvants (A1 and A3) at 0, 15 and 30 days post immunization. On day 45 post-immunization mice were sacrificed and spleens were processed. (A) Percentage of CD4 and CD8 positive cells by flow cytometry, between the groups immunized (n=3, except the adjuvant control). (B) IFN-γ ELISPOT of splenocytes between the groups immunized with purified RBD using A1 or A3 adjuvant (n=3, except the adjuvant control). (C) Intracellular staining of Th1 cytokines (IFN-γ, TNF-α and IL-2) of splenocytes stimulated with RBD (n=3, except the adjuvant control). ns: not significant (P&gt;0.05), *: P&lt;0.05.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S34">
<title>Safety</title>
<p id="P43">Histopathological analysis of the of the groups of mice immunized with purified RBD mixed or mixed with A1 or A3, including the unvaccinated group not showed signs of serious injury or damage. Lungs not showed clinical appearance of pneumonia and there was no evidence of kidney symptoms. Although in liver a slight vacuolar degeneration was identified, this was observed in all the groups tested, including the control group. (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8</xref>).</p>
<p id="P44">
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figure 8</xref>. Histopathological analysis of mice inoculated with purified RBD and control. Organs were obtained 45 days after the first immunization and stained with hematoxylin-eosin (H&amp;E). These images are representative slides from vaccinated mice and negative control mice. (A) Lung sections. (B) Liver sections. (C) Kidney sections. All the images are in a 200X magnification.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="S35" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p id="P45">SARS-CoV-2 continues to be a problem worldwide. As an immediate response to the emergence of new variants and their dissemination, the constant development and evaluation of vaccines are necessary. In the present study, production of a recombinant sub-domain RBD expressed in insect cells, and immunization together with two oil-based adjuvants, elicited an immune response in mice and hamsters while demonstrated to be safe.</p>
<p id="P46">Currently, most of the approved and candidate vaccines are based on the complete spike protein. However, there are several vaccine candidates based on the single RBD antigen, ongoing pre-clinical and clinical phase [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">20</xref>]. Although, in some reports the complete spike has shown greater immunogenicity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">21</xref>], the single RBD remains as a strong vaccine candidate because it comprises the most important epitopes to which neutralizing antibodies should target. In addition, it generates antibodies with enhanced neutralizing activity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">22</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref>]. The greater accumulation of mutations in the S1 and S2 domains can destabilize the protein, hindering its production and the yields obtained as a purified protein [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">26</xref>]. On the other hand, RBD has demonstrated an easier production [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27">27</xref>], and results in a more conserved antigen. Recent studies have bioengineered RBD variants with improved stability and higher immune response in mice compared to the current Wuhan-Hu-1 vaccine [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">28</xref>]. Likewise, a thermotolerant RBD fused to a trimerization motif has generated high neutralization titers in guinea pigs and mice, as well as protection in hamsters from viral challenge [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">29</xref>].</p>
<p id="P47">Despite that the purified RBD evaluated in this study comprised 22 amino acids less than the generally recognized RBD region (Arg319-Phe541) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">30</xref>], it was structurally and functionally viable as demonstrated by the binding assays by ELISA and flow cytometry. This functionality was maintained because the expressed region comprises the residues that form the disulfide bonds that give stability to the nucleus and the key external sub-domains of the RBD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">23</xref>] maintaining the integrity of the receptor binding motif, which ultimately is the main region that directly interacts with the ACE2 receptor. This was confirmed by the lack of RBD recognition of the hamster anti-S1 immune sera under reducing conditions, but the strong recognition of RBD by the immune sera under non-reducing conditions. This suggests, that the disulphide bonds are present and are favoring a correct folding and 3D structure of the RBD antigen, that may be presenting appropriate conformational epitopes, as most of the immune antibodies targets tertiary epitopes spanning the exposed sites of the RBD in the trimeric pre-fusion Spike [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31">31</xref>].</p>
<p id="P48">The production level of RBD in this study, was relatively low (0.8 mg/L), compared to previous reports of expression of the same domain using the baculovirus expression system [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27">27</xref>], it is likely that this is due to the baculovirus type used, which is not optimized for secreted expression, or to the second purification step required to obtain a higher degree of purity. These levels could be optimized using baculoviruses lacking the <italic>v-cath</italic> and <italic>chiA</italic> genes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32">32</xref>] or through optimization strategies of the amino acid sequence that have been proven to improve expression levels and immunogenicity of the RBD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33">33</xref>].</p>
<p id="P49">The chemical composition of an adjuvant is important because its components may interfere with organism responses. Most oil-water (O/W) adjuvants that contain squalene, also have other components (Tween 80, Span 85, polyethylene glycol or derivatives), which when emulsified in an aqueous phase, generate a stable chemical structure that allows the transport of antigens for their recognition by cells such as macrophages or dendritic cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34">34</xref>]. In the immunization experiments conducted in this study, adjuvant 3 (W/O + squalene) was associated to higher levels of anti-RBD antibodies than adjuvant 1 (O/W) at 15 days post immunization. However, after the second booster was administered (45 DPI), the antibody levels for both adjuvants were not significantly different. This could be explained by the fact that O/W emulsions, as an adjuvant for mice, generates higher levels of antibodies while directing the cellular immune response to the Th2 type [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34">34</xref>]. Also, it is known that O/W emulsions stimulate a strong production of TNF-α [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35">35</xref>] and do not generate local inflammation reactions when injected subcutaneously or intramuscularly [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36">36</xref>]. On the other hand, the W/O adjuvant formulations are not effective enough to induce strong humoral responses, as they can generate inflammatory responses and the formation of granulomas [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36">36</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37">37</xref>]. In contrast, adjuvant A3, which is a novel composition, demonstrates the stimulation of a strong humoral response. We believe further studies are necessary to clarify and confirm these observations</p>
<p id="P50">When adjuvant A1 was administered with the purified RBD, the formulation did not generate IFN-γ, IL-2 nor TNF-α in the evaluation by ICS. However, an increase in the percentage of CD4+ and CD8+ T cells was observed. This observation is in agreement with a previous study, where Arunachalam et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38">38</xref>] found that adjuvant A1 (Essai O/W 1849101, Seppic) added to RBD nanoparticles did not elicit a strong antibody response nor protection as expected in Rhesus monkeys. Nevertheless, when A1 was used with alpha-tocopherol it produced a stronger level of neutralizing antibodies and protection against infection with SARS-CoV-2. However, the use of this adjuvant generated an inflammatory response, associated with a high expression of TNF-α and IL-2. We found that the novel adjuvant A3 stimulated the secretion of greater IFN-γ levels in splenocytes compared to adjuvant A1, as well as IL-2 and TNF-α in CD8+ T cells. This is consistent with the possible inflammatory effect generated by adjuvants based on W/O emulsions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37">37</xref>].</p>
<p id="P51">The generation of neutralizing antibodies in hamsters was observed at 30 days post immunization. Although the surrogate test does not directly determine the neutralization of virus invasiveness in cells, it has been shown that it has a high correlation index with classic viral neutralization tests [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">8</xref>]. In addition, various studies have demonstrated a relationship between the development of neutralizing antibodies with the protection of re-infection in humans, as well as in challenge tests in hamsters [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39">39</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40">40</xref>].</p>
<p id="P52">Due to limitations in space and the availability of animals, this trial was conducted with 5 individuals per group, and the heterogeneity was evident as previously reported in a similar protocol [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41">41</xref>]. Unfortunately, it was not possible to establish clear conclusions about the tendency of the population when stimulated with the two different adjuvants, as there was no significant difference between the controls and the immunized groups. It is important to perform additional studies with a greater sample size to perform a better evaluation of cellular and humoral immunity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">28</xref>] to 8 per group [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35">35</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42">42</xref>].</p>
<p id="P53">In conclusion, the RBD vaccine candidate presented in this study, administered through an intramuscular route, was shown to be safe and able to induce humoral and cellular immunity as well as neutralizing antibodies in mice and hamsters. Further studies are required to evaluate protection in a challenge trial.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<fn-group>
<fn id="FN1">
<p id="P54">
<bold>Ethics statement</bold>
</p>
<p id="P55">This study was approved by the Bioethics Committee of the Universidad Nacional Hermilio Valdizán registered as approval certificates of Research Project No. 1, 2 and 10. Animal immunizations and procedures were performed by qualified personnel following the ARRIVE guidelines [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43">43</xref>]</p>
</fn>
<fn id="FN2" fn-type="con">
<p id="P56">
<bold>Authors’ contributions</bold>
</p>
<p id="P57">MFD, MZ, RCG, APA contributed to conception and designed the research. RCG, APA, RM, KGM, AM, DRM, SQG, MCM, AAA, IRO, MCO, EHG, YRL, NPM, GIR, YSA, DVP, KVS performed experiments. RCG, RMM, APA and DRM acquired the data of the study. RCG, APA and DRM analyzed and interpreted the data. RCG, RMM, APA, DRM and SQG wrote the paper, and all authors revised it, read and approved the final manuscript.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<ref id="R1">
<label>1</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zhou</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>X-L</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>X-G</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hu</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>A pneumonia outbreak associated with a new coronavirus of probable bat origin</article-title>
<source>Nature</source>
<year>2020</year>
<volume>579</volume>
<fpage>270</fpage>
<lpage>273</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41586-020-2012-7</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R2">
<label>2</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Walls</surname>
<given-names>AC</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Park</surname>
<given-names>Y-J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tortorici</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wall</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>McGuire</surname>
<given-names>AT</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Veesler</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Structure, Function, and Antigenicity of the SARS-CoV-2 Spike Glycoprotein</article-title>
<source>Cell</source>
<year>2020</year>
<fpage>1</fpage>
<lpage>12</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2020.02.058</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R3">
<label>3</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lan</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ge</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Yu</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Shan</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zhou</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Fan</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>Structure of the SARS-CoV-2 spike receptor-binding domain bound to the ACE2 receptor</article-title>
<source>Nat</source>
<year>2020</year>
<volume>581</volume>
<fpage>215</fpage>
<lpage>220</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41586-020-2180-5</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R4">
<label>4</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Tai</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>He</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Pu</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Voronin</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Jiang</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>Characterization of the receptor-binding domain (RBD) of 2019 novel coronavirus: implication for development of RBD protein as a viral attachment inhibitor and vaccine</article-title>
<source>Cell Mol Immunol 2020 176</source>
<year>2020</year>
<volume>17</volume>
<fpage>613</fpage>
<lpage>620</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41423-020-0400-4</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R5">
<label>5</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ou</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zhou</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dai</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zhao</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>V367F Mutation in SARS-CoV-2 Spike RBD Emerging during the Early Transmission Phase Enhances Viral Infectivity through Increased Human ACE2 Receptor Binding Affinity</article-title>
<source>J Virol</source>
<year>2021</year>
<fpage>95</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JVI.00617-21</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R6">
<label>6</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Premkumar</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Segovia-Chumbez</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Jadi</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Martinez</surname>
<given-names>DR</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Raut</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Markmann</surname>
<given-names>AJ</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>The receptor-binding domain of the viral spike protein is an immunodominant and highly specific target of antibodies in SARS-CoV-2 patients</article-title>
<source>Sci Immunol</source>
<year>2020</year>
<fpage>5</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/sciimmunol.abc8413</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R7">
<label>7</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Min</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sun</surname>
<given-names>Q</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Antibodies and Vaccines Target RBD of SARS-CoV-2</article-title>
<source>Front Mol Biosci</source>
<year>2021</year>
<fpage>8</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmolb.2021.671633</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R8">
<label>8</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Tan</surname>
<given-names>CW</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Chia</surname>
<given-names>WN</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Qin</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>MIC</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tiu</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>A SARS-CoV-2 surrogate virus neutralization test based on antibody-mediated blockage of ACE2-spike protein-protein interaction</article-title>
<source>Nat Biotechnol</source>
<year>2020</year>
<volume>38</volume>
<fpage>1073</fpage>
<lpage>1078</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41587-020-0631-z</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R9">
<label>9</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Cox</surname>
<given-names>MMJ</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Recombinant protein vaccines produced in insect cells</article-title>
<source>Vaccine</source>
<year>2012</year>
<volume>30</volume>
<fpage>1759</fpage>
<lpage>1766</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vaccine.2012.01.016</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R10">
<label>10</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Felberbaum</surname>
<given-names>RS</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>The baculovirus expression vector system: A commercial manufacturing platform for viral vaccines and gene therapy vectors</article-title>
<source>Biotechnol J</source>
<year>2015</year>
<volume>10</volume>
<fpage>702</fpage>
<lpage>714</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/biot.201400438</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R11">
<label>11</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lai</surname>
<given-names>C-C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cheng</surname>
<given-names>Y-C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>P-W</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lin</surname>
<given-names>T-H</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tzeng</surname>
<given-names>T-T</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lu</surname>
<given-names>C-C</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>Process development for pandemic influenza VLP vaccine production using a baculovirus expression system</article-title>
<source>J Biol Eng</source>
<year>2019</year>
<volume>13</volume>
<fpage>78</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13036-019-0206-z</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R12">
<label>12</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>S-M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hickey</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Miura</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Joshi</surname>
<given-names>SB</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Volkin</surname>
<given-names>DB</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>King</surname>
<given-names>CR</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>A C-terminal Pfs48/45 malaria transmission-blocking vaccine candidate produced in the baculovirus expression system</article-title>
<source>Sci Rep</source>
<year>2020</year>
<volume>10</volume>
<fpage>395</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-019-57384-w</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R13">
<label>13</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Shrivastava</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Singh</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rizvi</surname>
<given-names>ZA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Verma</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Goswami</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Vishwakarma</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>Comparative Immunomodulatory Evaluation of the Receptor Binding Domain of the SARS-CoV-2 Spike Protein; a Potential Vaccine Candidate Which Imparts Potent Humoral and Th1 Type Immune Response in a Mouse Model</article-title>
<source>Front Immunol</source>
<year>2021</year>
<fpage>12</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2021.641447</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R14">
<label>14</label>
<element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Shah</surname>
<given-names>RR</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Brito</surname>
<given-names>LA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>O’Hagan</surname>
<given-names>DT</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Amiji</surname>
<given-names>MM</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<chapter-title>Emulsions as Vaccine Adjuvants</chapter-title>
<person-group person-group-type="editor">
<name>
<surname>Foged</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rades</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Perrie</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hook</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source>Subunit Vaccine Delivery Advances in Delivery Science and Technology</source>
<publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
<publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>
<year>2015</year>
<fpage>59</fpage>
<lpage>76</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-1-4939-1417-3_4</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R15">
<label>15</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Shardlow</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mold</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Exley</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Unraveling the enigma: elucidating the relationship between the physicochemical properties of aluminium-based adjuvants and their immunological mechanisms of action</article-title>
<source>Allergy, Asthma Clin Immunol</source>
<year>2018</year>
<volume>14</volume>
<fpage>80</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13223-018-0305-2</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R16">
<label>16</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Yam</surname>
<given-names>KK</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gupta</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Allen</surname>
<given-names>EK</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Burt</surname>
<given-names>KR</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Beaulieu</surname>
<given-names>É</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mallett</surname>
<given-names>CP</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>Comparison of AS03 and Alum on immune responses elicited by A/H3N2 split influenza vaccine in young, mature and aged BALB/c mice</article-title>
<source>Vaccine</source>
<year>2016</year>
<volume>34</volume>
<fpage>1444</fpage>
<lpage>1451</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vaccine.2016.02.012</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R17">
<label>17</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Nies</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hidalgo</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bondy</surname>
<given-names>SC</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Campbell</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Distinctive cellular response to aluminum based adjuvants</article-title>
<source>Environ Toxicol Pharmacol</source>
<year>2020</year>
<volume>78</volume>
<elocation-id>103404</elocation-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.etap.2020.103404</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R18">
<label>18</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Burakova</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Madera</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>McVey</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Schlup</surname>
<given-names>JR</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Shi</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Adjuvants for Animal Vaccines</article-title>
<source>Viral Immunol</source>
<year>2018</year>
<volume>31</volume>
<fpage>11</fpage>
<lpage>22</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/vim.2017.0049</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R19">
<label>19</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Fernandez-Diaz</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Calderón</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rojas-Neyra</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Vakharia</surname>
<given-names>VN</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Choque Guevara</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Montalvan</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>Development and pre-clinical evaluation of Newcastle disease virus-vectored SARS-CoV-2 intranasal vaccine candidate</article-title>
<source>bioRxiv [Preprint]</source>
<year>2021</year>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2021.03.07.434276</pub-id>
<date-in-citation>cited 2021 November 13</date-in-citation>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R20">
<label>20</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Martínez-Flores</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zepeda-Cervantes</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cruz-Reséndiz</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Aguirre-Sampieri</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sampieri</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Vaca</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>SARS-CoV-2 Vaccines Based on the Spike Glycoprotein and Implications of New Viral Variants</article-title>
<source>Front Immunol</source>
<year>2021</year>
<fpage>12</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2021.701501</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R21">
<label>21</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Guo</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lu</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zhou</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Shi</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Shi</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>Single-Dose Immunization With a Chimpanzee Adenovirus-Based Vaccine Induces Sustained and Protective Immunity Against SARS-CoV-2 Infection</article-title>
<source>Front Immunol</source>
<year>2021</year>
<fpage>12</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2021.697074</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R22">
<label>22</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dai</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>He</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>Safety and immunogenicity of a recombinant tandem-repeat dimeric RBD-based protein subunit vaccine (ZF2001) against COVID-19 in adults: two randomised, double-blind, placebo-controlled, phase 1 and 2 trials</article-title>
<source>Lancet Infect Dis</source>
<year>2021</year>
<volume>21</volume>
<fpage>1107</fpage>
<lpage>1119</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1473-3099(21)00127-4</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R23">
<label>23</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lu</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bi</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>A vaccine targeting the RBD of the S protein of SARS-CoV-2 induces protective immunity</article-title>
<source>Nat 2020 5867830</source>
<year>2020</year>
<volume>586</volume>
<fpage>572</fpage>
<lpage>577</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41586-020-2599-8</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R24">
<label>24</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>N-N</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>X-F</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Deng</surname>
<given-names>Y-Q</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zhao</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Huang</surname>
<given-names>Y-J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>A Thermostable mRNA Vaccine against COVID-19</article-title>
<source>Cell</source>
<year>2020</year>
<volume>182</volume>
<fpage>1271</fpage>
<lpage>1283</lpage>
<elocation-id>e16</elocation-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2020.07.024</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R25">
<label>25</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Heinz</surname>
<given-names>FX</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Stiasny</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Distinguishing features of current COVID-19 vaccines: knowns and unknowns of antigen presentation and modes of action</article-title>
<source>npj Vaccines</source>
<year>2021</year>
<volume>6</volume>
<fpage>104</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41541-021-00369-6</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R26">
<label>26</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Berger</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Schaffitzel</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>The SARS-CoV-2 spike protein: balancing stability and infectivity</article-title>
<source>Cell Res</source>
<year>2020</year>
<volume>30</volume>
<fpage>1059</fpage>
<lpage>1060</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41422-020-00430-4</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R27">
<label>27</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zheng</surname>
<given-names>Q</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Yu</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Xue</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Xiong</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>SARS-CoV-2 spike produced in insect cells elicits high neutralization titres in non-human primates</article-title>
<source>Emerg Microbes Infect</source>
<year>2020</year>
<volume>9</volume>
<fpage>2076</fpage>
<lpage>2090</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/22221751.2020.1821583</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R28">
<label>28</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Dalvie</surname>
<given-names>NC</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rodriguez-Aponte</surname>
<given-names>SA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hartwell</surname>
<given-names>BL</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tostanoski</surname>
<given-names>LH</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Biedermann</surname>
<given-names>AM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Crowell</surname>
<given-names>LE</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>Engineered SARS-CoV-2 receptor binding domain improves manufacturability in yeast and immunogenicity in mice</article-title>
<source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
<year>2021</year>
<fpage>118</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/PNAS.2106845118</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R29">
<label>29</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Malladi</surname>
<given-names>SK</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Patel</surname>
<given-names>UR</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rajmani</surname>
<given-names>RS</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Singh</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Pandey</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kumar</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>Immunogenicity and Protective Efficacy of a Highly Thermotolerant, Trimeric SARS-CoV-2 Receptor Binding Domain Derivative</article-title>
<source>ACS Infect Dis</source>
<year>2021</year>
<volume>7</volume>
<fpage>2546</fpage>
<lpage>2564</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acsinfecdis.1c00276</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R30">
<label>30</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Xia</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zhu</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lan</surname>
<given-names>Q</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Xu</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>Fusion mechanism of 2019-nCoV and fusion inhibitors targeting HR1 domain in spike protein</article-title>
<source>Cell Mol Immunol 2020 177</source>
<year>2020</year>
<volume>17</volume>
<fpage>765</fpage>
<lpage>767</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41423-020-0374-2</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R31">
<label>31</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Dejnirattisai</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zhou</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ginn</surname>
<given-names>HM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Duyvesteyn</surname>
<given-names>HME</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Supasa</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Case</surname>
<given-names>JB</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>The antigenic anatomy of SARS-CoV-2 receptor binding domain</article-title>
<source>Cell</source>
<year>2021</year>
<volume>184</volume>
<fpage>2183</fpage>
<lpage>2200</lpage>
<elocation-id>e22</elocation-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/J.CELL.2021.02.032</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R32">
<label>32</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hitchman</surname>
<given-names>RB</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Possee</surname>
<given-names>RD</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Siaterli</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Richards</surname>
<given-names>KS</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Clayton</surname>
<given-names>AJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bird</surname>
<given-names>LE</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>Improved expression of secreted and membrane-targeted proteins in insect cells</article-title>
<source>Biotechnol Appl Biochem</source>
<year>2010</year>
<volume>56</volume>
<fpage>85</fpage>
<lpage>93</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1042/BA20090130</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R33">
<label>33</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ellis</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Brunette</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Crawford</surname>
<given-names>KHD</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Walls</surname>
<given-names>AC</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Pham</surname>
<given-names>MN</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>Stabilization of the SARS-CoV-2 Spike Receptor-Binding Domain Using Deep Mutational Scanning and Structure-Based Design</article-title>
<source>Front Immunol</source>
<year>2021</year>
<volume>0</volume>
<elocation-id>2605</elocation-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/FIMMU.2021.710263</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R34">
<label>34</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Calabro</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tritto</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Pezzotti</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Taccone</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Muzzi</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bertholet</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>The adjuvant effect of MF59 is due to the oil-in-water emulsion formulation, none of the individual components induce a comparable adjuvant effect</article-title>
<source>Vaccine</source>
<year>2013</year>
<volume>31</volume>
<fpage>3363</fpage>
<lpage>3369</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vaccine.2013.05.007</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R35">
<label>35</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Knudsen</surname>
<given-names>NPH</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Olsen</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Buonsanti</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Follmann</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Coler</surname>
<given-names>RN</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>Different human vaccine adjuvants promote distinct antigen-independent immunological signatures tailored to different pathogens</article-title>
<source>Sci Rep</source>
<year>2016</year>
<volume>6</volume>
<elocation-id>19570</elocation-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep19570</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R36">
<label>36</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Miao</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Han</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lu</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Deng</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lv</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>Development of a novel oilin-water emulsion and evaluation of its potential adjuvant function in a swine influenza vaccine in mice</article-title>
<source>BMC Vet Res</source>
<year>2018</year>
<volume>14</volume>
<fpage>415</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12917-018-1719-2</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R37">
<label>37</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Leenaars</surname>
<given-names>PPAM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Koedam</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wester</surname>
<given-names>PW</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Baumans</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Claassen</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hendriksen</surname>
<given-names>CFM</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Assessment of side effects induced by injection of different adjuvant/antigen combinations in rabbits and mice</article-title>
<source>Lab Anim</source>
<year>1998</year>
<volume>32</volume>
<fpage>387</fpage>
<lpage>406</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1258/002367798780599884</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R38">
<label>38</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Arunachalam</surname>
<given-names>PS</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Walls</surname>
<given-names>AC</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Golden</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Atyeo</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Fischinger</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>Adjuvanting a subunit COVID-19 vaccine to induce protective immunity</article-title>
<source>Nature</source>
<year>2021</year>
<volume>594</volume>
<fpage>253</fpage>
<lpage>258</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41586-021-03530-2</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R39">
<label>39</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Tostanoski</surname>
<given-names>LH</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wegmann</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Martinot</surname>
<given-names>AJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Loos</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>McMahan</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mercado</surname>
<given-names>NB</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>Ad26 vaccine protects against SARS-CoV-2 severe clinical disease in hamsters</article-title>
<source>Nat Med</source>
<year>2020</year>
<volume>26</volume>
<fpage>1694</fpage>
<lpage>1700</lpage>
<comment>2020 2611</comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41591-020-1070-6</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R40">
<label>40</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Addetia</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Crawford</surname>
<given-names>KHD</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dingens</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zhu</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Roychoudhury</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Huang</surname>
<given-names>ML</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>Neutralizing antibodies correlate with protection from SARS-CoV-2 in humans during a fishery vessel outbreak with a high attack rate</article-title>
<source>J Clin Microbiol</source>
<year>2020</year>
<fpage>58</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JCM.02107-20</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R41">
<label>41</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Arifin</surname>
<given-names>WN</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zahiruddin</surname>
<given-names>WM</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Sample Size Calculation in Animal Studies Using Resource Equation Approach</article-title>
<source>Malaysian J Med Sci</source>
<year>2017</year>
<volume>24</volume>
<fpage>101</fpage>
<lpage>105</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21315/mjms2017.24.5.11</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R42">
<label>42</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Vogel</surname>
<given-names>AB</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kanevsky</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Che</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Swanson</surname>
<given-names>KA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Muik</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Vormehr</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>BNT162b vaccines protect rhesus macaques from SARS-CoV-2</article-title>
<source>Nature</source>
<year>2021</year>
<volume>592</volume>
<fpage>283</fpage>
<lpage>289</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41586-021-03275-y</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R43">
<label>43</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Percie du Sert</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hurst</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ahluwalia</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Alam</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Avey</surname>
<given-names>MT</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Baker</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>The ARRIVE guidelines 2.0: Updated guidelines for reporting animal research</article-title>
<source>PLOS Biol</source>
<year>2020</year>
<volume>18</volume>
<elocation-id>e3000410</elocation-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.3000410</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
<floats-group>
<fig id="F1" position="float">
<label>Figure 1</label>
<graphic xlink:href="EMS140407-f001"/>
</fig>
<fig id="F2" position="float">
<label>Figure 2</label>
<graphic xlink:href="EMS140407-f002"/>
</fig>
<fig id="F3" position="float">
<label>Figure 3</label>
<graphic xlink:href="EMS140407-f003"/>
</fig>
<fig id="F4" position="float">
<label>Figure 4</label>
<graphic xlink:href="EMS140407-f004"/>
</fig>
<fig id="F5" position="float">
<label>Figure 5</label>
<graphic xlink:href="EMS140407-f005"/>
</fig>
<fig id="F6" position="float">
<label>Figure 6</label>
<graphic xlink:href="EMS140407-f006"/>
</fig>
<fig id="F7" position="float">
<label>Figure 7</label>
<graphic xlink:href="EMS140407-f007"/>
</fig>
<fig id="F8" position="float">
<label>Figure 8</label>
<graphic xlink:href="EMS140407-f008"/>
</fig>
</floats-group>
</article>
