<!DOCTYPE article
 PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" article-type="preprint"><?all-math-mml yes?><?use-mml?><?origin ukpmcpa?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">bioRxiv</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>bioRxiv : the preprint server for biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2692-8205</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">EMS197743</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2021.11.07.467596</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="archive">PPR416376</article-id><article-version-alternatives><article-version article-version-type="status">preprint</article-version><article-version article-version-type="number">3</article-version></article-version-alternatives><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Probing the modulation of enzyme kinetics by multi-temperature, time-resolved serial crystallography</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Schulz</surname><given-names>Eike C.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">a</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">b</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">c</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CR1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Prester</surname><given-names>Andreas</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>von Stetten</surname><given-names>David</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">d</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gore</surname><given-names>Gargi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hatton</surname><given-names>Caitlin E.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bartels</surname><given-names>Kim</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Leimkohl</surname><given-names>Jan-Philipp</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Schikora</surname><given-names>Hendrik</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ginn</surname><given-names>Helen M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">e</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Tellkamp</surname><given-names>Friedjof</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">b</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CR1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Mehrabi</surname><given-names>Pedram</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">b</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">c</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CR1">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1"><label>a</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/01zgy1s35</institution-id><institution>University Medical Center Hamburg-Eppendorf (UKE)</institution></institution-wrap>, <city>Hamburg</city>, <country country="DE">Germany</country></aff><aff id="A2"><label>b</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/0411b0f77</institution-id><institution>Max-Planck-Institute for the Structure and Dynamics of Matter</institution></institution-wrap>, <city>Hamburg</city>, <country country="DE">Germany</country></aff><aff id="A3"><label>c</label>Institute for Nanostructure and Solid State Physics, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/00g30e956</institution-id><institution>University of Hamburg</institution></institution-wrap>, <city>Hamburg</city>, <country country="DE">Germany</country></aff><aff id="A4"><label>d</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/03mstc592</institution-id><institution>European Molecular Biology Laboratory (EMBL)</institution></institution-wrap>, <city>Hamburg</city>, <country country="DE">Germany</country></aff><aff id="A5"><label>e</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/01js2sh04</institution-id><institution>Deutsches Elektronen Synchrotron (DESY)</institution></institution-wrap>, <city>Hamburg</city>, <country country="DE">Germany</country></aff><author-notes><corresp id="CR1">
<label>*</label> Corresponding author(s). <email>ec.schulz@uke.de</email>; <email>friedjof.tellkamp@mpsd.mpg.de</email>; <email>pedram.mehrabi@uni-hamburg.de</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted"><day>25</day><month>07</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="preprint"><day>24</day><month>07</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><permissions><ali:free_to_read/><license><ali:license_ref>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is licensed under a <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">CC BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p id="P1">We present an environmental enclosure for fixed-target serial crystallography, enabling X-ray diffraction experiments in a temperature window from below 10 °C to above 70 °C - a universal parameter of protein function. Via 5D-SSX time-resolved experiments can now be carried out at physiological temperatures, providing fundamentally new insights into protein function. We show temperature-dependent modulation of turnover kinetics for the mesophilic <italic>β</italic>-lactamase CTX-M-14 and for the hyperthermophilic enzyme xylose isomerase.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>serial crystallography</kwd><kwd>5D-SSX</kwd><kwd>multi-temperature crystallography</kwd><kwd>time-resolved crystallography</kwd><kwd>multi-dimensional crystallography</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="S1" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p id="P2">Life has evolved to occupy a wide range of different environmental niches, ranging from glaciers and arctic deserts to the hot ponds at Yellowstone [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">3</xref>]. Although enzymes operate over a wide range of temperatures, the vast majority of protein structures have been acquired at cryogenic temperatures, to reduce the rate of radiation damage [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">4</xref>]. However, flash-cooling may introduce structural artefacts, which are absent at physiological temperatures, that may affect biological interpretation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">8</xref>]. In addition, as proteins do not obtain a single unique conformation, but rather fluctuate around an energetic ground-state, the conformational dynamics of proteins are intimately linked to temperature, which is directly connected to their catalytic efficiency [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref>].The mismatch between data collection temperature and enzymatic activity optimum temperature becomes an acute problem during time-resolved structural studies that seek to provide detailed insight into catalytic mechanisms and allosteric regulation. While time-resolved structural studies are recently undergoing a resurgence, the majority of such experiments are carried out at ambient temperatures, regardless of the actual physiological or optimal temperature of the protein under study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref>]. A notable exception is the pioneering work on photoactive yellow (PYP) protein, where single-crystal time-resolved data were collected from -40 °C to +70 °C [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref>]. Although it is a key environmental variable for mechanistic time-resolved analyses, considerable technological difficulties have prevented routine use of physiologically relevant temperatures during serial femtosecond (SFX) and serial synchrotron crystallography (SSX) experiments, until now. To address this challenge we have developed a modular environmental control system for serial crystallography, that enables precise control of the relative humidity to within a percent and temperature from below 10 °C and over 70 °C (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig.1 a, extended data</xref>). This temperature window is large enough to encompass physiologically relevant temperatures of both mesophile and hyperthermophile enzymes. With full compatibility with our previously described liquid application method for time-resolved analyses (LAMA), this system permits multi-temperature time-resolved serial crystallography experiments [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref>]. These so-called 5D-crystallography experiments [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref>] now enable a unique view into a hitherto difficult to structurally access realm of protein function, that directly connects out-of-equilibrium structures to energetic considerations. To demonstrate the applicability of our new environmental control system to a variety of enzymes, we have used a mesophilic enzyme, the extended spectrum <italic>β</italic>-lactamase (CTX-M-14) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref>]) and a hyperthermophilic enzyme, xylose isomerase (XI) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">20</xref>] as model systems. For both systems we show that a modification of the environmental temperature modulates the underlying enzyme kinetics, enabling resolution of alternate structural intermediates not observed at high occupancy at ambient temperatures.</p></sec><sec id="S2" sec-type="results | discussion"><title>Results and Discussion</title><p id="P3">To benchmark the environmental control and systematically address different temperatures, five structures of both model systems were determined between 10 °C and 50 °C (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T5">Ext. Tab. 5</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="T6">6</xref>) (extended data). To assess the global variability of atomic positions in a comparable way, we determined the atomic displacement parameters (ADP), and fitted these to a shifted inverse gamma distribution as a function of temperature, as described previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">22</xref>]. For CTX-M-14 a shift in the ADP distribution can only be determined after a threshold temperature (ca. 50 °C), corresponding to its in-solution melting temperature and pairwise C<sub><italic>α</italic></sub>-RMSD (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig.1 b</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Ext. Fig. 6</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">7</xref>). XI on the other hand has a much higher in-solution melting temperature (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Ext. Fig. 6</xref>) and shows a monotonous ADP increase with higher temperatures (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig.1 c</xref>). We hypothesise that the respective response in conformational variability reflects the adaptation to a mesophilic or a thermophilic temperature optimum, respectively. In other words, the higher flexibility observed for XI serves to accommodate the higher degree of molecular motions concomitant with higher temperatures, without compromising its functionality [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">23</xref>]. However, ADPs do not only display local structural dynamics but also contain other sources of hierarchical disorder, such as lattice and molecular displacements [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref>], and may thus disguise subtle conformational changes. As changes in torsion angles are separated by lower energy barriers than changes in coordinates, they are more sensitive to conformational dynamics. Previously it was established that torsion angle deviations preserve temperature induced dynamics [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">21</xref>]. Therefore, we analysed the torsion angle distribution in both enzymes, to further investigate the response to altered environmental temperatures and delineate local structural changes. Clearly, both the CTX-M-14 as well as the XI sub-datasets assemble into temperature-specific clusters, emphasizing a coherent conformational space that corresponds to environmental temperature (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig.1 d,e</xref>). However, analysis of the torsion angle dynamics also permits identification of local structural elements that directly respond to temperature changes. Thus, mapping the torsion angle deviation onto the backbone of the protein structures highlights hinge regions with particular flexibility (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig.1 f,g</xref>). Collectively, these data unambiguously show a direct response of the conformational dynamics to the temperature inside of the environmental control box, and that these temperature changes can be effectively projected to structural changes.</p><p id="P4">Next, we analysed the effect of temperature on the catalytic activity of our two model enzymes. To assess thermal effects on catalysis, we equilibrated the crystals at a given temperature and triggered their reaction by adding the substrate solution <italic>via</italic> the LAMA-method [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref>] and monitored turnover at a constant time-delay of 3 s (CTX-M-14) and 60 s (XI) after reaction initiation, respectively (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T7">extended data table 7</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="T8">8</xref>). To minimize interpretation bias, we assembled the previously known, stable reaction intermediates into one structure and relied on constrained group refinement to determine the occupancy of the different overlapping sub-states at the respective delay time points (extended data) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">26</xref>]. Since different catalytic sub-states of CTX-M-14 can clearly be distinguished (unbound-state, acyl-enzyme intermediate, hydrolysed piperacillin product; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2 a-c</xref>), these data unambiguously show that both ligand diffusion as well as turnover kinetics of mesophilic enzymes can be modulated by temperature variation. While the piperacillin hydrolysis by CTX-M-14 is irreversible and progressively proceeds towards a product-bound state, glucose to fructose conversion by XI can also proceed in the backward direction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">23</xref>]. Accordingly, the system obtains an equilibrium between glucose and fructose over time. Snapshots along the reaction coordinate pathway would therefore reflect fractional occupancies of both species, mixed with open-chain reaction intermediates. As XI has an activity optimum at ca. 80 °C [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">23</xref>], an increase of the temperature for a given delay time should shift the population towards the product side. In line with this hypothesis, the XI snapshots 60 s after reaction initiation show progressively decreasing occupancy for the glucose substrate and increasing occupancy for the fructose product with increasing temperature (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2 d-f</xref>). This demonstrates that thermal modulation enables deriving even nuanced shifts in reaction equilibria and thus detailed mechanistic distinctions as a function of the systems energy. This suggests that addressing catalysis at different temperatures enables simultaneous correlation of mechanistic and thermodynamic aspects of protein function. Conducting similar experiments on other systems will allow a general understanding how proteins exchange energy with their environment and how this is related to conformational dynamics and turnover. That is, multi-dimensional analyses are the foundation to experimentally determining free-energy landscapes of proteins in action and thus their unique catalytic pathways [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref>].</p><p id="P5">In summary, our environmental control box permits charting new experimental space for the large number of enzymes that are amenable to time-resolved serial crystallography. <italic>Via</italic> temperature variation it enables the modulation of enzyme kinetics, thereby altering enzyme turnover and allowing for a more in-depth characterization of enzymatic mechanisms. We anticipate that such experiments will contribute to the changing role of structural biology to enable a comprehensive understanding of conformational dynamics and its role in protein function in the future.</p></sec><sec id="S3" sec-type="materials | methods"><title>Material and Methods</title><sec id="S4"><title>Environmental control system</title><p id="P6">For a detailed description of the environmental control box design and characterisation of the temperature and humidity controls, please refer to the extended data section. Briefly: the environmental control box consists of a rail-mounted, retractable, perspex housing with cycloolefin copolymer (COC) and mylar X-ray inlet and outlet windows, respectively. Constant relative humidity and temperature can be achieved by two independent closed loop control circuits, whereby the former is controlled by a flow of humidified air from a hot water bath. Two interchangeable modules are used to control the temperature. Module-1 contains water-cooled Peltier elements, while module-2 consists of simple heating resistors. The modules cover the ranges from +7 °C to +50 °C and +50 °C to +70 °C, respectively. All information that is required for reproduction of the hardware, including 3D-PDFs, CAD files, step-files, electronics, and a bill of materials can be obtained under following DOI: 10.5281/zenodo.12758835</p></sec><sec id="S5"><title>Sample preparation</title><p id="P7">Xylose isomerase was purified as described in detail in the extended data section. For crystallisation, the protein was then concentrated to 80 mg/ml using a 10 MWCO concentrator (Sartorius). Subsequently, microcrystals were obtained by vacuum induced crystallization, as described previously by Martin et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27">27</xref>], in XI crystallization buffer (35% (w/v) PEG 3350, 200 mM LiSO<sub>4</sub> and 10 mM Hepes/NaOH, pH 7.5). Sufficient microcrystal for a typical HARE chip were prepared from 25 µl protein solution (80 mg/ml for xylose isomerase) combined with 25 µl crystallization buffer. For droplet injection 1 M glucose solution was prepared in ddH<sub>2</sub>O prior to data collection and stored at room temperature.</p><p id="P8">CTX-M-14 was purified as described previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">28</xref>]. The CTX-M-14 solution (22 mg/ml) was mixed with 45% (v/v) crystallising agent (40% (w/v) PEG 8000, 200 mM LiSO<sub>4</sub>, 100 mM sodium acetate, pH 4.5) and with 5% (v/v) undiluted seed stock solution to induce micro-crystallization. This resulted in crystals with a homogeneous size distribution of 11-15 µm after approximately 90 minutes. To stop further crystal growth crystals were centrifuged at 200 x g for 5 min and the supernatant was replaced with a stabilisation buffer (28% (w/v) PEG 8000, 140 mM LiSO<sub>4</sub>, 70 mM sodium acetate, 6 mM MES pH 4.5, 15 mM NaCl).</p></sec><sec id="S6"><title>Determination of the melting temperatures</title><p id="P9">The melting temperatures of CTX-M-14 and XI were determined in four different buffer systems each. The buffers tested were the protein storage buffer (buffer 1), crystallization buffer (buffer 2), crystallization buffer without PEG (buffer 3) and activity assay buffer (buffer 4). The proteins were diluted to 1 mg/mL in the respective nanoDSF buffers and incubated for 20 min on ice. Standard grade nanoDSF capillaries (Nanotemper) were loaded into a Prometheus Panta (Nanotemper) controlled by PR. PantaControl (x64). Excitation power was adjusted to 25% and samples were heated from 20 °C to 95 °C with a slope of 1 °C/min. All samples were examined in triplicates and error bars represent standard deviations. Buffer details are listed in the extended data section.</p></sec><sec id="S7"><title>Experimental setup and data collection</title><p id="P10">Diffraction data were collected at the EMBL endstation P14.2 (T-REXX) at the PETRA-III synchrotron (DESY, Hamburg) with an X-ray beam of 10 <italic>×</italic> 7 µm (H×V) on an Eiger 4M detector (Dectris, Baden-Daettwil, Switzerland). Data collection was conducted as previously described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref>] within the environmental control box mounted on the T-REXX endstation. Briefly: microcrystals mounted in a HARE-chip solid target containing 20,736 wells were moved through the X-ray beam using a 3-axis piezo translation stage setup (SmarAct, Oldenburg, Germany) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">29</xref>]. Time delays for time-resolved data collection were generated <italic>via</italic> the HARE method and reaction initiation was achieved <italic>via in-situ</italic> droplet injection via the LAMA method, as previously described in detail [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">29</xref>]. As a broad guideline approximately 5000 still diffraction patterns were recorded per time-point as previously determined to be sufficient [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">30</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="S8"><title>Data processing and structure determination</title><p id="P11">Diffraction data were processed using the CrystFEL v0.10.0 package [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31">31</xref>]. Structures were solved by molecular replacement using PHASER with our previously determined XI and CTX-M-14 structures as a search model with one molecule in the asymmetric unit (PDB-ID: 6RNF, 6GTH) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32">32</xref>]. Structures were refined by iterative cycles in <italic>phenix.refine</italic> and manual model building of additional and disordered residues in COOT-v0.8 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33">33</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35">35</xref>]. Occupancy refinement was carried out in <italic>phenix.refine</italic> by defining constrained occupancy groups of ligand-free and ligand-bound proteins, and refining against all states simultaneously. Further details are given in the extended data section.</p></sec><sec id="S9"><title>Electron density figures</title><p id="P12">POLDER-OMIT maps were generated using <italic>phenix.polder</italic>, omitting the ligand residues in the constrained occupancy groups [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36">36</xref>]. Molecular images were generated in PyMOL [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37">37</xref>]. Further details are given in the extended data section.</p></sec><sec id="S10"><title>Fitting ADPs to a shifted inverse gamma distribution</title><p id="P13">The isotropic ADP frequency histograms of each structure were fitted with a three parameter Shifted Inverse Gamma Distribution (SIGD) function as shown previously by Masmaliyeva et al [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">22</xref>]. However, in contrast to the maximum-likelihood estimation using the Fisher scoring method applied previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">22</xref>], parameter estimation and optimization was carried out by using non-linear least squares with the python module <monospace>scipy.optimize.curve_fit</monospace>. To produce reasonable estimates, necessary parameter restraints [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">22</xref>], were applied during the estimation process. Briefly, the starting value of the shift parameter was taken to be equal to 90% of the minimum of the ADPs in the PDB file.</p></sec><sec id="S11"><title>Sub-dataset splitting and analysis with RoPE</title><p id="P14">For the RoPE analysis, each dataset was split into subsets of at least 2000 diffraction patterns each using <italic>partialator</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31">31</xref>], which were then independently refined with DIMPLE [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38">38</xref>], without human intervention. This allows us to assess the relative contributions of random fluctuation and genuinely temperature-dependent changes within the crystal structure, as employed previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39">39</xref>]. The output of these PDBs was analysed in RoPE [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">21</xref>] to show the first two principal components of atomic coordinate differences, and corresponding temperature metadata.</p></sec></sec><sec id="S12" sec-type="extended-data"><title>Extended Data</title><fig id="F3" position="anchor"><label>Ext. Fig. 1</label><caption><title>Schematic representation of the environmental control box setup.</title><p id="P27">Gas flow is indicated by blue lines, power supply is red, sensor cables are depicted in green, and cooling water is displayed in pink.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS197743-f003"/></fig><fig id="F4" position="anchor"><label>Ext. Fig. 2</label><caption><title>The Serial Crystallography Environmental Control Box.</title><p id="P28">a) overview of the environmental control box, with retracted LAMA nozzle and Peltier module-1. b) closeup of the Peltier module-1, c) top-view providing an overview of the arrangement inside the box, d) front-, side- and rear-view of the box. Note: for clarity module-2 and some technical elements of the box (e.g. tubing, electric connections etc.) or the beamline are not shown or described in detail. Elements mentioned in the text are numbered and shown in the figure legend.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS197743-f004"/></fig><fig id="F5" position="anchor"><label>Ext. Fig. 3</label><caption><title>Control unit of the serial crystallography environmental control box.</title><p id="P29">a) front panel: 1) main power switch; 2) humidity control/display; 3) air flow switch; 4) temperature display; 5) airflow on/off switch; 6) inflatable front-window flow on/off switch; 7) Temperature control start/stop button; 8) heat-belt switch; 9) socket for IR backlight switch; 10) fan-speed regulator; 11) air-flow valve; 12) front-window flow valve. b) rear panel: 1) main power inlet; 2) heat belt power outlet; 3) PT100 temperature sensor; 4) humidity sensor; 5) fan connection; 6) Peltier/resistor connection; 7) USB connection to PC; 8) backlight connection; 9) pressurized air in; 10) air flow to water bath; 11) dry air outlet; 12) backlight cylinder air outlet; 13) inflatable front-window air outlet.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS197743-f005"/></fig><fig id="F6" position="anchor"><label>Ext. Fig. 4</label><caption><title>Characterization of the environmental control.</title><p id="P30">a) module-1: 7.5 °C − 55 °C; b) module-2: 50-80 °C; The temperature was successively increased from 7.5 °C to 55 °C and 50 °C to 80 °C respectively. The temperature was measured at three positions inside of the chamber: green inside the box near the panel opposite to the access hatch, blue directly above the humidity sensor, red directly on the chip. The target humidity was set to 95%. The grey bars indicate the equilibration time, blue bars indicate the target window.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS197743-f006"/></fig><fig id="F7" position="anchor"><label>Ext. Fig. 5</label><caption><title>Humidity dependent unit-cell modulation displayed in a hit map.</title><p id="P31">The HARE chips consist of 6x6 compartments, divided into 24x24 features. Each feature is indicated by a small square; a blue square indicates a diffraction pattern in the low humidity unit cell, a red square a diffraction pattern in the larger high-humidity unit cell. Humidity has been reduced by 5% for each row of compartments. a) low-humidity diffraction patterns b) high-humidity diffraction patterns; c) overlay of low- and high-humidity diffraction pattern hits; d) comparison of high- and low-humidity unit-cells.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS197743-f007"/></fig><fig id="F8" position="anchor"><label>Ext. Fig. 6</label><caption><title>Melting temperature determination.</title><p id="P32">The figure shows the melting temperature for CTX-M-14 and XI determined by nanoDSF in 4 different buffer systems each. The in-solution melting temperature reflects the activity optima of the mesophilic and hyperthermophilic proteins, respectively.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS197743-f008"/></fig><fig id="F9" position="anchor"><label>Ext. Fig. 7</label><caption><title>Pairwise C<italic><sub>α</sub></italic> RMSD heatmap.</title><p id="P33">Backbone RMSDs in Å between pairs of structures at different temperatures for both model systems.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS197743-f009"/></fig><table-wrap id="T1" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"><label>Ext. Tab. 1</label><caption><title>PyMol color settings to display volume elements.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left">Color</th><th valign="top" align="center">map RMSD.</th><th valign="top" align="left">R</th><th valign="top" align="left">G</th><th valign="top" align="left">B</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left">Blue</td><td valign="top" align="center">1.0</td><td valign="top" align="left">19</td><td valign="top" align="left">43</td><td valign="top" align="left">157</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">Cyan</td><td valign="top" align="center">1.5</td><td valign="top" align="left">153</td><td valign="top" align="left">219</td><td valign="top" align="left">223</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">Green</td><td valign="top" align="center">2.0</td><td valign="top" align="left">101</td><td valign="top" align="left">198</td><td valign="top" align="left">66</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">Yellow</td><td valign="top" align="center">2.5</td><td valign="top" align="left">255</td><td valign="top" align="left">240</td><td valign="top" align="left">0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">Orange</td><td valign="top" align="center">3.0</td><td valign="top" align="left">252</td><td valign="top" align="left">131</td><td valign="top" align="left">0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">Red</td><td valign="top" align="center">3.5</td><td valign="top" align="left">245</td><td valign="top" align="left">38</td><td valign="top" align="left">0</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T2" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"><label>Ext. Tab. 2</label><caption><title>Environmental control parameter settings</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="center"/><th valign="top" align="center">desired temp. °C</th><th valign="top" align="center">flow rate L min<sup>−1</sup></th><th valign="top" align="center">desired humidity (%)</th><th valign="top" align="center">actual humidity (%)</th><th valign="top" align="center">water bath temp °C</th><th valign="top" align="center">heat belt power (%)</th><th valign="top" align="center">module current (A)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="6" style="writing-mode:tb-rl;writing-mode:vertical-rl">module-1</td><td valign="top" align="center">7.5</td><td valign="top" align="center">5</td><td valign="top" align="center">95</td><td valign="top" align="center">95</td><td valign="top" align="center">75</td><td valign="top" align="center">0</td><td valign="top" align="center">-12.3</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="center">15</td><td valign="top" align="center">5</td><td valign="top" align="center">95</td><td valign="top" align="center">95</td><td valign="top" align="center">75</td><td valign="top" align="center">50</td><td valign="top" align="center">-2.1</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="center">25</td><td valign="top" align="center">5</td><td valign="top" align="center">95</td><td valign="top" align="center">95</td><td valign="top" align="center">75</td><td valign="top" align="center">100</td><td valign="top" align="center">1.7</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="center">35</td><td valign="top" align="center">4</td><td valign="top" align="center">95</td><td valign="top" align="center">95</td><td valign="top" align="center">85</td><td valign="top" align="center">100</td><td valign="top" align="center">3.5</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="center">45</td><td valign="top" align="center">4</td><td valign="top" align="center">95</td><td valign="top" align="center">95</td><td valign="top" align="center">95</td><td valign="top" align="center">100</td><td valign="top" align="center">4.8</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="center">55</td><td valign="top" align="center">4</td><td valign="top" align="center">95</td><td valign="top" align="center">95</td><td valign="top" align="center">95</td><td valign="top" align="center">100</td><td valign="top" align="center">6</td></tr><tr style="border-top: solid thin"><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="7" style="writing-mode:tb-rl;writing-mode:vertical-rl">module-2</td><td valign="top" align="center">50</td><td valign="top" align="center">4</td><td valign="top" align="center">95</td><td valign="top" align="center">95</td><td valign="top" align="center">95</td><td valign="top" align="center">100</td><td valign="top" align="center">2.4</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="center">55</td><td valign="top" align="center">4</td><td valign="top" align="center">95</td><td valign="top" align="center">95</td><td valign="top" align="center">95</td><td valign="top" align="center">100</td><td valign="top" align="center">2.9</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="center">60</td><td valign="top" align="center">4</td><td valign="top" align="center">9</td><td valign="top" align="center">95</td><td valign="top" align="center">95</td><td valign="top" align="center">100</td><td valign="top" align="center">2.6</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="center">65</td><td valign="top" align="center">4</td><td valign="top" align="center">95</td><td valign="top" align="center">95</td><td valign="top" align="center">95</td><td valign="top" align="center">100</td><td valign="top" align="center">2.9</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="center">70</td><td valign="top" align="center">4</td><td valign="top" align="center">95</td><td valign="top" align="center">95</td><td valign="top" align="center">95</td><td valign="top" align="center">100</td><td valign="top" align="center">3.1</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="center">75</td><td valign="top" align="center">4</td><td valign="top" align="center">95</td><td valign="top" align="center">95</td><td valign="top" align="center">95</td><td valign="top" align="center">100</td><td valign="top" align="center">4.3</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="center">80</td><td valign="top" align="center">4</td><td valign="top" align="center">95</td><td valign="top" align="center">95</td><td valign="top" align="center">95</td><td valign="top" align="center">100</td><td valign="top" align="center">3.4</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T3" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"><label>Ext. Tab. 3</label><caption><title>Environmental parameters during X-ray diffraction data collection.</title><p id="P34">*values are derived from a long-term, (10 h) data-collection</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left">nominal temp. (° C)</th><th valign="top" align="center">nominal rel. humidity (%)</th><th valign="top" align="center">measured rel. humidity (%)</th><th valign="top" align="center">RMSD (%)</th><th valign="top" align="center">measured temp. (° C)</th><th valign="top" align="center">RMSD (° C)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left">20</td><td valign="top" align="center">95</td><td valign="top" align="center">95.4</td><td valign="top" align="center">0.5</td><td valign="top" align="center">19.8</td><td valign="top" align="center">0.2</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">40</td><td valign="top" align="center">95</td><td valign="top" align="center">95.5</td><td valign="top" align="center">0.9</td><td valign="top" align="center">40.3</td><td valign="top" align="center">0.3</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">55</td><td valign="top" align="center">95</td><td valign="top" align="center">95.5</td><td valign="top" align="center">0.7</td><td valign="top" align="center">55.3</td><td valign="top" align="center">0.7</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">80</td><td valign="top" align="center">95</td><td valign="top" align="center">95.2</td><td valign="top" align="center">0.7</td><td valign="top" align="center">80.1</td><td valign="top" align="center">0.3</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">20*</td><td valign="top" align="center">95*</td><td valign="top" align="center">95.2*</td><td valign="top" align="center">0.7*</td><td valign="top" align="center">19.8*</td><td valign="top" align="center">0.2*</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T4" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"><label>Ext. Tab. 4</label><caption><title>Nano-DSF buffer for T<sub><italic>M</italic></sub> determination</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left">CTX-M-14-buffer 1</td><td valign="top" align="left">20 mM MES pH 6.0, 50 mM NaCl</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">CTX-M-14-buffer 2</td><td valign="top" align="left">140 mM Li<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>, 15 mM NaCl, 70 mM NaOAc pH 4.5, 6 mM MES, 28% PEG 8000</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">CTX-M-14-buffer 3</td><td valign="top" align="left">140 mM Li<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>, 15 mM NaCl, 70 mM NaOAc pH 4.5, 6 mM MES</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">CTX-M-14-buffer 4</td><td valign="top" align="left">140 mM Li<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>, 15 mM NaCl, 70 mM NaOAc pH 4.5, 6 mM MES, 1.5% PEG 8000</td></tr><tr style="border-top: 1px solid"><td valign="top" align="center"> XI-buffer 1</td><td valign="top" align="left">20 mM HEPES pH 7.5</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="center"> XI-buffer 2</td><td valign="top" align="left">10 mM HEPES pH 7.5, 0.2 M Li<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>, 25% PEG 3350</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="center"> XI-buffer 3</td><td valign="top" align="left">10 mM HEPES pH 7.5, 0.2 M Li<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="center"> XI-buffer 4</td><td valign="top" align="left">10 mM HEPES pH 7.5, 0.05 M MgCl<sub>2</sub></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T5" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"><label>Ext. Tab. 5</label><caption><title>Data collection and refinement statistics for CTX-M-14 apo data.</title><p id="P35">Values in the highest resolution shell are shown in parentheses.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left">Temperature (°C) (PDB-ID)</th><th valign="top" align="center">10° C (9G7V)</th><th valign="top" align="center">20° C (9G7W)</th><th valign="top" align="center">30° C (9G7X)</th><th valign="top" align="center">40° C (9G7Y)</th><th valign="top" align="center">50° C (9G7Z)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left"><italic><bold>Data collection</bold></italic></td><td valign="top" align="center"/><td valign="top" align="center"/><td valign="top" align="center"/><td valign="top" align="center"/><td valign="top" align="center"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">Space group</td><td valign="top" align="center">P3221</td><td valign="top" align="center">P3221</td><td valign="top" align="center">P3221</td><td valign="top" align="center">P3221</td><td valign="top" align="center">P3221</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">Cell dimensions</td><td valign="top" align="center"/><td valign="top" align="center"/><td valign="top" align="center"/><td valign="top" align="center"/><td valign="top" align="center"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left"><italic>a, b, c (Å)</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center">42.23, 42.26,</td><td valign="top" align="center">42.22, 42.24,</td><td valign="top" align="center">42.28, 42.31,</td><td valign="top" align="center">42.32, 42.34,</td><td valign="top" align="center">42.40, 42.44,</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left"/><td valign="top" align="center">234.09</td><td valign="top" align="center">234.15</td><td valign="top" align="center">234.66</td><td valign="top" align="center">234.84</td><td valign="top" align="center">235.33</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left"><italic>α, β, γ (°)</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center">90.0, 90.0,</td><td valign="top" align="center">90.0, 90.0,</td><td valign="top" align="center">90.0, 90.0,</td><td valign="top" align="center">90.0, 90.0,</td><td valign="top" align="center">90.0, 90.0,</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left"/><td valign="top" align="center">120.0</td><td valign="top" align="center">120.0</td><td valign="top" align="center">120.0</td><td valign="top" align="center">120.0</td><td valign="top" align="center">120.0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">Resolution</td><td valign="top" align="center">77.62 - 1.70</td><td valign="top" align="center">77.62 - 1.70</td><td valign="top" align="center">77.62 - 1.70</td><td valign="top" align="center">77.62 - 1.70</td><td valign="top" align="center">77.62 - 1.70</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">range (Å)</td><td valign="top" align="center">(1.76 -1.70)</td><td valign="top" align="center">(1.76 -1.70)</td><td valign="top" align="center">(1.76 -1.70)</td><td valign="top" align="center">(1.76 -1.70)</td><td valign="top" align="center">(1.76 -1.70)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">Total reflections</td><td valign="top" align="center">12049024</td><td valign="top" align="center">9717308</td><td valign="top" align="center">7141365</td><td valign="top" align="center">9167246</td><td valign="top" align="center">6703777</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left"/><td valign="top" align="center">(713700)</td><td valign="top" align="center">(575163)</td><td valign="top" align="center">(422198)</td><td valign="top" align="center">(544370)</td><td valign="top" align="center">(398067)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">Unique reflections</td><td valign="top" align="center">27454 (2685)</td><td valign="top" align="center">27455 (2685)</td><td valign="top" align="center">27454 (2685)</td><td valign="top" align="center">27454 (2685)</td><td valign="top" align="center">27455 (2685)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left"/><td valign="top" align="center"/><td valign="top" align="center"/><td valign="top" align="center"/><td valign="top" align="center"/><td valign="top" align="center"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">Redundancy</td><td valign="top" align="center">428.9 (265.8)</td><td valign="top" align="center">353.9 (214.2)</td><td valign="top" align="center">260.1 (157.2)</td><td valign="top" align="center">333.9 (202.7)</td><td valign="top" align="center">244.2 (148.3)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">Completeness</td><td valign="top" align="center">1.00 (1.00)</td><td valign="top" align="center">1.00 (1.00)</td><td valign="top" align="center">1.00 (1.00)</td><td valign="top" align="center">1.00 (1.00)</td><td valign="top" align="center">1.00 (1.00)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">(%)</td><td valign="top" align="center"/><td valign="top" align="center"/><td valign="top" align="center"/><td valign="top" align="center"/><td valign="top" align="center"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">Mean I/<italic>σ</italic> (I)</td><td valign="top" align="center">7.99 (1.99)</td><td valign="top" align="center">7.40 (2.17)</td><td valign="top" align="center">6.32 (1.79)</td><td valign="top" align="center">7.02 (1.71)</td><td valign="top" align="center">5.65 (1.04)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">Wilson B-factor (Å<sup>2</sup>)</td><td valign="top" align="center">22.12</td><td valign="top" align="center">21.19</td><td valign="top" align="center">21.97</td><td valign="top" align="center">23.14</td><td valign="top" align="center">25.98</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left"><italic>R</italic><sub>split</sub></td><td valign="top" align="center">0.101 (0.503)</td><td valign="top" align="center">0.112 (0.453)</td><td valign="top" align="center">0.127 (0.550)</td><td valign="top" align="center">0.112 (0.590)</td><td valign="top" align="center">0.133 (0.962)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">CC1/2</td><td valign="top" align="center">0.985 (0.756)</td><td valign="top" align="center">0.979 (0.803)</td><td valign="top" align="center">0.972 (0.723)</td><td valign="top" align="center">0.978 (0.714)</td><td valign="top" align="center">0.967 (0.481)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">CC*</td><td valign="top" align="center">0.996 (0.928)</td><td valign="top" align="center">0.995 (0.944)</td><td valign="top" align="center">0.993 (0.916)</td><td valign="top" align="center">0.994 (0.913)</td><td valign="top" align="center">0.992 (0.806)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left"><italic><bold>Refinement</bold></italic></td><td valign="top" align="center"/><td valign="top" align="center"/><td valign="top" align="center"/><td valign="top" align="center"/><td valign="top" align="center"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">Reflections</td><td valign="top" align="center">27325 (2673)</td><td valign="top" align="center">27341 (2676)</td><td valign="top" align="center">27337 (2671)</td><td valign="top" align="center">27344 (2675)</td><td valign="top" align="center">27322 (2557)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">used in refinement</td><td valign="top" align="center"/><td valign="top" align="center"/><td valign="top" align="center"/><td valign="top" align="center"/><td valign="top" align="center"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left"><italic>R</italic>work</td><td valign="top" align="center">0.1614</td><td valign="top" align="center">0.1678</td><td valign="top" align="center">0.1569</td><td valign="top" align="center">0.1550</td><td valign="top" align="center">0.1598</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left"/><td valign="top" align="center">(0.2504)</td><td valign="top" align="center">(0.2417)</td><td valign="top" align="center">(0.2526)</td><td valign="top" align="center">(0.2527)</td><td valign="top" align="center">(0.3133)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left"><italic>R</italic>free</td><td valign="top" align="center">0.1901</td><td valign="top" align="center">0.1907</td><td valign="top" align="center">0.1836</td><td valign="top" align="center">0.1784</td><td valign="top" align="center">0.1861</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left"/><td valign="top" align="center">(0.2452)</td><td valign="top" align="center">(0.2444)</td><td valign="top" align="center">(0.2390)</td><td valign="top" align="center">(0.2756)</td><td valign="top" align="center">(0.2915)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">Reflections used for <italic>R</italic><sub>free</sub></td><td valign="top" align="center">1354 (112)</td><td valign="top" align="center">1354 (111)</td><td valign="top" align="center">1353 (112)</td><td valign="top" align="center">1354 (112)</td><td valign="top" align="center">1353 (111)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">Number of non-hydrogen</td><td valign="top" align="center">2242</td><td valign="top" align="center">2230</td><td valign="top" align="center">2209</td><td valign="top" align="center">2196</td><td valign="top" align="center">2177</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">atoms</td><td valign="top" align="center"/><td valign="top" align="center"/><td valign="top" align="center"/><td valign="top" align="center"/><td valign="top" align="center"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">macromolecules</td><td valign="top" align="center">2067</td><td valign="top" align="center">2060</td><td valign="top" align="center">2046</td><td valign="top" align="center">2044</td><td valign="top" align="center">2037</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">ligands</td><td valign="top" align="center">5</td><td valign="top" align="center">5</td><td valign="top" align="center">5</td><td valign="top" align="center">5</td><td valign="top" align="center">5</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">solvent</td><td valign="top" align="center">170</td><td valign="top" align="center">165</td><td valign="top" align="center">158</td><td valign="top" align="center">147</td><td valign="top" align="center">135</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left"><italic>Average B-factor (Å</italic><sup>2</sup><italic>)</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center">28.15</td><td valign="top" align="center">27.03</td><td valign="top" align="center">27.87</td><td valign="top" align="center">28.20</td><td valign="top" align="center">31.46</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">macromolecules</td><td valign="top" align="center">27.24</td><td valign="top" align="center">26.22</td><td valign="top" align="center">26.97</td><td valign="top" align="center">27.36</td><td valign="top" align="center">30.69</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">ligands</td><td valign="top" align="center">36.95</td><td valign="top" align="center">34.88</td><td valign="top" align="center">38.77</td><td valign="top" align="center">42.07</td><td valign="top" align="center">46.95</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">solvent</td><td valign="top" align="center">38.89</td><td valign="top" align="center">36.81</td><td valign="top" align="center">39.20</td><td valign="top" align="center">39.32</td><td valign="top" align="center">42.47</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left"><italic>RMS deviations</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center"/><td valign="top" align="center"/><td valign="top" align="center"/><td valign="top" align="center"/><td valign="top" align="center"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">Bond lengths (Å)</td><td valign="top" align="center">0.005</td><td valign="top" align="center">0.004</td><td valign="top" align="center">0.005</td><td valign="top" align="center">0.005</td><td valign="top" align="center">0.005</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">Bond angles (°)</td><td valign="top" align="center">0.772</td><td valign="top" align="center">0.675</td><td valign="top" align="center">0.812</td><td valign="top" align="center">0.825</td><td valign="top" align="center">0.795</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T6" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"><label>Ext. Tab. 6</label><caption><title>Data collection and refinement statistics of the XI apo data.</title><p id="P36">Values in the highest resolution shell are shown in parentheses</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left">Temperature (°C) (PDB- ID)</th><th valign="top" align="center">20° C (9G5N)</th><th valign="top" align="center">30°C (9G5S)</th><th valign="top" align="center">40°C (9G5W)</th><th valign="top" align="center">45°C (9G5X)</th><th valign="top" align="center">50°C (9G61)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left"><italic><bold>Data collection</bold></italic></td><td valign="top" align="center"/><td valign="top" align="center"/><td valign="top" align="center"/><td valign="top" align="center"/><td valign="top" align="center"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">Space group</td><td valign="top" align="center">I 2 2 2</td><td valign="top" align="center">I 2 2 2</td><td valign="top" align="center">I 2 2 2</td><td valign="top" align="center">I 2 2 2</td><td valign="top" align="center">I 2 2 2</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">Cell dimensions</td><td valign="top" align="center"/><td valign="top" align="center"/><td valign="top" align="center"/><td valign="top" align="center"/><td valign="top" align="center"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left"><italic>a, b, c (Å)</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center">94.2 103.05</td><td valign="top" align="center">94.2 103.05</td><td valign="top" align="center">94.2 103.05</td><td valign="top" align="center">94.2 103.05</td><td valign="top" align="center">94.2 103.05</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left"/><td valign="top" align="center">99.25</td><td valign="top" align="center">99.25</td><td valign="top" align="center">99.25</td><td valign="top" align="center">99.25</td><td valign="top" align="center">99.25</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left"><italic>α</italic>, <italic>β</italic>, <italic>γ</italic> (°)</td><td valign="top" align="center">90.0 90.0 90.0</td><td valign="top" align="center">90.0 90.0 90.0</td><td valign="top" align="center">90.0 90.0 90.0</td><td valign="top" align="center">90.0 90.0 90.0</td><td valign="top" align="center">90.0 90.0 90.0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">Resolution</td><td valign="top" align="center">71.49 - 1.7</td><td valign="top" align="center">71.49 - 1.7</td><td valign="top" align="center">71.49 - 1.7</td><td valign="top" align="center">71.49 - 1.7</td><td valign="top" align="center">71.49 - 1.7</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">range (Å)</td><td valign="top" align="center">(1.761 - 1.7)</td><td valign="top" align="center">(1.761 - 1.7)</td><td valign="top" align="center">(1.761 - 1.7)</td><td valign="top" align="center">(1.761 - 1.7)</td><td valign="top" align="center">(1.761 - 1.7)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">Total reflections</td><td valign="top" align="center">20298653</td><td valign="top" align="center">10229855</td><td valign="top" align="center">10613133</td><td valign="top" align="center">81189855</td><td valign="top" align="center">23289164</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">Unique reflections</td><td valign="top" align="center">53351 (5284)</td><td valign="top" align="center">53338 (5277)</td><td valign="top" align="center">53317 (5271)</td><td valign="top" align="center">53331 (5273)</td><td valign="top" align="center">53297 (5253)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">Redundancy</td><td valign="top" align="center">380.3(224.3)</td><td valign="top" align="center">191.7(113.2)</td><td valign="top" align="center">198.8(117.7)</td><td valign="top" align="center">1521.2(904.5)</td><td valign="top" align="center">436.3(258.8)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">Completeness</td><td valign="top" align="center">99.96 (99.96)</td><td valign="top" align="center">99.93 (99.83)</td><td valign="top" align="center">99.89 (99.72)</td><td valign="top" align="center">99.92 (99.75)</td><td valign="top" align="center">99.85 (99.38)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">(%)</td><td valign="top" align="center"/><td valign="top" align="center"/><td valign="top" align="center"/><td valign="top" align="center"/><td valign="top" align="center"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">Mean I/<italic>σ</italic>(I)</td><td valign="top" align="center">5.55(3.31)</td><td valign="top" align="center">3.83(1.50)</td><td valign="top" align="center">3.59(0.98)</td><td valign="top" align="center">8.57(2.88)</td><td valign="top" align="center">4.87(1.14)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">Wilson B-factor</td><td valign="top" align="center">15.26</td><td valign="top" align="center">17.54</td><td valign="top" align="center">20.14</td><td valign="top" align="center">19.82</td><td valign="top" align="center">21.96</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left"><italic>Rsplit</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center">20.92(33.98)</td><td valign="top" align="center">26.71(66.18)</td><td valign="top" align="center">24.74(102.55)</td><td valign="top" align="center">10.09(31.25)</td><td valign="top" align="center">17.46(90.39)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">CC<sup>1<italic>/</italic></sup><sup>2</sup></td><td valign="top" align="center">92.76(76.23)</td><td valign="top" align="center">89.39(56.02)</td><td valign="top" align="center">92.27(38.03)</td><td valign="top" align="center">98.64(86.29)</td><td valign="top" align="center">96.25(45.20)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">CC*</td><td valign="top" align="center">98.10(93.01)</td><td valign="top" align="center">97.16(84.74)</td><td valign="top" align="center">97.97(74.23)</td><td valign="top" align="center">99.66(96.25)</td><td valign="top" align="center">99.04(78.90)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left"><italic><bold>Refinement</bold></italic></td><td valign="top" align="center"/><td valign="top" align="center"/><td valign="top" align="center"/><td valign="top" align="center"/><td valign="top" align="center"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">Reflections</td><td valign="top" align="center">53351 (5284)</td><td valign="top" align="center">53338 (5277)</td><td valign="top" align="center">53317 (5271)</td><td valign="top" align="center">53331 (5273)</td><td valign="top" align="center">53297 (5253)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">used in refinement</td><td valign="top" align="center"/><td valign="top" align="center"/><td valign="top" align="center"/><td valign="top" align="center"/><td valign="top" align="center"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left"><italic>R<sub>work</sub></italic></td><td valign="top" align="center">0.1624</td><td valign="top" align="center">0.1680</td><td valign="top" align="left">0.1727</td><td valign="top" align="center">0.1453</td><td valign="top" align="center">0.1590</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left"/><td valign="top" align="center">(0.2901)</td><td valign="top" align="center">(0.3272)</td><td valign="top" align="center">(0.3735)</td><td valign="top" align="center">(0.3158)</td><td valign="top" align="center">(0.3597)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left"><italic>R<sub>free</sub></italic></td><td valign="top" align="center">0.1906</td><td valign="top" align="center">0.2096</td><td valign="top" align="center">0.2072</td><td valign="top" align="center">0.1824</td><td valign="top" align="center">0.1903</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left"/><td valign="top" align="center">(0.3290)</td><td valign="top" align="center">(0.3910)</td><td valign="top" align="center">(0.4166)</td><td valign="top" align="center">(0.3611)</td><td valign="top" align="center">(0.3987)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">Reflections used for <italic>R<sub>free</sub></italic></td><td valign="top" align="center">2607 (291)</td><td valign="top" align="center">2607 (291)</td><td valign="top" align="center">2606 (291)</td><td valign="top" align="center">2605 (290)</td><td valign="top" align="center">2603 (288)</td><td valign="top" align="center"/><td valign="top" align="center"/><td valign="top" align="center"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">Number of</td><td valign="top" align="center">3637</td><td valign="top" align="center">3566</td><td valign="top" align="center">3638</td><td valign="top" align="center">3552</td><td valign="top" align="center">3543</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">non-hydrogen atoms</td><td valign="top" align="center"/><td valign="top" align="center"/><td valign="top" align="center"/><td valign="top" align="center"/><td valign="top" align="center"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">macromolecules</td><td valign="top" align="center">3275</td><td valign="top" align="center">3234</td><td valign="top" align="center">3325</td><td valign="top" align="center">3261</td><td valign="top" align="center">3284</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">ligands</td><td valign="top" align="center">2</td><td valign="top" align="center">3</td><td valign="top" align="center">2</td><td valign="top" align="center">3</td><td valign="top" align="center">2</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">solvent</td><td valign="top" align="center">360</td><td valign="top" align="center">329</td><td valign="top" align="center">311</td><td valign="top" align="center">288</td><td valign="top" align="center">257</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">Average B-factor (Å<sup>2</sup>)</td><td valign="top" align="center">17.69</td><td valign="top" align="center">20.2</td><td valign="top" align="center">23.47</td><td valign="top" align="center">22.92</td><td valign="top" align="center">25.36</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">macromolecules</td><td valign="top" align="center">16.22</td><td valign="top" align="center">19.02</td><td valign="top" align="center">22.33</td><td valign="top" align="center">21.86</td><td valign="top" align="center">24.56</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">ligands</td><td valign="top" align="center">16.02</td><td valign="top" align="center">11.48</td><td valign="top" align="center">17.73</td><td valign="top" align="center">12.44</td><td valign="top" align="center">18.2</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">solvent</td><td valign="top" align="center">31.14</td><td valign="top" align="center">31.91</td><td valign="top" align="center">35.64</td><td valign="top" align="center">35.04</td><td valign="top" align="center">35.67</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left"><italic>RMS deviations</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center"/><td valign="top" align="center"/><td valign="top" align="center"/><td valign="top" align="center"/><td valign="top" align="center"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">Bond lengths</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">(Å)</td><td valign="top" align="center">0.006</td><td valign="top" align="center">0.016</td><td valign="top" align="center">0.004</td><td valign="top" align="center">0.013</td><td valign="top" align="center">0.004</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">Bond angles</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">(°)</td><td valign="top" align="center">0.8</td><td valign="top" align="center">1.34</td><td valign="top" align="center">0.65</td><td valign="top" align="center">1.23</td><td valign="top" align="center">0.67</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T7" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"><label>Ext. Tab. 7</label><caption><title>Data collection and refinement statistics of the CTX-M-14 Piperacillin data at a time-delay of 3s.</title><p id="P37">Values in the highest resolution shell are shown in parentheses.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left">Temperature (°C) (PDB-ID)</th><th valign="top" align="center">20 °C (9G80)</th><th valign="top" align="center">30 °C (9G81)</th><th valign="top" align="center">37 °C (9G82)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left"><italic><bold>Data collection</bold></italic></td><td valign="top" align="center"/><td valign="top" align="center"/><td valign="top" align="center"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">Space group</td><td valign="top" align="center">P322<sub>1</sub></td><td valign="top" align="center">P322<sub>1</sub></td><td valign="top" align="center">P322<sub>1</sub></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">Cell dimensions</td><td valign="top" align="center"/><td valign="top" align="center"/><td valign="top" align="center"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left"><italic>a, b, c (Å)</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center">42.15, 42.15,</td><td valign="top" align="center">42.20, 42.20,</td><td valign="top" align="center">42.25, 42.25,</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left"/><td valign="top" align="center">234.14</td><td valign="top" align="center">234.53</td><td valign="top" align="center">234.85</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left"><italic>α, β, γ (°)</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center">89.99, 89.99,</td><td valign="top" align="center">89.99, 89.99,</td><td valign="top" align="center">89.99, 89.98,</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left"/><td valign="top" align="center">119.98</td><td valign="top" align="center">119.93</td><td valign="top" align="center">119.93</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">Resolution range</td><td valign="top" align="center">78.07 - 1.70 (1.76</td><td valign="top" align="center">78.07 - 1.70 (1.76</td><td valign="top" align="center">78.07 - 1.70 (1.76</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">(Å)</td><td valign="top" align="center">-1.70)</td><td valign="top" align="center">-1.70)</td><td valign="top" align="center">-1.70)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">Total reflections</td><td valign="top" align="center">1266008 (75053)</td><td valign="top" align="center">3599661 (216133)</td><td valign="top" align="center">4883576 (290896)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">Unique reflections</td><td valign="top" align="center">27981 (2739)</td><td valign="top" align="center">27439 (2662)</td><td valign="top" align="center">27982 (2734)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">Redundancy</td><td valign="top" align="center">45.2 (27.4)</td><td valign="top" align="center">131.2 (81.2)</td><td valign="top" align="center">174.5 (106.4)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">Completeness (%)</td><td valign="top" align="center">1.00 (1.00)</td><td valign="top" align="center">1.00 (1.00)</td><td valign="top" align="center">1.00 (1.00)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">Mean I/<italic>σ</italic> (I)</td><td valign="top" align="center">1.91 (0.25)</td><td valign="top" align="center">4.46 (1.04)</td><td valign="top" align="center">4.36 (0.66)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">Wilson B-factor</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">(Å<sup>2</sup>)</td><td valign="top" align="center">26.44</td><td valign="top" align="center">22.25</td><td valign="top" align="center">24.78</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">R<sub><italic>split</italic></sub></td><td valign="top" align="center">0.364 (4.577)</td><td valign="top" align="center">0.182 (0.995)</td><td valign="top" align="center">0.163 (1.595)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">CC1/2</td><td valign="top" align="center">0.862 (0.034)</td><td valign="top" align="center">0.952 (0.446)</td><td valign="top" align="center">0.959 (0.252)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">CC*</td><td valign="top" align="center">0.962 (0.257)</td><td valign="top" align="center">0.988 (0.786)</td><td valign="top" align="center">0.990 (0.634)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left"><italic><bold>Refinement</bold></italic></td><td valign="top" align="center"/><td valign="top" align="center"/><td valign="top" align="center"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">Reflections used</td><td valign="top" align="center">26826 (1948)</td><td valign="top" align="center">27336 (2363)</td><td valign="top" align="center">27851 (2569)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">in refinement</td><td valign="top" align="center"/><td valign="top" align="center"/><td valign="top" align="center"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">R<italic>work</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center">0.2281 (0.4130)</td><td valign="top" align="center">0.1645 (0.3038)</td><td valign="top" align="center">0.1687 (0.3592)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">R<italic>free</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center">0.2556 (0.4706)</td><td valign="top" align="center">0.1948 (0.3061)</td><td valign="top" align="center">0.1995 (0.3746)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">Reflections used</td><td valign="top" align="center">1315 (103)</td><td valign="top" align="center">1354 (141)</td><td valign="top" align="center">1377 (154)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">for R<sub><italic>free</italic></sub></td><td valign="top" align="center"/><td valign="top" align="center"/><td valign="top" align="center"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">Number of non-hydrogen atoms</td><td valign="top" align="center">2362</td><td valign="top" align="center">2371</td><td valign="top" align="center">2408</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">macromolecules</td><td valign="top" align="center">2156</td><td valign="top" align="center">2148</td><td valign="top" align="center">2193</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">ligands</td><td valign="top" align="center">41</td><td valign="top" align="center">41</td><td valign="top" align="center">41</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">solvent</td><td valign="top" align="center">165</td><td valign="top" align="center">182</td><td valign="top" align="center">174</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left"><italic>Average B-factor (Å</italic><sup>2</sup><italic>)</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center">36.58</td><td valign="top" align="center">29.28</td><td valign="top" align="center">33.14</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">macromolecules</td><td valign="top" align="center">35.32</td><td valign="top" align="center">28.21</td><td valign="top" align="center">31.89</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">ligands</td><td valign="top" align="center">49.55</td><td valign="top" align="center">30.60</td><td valign="top" align="center">39.74</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">solvent</td><td valign="top" align="center">43.45</td><td valign="top" align="center">40.71</td><td valign="top" align="center">44.02</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left"><italic>RMS deviations</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center"/><td valign="top" align="center"/><td valign="top" align="center"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">Bond lengths (Å)</td><td valign="top" align="center">0.002</td><td valign="top" align="center">0.005</td><td valign="top" align="center">0.003</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">Bond angles (°)</td><td valign="top" align="center">0.861</td><td valign="top" align="center">1.046</td><td valign="top" align="center">0.949</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T8" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"><label>Ext. Tab. 8</label><caption><title>Data collection and refinement statistics of the XI 60s data.</title><p id="P38">Values in the highest resolution shell are shown in parentheses.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left">Temperatutre (°C) (PDB- ID)</th><th valign="top" align="center">20°C (9G6L)</th><th valign="top" align="center">30°C (9G6M)</th><th valign="top" align="center">40°C (9G6N)</th><th valign="top" align="center">45°C (9G6O)</th><th valign="top" align="center">50°C (9G6P)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left"><italic><bold>Data collection</bold></italic></td><td valign="top" align="center"/><td valign="top" align="center"/><td valign="top" align="center"/><td valign="top" align="center"/><td valign="top" align="center"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left"><bold>Space</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center">I 2 2 2</td><td valign="top" align="center">I 2 2 2</td><td valign="top" align="center">I 2 2 2</td><td valign="top" align="center">I 2 2 2</td><td valign="top" align="center">I 2 2 2</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left"><bold>group</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center"/><td valign="top" align="center"/><td valign="top" align="center"/><td valign="top" align="center"/><td valign="top" align="center"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left"><bold>Cell dimensions</bold></td><td valign="top" align="left"/><td valign="top" align="left"/><td valign="top" align="left"/><td valign="top" align="left"/><td valign="top" align="left"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left"><italic>a, b, c (Å)</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center">94.2 103.05</td><td valign="top" align="center">94.2 103.05</td><td valign="top" align="center">94.2 103.05</td><td valign="top" align="center">94.2 103.05</td><td valign="top" align="center">94.2 103.05</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left"/><td valign="top" align="center">99.25</td><td valign="top" align="center">99.25</td><td valign="top" align="center">99.25</td><td valign="top" align="center">99.25</td><td valign="top" align="center">99.25</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left"><italic>α</italic>,<italic>β</italic>,<italic>γ</italic> (°)</td><td valign="top" align="center">90.0 90.0 90.0</td><td valign="top" align="center">90.0 90.0 90.0</td><td valign="top" align="center">90.0 90.0 90.0</td><td valign="top" align="center">90.0 90.0 90.0</td><td valign="top" align="center">90.0 90.0 90.0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">Resolution</td><td valign="top" align="center">71.49 - 1.7</td><td valign="top" align="center">71.49 - 1.7</td><td valign="top" align="center">71.49 - 1.7</td><td valign="top" align="center">71.49 - 1.7</td><td valign="top" align="center">71.49 - 1.7</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">range (<italic>Å</italic>)</td><td valign="top" align="center">(1.761 - 1.7)</td><td valign="top" align="center">(1.761 - 1.7)</td><td valign="top" align="center">(1.761 - 1.7)</td><td valign="top" align="center">(1.761 - 1.7)</td><td valign="top" align="center">(1.761 - 1.7)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">Total reflections</td><td valign="top" align="center">9415749</td><td valign="top" align="center">12055922</td><td valign="top" align="center">11970298</td><td valign="top" align="center">26069844</td><td valign="top" align="center">8506453</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">Unique</td><td valign="top" align="center">53357 (5281)</td><td valign="top" align="center">53350 (5281)</td><td valign="top" align="center">53330 (5270)</td><td valign="top" align="center">53342 (5278)</td><td valign="top" align="center">53317 (5273)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">reflections</td><td valign="top" align="center"/><td valign="top" align="center"/><td valign="top" align="center"/><td valign="top" align="center"/><td valign="top" align="center"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">Redundancy</td><td valign="top" align="center">176.4(104.5)</td><td valign="top" align="center">225.9(134.2)</td><td valign="top" align="center">224.3(133.2)</td><td valign="top" align="center">488.4(290.4)</td><td valign="top" align="center">159.4(94.7)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">Completeness</td><td valign="top" align="center">99.97 (99.91)</td><td valign="top" align="center">99.95 (99.91)</td><td valign="top" align="center">99.92 (99.70)</td><td valign="top" align="center">99.94 (99.85)</td><td valign="top" align="center">99.89 (99.75)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">(%)</td><td valign="top" align="center"/><td valign="top" align="center"/><td valign="top" align="center"/><td valign="top" align="center"/><td valign="top" align="center"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">Mean I/<italic>σ</italic>(I)</td><td valign="top" align="center">4.37(2.68)</td><td valign="top" align="center">4.99(2.46)</td><td valign="top" align="center">4.42(1.65)</td><td valign="top" align="center">6.39(2.67)</td><td valign="top" align="center">3.24(0.93)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">Wilson B-factor</td><td valign="top" align="center">15.89</td><td valign="top" align="center">17.92</td><td valign="top" align="center">19.59</td><td valign="top" align="center">21.24</td><td valign="top" align="center">22.4</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">CC1/2</td><td valign="top" align="center">89.59(73.39)</td><td valign="top" align="center">92.56(76.39)</td><td valign="top" align="center">93.27(62.3)</td><td valign="top" align="center">96.44(79.42)</td><td valign="top" align="center">89.5(36.2)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">CC*</td><td valign="top" align="center">97.22(92.01)</td><td valign="top" align="center">98.05(93.07)</td><td valign="top" align="center">98.24(87.62)</td><td valign="top" align="center">99.09(94.09)</td><td valign="top" align="center">97.19(72.91</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left"><italic><bold>Refinment</bold></italic></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">Reflections used in refinement</td><td valign="top" align="center">53357 (5281)</td><td valign="top" align="center">53350 (5281)</td><td valign="top" align="center">53330 (5270)</td><td valign="top" align="center">53342 (5278)</td><td valign="top" align="center">53317 (5273)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">Reflections used for R-free</td><td valign="top" align="center">2608 (291)</td><td valign="top" align="center">2607 (290)</td><td valign="top" align="center">2605 (289)</td><td valign="top" align="center">2608 (291)</td><td valign="top" align="center">2606 (290)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">R<italic>work</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center">0.1657 (0.2765)</td><td valign="top" align="center">0.1549 (0.2899)</td><td valign="top" align="center">0.1604 (0.3401)</td><td valign="top" align="center">0.1479 (0.2998)</td><td valign="top" align="center">0.1744 (0.3566)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">R<italic>free</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center">0.2051 (0.3178)</td><td valign="top" align="center">0.1922 (0.3259)</td><td valign="top" align="center">0.1997 (0.4004)</td><td valign="top" align="center">0.1859 (0.3468)</td><td valign="top" align="center">0.2153 (0.3938)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">Number of non-hydrogen atoms</td><td valign="top" align="center">3617</td><td valign="top" align="center">3553</td><td valign="top" align="center">3590</td><td valign="top" align="center">3568</td><td valign="top" align="center">3507</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">macromolecules</td><td valign="top" align="center">3259</td><td valign="top" align="center">3224</td><td valign="top" align="center">3282</td><td valign="top" align="center">3270</td><td valign="top" align="center">3221</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">ligands</td><td valign="top" align="center">27</td><td valign="top" align="center">27</td><td valign="top" align="center">27</td><td valign="top" align="center">27</td><td valign="top" align="center">27</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">solvent</td><td valign="top" align="center">331</td><td valign="top" align="center">302</td><td valign="top" align="center">281</td><td valign="top" align="center">271</td><td valign="top" align="center">259</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left"><italic>Average B-factor</italic> (Å<sup>2</sup>)</td><td valign="top" align="center">19.03</td><td valign="top" align="center">21</td><td valign="top" align="center">23.39</td><td valign="top" align="center">24.18</td><td valign="top" align="center">26.14</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">macromolecules</td><td valign="top" align="center">17.77</td><td valign="top" align="center">19.93</td><td valign="top" align="center">22.44</td><td valign="top" align="center">23.3</td><td valign="top" align="center">25.37</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">ligands</td><td valign="top" align="center">14.24</td><td valign="top" align="center">16.09</td><td valign="top" align="center">18.23</td><td valign="top" align="center">19.95</td><td valign="top" align="center">21.63</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">solvent</td><td valign="top" align="center">31.89</td><td valign="top" align="center">32.89</td><td valign="top" align="center">35.02</td><td valign="top" align="center">35.25</td><td valign="top" align="center">36.23</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left"><italic>RMS</italic> deviations</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">Bond lengths (Å)</td><td valign="top" align="center">0.011</td><td valign="top" align="center">0.014</td><td valign="top" align="center">0.00</td><td valign="top" align="center">6</td><td valign="top" align="center">0.017</td><td valign="top" align="center">0.006</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">Bond angles (°)</td><td valign="top" align="center">1.09</td><td valign="top" align="center">1.29</td><td valign="top" align="center">0.8</td><td valign="top" align="center">1.49</td><td valign="top" align="center">0.7</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec id="S13"><title>Extended methods</title><sec id="S14"><title>Protein purification</title><p id="P15">Xylose isomerase (Uniprot ID: P24300) was cloned into pET-24a(+). The construct was transformed into <italic>E. coli</italic> strain BL21 (DE3) Gold and grown in TB medium supplemented with 25 µg/mL kanamycin at 37 °C until an OD<sub>600</sub> of 1.0 - 1.2 was reached. Protein expression was induced by addition of 1 mM IPTG, and the cells were incubated further at 18 °C for 16 h. The cells were harvested by centrifugation (7000 g, 15 min, 4 °C) and resuspended in lysis buffer (50 mM HEPES pH 7.5, 500 mM NaCl, 5% (v/v) glycerol, 5 mM imidazole, 5 units/mL DnaseI, and protease inhibitor). After the cells were lysed by sonication, undisrupted cells and debris was separated by centrifugation (30,000 g, 1 h, 4 °C). The supernatant was applied to a 5 mL HisTrap FF (Cytiva), washed with wash buffer (50 mM HEPES pH 7.5, 500 mM NaCl, 5% (v/v) glycerol, 30 mM imidazole), and XI was eluted in elution buffer (50 mM HEPES pH 7.5, 500 mM NaCl, 5% (v/v) glycerol, 250 mM imidazole). Protein containing fractions were pooled and HRV-3C protease was added to the eluate (0.3 mg HRV-3C protease for material derived from a 1 L culture). The sample was dialysed overnight against SEC buffer (50 mM HEPES pH 7.5, 150 mM NaCl) at 4 °C. Negative IMAC was performed to recover the cleaved XI. The protein was concentrated to 3 mL using a 10 MWCO concentrator (Sartorius) and applied to a Superdex 200 HiLoad 16/60 column (Cytiva) equilibrated with SEC buffer. Fractions containing the protein were pooled and a buffer exchange into crystallisation buffer (10 mM HEPES pH 7.5) was performed using a PD10 column (Cytiva).</p></sec><sec id="S15"><title>Group occupancy refinement settings</title><p id="P16">Following group occupancy refinement setting have been used for CTX-M-14:
<preformat preformat-type="computer code"><styled-content style="font-size:12px;">
1 occupancies {
2     individual = None 
3     remove_selection = None 
4  
5     constrained_group { 
6         selection = resseq 301 <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">and</styled-content> chain A <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">and</styled-content> altloc A
7         selection = resseq 302 <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">and</styled-content> chain A <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">and</styled-content> altloc B
8         selection = resseq 302 <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">and</styled-content> chain A <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">and</styled-content> altloc C or resseq 70 <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">and</styled-content> chain A <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">and</styled-content> altloc C      
9         selection = resseq 162 <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">and</styled-content> chain S <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">or</styled-content> resseq 163 <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">and</styled-content> chain S <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">or</styled-content> resseq 164 <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">and</styled-content> chain S <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">or</styled-content> resseq 165 <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">and</styled-content> chain S <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">or</styled-content> resseq 167 <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">and</styled-content> chain S <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">or</styled-content> resseq 168
 <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">and</styled-content> chain S <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">or</styled-content> resseq 171 <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">and</styled-content> chain S <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">or</styled-content> resseq 173 <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">and</styled-content> chain S <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">or</styled-content> resseq 174
 <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">and</styled-content> chain S <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">or</styled-content> resseq 176 <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">and</styled-content> chain S <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">or</styled-content> resseq 177 <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">and</styled-content> chain S <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">or</styled-content> resseq 180
 <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">and</styled-content> chain S <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">or</styled-content> resseq 181 <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">and</styled-content> chain S <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">or</styled-content> resseq 1 <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">and</styled-content> chain B
10     }
11     constrained_group {
12         selection = resseq 70 <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">and</styled-content> chain A <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">and</styled-content> altloc C
13         selection = resseq 70 <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">and</styled-content> chain A <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">and</styled-content> altloc A
14         }
15 }</styled-content></preformat></p><p id="P17">Following group occupancy refinement setting have been used for XI:<preformat preformat-type="computer code"><styled-content style="font-size:12px;">
1 occupancies {
2       individual = None
3       remove_selection = None
4       constrained_group {
5         selection = chain C <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">and</styled-content> element Mg
6       }
7       constrained_group {
8         selection = chain D <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">and</styled-content> element Mg
9       }
10       constrained_group {
11         selection = chain A <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">and</styled-content> resseq 402 <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">and</styled-content> resname HOH or chain A <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">and</styled-content> \
12                     resseq 403 <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">and</styled-content> resname HOH or chain A <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">and</styled-content> resseq 404 <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">and</styled-content> \
13                     resname HOH <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">or</styled-content> chain A <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">and</styled-content> resseq 405 <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">and</styled-content> resname HOH <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">or</styled-content> \
14                     chain A <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">and</styled-content> resseq 406 <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">and</styled-content> resname HOH <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">or</styled-content> chain A <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">and</styled-content> \
15                     resseq 407 <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">and</styled-content> resname HOH
16         selection = chain A <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">and</styled-content> resseq 401 <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">and</styled-content> resname GLO
17         selection = chain A <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">and</styled-content> resseq 401 <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">and</styled-content> resname GLC
18       }
19       }</styled-content></preformat></p></sec><sec id="S16"><title>Electron density figure details</title><p id="P18">The 2<italic>F<sub>o</sub> - F<sub>c</sub></italic> electron density as volume elements with different RMSD levels were generated in PyMol <italic>via</italic> the volume command (<monospace>volume volumename, mapname, level, ligandname, carve=1.4</monospace>), where color and RMSD-level settings were according to <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Ext. Tab. 1</xref> have been used. Ligand occupancy was displayed via following command: <monospace>spectrum q, teal_hotpink, imp, minimum=0.1, maximum=0.6</monospace> for CTX-M-14 and <monospace>spectrum q, teal_hotpink, imp, minimum=0.3, maximum=0.5</monospace>.</p></sec></sec><sec id="S17"><title>Environmental control box</title><sec id="S18"><title>Design</title><p id="P19">To maintain a controlled humidity environment for our hit-and-return (HARE) chip setup including the liquid-application-method for time-resolved crystallography (LAMA) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">30</xref>], required the development of a solution that could accommodate this experimental setup. To this end we have constructed a modular, compact environmental control box that encloses our previously described chip setup including the LAMA droplet injector nozzle on a footprint of 118 mm x 283 mm (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Ext. Fig. 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">2</xref>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref>]. Humidity control is achieved by flowing dry air either directly into the box, or first passing through a water bath (20-95 °C), with the proportion of gas through each channel controlled by a toggling ball valve in a (proportional-integral-derivative) PID-feedback loop. The water-bath is connected to the environmental control box via a silicone hose, to which a heating belt is attached preventing condensation. The set point can be achieved with high accuracy, enabling humidity control within 1 percent points of relative humidity, which allows to perform controlled crystal dehydration if that is required. Many beamlines are equipped with a temperature control solution via a gas stream that is directed at the sample, often encompassing wide temperature windows. Interestingly, however, a combined temperature-humidity control is rarely found. Such a situation mandates the use of e.g., glass capillaries to maintain the crystals in a humid environment, which complicates time-resolved applications that are based on in-situ mixing. Historically, flow-cells were developed for time-resolved applications that allowed for in-situ mixing experiments with single crystals and for trapping reaction intermediates on comparably slow time scales [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40">40</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42">42</xref>], which were recently extended to SSX experiments [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43">43</xref>]. However, to the best of our knowledge these were not applied to multi-temperature experiments. Serial crystallography experiments can also be conducted in controlled, closed-boundary environments as demonstrated by the drop-on-demand device, which permits humidity control and fully anaerobic experiments via the exchange of the surrounding atmosphere [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R44">44</xref>]. In addition to humidity control, the temperature within our enclosure can be adjusted anywhere within the range of approximately 7 °C to above 70 °C. An aluminum air-stream reflector directs the stream of humid air around the chip. In order to enable effective control over this wide temperature range, the box uses two interchangeable modular temperature control units (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Ext. Fig. 2</xref>). Module-1 covers a temperature range from approximately +7 °C to approximately +50 °C, while module-2 covers a temperature range from approximately +50 °C to over +70 °C. Rapid exchange of the modules is possible without tools, enabling switching between different temperature regimes within a few minutes. Module-1 are water-cooled Peltier-elements that enable active cooling or heating of the interior of the box. To ensure that the temperature is equilibrated across the box, the module is equipped with fans. Cooling water and electric power are fed in through the top side of the module. The heating element in module-2 is a power resistor network that disseminates sufficient heat to increase the interior temperature of the box to over 80 °C, while the relative humidity can be sustained at over 95%. Temperature control is achieved by a PID controller that sets the current through the Peltier elements and resistor network, respectively, to maintain the target temperature. The base plate of the box is made from durable polyether ether ketone (PEEK). To drain condensation water, several cotton wicks are fixed around the bottom corners and connected to an active pumping system that quickly drains excess liquid from the box. The sides and the lid of the box are made of 6 mm thick acrylic glass, while the rear panel (X-ray side) is made of acrylic glass and polyoxymethylene (POM). As an X-ray entrance window, an 8 mm opening in the POM is covered with two spaced layers of COC foil, about 1 mm apart. To enable easy replacement of the X-ray entrance window, the COC foil is placed on a magnetically mounted ring that tightly seals the inside of the box. While the right panel is solid, the left panel has a feedthrough for the humidity tube, and an access hatch through which HARE chips can be loaded onto the sample translation stage. The front panel (detector side) is an aluminum frame with a 190 mm opening. This is sealed with two X-ray transparent Mylar foils (6 µm), as an exit window for the diffracted beam. To reduce condensation on this window, the space between the Mylar foils is continuously flushed with warm air. The lid of the box contains feedthroughs for the humidity and temperature sensors, as well as for the electropneumatic retractable, infrared (IR) backlight, the LAMA-nozzle lever, and an access port for heating module exchange. The translation stage system implemented at the T-REXX endstation is not humidity resistant and therefore has to be kept outside of the box. Hence, the translation stages are connected to the box via a flexible bellow, custom cut from two layers of commercial plastic wrap. On the inside, the bellow is sealed between the translation stages and the kinematic mount for the chip holder [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">29</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R45">45</xref>]. To reduce the heat capacity of the chip holder and thus achieve faster temperature equilibration, the previously described aluminum chip holder was redesigned from PEEK, providing the same functionality at a lighter weight [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">29</xref>]. The LAMA nozzle is attached <italic>via</italic> a kinematic mount to a retractable lever that enables retraction of the nozzle from its injection position during chip exchange. To avoid the unnecessary opening of the box, which might lead to temperature and humidity fluctuations, the nozzle retracts into a parking position under the lid of the box. Fine alignment of the LAMA nozzle in the injector position is achieved <italic>via</italic> motorized translation stages (Thorlabs). The whole box system is mounted on rails, residing on a stainless-steel baseplate that can be moved between “data collection” or “beam location” position, where the latter allows to use the X-ray scintillator built into the beam-shaping device (BSD; Arinax, Moirans, France). Operation of the serial crystallography environmental control enclosure is achieved <italic>via</italic> an external control unit where temperature and humidity parameters are electronically set (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Ext. Fig. 3</xref>). Parameters needed to achieve certain conditions were calibrated and are listed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Ext. Tab. 2</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="S19"><title>Characterization of temperature and humidity stability</title><p id="P20">To characterize how the environmental parameters can be controlled within the box, we recorded temperature and humidity changes as a function of time in 30 s intervals. The temperature was modified as a step function, with the humidity target set to 95%. While the humidity rapidly equilibrates throughout the box, temperature gradients closer to the walls needs to be avoided. In addition to the overall temperature inside the box, measured near the panel opposite to the access hatch, we also monitored the temperature at two additional locations, directly on the surface of the backside of the HARE chip and directly above the humidity sensor (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Ext. Fig. 4</xref>). To assess how effectively different temperatures in the box can be achieved and maintained, we characterized the temperature increase from 7.5 °C to 80 °C. The data show that for both temperature control modules the humidity values quickly reach the target values. Over a temperature window of almost 70 °C the humidity remains stable within 2.5% of the set point. Analysis of the deviation of the chip temperature from the box temperature shows that the chip temperature follows the box temperature with a median difference of 0.7 °C, over a temperature window of almost 70 °C. Temperature and humidity typically equilibrate across the box and the chip within 10-15 minutes. We also examined the reliability of maintaining environmental set points during X-ray data-collection. To this end we collected X-ray diffraction data at 20 °C, 40 °C, 55 °C and 80 °C, for ca. 120 minutes and recorded temperature and humidity values in 30 s intervals during this period (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">Ext. Tab. 3</xref>). Remarkably, during the data collection the target humidity could be maintained within approximately 1%, while the temperature remained stable within approximately 0.5 °C. Clear deviations from this behavior are only observed during chip exchange, when the hatch of the box is opened and during the subsequent re-equilibration time while the environment stabilises. Re-equilibration of the environmental parameters could be achieved within 10-15 minutes, depending on the duration of the manual chip exchange. In conclusion, these data show that after an equilibration time of approximately 10-15 minutes the environment in the control box has reached its target value, and can be maintained throughout extended periods of time, well beyond the typical data collection time of a chip (ca. 30 minutes). This enables collection of serial X-ray diffraction data at a variety of different temperature and humidity levels with high accuracy and precision.</p></sec></sec><sec id="S20"><title>Humidity controlled SSX</title><p id="P21">A hallmark of protein crystals is their large solvent-content, which is typically in the range between 40% and 70% of the crystal volume. An advantage of this property is that proteins generally retain their function even in the crystalline state [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R46">46</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R47">47</xref>]. A commonly known disadvantage is, however, their sensitivity to changes in environmental humidity, which in addition to the higher rates of radiation damage associated with higher temperatures makes routine data collection at even ambient temperatures a difficult task. Accordingly, starting with traditional wax-enclosed glass capillaries, environmental control has consistently been a key aspect of macromolecular crystallography, and several solutions have been developed to maintain crystal hydration for single crystals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R48">48</xref>]. Open- and closed boundary environmental control solutions have been developed since the advent of structural biology. In the simplest instances, closed boundary devices include glass capillaries, which contain protein crystals and typically a drop of mother liquor to sustain a humid atmosphere during data collection [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R48">48</xref>]. More modern variations of this classic solution are the many fixed-target serial crystallography environments, which protect protein microcrystals against evaporation by some form of X-ray transparent window material [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R49">49</xref>]. For single crystal experiments a variety of solutions, sometimes for advanced parameter control, such as humidity, temperature, and electric fields have also been developed over the years [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R50">50</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R52">52</xref>]. With the onset of cryo-crystallography, larger boxes were developed, which sometimes enclosed the stream of cryogenic gas in a dry atmosphere to prevent ice-formation during data-collection [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R53">53</xref>]. However, for single-crystal experiments the majority of environmental control solutions fall into the open-boundary category, such as placing the crystal in an vapor stream with controlled humidity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R51">51</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R54">54</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R58">58</xref>]. Historically, the water content of protein crystals was controlled by post-crystallization treatments via chemical dehydration prior to crystal freezing [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R59">59</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R60">60</xref>]. However, controlling the humidity around the mounted crystals enables the convenient identification of the optimal conditions for a particular sample during an X-ray diffraction experiment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R51">51</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R54">54</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R58">58</xref>]. Adjusting the relative humidity either prior to or during data collection can improve several aspects of data quality (resolution, mosaicity and anisotropy) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R54">54</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R55">55</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R57">57</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R61">61</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R66">66</xref>]. To estimate the effect of the environmental humidity on diffraction data quality we monitored the unit-cell size of XI as a function of decreasing humidity. We started data collection at a relative humidity of 95% and reduced the humidity in steps of 5% per compartment row on the chip (<bold>Fig. 5</bold>). With decreasing humidity the crystals do not simply cease to diffract but undergo a change in unit-cell size. While at or above a relative humidity of 95% most diffraction patterns could be indexed with a larger unit-cell (a = 94.2 Å, b = 99.3 Å, c = 103.1 Å; <italic>α, β, γ</italic> = 90.0°), but the proportion rapidly changed to a smaller unit cell (a = 94.6 Å, b = 99.4 Å, c = 87.5 Å; <italic>α, β, γ</italic> = 90.0°) as the relative humidity dropped from 90% to 75%. If the humidity is reduced even further the micro-crystals cease to diffract, presumably due to complete dehydration. This emphasizes the sensitivity of protein micro-crystals to environmental humidity, which must be precisely controlled to maintain their diffraction properties. On the other hand, this also opens the opportunity for crystals with large unit cells to be specifically dehydrated to modulate their diffraction properties. The response of protein crystals hydration to their environment has long been known [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R59">59</xref>] and chemical dehydration devices [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R60">60</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R67">67</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R69">69</xref>] as well as dedicated de-humidification devices have successfully been used for this purpose on single, loop-mounted crystals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R54">54</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R57">57</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R62">62</xref>]. With our environmental control box these post-crystallization optimization protocols are now open to serial crystallography.</p></sec><sec id="S21"><title>Multi-temperature SSX</title><p id="P22">To establish that the influence of temperature on the resting state of the CTX-M-14, and XI structures can be accurately determined, initial data were collected without triggering a reaction. After equilibration of the respective temperatures, all parameters were kept equivalent between chips (humidity, beamline, data-collection), and structures were determined using crystals from the same batch of crystals. Five structure of CTX-M-14 were determined at 10 °C, 20 °C, 30 °C, 40 °C, and 50 °C, and five structures of XI at 20°C, 30 °C, 40 °C, 45 °C, and 50 °C (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T5">Ext. Tab. 5</xref>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="T6">6</xref>). This systematic normalization of all experimental parameters, permits direct side-by-side comparison of the structures and consequently allows to directly assign temperature-induced structural differences. To this end we addressed the global structural differences of the individual structures, by fitting the ADPs to a shifted inverse gamma distribution (SIGD) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>). A marked response can be seen in the SIGD of CTX-M-14 once the temperature is increased to 50 °C, which matches the unfolding temperature determined in solution and its pairwise C<italic><sub>α</sub>RMSD</italic> (see below). By contrast, the SIGD of the XI structures show a gradual response to increasing temperatures. An interesting deviation from the trend can be seen in the 45 °C structure, however, the same pattern can be observed in RoPE-space as well as in the pairwise C<italic><sub>α</sub>RMSD</italic>, indicating a general structural response in this structure. Taking the general trend into account, the combination with the much higher unfolding temperature of XI in solution, and the gradual increase in ADPs with increasing temperature suggests a different temperature response mechanism of the hyperthermophile XI than the seen in the mesophilic CTX-M-14 protein (see main text).</p><sec id="S22"><title>Melting point determination by differential scanning flurometry</title><p id="P23">To correlate the global structural differences seen in the SIGD with an in-solution behaviour of our model systems, we determined their melting points <italic>via</italic> differential scanning flurometry (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Ext. Fig. 6</xref>) in four different buffer systems, also taking the crystallization condition into account (see below). The melting point of CTX-M-14 (ca. 53 °C) matches the displacement of the SIGD for the 50 °C SSX structure. By contrast, the multi-temperature SSX experiments for XI do not reach the melting point of XI (ca. 83 °C), but continuously increasing ADPs of XI can be observed in the SIGD.</p></sec></sec><sec id="S23"><title>C<sub>α</sub> RMSD</title><p id="P24">In order to quantify and visualise the changing global structural differences, a pairwise backbone Root Mean Square Deviation (C<italic>α</italic> RMSD) was calculated for both model systems and represented as a categorical heatmap (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Ext.Fig. 7</xref>). Before calculating the RMSD for a pair, the two structures were aligned <italic>via</italic> Singular Value Decomposition (SVD) using the Biopython package <monospace>Bio.SVDSuperimposer</monospace> in order to minimise the resulting RMSD value. A temperature dependent clustering is observed for both model systems.</p></sec><sec id="S24"><title>Multi-temperature time-resolved SSX</title><p id="P25">To study temperature effects on catalytic turnover we determined three CTX-M-14 crystal structures 3 s after reaction initiation with piperacillin at 20 °C, 30 °C and 37 °C, respectively (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T7">Ext. Tab. 7</xref>), and for XI we determined five crystal structures 60 s after reaction initiation with glucose at 20 °C, 30 °C, 40 °C, 45 °C and 50 °C, respectively (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T8">Extended data table 8</xref>). Any time-resolved crystallographic analysis will result in a superimposed mixture of sub-states, generating an ensemble of structures with respective fractional occupancies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">25</xref>]. To address this situation and minimize interpretation bias, we initially assembled all previously known stable intermediates into one structure and relied on constrained group refinement to determine the occupancy of the different overlapping states at the respective datasets [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">26</xref>]. For CTX-M-14 the 20 °C structure corresponds to the unbound state, exhibited by rather discontinuous difference electron density and accordingly low occupancy for any of the piperacillin intermediates. The 30 °C structure on the other hand is clearly populated by ligand difference density. Occupancy refinement indicated a mixture that predominantly corresponds to the acyl-enzyme intermediate and a complex with the hydrolysed piperacillin product. Finally, the 37 °C structure mainly corresponds to CTX-M-14 in complex with the hydrolysed piperacillin product (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2 a-c</xref>).</p><p id="P26">For XI on the other hand, we modelled the unbound state, the Michaelis-Menten complex with closed-ring glucose as well as an open-chain glucose intermediate consistent with previously determined structures. The respective substrate complex structure at 20°C can be superimposed with an RMSD. of 0.1 Å to previously reported substrate complexes at room temperature (PDB-ID: 3KCL) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R70">70</xref>] (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>). The multiple overlapping states make an unambiguous interpretation based on the electron density alone difficult, which mandates the use of more complex modelling and analysis protocols in future experiments [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">26</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R71">71</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R72">72</xref>]. However, by increasing the temperature, different catalytic states (<italic>i.e.</italic>, closed and open-chain intermediates) can be captured at the same delay time, clearly indicating an increase in the catalytic activity of XI with increasing temperature.</p></sec><sec id="S25"><title>Code</title><sec id="S26"><title>Script for the Shifted inverse gamma distribution</title><preformat preformat-type="computer code"><styled-content style="font-size:12px;">
1 #!/ usr/ bin / env python3
2 # -*- coding : utf -8 -*-
3 """
4 
4 Created on Wed Jul 17 10 :08 :46 2024
5
6 @author : gargi
7 """
8
9 <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">import</styled-content> numpy as np
10 <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">import</styled-content> matplotlib . pyplot as plt
11 <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">from</styled-content> scipy . special <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">import</styled-content> gamma
12 <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">from</styled-content> scipy . optimize <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">import</styled-content> curve_fit
13
14 # Define a Shifted Inverse Gamma Function
15 <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">def</styled-content> sigd (x, a, b, d):
16     <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">return</styled-content> (b**a / gamma (a)) * ((x - d)**( -a - 1)) * (1 / np. exp (b / (x - d)))
17
18 # Common settings for plots
19 plt . rcParams [’figure . dpi ’] = 300
20 plt . rcParams [’savefig . dpi ’] = 300
21
22 # File paths and colors
23 file_paths = [",",",",","]
24
25
26 colors = [’royalblue ’, ’darkviolet ’, ’limegreen ’, ’gold ’, ’orangered ’]
27 labels = [’10 C ’, ’20 C ’, ’30 C ’, ’40 C ’, ’50 C ’]
28
29 all_fits = []
30
31 <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">for</styled-content>or idx , ( file_path , color , label ) in enumerate (zip( file_paths , colors , labels )):
32       b_values = np. loadtxt ( file_path , dtype = <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">float</styled-content>)
33       freq , bins , _ = plt . hist ( b_values , bins =80 , density =True , color =’skyblue ’)
34       plt . xlim (0, 150)
35
36       bincenters = 0.5 * ( bins [: -1] + bins [1:])
37       s = <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">min</styled-content> ( bincenters )
38       d = 0.9 * s
39
40       popt , _ = curve_fit ( lambda x, a, b: sigd (x, a, b, d), bincenters , freq , bounds=([2 , 0], [4, 200]) )
41       fit = sigd ( bincenters , popt [0] , popt [1] , d)
42
43       all_fits . append (( bincenters , fit , color , label ))
44
45       plt . xlim (0, 100)
46       plt . ylim (0, 0.10)
47       plt . xlabel (’B Values [ $ ^2$]’)
48       plt . ylabel (’Frequency ’)
49       plt . title (f’SIGD Fit { label } Data ’)
50       plt . plot ( bincenters , fit , color )
51       plt . show ()
52
53 # Combined plot
54 <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">for</styled-content> bincenters , fit , color , label <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">in</styled-content> all_fits :
55     plt . plot ( bincenters , fit , color , label = label )
56
57 plt . legend (loc=" upper right ")
58 plt . xlabel (’B Values [ $ ^2$]’)
59 plt . ylabel (’Frequency ’)
60 plt . title (’SIGD Fit : CTXM ’)
61 plt . xlim (0, 100)
62 plt . ylim (0, 0.10)
63 plt . show ()
</styled-content></preformat></sec><sec id="S27"><title>Script to calculate the C<sub><italic>α</italic></sub> RMSD</title><preformat preformat-type="computer code"><styled-content style="font-size:12px;">
1 #!/ usr/ bin / env python3
2 # -*- coding : utf -8 -*-
3 """
4 Created on Wed Jul 17 10:51:55 2024
5
6 @author : gargi
7 """
8
9 #!/ usr/ bin / env python3
10 # -*- coding : utf -8 -*-
11 """
12 Created on Thu Jul 11 12:05:00 2024
13
14 @author : user
15 """
16
17 <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">from</styled-content> Bio . PDB . PDBParser <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">import</styled-content> PDBParser
18 <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">from</styled-content> Bio . SVDSuperimposer <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">import</styled-content> SVDSuperimposer
19 <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">import</styled-content> numpy as np
20 <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">import</styled-content> matplotlib as mpl
21 <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">import</styled-content> matplotlib . pyplot as plt
22
23 # Define amino acids
24 AA = ["ALA", "CYS", "ASP", "GLU", "PHE", "GLY", "HIS", "ILE", "LYS", "LEU", "MET",
	"ASN", "PRO", "GLN", "ARG", "SER", "THR", "VAL", "TRP", "TYR"]
25
26 # Define PDBs
27 p = PDBParser ( QUIET = True )
28 structure_files = ["", "", "", "", ""]
29 structures = [p. get_structure (f’ ctxm_ {i *10} c",, <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">file</styled-content>) <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">for</styled-content> i, <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">file in enumerate</styled-content> (
	structure_files , start =1)]
30
31 # Superposition with SVD
32 <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">def</styled-content> align (model1 , model2 , atom_types =["CA"]):
33 	model1 _coords = [a. coord <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">for</styled-content> a <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">in</styled-content> model1 [0]. get_atoms () <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">if</styled-content> a. parent. resname in 
	 AA <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">and</styled-content> a. name <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">in</styled-content> atom_types]
34 	model2_coords = [a. coord <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">for</styled-content> a <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">in</styled-content> model2 [0]. get_atoms () <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">if</styled-content> a. parent. resname <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">in</styled-content> 
	 AA and a. name in atom_types]
35 	si = SVDSuperimposer ()
36 	si. <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">set</styled-content> (np. array ( model1_coords ), np. array ( model2_coords ))
37 	si. run ()
38 	<styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">return</styled-content> si
39
40 # Calculate RMSDs and populate the matrix
41 num_structures = <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">len</styled-content> ( structures )
42 C_aRMSD = np. zeros ((num_structures , num_structures))
43
44 rmsds = []
45 <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">for</styled-content> i <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">in range</styled-content> (num_structures):
46 	<styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">for</styled-content> j <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">in range</styled-content> (i, num_structures):
47 	    si = align ( structures [i], structures [j])
48 	    rmsd_value = si. get_rms ()
49 	    rmsds . append ( rmsd_value )
50 	    C_aRMSD [i, j] = rmsd_value
51 	    C_aRMSD [j, i] = rmsd_value # Symmetric matrix
52
53 formatted_rmsds = [’%.3 f’ % elem <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">for</styled-content> elem <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">in</styled-content> rmsds]
54 <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">print</styled-content>(formatted_rmsds)
55
56 structures_labels = structures_labels = ["10 C ", "20 C ", "30 C ", "40 C ", "50 C "]
57
58 # Plotting
59 fig , ax = plt . subplots ()
60 im = ax. imshow ( C_aRMSD )
61
62 plt . rcParams [" font . family "] = " arial "
63 mpl .rc(’text . latex ’, preamble =r’\ usepackage { amsmath }’)
64
65 # Show all ticks and label them with the respective list entries
66 ax. set_xticks (np. arange (len( structures_labels )), labels = structures_labels , weight =" bold ")
67 ax. set_yticks (np. arange (<styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">len</styled-content> ( structures_labels )), labels=structures_labels , weight="bold")
68
69 # Loop over data dimensions and create text annotations
70 <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">for</styled-content> i <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">in range</styled-content> (<styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">len</styled-content> ( structures_labels )):
71     <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">for</styled-content> j <styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">in range</styled-content> (<styled-content style="font-size:12px;color:#f20b88;">len</styled-content> ( structures_labels )):
72 	    ax. text(j, i, f’ {C_aRMSD [i, j]:.3 f}’, ha="center", va="center", color="w",
       weight="bold")
73
74 ax. set_title (r’C$_ {\ mathbf {\ alpha }}$ Pairwise RMSD : CTX -M -14 ’, weight="bold")
75
76 cbar = plt . colorbar (im , ax=ax)
77 cbar . set_label ( label =’RMSD ($\ mathbf {\ AA}$)’, rotation = -90.0 , va=" bottom ", weight =’bold ’)
78 cbar .ax. set_yticklabels (np. arange (0.00 , 0.09 , 0.01) , fontweight =’bold ’)
79
80 fig . tight_layout ()
81 plt . rcParams [’figure . dpi ’] = 800
82 plt . rcParams [’savefig . dpi ’] = 800
83 plt . show ()
</styled-content>
</preformat></sec></sec></body><back><ack id="S29"><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>All multi-temperature SSX data were collected at endstation P14.2 (T-REXX) operated by EMBL Hamburg at the PETRA-III storage ring (DESY, Hamburg, Germany). We would like to thank our colleagues G. Bourenkov, M. Agthe, and A.R. Pearson for their continuous support, helpful discussions and critical reading of the manuscript.</p><sec id="S30"><title>Funding</title><p>Construction of T-REXX was funded by the BMBF (Verbundforschungsprojekt 05K16GU1, 05K19GU1, and 05K22GU6). T-REXX beamtime was awarded as part of the EMBL BAG MX-660 and MX-1008. The authors gratefully acknowledge the support provided by the Max Planck Society and the Cluster of Excellence ’The Hamburg Centre for Ultrafast Imaging’ of the Deutsche Forschungs-gemeinschaft (DFG) (EXC 1074, project ID 194651731) and the Joachim Herz foundation (Biomedical physics of infection) (E.C.S.) and from the Joachim Herz Stiftung add-on fellowship (P.M.). Additional funding was provided by the DFG <italic>via</italic> grant No. 451079909 to P.M.. E.C.S. acknowledges support by the DFG via grant no. 458246365 and by the Federal Ministry of Education and Research, Germany, under grant number 01KI2114, and the European Union (ERC, DynaPLIX, SyG-2022 101071843). Views and opinions expressed are however those of the authors only and do not necessarily reflect those of the European Union or the European Research Council. Neither the European Union nor the granting authority can be held responsible for them.</p></sec></ack><fn-group><title>Declarations</title><fn id="FN1" fn-type="con"><p id="P39"><bold>Author Contributions</bold> P.M. and E.C.S. designed the experiments; E.C.S. and P.M. performed the experiments with support from D.v.S. and F.T.; P.M., A.P., C.E.H. and K.B. prepared protein and the protein crystals; E.C.S., P.M., J.P.L. and F.T. designed and built the environmental control box; D.v.S, A.P, E.C.S. and P.M. processed and analyzed the diffraction data; P.M., E.C.S., H.S., J.P.L. and F.T. characterized the control box; P.M. and E.C.S. wrote the manuscript; All authors discussed and corrected the manuscript.</p></fn><fn id="FN2" fn-type="conflict"><p id="P40">Competing Financial Interests Statement: The authors declare no competing financial interests.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><ref id="R1"><label>[1]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Deamer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Weber</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bioenergetics and life’s origins</article-title><source>Cold Spring Harbor Perspectives in Biology</source><year>2010</year><volume>2</volume><elocation-id>a004929</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2828274</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20182625</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/cshperspect.a004929</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>[2]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Feller</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Protein stability and enzyme activity at extreme biological temperatures</article-title><source>Journal of Physics: Condensed Matter</source><year>2010</year><volume>22</volume><elocation-id>323101</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21386475</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>[3]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Elias</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wieczorek</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosenne</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Tawfik</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The universality of enzymatic rate–temperature dependency</article-title><source>Trends in Biochemical Sciences</source><year>2014</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24315123</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>[4]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Garman</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Radiation damage in macromolecular crystallography: what is it and why should we care?</article-title><source>Acta Crystallographica Section D: Biological Crystallography</source><year>2010</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>339</fpage><lpage>351</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2852297</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20382986</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1107/S0907444910008656</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>[5]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fraser</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Hidden alternative structures of proline isomerase essential for catalysis</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2009</year><volume>462</volume><fpage>669</fpage><lpage>673</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2805857</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19956261</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature08615</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>[6]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Keedy</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Crystal cryocooling distorts conformational heterogeneity in a model michaelis complex of dhfr</article-title><source>Structure</source><year>2014</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>899</fpage><lpage>910</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4082491</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24882744</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.str.2014.04.016</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>[7]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Keedy</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Mapping the conformational landscape of a dynamic enzyme by multitemperature and xfel crystallography</article-title><source>Elife</source><year>2015</year><volume>4</volume><elocation-id>e07574</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4721965</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26422513</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.07574</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>[8]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lang</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name><name><surname>Holton</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Fraser</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Alber</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Protein structural ensembles are revealed by redefining x-ray electron density noise</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</source><year>2014</year><volume>111</volume><fpage>237</fpage><lpage>242</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3890839</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24363322</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1302823110</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>[9]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eisenmesser</surname><given-names>EZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bosco</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Akke</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kern</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Enzyme dynamics during catalysis</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2002</year><volume>295</volume><fpage>1520</fpage><lpage>1523</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11859194</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>[10]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Henzler-Wildman</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kern</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dynamic personalities of proteins</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2007</year><volume>450</volume><fpage>964</fpage><lpage>972</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18075575</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>[11]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arcus</surname><given-names>VL</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Der Kamp</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Pudney</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Mulholland</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Enzyme evolution and the temperature dependence of enzyme catalysis</article-title><source>Current Opinion in Structural Biology</source><year>2020</year><volume>65</volume><fpage>96</fpage><lpage>101</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32659635</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>[12]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Knapp</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effects of temperature on cellular physiology</article-title><source>Annual Review of Biophysics</source><year>2022</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>499</fpage><lpage>526</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35534014</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>[13]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pearson</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Mehrabi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Serial synchrotron crystallography for time-resolved structural biology</article-title><source>Current Opinion in Structural Biology</source><year>2020</year><volume>65</volume><fpage>168</fpage><lpage>174</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32846363</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>[14]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chapman</surname><given-names>HN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>X-ray free-electron lasers for the structure and dynamics of macromolecules</article-title><source>Annual review of biochemistry</source><year>2019</year><volume>88</volume><fpage>35</fpage><lpage>58</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30601681</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>[15]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Graber</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Henning</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Srajer</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Five-dimensional crystallography</article-title><source>Acta Crystallographica Section A: Foundations of Crystallography</source><year>2010</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>198</fpage><lpage>206</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2824529</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20164643</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1107/S0108767309054166</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>[16]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Protein energy landscapes determined by five-dimensional crystallography</article-title><source>Acta Crystallographica Section D: Biological Crystallography</source><year>2013</year><volume>69</volume><fpage>2534</fpage><lpage>2542</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3852658</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24311594</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1107/S0907444913025997</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>[17]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mehrabi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Liquid application method for time-resolved analyses by serial synchrotron crystallography</article-title><source>Nature methods</source><year>2019</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>979</fpage><lpage>982</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31527838</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>[18]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schulz</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The hit-and-return system enables efficient time-resolved serial synchrotron crystallography</article-title><source>Nature methods</source><year>2018</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>901</fpage><lpage>904</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30377366</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>[19]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ishii</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Galleni</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Frère</surname><given-names>J-M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamaguchi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biochemical characterisation of the ctx-m-14 <italic>β</italic>-lactamase</article-title><source>International journal of antimicrobial agents</source><year>2007</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>159</fpage><lpage>164</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17207608</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>[20]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sanchez</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Smiley</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Properties of d-xylose isomerase from streptomyces albus</article-title><source>Applied Microbiology</source><year>1975</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>745</fpage><lpage>750</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC187073</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">239628</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/am.29.6.745-750.1975</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>[21]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ginn</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Torsion angles to map and visualize the conformational space of a protein</article-title><source>Protein Science</source><year>2023</year><volume>32</volume><elocation-id>e4608</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10022581</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36840926</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/pro.4608</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>[22]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Masmaliyeva</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Murshudov</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analysis and validation of macromolecular b values</article-title><source>Acta Crystallographica Section D: Structural Biology</source><year>2019</year><volume>75</volume><fpage>505</fpage><lpage>518</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6503761</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31063153</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1107/S2059798319004807</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>[23]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nam</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Glucose isomerase: functions, structures, and applications</article-title><source>Applied Sciences</source><year>2022</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>428</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>[24]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pearce</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><name><surname>Gros</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A method for intuitively extracting macromolecular dynamics from structural disorder</article-title><source>Nature communications</source><year>2021</year><volume>12</volume><elocation-id>5493</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8448762</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34535675</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-021-25814-x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>[25]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Resolution of structural heterogeneity in dynamic crystallography</article-title><source>Acta Crystallographica Section D: Biological Crystallography</source><year>2013</year><volume>69</volume><fpage>946</fpage><lpage>959</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3663119</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23695239</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1107/S0907444913003454</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>[26]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pearce</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A multi-crystal method for extracting obscured crystallographic states from conventionally uninterpretable electron density</article-title><source>Nature communications</source><year>2017</year><volume>8</volume><elocation-id>15123</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5413968</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28436492</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncomms15123</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>[27]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name><surname>Zilm</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Preparation of protein nanocrystals and their characterization by solid state nmr</article-title><source>Journal of Magnetic Resonance</source><year>2003</year><volume>165</volume><fpage>162</fpage><lpage>174</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14568526</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>[28]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wiedorn</surname><given-names>MO</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Megahertz serial crystallography</article-title><source>Nature communications</source><year>2018</year><volume>9</volume><elocation-id>4025</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6168542</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30279492</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-018-06156-7</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>[29]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mehrabi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The hare chip for efficient time-resolved serial synchrotron crystallography</article-title><source>Journal of Synchrotron Radiation</source><year>2020</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>360</fpage><lpage>370</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7064102</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32153274</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1107/S1600577520000685</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>[30]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mehrabi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Serial femtosecond and serial synchrotron crystallography can yield data of equivalent quality: A systematic comparison</article-title><source>Science advances</source><year>2021</year><volume>7</volume><elocation-id>eabf1380</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7968842</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33731353</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/sciadv.abf1380</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>[31]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Crystfel: a software suite for snapshot serial crystallography</article-title><source>Journal of applied crystallography</source><year>2012</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>335</fpage><lpage>341</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><label>[32]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McCoy</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Phaser crystallographic software</article-title><source>Journal of applied crystallography</source><year>2007</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>658</fpage><lpage>674</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2483472</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19461840</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1107/S0021889807021206</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><label>[33]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Recent developments in the phenix software for automated crystallographic structure determination</article-title><source>Journal of synchrotron radiation</source><year>2004</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>53</fpage><lpage>55</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14646133</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><label>[34]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Emsley</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Cowtan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Coot: model-building tools for molecular graphics</article-title><source>Acta crystallographica section D: biological crystallography</source><year>2004</year><volume>60</volume><fpage>2126</fpage><lpage>2132</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15572765</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><label>[35]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lohkamp</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Cowtan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Features and development of coot</article-title><source>Acta Crystallographica. Section D: Biological Crystallography</source><year>2010</year><volume>66</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2852313</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20383002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1107/S0907444910007493</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><label>[36]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liebschner</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Polder maps: improving omit maps by excluding bulk solvent</article-title><source>Acta Crystallographica Section D: Structural Biology</source><year>2017</year><volume>73</volume><fpage>148</fpage><lpage>157</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5297918</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28177311</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1107/S2059798316018210</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R37"><label>[37]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schrödinger</surname><given-names>LLC</given-names></name></person-group><source>The PyMOL molecular graphics system, version 1.8</source><year>2015</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R38"><label>[38]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Agirre</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The ccp4 suite: integrative software for macromolecular crystallography</article-title><source>Acta Crystallographica Section D: Structural Biology</source><year>2023</year><volume>79</volume><fpage>449</fpage><lpage>461</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10233625</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37259835</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1107/S2059798323003595</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R39"><label>[39]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>An ultraviolet-driven rescue pathway for oxidative stress to eye lens protein human gamma-d crystallin</article-title><source>Communications Chemistry</source><year>2024</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>81</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11006947</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38600176</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s42004-024-01163-w</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R40"><label>[40]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wyckoff</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The structure of ribonuclease-s at 3.5 a resolution</article-title><source>Journal of Biological Chemistry</source><year>1967</year><volume>242</volume><fpage>3984</fpage><lpage>3988</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6037556</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R41"><label>[41]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kurisu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Sugimoto</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kai</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Harada</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A flow cell suitable for time-resolved x-ray crystallography by the laue method</article-title><source>Journal of applied crystallography</source><year>1997</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>555</fpage><lpage>556</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R42"><label>[42]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Helliwell</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Time-resolved and static-ensemble structural chemistry of hydroxymethylbilane synthase</article-title><source>Faraday discussions</source><year>2003</year><volume>122</volume><fpage>131</fpage><lpage>144</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12555854</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R43"><label>[43]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Monteiro</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>3d-mixd: 3d-printed x-ray-compatible microfluidic devices for rapid, low-consumption serial synchrotron crystallography data collection in flow</article-title><source>IUCrJ</source><year>2020</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>207</fpage><lpage>219</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7055382</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32148849</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1107/S2052252519016865</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R44"><label>[44]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fuller</surname><given-names>FD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Drop-on-demand sample delivery for studying biocatalysts in action at x-ray free-electron lasers</article-title><source>Nature methods</source><year>2017</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>443</fpage><lpage>449</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5376230</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28250468</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.4195</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R45"><label>[45]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sherrell</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A modular and compact portable mini-endstation for high-precision, high-speed fixed target serial crystallography at fel and synchrotron sources</article-title><source>Journal of synchrotron radiation</source><year>2015</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>1372</fpage><lpage>1378</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4629865</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26524301</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1107/S1600577515016938</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R46"><label>[46]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Makinen</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Fink</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reactivity and cryoenzymology of enzymes in the crystalline state</article-title><source>Annual review of biophysics and bioengineering</source><year>1977</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>301</fpage><lpage>343</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">194529</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R47"><label>[47]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moffat</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Time-resolved macromolecular crystallography</article-title><source>Annual review of biophysics and biophysical chemistry</source><year>1989</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>309</fpage><lpage>332</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2660828</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R48"><label>[48]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Macromolecular room temperature crystallography</article-title><source>Quarterly Reviews of Biophysics</source><year>2021</year><volume>54</volume><fpage>e1</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33413726</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R49"><label>[49]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martiel</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Müller-Werkmeister</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Strategies for sample delivery for femtosecond crystallography</article-title><source>Acta Crystallographica Section D: Structural Biology</source><year>2019</year><volume>75</volume><fpage>160</fpage><lpage>177</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6400256</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30821705</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1107/S2059798318017953</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R50"><label>[50]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hekstra</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Electric-field-stimulated protein mechanics</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2016</year><volume>540</volume><fpage>400</fpage><lpage>405</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5730412</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27926732</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature20571</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R51"><label>[51]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mo</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramsøskar</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A sample cell for diffraction studies with control of temperature, relative humidity and applied electric field</article-title><source>Journal of Applied Crystallography</source><year>2009</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>531</fpage><lpage>534</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R52"><label>[52]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saunders</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>An electric field cell for performing in situ single-crystal synchrotron x-ray diffraction</article-title><source>Journal of Applied Crystallography</source><year>2021</year><volume>54</volume><fpage>1349</fpage><lpage>1359</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8493620</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34667446</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1107/S1600576721007469</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R53"><label>[53]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Garman</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></name><name><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Macromolecular cryocrystallography</article-title><source>Journal of Applied Crystallography</source><year>1997</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>211</fpage><lpage>237</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R54"><label>[54]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bowler</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Montgomery</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Leslie</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reproducible improvements in order and diffraction limit of crystals of bovine mitochondrial f1-atpase by controlled dehydration</article-title><source>Acta Crystallographica Section D: Biological Crystallography</source><year>2006</year><volume>62</volume><fpage>991</fpage><lpage>995</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16929099</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R55"><label>[55]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kiefersauer</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A novel free-mounting system for protein crystals: transformation and improvement of diffraction power by accurately controlled humidity changes</article-title><source>Journal of applied crystallography</source><year>2000</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>1223</fpage><lpage>1230</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R56"><label>[56]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sjögren</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Protein crystallography in a vapour stream: data collection, reaction initiation and intermediate trapping in naked hydrated protein crystals</article-title><source>Journal of applied crystallography</source><year>2002</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>113</fpage><lpage>116</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R57"><label>[57]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sanchez-Weatherby</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Improving diffraction by humidity control: a novel device compatible with x-ray beamlines</article-title><source>Acta Crystallographica Section D: Biological Crystallography</source><year>2009</year><volume>65</volume><fpage>1237</fpage><lpage>1246</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19966409</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R58"><label>[58]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baba</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A temperature-controlled cold-gas humidifier and its application to protein crystals with the humid-air and glue-coating method</article-title><source>Journal of Applied Crystallography</source><year>2019</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>699</fpage><lpage>705</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6662993</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31396025</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1107/S1600576719006435</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R59"><label>[59]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Perutz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The composition and swelling properties of haemoglobin crystals</article-title><source>Transactions of the Faraday Society</source><year>1946</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>B187</fpage><lpage>B195</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R60"><label>[60]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heras</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Post-crystallization treatments for improving diffraction quality of protein crystals</article-title><source>Acta Crystallographica Section D: Biological Crystallography</source><year>2005</year><volume>61</volume><fpage>1173</fpage><lpage>1180</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16131749</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R61"><label>[61]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Tran</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Disney</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Controlled dehydration improves the diffraction quality of two rna crystals</article-title><source>BMC Structural Biology</source><year>2016</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5093936</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27809904</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12900-016-0069-1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R62"><label>[62]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bowler</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Automation and experience of controlled crystal dehydration: results from the european synchrotron hc1 collaboration</article-title><source>Crystal Growth &amp; Design</source><year>2015</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>1043</fpage><lpage>1054</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R63"><label>[63]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sanchez-Weatherby</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Moraes</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Crystal dehydration in membrane protein crystallography</article-title><source>The Next Generation in Membrane Protein Structure Determination</source><year>2016</year><fpage>73</fpage><lpage>89</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R64"><label>[64]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Awad</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Svensson Birkedal</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Thunnissen</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Mani</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Logan</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Improvements in the order, isotropy and electron density of glypican-1 crystals by controlled dehydration</article-title><source>Acta Crystallographica Section D: Biological Crystallography</source><year>2013</year><volume>69</volume><fpage>2524</fpage><lpage>2533</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3852657</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24311593</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1107/S0907444913025250</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R65"><label>[65]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Atakisi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Moreau</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Thorne</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of protein-crystal hydration and temperature on side-chain conformational heterogeneity in monoclinic lysozyme crystals</article-title><source>Acta Crystallographica Section D: Structural Biology</source><year>2018</year><volume>74</volume><fpage>264</fpage><lpage>278</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5892876</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29652254</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1107/S2059798318000207</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R66"><label>[66]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Klingl</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Scherer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Stamminger</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Muller</surname><given-names>YA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Controlled crystal dehydration triggers a space-group switch and shapes the tertiary structure of cytomegalovirus immediate-early 1 (ie1) protein</article-title><source>Acta Crystallographica Section D: Biological Crystallography</source><year>2015</year><volume>71</volume><fpage>1493</fpage><lpage>1504</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26143921</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R67"><label>[67]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heras</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Dehydration converts dsbg crystal diffraction from low to high resolution</article-title><source>Structure</source><year>2003</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>139</fpage><lpage>145</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12575933</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R68"><label>[68]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abergel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Spectacular improvement of x-ray diffraction through fast desiccation of protein crystals</article-title><source>Acta Crystallographica Section D: Biological Crystallography</source><year>2004</year><volume>60</volume><fpage>1413</fpage><lpage>1416</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15272164</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R69"><label>[69]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Szebenyi</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Improving diffraction resolution using a new dehydration method</article-title><source>Acta Crystallographica Section F: Structural Biology Communications</source><year>2016</year><volume>72</volume><fpage>152</fpage><lpage>159</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4741197</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26841767</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1107/S2053230X16000261</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R70"><label>[70]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kovalevsky</surname><given-names>AY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Metal ion roles and the movement of hydrogen during reaction catalyzed by d-xylose isomerase: a joint x-ray and neutron diffraction study</article-title><source>Structure</source><year>2010</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>688</fpage><lpage>699</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2887347</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20541506</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.str.2010.03.011</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R71"><label>[71]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pearce</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><name><surname>Krojer</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Von Delft</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Proper modelling of ligand binding requires an ensemble of bound and unbound states</article-title><source>Acta Crystallographica Section D: Structural Biology</source><year>2017</year><volume>73</volume><fpage>256</fpage><lpage>266</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5349438</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28291761</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1107/S2059798317003412</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R72"><label>[72]</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Biener</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Malla</surname><given-names>TN</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwander</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Kinntrex: a neural network to unveil protein mechanisms from time-resolved x-ray crystallography</article-title><source>IUCrJ</source><year>2024</year><volume>11</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11067743</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38662478</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1107/S2052252524002392</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><title>The environmental control box enables recording multi-temperature serial crystallography data.</title><p>a) The environmental control box, the portal translation for the LAMA nozzle is hidden for clarity (further details in the extended data section). b,c) ADPs of CTX-M-14 and XI for models derived from data recorded at different temperatures, fitted to a shifted inverse gamma distribution. d,e) Atomic coordinate-based RoPE space for both proteins at each temperature [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">21</xref>]. Each point corresponds to an experimentally determined structure based on an image subset, showing the first two principal components. f,g) shows magnitude in torsion angle deviation corresponding to the first principal component of d) and e) respectively, plotted as a heatmap onto the backbone of the structures, illustrating the local structural response to temperature changes. In CTX-M-14 these are residues 52-54, 193-196, 226-231 and 251-255, while in XI the region around 25-26, 126-129 and 206-210 shows the largest torsion angle deviation.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS197743-f001"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><title>Altering enzyme kinetics by temperature modulation.</title><p>a-c) CTX-M-14 active site, 3 s after reaction initiation at 20 °C, 30 °C, and 37 °C; d-f) XI active site, 60 s after reaction initiation at 20 °C, 30 °C, 40 °C, 45 °C, and 50 °C; a,d) 2<italic>F<sub>o</sub> − F<sub>c</sub></italic> density shown at RMSD levels from 1.0 - 3.5, strongest density is shown in red; b,e) refined fractional occupancy level; c,f) polder-OMIT map shown around the ligands as a green mesh at the indicated RMSD levels.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS197743-f002"/></fig></floats-group></article>