<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="preprint">
<?all-math-mml yes?>
<?use-mml?>
<?origin ukpmcpa?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">bioRxiv</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>bioRxiv : the preprint server for biology</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub"/>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">EMS136956</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2021.10.14.464414</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="archive">PPR407584</article-id>
<article-version article-version-type="publisher-id">1</article-version>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Deep learning based on stacked sparse autoencoder applied to viral genome classification of SARS-CoV-2 virus</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-8167-5568</contrib-id>
<name>
<surname>Coutinho</surname>
<given-names>Maria G. F.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-5736-0782</contrib-id>
<name>
<surname>Câmara</surname>
<given-names>Gabriel B. M.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-3798-5512</contrib-id>
<name>
<surname>Barbosa</surname>
<given-names>Raquel de M.</given-names>
</name>
<email>m.g.barbosafernandes@gmail.com</email>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
<contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7536-2506</contrib-id>
<name>
<surname>Fernandes</surname>
<given-names>Marcelo A. C.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CR1">*</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="A1">
<label>1</label>Laboratory of Machine Learning and Intelligent Instrumentation, Federal University of Rio Grande do Norte, Natal 59078-970, Brazil</aff>
<aff id="A2">
<label>2</label>Laboratory of Drug Development, Department of Pharmacy, Federal University of Rio Grande do Norte, Natal 59078-970, Brazil</aff>
<aff id="A3">
<label>3</label>Department of Computer Engineering and Automation, Federal University of Rio Grande do Norte, Natal, RN, 59078-970, Brazil</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="CR1">
<label>*</label> Correspondence: <email>mfernandes@dca.ufrn.br</email>
</corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted">
<day>16</day>
<month>10</month>
<year>2021</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="preprint">
<day>15</day>
<month>10</month>
<year>2021</year>
</pub-date>
<permissions>
<ali:free_to_read/>
<license>
<ali:license_ref>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
<license-p>This work is licensed under a <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">CC BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license</ext-link>.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p id="P1">Since December 2019, the world has been intensely affected by the COVID-19 pandemic, caused by the SARS-CoV-2 virus, first identified in Wuhan, China. In the case of a novel virus identification, the early elucidation of taxonomic classification and origin of the virus genomic sequence is essential for strategic planning, containment, and treatments. Deep learning techniques have been successfully used in many viral classification problems associated with viral infections diagnosis, metagenomics, phylogenetic, and analysis. This work proposes to generate an efficient viral genome classifier for the SARS-CoV-2 virus using the deep neural network (DNN) based on stacked sparse autoencoder (SSAE) technique. We performed four different experiments to provide different levels of taxonomic classification of the SARS-CoV-2 virus. The confusion matrix presented the validation and test sets and the ROC curve for the validation set. In all experiments, the SSAE technique provided great performance results. In this work, we explored the utilization of image representations of the complete genome sequences as the SSAE input to provide a viral classification of the SARS-CoV-2. For that, a dataset based on <italic>k</italic>-mers image representation, with <italic>k</italic> = 6, was applied. The results indicated the applicability of using this deep learning technique in genome classification problems.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>SARS-CoV-2</kwd>
<kwd>COVID-19</kwd>
<kwd>Deep Learning</kwd>
<kwd>Stacked Sparse Autoencoder</kwd>
<kwd>Viral classification</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="S1" sec-type="intro">
<label>1</label>
<title>Introduction</title>
<p id="P2">Since the emergence of the SARS-CoV-2 virus at the end of 2019, many works are been developed aiming to provide more comprehension about this novel virus. In March 2020,	the World Health Organization (WHO) raised the level of contamination to the COVID-19 pandemic, due to its geographical spread across several countries. On July 9, 2021, the disease had registered more than 185 million confirmed cases, and more than 4 million confirmed deaths. In the case of a novel virus identification, the early elucidation of taxonomic classification and origin of the virus genomic sequence is essential for strategic planning, containment, and treatments of the disease [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">3</xref>].</p>
<p id="P3">One of the fields of research in the bioinformatics area is the analysis of genomic sequences. In the last years, many strategies based on alignment-free methods have been explored as an alternative for the alignment-based methods, considering the limitations of the second approach. Alignment-based programs assume that homologous sequences comprise a series of linearly arranged and more or less conserved sequence stretches, which is not always the case in the real world [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">4</xref>].</p>
<p id="P4">Among the alignment-free methodologies, there are some models based on deep learning (DL) techniques, that can provide significant performance in applications of genome analysis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref>]. Deep neural networks (DNN) can improve prediction accuracy by discovering relevant features of high complexity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref>].</p>
<p id="P5">
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref> presents the genome analysis stages and how deep learning integrates this process. The genome analysis stages include the primary analysis, the secondary analysis, and the tertiary analysis. The primary and secondary analysis compose the genome sequencing. The primary analysis receives the biological sample and generates genomic data information, called “reads”, after the processing by the sequencer machine. Then, the secondary analysis processes the reads and produces the complete genome sequence. Lastly, the tertiary analysis provides the genome interpretation, which can be performed for many algorithms and techniques [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">8</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>]. The deep learning techniques have been successful used for the tertiary analysis in many viral classification problems associated with the diagnosis of viral infections, metagenomics, pharmacogenomics, and others [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref>].</p>
<p id="P6">
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref> shows the steps of the tertiary analysis using DL, that are the mapping and processing stages. The mapping stage receives the DNA sequence information, that can be the reads, contigs, or the whole genome sequence, and maps this data into a feature space. Various mapping strategies have been present in the works from the state of the art, such as one-hot encoding [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref>], number representation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref>], digital signal processing [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref>], and other strategies, including multiple mapping strategies applied sequentially [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">21</xref>]. The processing stage consists of the utilization of a DNN to perform classification, prediction, and other assumptions about the genome information.</p>
<p id="P7">The mapping stage is crucial for the performance of the processing stage. The genome sequence length varies by the type of the virus. Since the DNN only receive a fixed-size input, some researchers have not been using the whole or long sequence length. Nevertheless, longer sequences contain more information and thus are more convenient to make predictions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref>]. In this work, we will explore the utilization of the whole genome sequence mapped by image representation for the use as the DNN input in order to provide viral classification.</p>
<p id="P8">Recently works in literature have been applying deep learning as tertiary analysis such as viral prediction, viral host prediction, and viral segments prediction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">22</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">30</xref>].</p>
<p id="P9">
<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Tables 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref> present some works from the state of the art that applied DNNs in order to analyse viral genome sequences. <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref> details the focus of each work as the biology name, the group, the aim, indicates if the proposal was or was not applied for the COVID-19 and present the DNN used. The DNNs applied in those references are divide into 5 groups (CNN+FC, LSTM+FC, BLSTM+FC, BLSTM+CNN+FC, CNN+BLSTM+FC), as we show in the last column of <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>. <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref> shows the details about the input and the output of the DNN, besides the biology fields and the bioinformatics area.</p>
<p id="P10">In the work presented in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref>] was proposed a viral genome deep classifier (VGDC), the first viral genome subtyping based on deep learning techniques found in the literature. Their approach uses a Convolutional Neural Network (CNN) with 25 layers to classify several groups of viruses in subtypes. For the tests, were used five different datasets, each one containing genomes sequences of a specific type of virus. The whole virus genome sequence was used as the input to the network, where the corresponding ASCII code represented each nucleotide. The results indicated that the VGDC was able to achieve better results in comparison with previous works from the state of the art.</p>
<p id="P11">In [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref>] was proposed an approach to assist the tests in the detection of SARS-CoV-2, based on the use of DL techniques. For this, a CNN architecture with 4 layers was used to extract characteristics of the virus genomes, as well as to classify SARS-CoV-2 among Coronavirus type viruses. As presented in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref>], the CNN received as input the whole virus genome sequences. The nucleotides were mapped in numerical values (C = 0.25, T = 0.50, G = 0.75, A = 1.0). Missing entries received a value of 0.0. The experiments showed that the CNN was able to correctly identify the sequences even in cases where the noise was added to the genome, reaching accuracies between 0.9674 (with noise) and 0.9875 (without noise). Through the results, the authors also identified a sequence as exclusive for the SARS-CoV-2 virus. They proposed the use of this sequence as a primer for PCR tests.</p>
<p id="P12">In [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref>], was proposed an approach to provide viral classification using the contigs (fragments of the genome sequence) and two different reverse-complement (RC) neural networks architectures: a RC-CNN and a RC-LSTM. These models were also applied to the SARS-CoV-2 virus.</p>
<p id="P13">In works presented in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref>] and [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref>], a taxonomic classification for metagenomics applications is proposed. Both works used segments of genome (reads) with DL input (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>), and the output is the number of the classes. In [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref>], it was proposed two DL models, one to classify species, and another to classify genus. In [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref>], a hierarchical taxonomic classification for viral metagenomic data via DL, called CHEER, was proposed. Similar to the work proposed in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref>], the CHEER framework classifies the genus, family, and genus.</p>
<p id="P14">Proposals presented in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref>] and [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">23</xref>] used the contigs with DL input for viral prediction, and classification. In [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref>], and [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref>] a DL virus identification framework was proposed and both cases try to recognize if the input is a virus or not.</p>
<p id="P15">In work from [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref>], called ViraMiner, was proposed and approach to detect the presence of viruses on raw metagenomic contigs from different human samples. They used a CNN architecture with two different convolutional branches (pattern and frequency branch) in order to extract relevant features. The outputs of these branches are concatenated and inserted into the fully connected (FC) layer. The ViraMiner output produces a single value that indicates the likelihood of the sequence belonging to the virus class.</p>
<p id="P16">In the proposal presented in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref>], called DeepVirFinder, the output is a score between 0 and 1 for a binary classification between virus and prokaryote. They fragmented the genomes into non-overlapping sequences of different sizes (150, 300, 500, 1000, and 3000 bp). The sequences were mapped for the network input using the one-hot encoding method. Since they increase the length of the input, i.e. the sequence fragment, they achieve better performance results, which was measured by the area under the receiver operating characteristic curve (AUROC). The maximum AUROC achieved was 0.98 for the 3000 bp fragment.</p>
<p id="P17">The work presented in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">23</xref>] identifies metagenomic fragments as phages, chromosomes or plasmids using the CNN technique. The experiments were performed using artificial contigs and real metagenomic data. The network output, provided by a softmax layer, consists of 3 scores that indicate the probability that each fragment belongs to a specific class.</p>
<p id="P18">In the works from [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">22</xref>] and [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref>] are present DL architectures for host prediction and classification. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">22</xref>] used a CNN to provide host and infectivity prediction of SARS-CoV-2 virus. In [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref>] was proposed an approach to predict viral host from three different virus species (influenza A virus, rabies lyssavirus and rotavirus A) from the whole or only fractions of a given viral genome.</p>
<p id="P19">In the works from [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref>], [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">25</xref>] and [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">26</xref>] were proposed methodologies to predict or classify specific regions in the genome sequence. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref>] presented a methodology for the classification of three different functional genome types: coding regions, long noncoding regions, and pseudogenes in genomic data. They used a digital signal processing (DSP) methods, called Genomic signal processing (GSP), that converts the nucleotide sequence into a graphical representation of the information contained in the sequence. A CNN with 19 layers was used to perform the classification results.</p>
<p id="P20">The authors in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref>] proposed a DL framework to identify similar patterns in DNA N6-methyladenine (6mA) sites prediction. This framework, called Deep6mA, is composed of a CNN to extract high-level features in the sequence and a Bi-directional LSTM (BLSTM) to learn dependence structure along the sequence, besides a fully connected layer that determines whether the site is a 6mA site.</p>
<p id="P21">In [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">25</xref>] was provided a method based on CNN and BLSTM for exploring the RNA recognition patterns of the CCCTC-binding factor (CTCF) and identify candidate IncRNAs binding. The experiments conducted with two different datasets (human U2OS and mouse ESC) were able to predict CTCF-binding RNA sites from nucleotide sequences. Moreover, [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">26</xref>] propose a computational prediction approach for DNA–protein binding based on CNN and BLSTM.</p>
<p id="P22">We intend to provide viral classification using the whole genome sequences, as presented in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref>] and [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref>]. However, in these works were used the length of the longest genome sequence of the dataset as the input of the DNN. So, it was necessary to add some padding for the missing entries. In this work, we will explore the utilization of <italic>k</italic>-mers image representation of the complete genome sequences as the DNN input, which will feasibly the use of genome sequences of any length and enable the use of smaller network inputs. The <italic>k</italic>-mers representation was used in many works that provide genome sequence classification, as presented in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31">31</xref>], which explores the spectral sequence representation based on <italic>k</italic>-mers occurrences. However, that work doesn’t explore the <italic>k</italic>-mers image representation.</p>
<p id="P23">We also explore the utilization of the stacked sparse autoencoder (SSAE) technique as an efficient viral genome classifier. The SSAE has been successfully applied in many biomedical works from the state of the art [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32">32</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34">34</xref>]. We performed some experiments to provide various levels of taxonomic classification of the SARS-CoV-2 virus, similar to the proposed experiments in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35">35</xref>], using the SSAE technique with a dataset of <italic>k</italic>-mers images representations, available on [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36">36</xref>].</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S2" sec-type="materials | methods">
<label>2</label>
<title>Materials and Methods</title>
<sec id="S3">
<label>2.1</label>
<title>Dataset</title>
<p id="P24">For the experiments, we used a <italic>k</italic>-mers representation dataset of SARS-CoV-2 genome, available on [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36">36</xref>]. This dataset is composed of 1557 virus instances of SARS-CoV-2, as also, a data stream of 11540 viruses from the Virus-Host DB dataset and the other three Riboviria viruses from NCBI (Betacoronavirus RaTG13, bat-SL-CoVZC45, and bat-SL-CoVZXC21). It also provides <italic>k</italic>-mers image representation of all data. The <italic>k</italic>-mers images were used to perform the experiments for this work.</p>
<p id="P25">Each <italic>d</italic>-th sequence, stored in dataset, is expressed by
<disp-formula id="FD1">
<label>(1)</label>
<mml:math id="M1">
<mml:msub>
<mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal">
<mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
</mml:mstyle>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>[</mml:mo>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>…</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>…</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>N</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>]</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
where <italic>N<sub>d</sub>
</italic> is the length of <italic>d</italic>-th sequence and <italic>s</italic>
<sub>
<italic>d</italic>,<italic>n</italic>
</sub> is the n-th nucleotide of the sequence. Each <italic>n</italic>-th <italic>s</italic>
<sub>
<italic>d</italic>,<italic>n</italic>
</sub> can be characterized as a symbol belonging to an alphabet of 4 possible symbols expressed by set {A, T, C, G} for DNA or by set {A, U, C, G} for RNA, that is,
<disp-formula id="FD2">
<label>(2)</label>
<mml:math id="M2">
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>n</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>∈</mml:mo>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>{</mml:mo>
<mml:mtext>A</mml:mtext>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mtext>T</mml:mtext>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mtext>C</mml:mtext>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mtext>G</mml:mtext>
<mml:mo>}</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>∨</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>{</mml:mo>
<mml:mtext>A</mml:mtext>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mtext>U</mml:mtext>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mtext>C</mml:mtext>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mtext>G</mml:mtext>
<mml:mo>}</mml:mo>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
</p>
<p id="P26">In <italic>k</italic>-mers representation, each <italic>d</italic>-th nucleotide sequence, <bold>s</bold>
<sub>
<italic>d</italic>
</sub>, is grouped in <italic>k</italic>-mers sub-sequences [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37">37</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38">38</xref>] that can be expressed as
<disp-formula id="FD3">
<label>(3)</label>
<mml:math id="M3">
<mml:mtable>
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi mathvariant="bold">H</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>[</mml:mo>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mtable>
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal">
<mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
</mml:mstyle>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal">
<mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
</mml:mstyle>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mo>⋮</mml:mo>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal">
<mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
</mml:mstyle>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mo>⋮</mml:mo>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal">
<mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
</mml:mstyle>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>N</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal">
<mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
</mml:mstyle>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>N</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
</mml:mtable>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>]</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mspace width="0.2em"/>
<mml:mspace width="0.2em"/>
<mml:mspace width="0.2em"/>
<mml:mspace width="0.2em"/>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>[</mml:mo>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mtable>
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mo>⋯</mml:mo>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mo>⋯</mml:mo>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mo>⋮</mml:mo>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mo>⋱</mml:mo>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mo>⋮</mml:mo>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mo>⋯</mml:mo>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mo>⋮</mml:mo>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mo>⋱</mml:mo>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mo>⋮</mml:mo>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>N</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mo>⋯</mml:mo>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>N</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>N</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mo>⋯</mml:mo>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>N</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
</mml:mtable>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>]</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
</mml:mtable>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
where the matrix <bold>H</bold>
<sub>
<italic>d</italic>
</sub> stores the <italic>k</italic>-mers associated with each <italic>d</italic>-th sequence <bold>s</bold>
<sub>
<italic>d</italic>
</sub>. The <italic>k</italic>-mers representations are based in each <italic>d</italic>-th matrix <bold>H</bold>
<sub>
<italic>d</italic>
</sub> and the matrix <bold>Γ</bold>, call here as symbol matrix. The symbol matrix is expressed as
<disp-formula id="FD4">
<label>(4)</label>
<mml:math id="M4">
<mml:mi mathvariant="bold">Γ</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>[</mml:mo>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mtable>
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>γ</mml:mi>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mo>⋮</mml:mo>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>γ</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mo>⋮</mml:mo>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>γ</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>M</mml:mi>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
</mml:mtable>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>]</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>[</mml:mo>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mtable>
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>γ</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mo>⋯</mml:mo>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>γ</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mo>⋮</mml:mo>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mo>⋱</mml:mo>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mo>⋮</mml:mo>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>γ</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mo>⋯</mml:mo>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>γ</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mo>⋮</mml:mo>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mo>⋱</mml:mo>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mo>⋮</mml:mo>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>γ</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>M</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mo>⋯</mml:mo>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>γ</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>M</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
</mml:mtable>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>]</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
where each element <italic>γ</italic>
<sub>
<italic>i</italic>,<italic>j</italic>
</sub> ∈ ({A,T,C,G} ∨ {A,U,C,G}). The symbol matrix, <bold>Γ</bold>, stores all <italic>M</italic> possibilities of the <italic>k</italic>-mers, where
<disp-formula id="FD5">
<label>(5)</label>
<mml:math id="M5">
<mml:mi>M</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:msup>
<mml:mn>4</mml:mn>
<mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
</mml:msup>
<mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
</p>
<p id="P27">The <italic>k</italic>-mers count 1D representation can be expressed as
<disp-formula id="FD6">
<label>(6)</label>
<mml:math id="M6">
<mml:msub>
<mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal">
<mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
</mml:mstyle>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>[</mml:mo>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>…</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>…</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>M</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>]</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
where
<disp-formula id="FD7">
<label>(7)</label>
<mml:math id="M7">
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:munderover>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msup>
<mml:mstyle displaystyle="true">
<mml:mo>∑</mml:mo>
</mml:mstyle>
<mml:mtext>​</mml:mtext>
</mml:msup>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>M</mml:mi>
</mml:munderover>
<mml:munderover>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msup>
<mml:mstyle displaystyle="true">
<mml:mo>∑</mml:mo>
</mml:mstyle>
<mml:mtext>​</mml:mtext>
</mml:msup>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>N</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:munderover>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>B</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
and
<disp-formula id="FD8">
<label>(8)</label>
<mml:math id="M8">
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>B</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>{</mml:mo>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mtable>
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
<mml:mspace width="0.6em"/>
<mml:mtext> for </mml:mtext>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>γ</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>≠</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal">
<mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
</mml:mstyle>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>∃</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>…</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>:</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>γ</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>≠</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
<mml:mspace width="0.6em"/>
<mml:mtext> for </mml:mtext>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>γ</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal">
<mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
</mml:mstyle>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>∀</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>…</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>:</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>γ</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
</mml:mtable>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mtext>.</mml:mtext>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
</p>
<p id="P28">
<xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">Table 3</xref> shows a example of the <italic>k</italic>-mers count 1D representation values (with <italic>k</italic> = 2) for SARS-CoV-2 from China-Wuhan (ID: LR757995), USA-MA (ID: MT039888), Brazil (ID: MT126808), and Italy (ID: MT066156). The dataset provide in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36">36</xref>] has <italic>k</italic>-mers count 1D representation for <italic>k</italic> = 2, . . . , 6.</p>
<p id="P29">The <italic>k</italic>-mers count 2D representation for each <italic>d</italic>-th sequence, <italic>
<bold>s</bold>
<sub>d</sub>
</italic>, is described by
<disp-formula id="FD9">
<label>(9)</label>
<mml:math id="M9">
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi mathvariant="bold">Λ</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>[</mml:mo>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mtable>
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>λ</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mo>⋯</mml:mo>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>λ</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>L</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mo>⋮</mml:mo>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mo>⋱</mml:mo>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mo>⋮</mml:mo>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>λ</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mo>⋯</mml:mo>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>λ</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>L</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mo>⋮</mml:mo>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mo>⋱</mml:mo>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mo>⋮</mml:mo>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>λ</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>L</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mo>⋯</mml:mo>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>λ</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>L</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>L</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
</mml:mtable>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>]</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>[</mml:mo>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mtable>
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mo>⋯</mml:mo>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>L</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mo>⋮</mml:mo>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mo>⋱</mml:mo>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mo>⋮</mml:mo>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
<mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>×</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>L</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mo>⋯</mml:mo>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>×</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>L</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mo>⋮</mml:mo>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mo>⋱</mml:mo>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mo>⋮</mml:mo>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>M</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>L</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mo>⋯</mml:mo>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>M</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
</mml:mtable>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>]</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
where
<disp-formula id="FD10">
<label>(10)</label>
<mml:math id="M10">
<mml:mi>L</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:msqrt>
<mml:mi>M</mml:mi>
</mml:msqrt>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:msqrt>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msup>
<mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
<mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
</mml:msup>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msqrt>
<mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
</p>
<p id="P30">Finally, the <italic>k</italic>-mers image representation, for each <italic>d</italic>-th sequence, can be represented as
<disp-formula id="FD11">
<label>(11)</label>
<mml:math id="M11">
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi mathvariant="bold">Φ</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>[</mml:mo>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mtable>
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mo>⋯</mml:mo>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>L</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mo>⋮</mml:mo>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mo>⋱</mml:mo>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mo>⋮</mml:mo>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mo>⋯</mml:mo>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>L</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mo>⋮</mml:mo>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mo>⋱</mml:mo>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mo>⋮</mml:mo>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>L</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mo>⋯</mml:mo>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>L</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>L</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
</mml:mtable>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>]</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
where <italic>ϕ</italic>
<sub>
<italic>d</italic>,<italic>i</italic>,<italic>j</italic>
</sub> represents each pixel associated with <italic>d</italic>-th image <bold>Φ</bold>
<sub>
<italic>d</italic>
</sub>. Each pixel, <italic>ϕ</italic>
<sub>
<italic>d</italic>,<italic>i</italic>,<italic>j</italic>
</sub>, is be expressed as
<disp-formula id="FD12">
<label>(12)</label>
<mml:math id="M12">
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mo>⌊</mml:mo>
<mml:mfrac>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msup>
<mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
<mml:mi>b</mml:mi>
</mml:msup>
<mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>max</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>{</mml:mo>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi mathvariant="bold">Λ</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>}</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mfrac>
<mml:mo>×</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>λ</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>⌊</mml:mo>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
where max{·} is the maximum value in <italic>d</italic>-th matrix <bold>Λ</bold>
<sub>
<italic>d</italic>
</sub>, ⌊·⌋ is the greatest integer less than or equal, and <italic>b</italic> is number of bits associated with the image pixels. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref> show the <italic>k</italic>-mers image representation, matrix <bold>Φ</bold>, (with <italic>k</italic> = 6 and <italic>b</italic> = 8) for Geminiviridae (ID: HE616777), Alphacoronavirus (ID: JQ410000), and SARS-CoV-2 (Betacoronavirus) from China-Wuhan (ID: LR757995) and Brazil (ID: MT126808).</p>
<p id="P31">In this work, we used <italic>k</italic>-mers image representation with <italic>k</italic> = 6. In the work presented in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref>], the 6-mers reached the best performance in comparisons with other values of <italic>k</italic> (3, 4, 5 and 7). The data of each experiment was partitioned using the holdout method, which splits the data into a training set and a validation set at random. We used the proportion of 80% for the training set and 20% for the validation set. Each class data was split respecting these percentages. The SARS-CoV-2 <italic>k</italic>-mers images were used only for the test set.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S4">
<label>2.2</label>
<title>DNN Architecture</title>
<p id="P32">All experiments were performed using the SSAE technique. In these models each hidden layer is composed of an individually trained sparse autoencoder in an unsupervised way. A sparse autoencoder is an autoencoder whose training involves a sparse penalty, which functions as a regularizing term added to the loss function [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39">39</xref>]. The autoencoder (AE) is a DL technique specialized in dimensionality reduction and feature extraction. The AE output can provide the reconstruction of the input information. These networks are composed of three layers: an input, a hidden and an output. The encoder is formed by the input and hidden layers, and the decoder is formed by the hidden and output layers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39">39</xref>]. For the output layer, we used a softmax layer, where the number of neurons consists of the number of classes of the experiment. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref> illustrates the DL SSAE with <italic>P</italic> inputs, <italic>K</italic> hidden layers, and a output layer. Each <italic>i</italic>-th hidden layer has <italic>Q<sub>i</sub>
</italic> neurons and the output layer has <italic>U</italic> neurons. Functions <italic>φ</italic>(·) and <italic>f</italic> (·) are the action functions in each <italic>p</italic>-th neuron (in each <italic>i</italic>-th hidden layer) and each <italic>u</italic>-th neuron in output layer, respectively.</p>
<p id="P33">For all experiments, the network architecture used three hidden layers (<italic>K</italic> = 3), containing 3000 neurons in the first hidden layer, <italic>Q</italic>
<sub>1</sub>, 1000 in the second hidden layer, <italic>Q</italic>
<sub>2</sub>, and 500 in the third hidden layer <italic>Q</italic>
<sub>3</sub>. For input of the SSAE, it was used <italic>k</italic>-mers images, with <italic>k</italic> = 6, generating images, matrix <bold>Φ</bold>, with 64 × 64 pixels (based on <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD10">Equation 10</xref>, <inline-formula>
<mml:math id="M17">
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>L</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:msqrt>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msup>
<mml:mn>4</mml:mn>
<mml:mn>6</mml:mn>
</mml:msup>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msqrt>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>64</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>. Each <italic>d</italic>-th image, <bold>Φ</bold>
<sub>
<italic>d</italic>
</sub>, associated with a <italic>d</italic>-th viral genome sequence is reshaped into a vector expressed by
<disp-formula id="FD13">
<label>(13)</label>
<mml:math id="M13">
<mml:msub>
<mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal">
<mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
</mml:mstyle>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>[</mml:mo>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mtable>
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msubsup>
<mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
</mml:msubsup>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msubsup>
<mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
</mml:msubsup>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mo>⋮</mml:mo>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msubsup>
<mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
</mml:msubsup>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msubsup>
<mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
</mml:msubsup>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msubsup>
<mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msubsup>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mo>⋮</mml:mo>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msubsup>
<mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>P</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
</mml:msubsup>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msubsup>
<mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>P</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
</mml:msubsup>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
</mml:mtable>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>]</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>[</mml:mo>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mtable>
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mo>⋮</mml:mo>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>L</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mo>⋮</mml:mo>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>L</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mo>⋮</mml:mo>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>L</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mo>⋮</mml:mo>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>L</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>L</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
</mml:mtable>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>]</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
with <italic>P</italic> = 64 × 64 = 4096 values and applied to the SSAE. The number of neurons in output layer, <italic>U</italic>, is defined by the number of different viruses in a specific taxonomic level such as family, genus, realm and other. The output can be expressed by 
<disp-formula id="FD14">
<label>(14)</label>
<mml:math id="M14">
<mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal">
<mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
</mml:mstyle>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>[</mml:mo>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mtable>
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mo>⋮</mml:mo>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mo>⋮</mml:mo>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>U</mml:mi>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
</mml:mtable>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>]</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
where each <italic>u</italic>-th output, <italic>o<sub>u</sub>
</italic>, represents a specific virus in a taxonomic level classification and is defined by
<disp-formula id="FD15">
<label>(15)</label>
<mml:math id="M15">
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>{</mml:mo>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mtable>
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mtable>
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
</mml:mtable>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mtable columnalign="left">
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mtext> if </mml:mtext>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mstyle mathvariant="bold" mathsize="normal">
<mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
</mml:mstyle>
<mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mtext> is the </mml:mtext>
<mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
<mml:mtext>-th virus </mml:mtext>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mtext> otherwise </mml:mtext>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
</mml:mtable>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
</mml:mtable>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
</p>
<p id="P34">
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref> illustrates how the sequence information is passed through the DL-SSAE to perform the viral classification. The DL-SSAE input was normalized in the range of 0 to 1. First, the SSAE receives the training set as input to perform the training phase. Then, the validation set, which only contains samples that were not applied in the training phase, is used to identify the capacity of generalization of the DNN. After the network validation, the SSAE was applied for the test set, which only contains SARS-CoV-2 sequences. The SARS-CoV-2 <italic>k</italic>-mers images were not used for the training phase of the SSAE.</p>
<p id="P35">The SSAE was implemented in the Matlab platform (License 596681) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40">40</xref>], adopting the deep learning toolbox. All network was trained with the Scaled Conjugate Gradient (SCG) algorithm. The loss function used for the training in each AE was the Mean Squared Error with L2 and Sparsity Regularizers, that can be expressed as
<disp-formula id="FD16">
<label>(16)</label>
<mml:math id="M16">
<mml:mi>E</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mfrac>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
<mml:mi>I</mml:mi>
</mml:mfrac>
<mml:munderover>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msup>
<mml:mstyle displaystyle="true">
<mml:mo>∑</mml:mo>
</mml:mstyle>
<mml:mtext>​</mml:mtext>
</mml:msup>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>I</mml:mi>
</mml:munderover>
<mml:munderover>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msup>
<mml:mstyle displaystyle="true">
<mml:mo>∑</mml:mo>
</mml:mstyle>
<mml:mtext>​</mml:mtext>
</mml:msup>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>U</mml:mi>
</mml:munderover>
<mml:msup>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:msubsup>
<mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msubsup>
<mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mi>o</mml:mi>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>u</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
</mml:msup>
<mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>λ</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>×</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mtext>Ω</mml:mtext>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
<mml:mtext> </mml:mtext>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>+</mml:mo>
<mml:mi>β</mml:mi>
<mml:mo>×</mml:mo>
<mml:msub>
<mml:mtext>Ω</mml:mtext>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>s</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
<mml:mi>y</mml:mi>
<mml:mo> </mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
</mml:math>
</disp-formula>
where <italic>I</italic> is the number of training examples, <italic>U</italic> is the number of classes, Ω<italic>
<sub>weights</sub>
</italic> is the L2 regularization term, <italic>λ</italic> is the coefficient for the L2 regularization term, Ω<italic>
<sub>sparsity</sub>
</italic> is the sparsity regularization term, and <italic>β</italic> is the coefficient for the sparsity regularization term.</p>
<p id="P36">The loss function applied for the softmax layer was the Cross-Entropy. In this work, after the training in each layer, the fine-tuning was performed, which retrained all the stacked network in a supervised way in order to improve the classification results. The fine-tuning process also used the Cross-Entropy as the loss function, as in the softmax layer.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="S5" sec-type="results | discussion">
<label>3</label>
<title>Results and discussion</title>
<p id="P37">We performed four different experiments to provide different levels of taxonomic classification of the SARS-CoV-2 virus, similar to the experimental methodology present in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35">35</xref>]. The details about the data and the network architecture used in each experiment are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T5">Table 5</xref>. The SSAE architecture was chosen by the observation of the MSE obtained with the reconstruction of the validation set in each AE. In order to validate the proposed idea of this work, the results are present by the confusion matrix for the validation and test sets. We also measured the performance of the viral classifier proposed with some popular classification metrics, as precision, recall, F1-score, and specificity. The precision value measure the percentages of all the examples predicted to belong to each class that are correctly classified, which corresponds to the positive predictive value. The recall, also called sensibility, corresponds to the percentages of all the examples belonging to each class that are correctly classified, which is the true positive rate. The F1-score can be interpreted as a weighted average of the precision and recall, and the specificity indicates the true negative rate. The column on the far right of each confusion matrix shows the percentages of precision per class, and the row at the bottom of each confusion matrix shows the percentages of recall per class. The cell in the bottom right of the plot of each confusion matrix shows the overall accuracy. Besides, for the validation set we also present the receiver operating characteristic (ROC) curve. The ROC curve measures the classification performance, that is the true positive rate and the false positive rate of each class, at various thresholds settings.</p>
<p id="P38">In Experiment 1, we intended to classify the viruses in 14 different classes, as presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T5">Table 5</xref>, which consists of 10 families (Adenoviridae, Anelloviridae, Circoviridae, Geminiviridae, Genomoviridae, Microviridae, Papillomaviridae, Parvoviridae, Polyomaviridae and Tolecusatellitidae), three orders (Caudovirales, Herpesvirales and Ortervirales) and Riboviria realm. The Riboviria class contains various families that belong to the realm Riboviria, including the Coronaviridae family. To ensure data balance, only the classes with at least 100 sequences from the original dataset were considered. For the classes with more than 500 sequences, only 500 sequences were selected at random, except for the Riboviria class, in which was prioritized the Coronaviridade family sequences, to guarantee the correct classification of the test data (SARS-CoV-2 sequences), which is the focus of this work. In this particular case, were selected all Coronaviridade family sequences available in the dataset (206 samples), and the other 294 sequences were select from the rest of the Riboviria data at random. After this balancing, Experiment 1 comprised 3433 samples of virus sequences.</p>
<p id="P39">The SSAE architecture used in Experiment 1 was the 4096 − 3000 − 1000 − 500 − 14 architecture. The three AEs were trained for 400 epochs. The softmax layer was trained for 3000 epochs or until reach the minimum gradient (&lt; 1 × 10<sup>−6</sup>). Lastly, the fine-tuning was performed. For each experiment, the fine-tuning phase uses the same stopping condition as the softmax layer.</p>
<p id="P40">The confusion matrix and the ROC curve from the validation set of Experiment 1 are present in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figures 6</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7</xref>, respectively. In Experiment 1, the classification accuracy from the validation set reached 92%. This result is promising, especially considering the challenges of the classification in high-level taxonomies because of the high diversity of the viruses sequences. It is essential to mention that the balancing process may have caused the classification more complicated because some crucial sequences may have been excluded from the dataset. However, this result can be improved in many ways that will be discussed following.</p>
<p id="P41">Regarded to the classification performance per class, the precision value presented in the last column shows that the worse result was obtained from an order class (71.4% from the Herpesvirales). Among the five worst classification results, two are from order classes (71.4% and 83.3% from Herpesvirales and Ortervirales, respectively). Since these classes can contain viruses from many different realms and families, they can difficult the training process. The Riboviria realm, which is the focus of this work, reached a classification accuracy of 93%. Analyse the results per classes can give more understanding about the dataset used and the implications of this dataset for the results, which is important to make decisions for the next experiments.</p>
<p id="P42">The confusion matrix from the test set of Experiment 1 is present in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figure 8</xref>. In the test phase of this experiment, all the 1557 sequences of SARS-CoV-2 was correctly classified as belonging to the Riboviria realm, so the classification accuracy reached 100%.</p>
<p id="P43">Experiment 2 performs the classification of Riboviria families. As in Experiment 1, only classes with at least 100 sequences were considered. This experiment includes 1896 sequences separated into eight families (Picornaviridae, Caliciviridae, Coronaviridae, Potyviridae, Flaviviridae, Rhabdoviridae, Betaflexiviridae and Reoviridae). We used the 4096 − 3000 − 1000 − 500 − 8 SSAE architecture. The three AEs were trained for 400 epochs each and the softmax layer was trained for 1000 epochs or until reaching the minimum gradient, as well as the fine-tuning phase.</p>
<p id="P44">The confusion matrix and the ROC curve from the validation set of Experiment 2 are present in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figures 9</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">10</xref>, respectively. The classification accuracy from Experiment 2 reached 96.3%. From the 379 sequences applied in this validation, only 11 were not correctly classified. Besides, the SSAE classified all sequences that belong to the Coronaviridade family correctly. The ROC curve from Experiment 2 also provides excellent results.</p>
<p id="P45">The confusion matrix from the test set of Experiment 2 is present in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Figure 11</xref>. The SSAE achieve 100% of classification accuracy, i.e., all SARS-CoV-2 sequences applied in this experiment were perfectly classified as Coronaviridae family sequences.</p>
<p id="P46">In Experiment 3 we aim to provide the classification among the Coronaviridae genera. For this experiment, 204 sequences divided into four genera (Alphacoronavirus, Betacoronavirus, Deltacoronavirus and Gammacoronavirus) were used. The SSAE architecture used in this experiment was the 4096 − 3000 − 1000 − 500 − 4 architecture. The three AEs were trained for 400 epochs each, and the softmax layer was trained for 2000 epochs or until reaching the minimum gradient.</p>
<p id="P47">
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">Figures 12</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">13</xref> show the resulting confusion matrix and ROC curve from the Experiment 3, respectively. This experiment achieved 95% of classification accuracy of the validation set. The classification performance of the model obtained for the Betacoronavirus genus was 95.8%. Also, the ROC curve plotted for all classes of Experiment 3 provides satisfactory results.</p>
<p id="P48">Regarding the test set of Experiment 3, the confusion matrix is present in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">Figure 14</xref>. The test phase of Experiment 3 achieved 98.9% of classification accuracy. In the validation phase of Experiment 3, the Betacoronavirus genus did not reach the highest performance, which probably explains these result in the test phase.</p>
<p id="P49">In Experiment 4, we provide the Betacoronaviridae subgenera classification. This test includes 119 genome sequences divided into four classes (Embecovirus, Marbecovirus, Nobecovirus and Sarbecovirus). The SSAE architecture was the same as the architecture used in Experiment 3 (4096 − 3000 − 1000 − 500 − 4), as well as the training parameters.</p>
<p id="P50">The confusion matrix and the ROC curve from the validation set of Experiment 4 are present in Figures 15 and 16, respectively. In this experiment, the SSAE achieved the highest classification accuracy (100%), which is reaffirmed for the ROC curve plot.</p>
<p id="P51">
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F15">Figure 15</xref> exposes the confusion matrix from the test set of Experiment 4. In this case, the SSAE achieved 99.9% of classification accuracy, that is equivalent to only one sequence wrong classified.</p>
<p id="P52">
<xref ref-type="table" rid="T6">Table 6</xref> presents the results regarding some popular classification performance metrics obtained from the validation set. The first column of the table indicates the experiment proposed. The second column shows the overall accuracy for each experiment. The precision, recall, F1-score, and specificity are present in the others columns, which were obtained by the average of the values obtained for each class.</p>
<p id="P53">All the metrics presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T6">Table 6</xref> indicate that the viral classifier proposed performs great for all experiments. The highest performance was obtained for the Experiment 4. Besides, Experiments 2 and 3, reached values more than 0.95 for all the metrics evaluated. The classification performance slightly decreased in the Experiment 1, which is acceptable because of the high diversity of the viruses sequences applied. However, considering all the experiments, the specificity (true negative rate) reached values between 0.983 and 1.</p>
<p id="P54">
<xref ref-type="table" rid="T7">Table 7</xref> presents the results regarding some popular classification performance metrics obtained from the test set. The first column of the table indicates the experiment proposed. The second column shows the overall accuracy for each experiment. And the last column shows the recall, or true positive rate, which were obtained only for the class that corresponds to the SARS-CoV-2 samples. The other metrics (precision, F1-score, and specificity) are not presented because in the tests we do not have false positives samples.</p>
<p id="P55">When the SARS-CoV-2 samples were applied, all the experiments perform excellently. The accuracy reached values between 98.9% and 100%, as well as the recall (true positive rate). The results presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T7">Table 7</xref> are very significant since the classification of the SARS-CoV-2 virus was the main objective of this study.</p>
<p id="P56">In all experiments, the SSAE technique provided great performance results, especially for the test set. However, some strategies can be applied in future experiments to improve classification accuracy results. One of them consists in the use of the <italic>k</italic>-fold cross-validation scheme. Besides, we also intend to study data balancing alternatives, based on the analysis of the results presented here.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S6" sec-type="conclusions">
<label>4</label>
<title>Conclusions</title>
<p id="P57">This work presented an alignment-free methodology, based on the stacked sparse autoencoder technique, in order to classify genome sequences of the SARS-CoV-2 virus in various levels of taxonomy (realm, family, genus and subgenus). We explored the utilization of <italic>k</italic>-mers image representation of the whole genome sequence, which feasibility the use of genome sequences of any length and enable the use of smaller network inputs. The results were presented by the confusion matrix for the validation and test sets, and the ROC curve for the validation set. All experiments provided great performance results, reaching accuracies between 98.9% and 100% for the test set. These results indicated the applicability of using the stacked sparse autoencoder technique in genome classification problems.</p>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack id="S7">
<title>Acknowledgements</title>
<p>The authors wish to acknowledge the financial support of the Coordenação de Aperfeiçoamento de Pessoal de Nível Superior (CAPES) for their financial support.</p>
<sec id="S8">
<title>Funding</title>
<p>This study was financed in part by the Coordenação de Aperfeiçoamento de Pessoal de Nível Superior (CAPES)—Finance Code 001.</p>
</sec>
</ack>
<fn-group>
<fn id="FN1" fn-type="con">
<p id="P58">
<bold>Author contributions</bold>
</p>
<p id="P59">All the authors have contributed in various degrees to ensure the quality of this work. (e.g., Maria G. F Coutinho, Gabriel B. M. Câmara, Raquel de M. Barbosa and Marcelo A. C. Fernandes conceived the idea and experiments; Maria G. F Coutinho, Gabriel B. M. Câmara, Raquel de M. Barbosa and Marcelo A. C. Fernandes designed and performed the experiments; Maria G. F Coutinho, Gabriel B. M. Câmara, Raquel de M. Barbosa and Marcelo A. C. Fernandes analyzed the data; Maria G. F Coutinho, Gabriel B. M. Câmara, Raquel de M. Barbosa and Marcelo A. C. Fernandes wrote the paper. Marcelo A. C. Fernandes coordinated the project.). All authors have read and agreed to the published version of the manuscript.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="FN2" fn-type="conflict">
<p id="P60">
<bold>Conflicts of Interest:</bold>
</p>
<p id="P61">The authors declare no conflict of interest.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="FN3">
<p id="P62">
<bold>Publisher’s Note:</bold>
</p>
<p id="P63">MDPI stays neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<ref id="R1">
<label>1</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lam</surname>
<given-names>TTY</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Shum</surname>
<given-names>MHH</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zhu</surname>
<given-names>HC</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tong</surname>
<given-names>YG</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ni</surname>
<given-names>XB</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Liao</surname>
<given-names>YS</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wei</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cheung</surname>
<given-names>WYM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>WJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>LF</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Identifying SARS-CoV-2 related coronaviruses in Malayan pangolins</article-title>
<source>Nature</source>
<year>2020</year>
<fpage>1</fpage>
<lpage>6</lpage>
<comment>others</comment>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R2">
<label>2</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Andersen</surname>
<given-names>KG</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rambaut</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lipkin</surname>
<given-names>WI</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Holmes</surname>
<given-names>EC</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Garry</surname>
<given-names>RF</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>The proximal origin of SARS-CoV-2</article-title>
<source>Nature medicine</source>
<year>2020</year>
<volume>26</volume>
<fpage>450</fpage>
<lpage>452</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R3">
<label>3</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Graham</surname>
<given-names>RL</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Baric</surname>
<given-names>RS</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>SARS-CoV-2: Combating Coronavirus Emergence</article-title>
<source>Immunity</source>
<year>2020</year>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R4">
<label>4</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zielezinski</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Vinga</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Almeida</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Karlowski</surname>
<given-names>WM</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Alignment-free sequence comparison: benefits, applications, and tools</article-title>
<source>Genome biology</source>
<year>2017</year>
<volume>18</volume>
<fpage>186</fpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R5">
<label>5</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zou</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Huss</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Abid</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mohammadi</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Torkamani</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Telenti</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>A primer on deep learning in genomics</article-title>
<source>Nature genetics</source>
<year>2019</year>
<volume>51</volume>
<fpage>12</fpage>
<lpage>18</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R6">
<label>6</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Tang</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Pan</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Yin</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Khateeb</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Recent advances of deep learning in bioinformatics and computational biology</article-title>
<source>Frontiers in genetics</source>
<year>2019</year>
<volume>10</volume>
<fpage>214</fpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R7">
<label>7</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Eraslan</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Avsec</surname>
<given-names>Ž</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gagneur</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Theis</surname>
<given-names>FJ</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Deep learning: new computational modelling techniques for genomics</article-title>
<source>Nature Reviews Genetics</source>
<year>2019</year>
<volume>20</volume>
<fpage>389</fpage>
<lpage>403</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R8">
<label>8</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Pareek</surname>
<given-names>CS</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Smoczynski</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tretyn</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Sequencing technologies and genome sequencing</article-title>
<source>Journal of applied genetics</source>
<year>2011</year>
<volume>52</volume>
<fpage>413</fpage>
<lpage>435</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R9">
<label>9</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Pabinger</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dander</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Fischer</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Snajder</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sperk</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Efremova</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Krabichler</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Speicher</surname>
<given-names>MR</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zschocke</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Trajanoski</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>A survey of tools for variant analysis of next-generation genome sequencing data</article-title>
<source>Briefings in bioinformatics</source>
<year>2014</year>
<volume>15</volume>
<fpage>256</fpage>
<lpage>278</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R10">
<label>10</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Posada-Cespedes</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Seifert</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Beerenwinkel</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Recent advances in inferring viral diversity from high-throughput sequencing data</article-title>
<source>Virus research</source>
<year>2017</year>
<volume>239</volume>
<fpage>17</fpage>
<lpage>32</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R11">
<label>11</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Fabijańska</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Grabowski</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Viral Genome Deep Classifier</article-title>
<source>IEEE Access</source>
<year>2019</year>
<volume>7</volume>
<fpage>81297</fpage>
<lpage>81307</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R12">
<label>12</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lopez-Rincon</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tonda</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mendoza-Maldonado</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Claassen</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Garssen</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kraneveld</surname>
<given-names>AD</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Accurate identification of sars-cov-2 from viral genome sequences using deep learning</article-title>
<source>bioRxiv</source>
<year>2020</year>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R13">
<label>13</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bartoszewicz</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Seidel</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Renard</surname>
<given-names>BY</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Interpretable detection of novel human viruses from genome sequencing data</article-title>
<source>bioRxiv</source>
<year>2020</year>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2020.01.29.925354</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R14">
<label>14</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Liang</surname>
<given-names>Q</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bible</surname>
<given-names>PW</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zou</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wei</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>DeepMicrobes: taxonomic classification for metagenomics with deep learning</article-title>
<source>NAR Genomics and Bioinformatics</source>
<year>2020</year>
<volume>2</volume>
<elocation-id>lqaa009</elocation-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R15">
<label>15</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Shang</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sun</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>CHEER: hierarCHical taxonomic classification for viral mEtagEnomic data via deep leaRning</article-title>
<source>Methods</source>
<year>2020</year>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R16">
<label>16</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Tampuu</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bzhalava</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dillner</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Vicente</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>ViraMiner: Deep learning on raw DNA sequences for identifying viral genomes in human samples</article-title>
<source>PloS one</source>
<year>2019</year>
<volume>14</volume>
<elocation-id>e0222271</elocation-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R17">
<label>17</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ren</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Song</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Deng</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ahlgren</surname>
<given-names>NA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Fuhrman</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Xie</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Poplin</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sun</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Identifying viruses from metagenomic data using deep learning</article-title>
<source>Quantitative Biology</source>
<year>2020</year>
<fpage>1</fpage>
<lpage>14</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R18">
<label>18</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Mock</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Viehweger</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Barth</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Marz</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Viral host prediction with Deep Learning</article-title>
<source>bioRxiv</source>
<year>2019</year>
<elocation-id>575571</elocation-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R19">
<label>19</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Morales</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Saldaña</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Santana-Castolo</surname>
<given-names>MH</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Torres-Cerna</surname>
<given-names>CE</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Borrayo</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mendizabal-Ruiz</surname>
<given-names>AP</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Vélez-Pérez</surname>
<given-names>HA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mendizabal-Ruiz</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Deep Learning for the Classification of Genomic Signals</article-title>
<source>Mathematical Problems in Engineering</source>
<year>2020</year>
<volume>2020</volume>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R20">
<label>20</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Nguyen</surname>
<given-names>NG</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tran</surname>
<given-names>VA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ngo</surname>
<given-names>DL</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Phan</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lumbanraja</surname>
<given-names>FR</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Faisal</surname>
<given-names>MR</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Abapihi</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kubo</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Satou</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>DNA sequence classification by convolutional neural network</article-title>
<source>Journal of Biomedical Science and Engineering</source>
<year>2016</year>
<volume>9</volume>
<fpage>280</fpage>
<comment>others</comment>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R21">
<label>21</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Guo</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zhou</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>DeepACLSTM: deep asymmetric convolutional long short-term memory neural models for protein secondary structure prediction</article-title>
<source>BMC bioinformatics</source>
<year>2019</year>
<volume>20</volume>
<fpage>1</fpage>
<lpage>12</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R22">
<label>22</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zhu</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Guo</surname>
<given-names>Q</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Fang</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tan</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Xiao</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Host and infectivity prediction of Wuhan 2019 novel coronavirus using deep learning algorithm</article-title>
<source>BioRxiv</source>
<year>2020</year>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R23">
<label>23</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Fang</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tan</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Xu</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Xie</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zhu</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>PPR-Meta: a tool for identifying phages and plasmids from metagenomic fragments using deep learning</article-title>
<source>GigaScience</source>
<year>2019</year>
<volume>8</volume>
<elocation-id>giz066</elocation-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R24">
<label>24</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Pian</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Jiang</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kong</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Deep6mA: a deep learning framework for exploring similar patterns in DNA N6-methyladenine sites across different species</article-title>
<source>bioRxiv</source>
<year>2019</year>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R25">
<label>25</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kuang</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Identification and analysis of consensus RNA motifs binding to the genome regulator CTCF</article-title>
<source>NAR Genomics and Bioinformatics</source>
<year>2020</year>
<volume>2</volume>
<elocation-id>lqaa031</elocation-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R26">
<label>26</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Qiao</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ji</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>DeepSite: bidirectional LSTM and CNN models for predicting DNA–protein binding</article-title>
<source>International Journal of Machine Learning and Cybernetics</source>
<year>2019</year>
<fpage>1</fpage>
<lpage>11</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R27">
<label>27</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Remita</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Halioui</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Daigle</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kiani</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Diallo</surname>
<given-names>AB</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>A machine learning approach for viral genome classification</article-title>
<source>BMC bioinformatics</source>
<year>2017</year>
<volume>18</volume>
<fpage>208</fpage>
<comment>others</comment>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R28">
<label>28</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ren</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Song</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Deng</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ahlgren</surname>
<given-names>NA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Fuhrman</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Xie</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Poplin</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sun</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Identifying viruses from metagenomic data using deep learning</article-title>
<source>Quantitative Biology</source>
<year>2020</year>
<fpage>1</fpage>
<lpage>14</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R29">
<label>29</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Dey</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Chakraborty</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mukhopadhyay</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Machine learning techniques for sequence-based prediction of viral–host interactions between SARS-CoV-2 and human proteins</article-title>
<source>Biomedical journal</source>
<year>2020</year>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R30">
<label>30</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bzhalava</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tampuu</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bała</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Vicente</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dillner</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Machine Learning for detection of viral sequences in human metagenomic datasets</article-title>
<source>BMC bioinformatics</source>
<year>2018</year>
<volume>19</volume>
<fpage>336</fpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R31">
<label>31</label>
<element-citation publication-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Rizzo</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Fiannaca</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>La Rosa</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Urso</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source>A deep learning approach to dna sequence classification</source>
<conf-name>International Meeting on Computational Intelligence Methods for Bioinformatics and Biostatistics</conf-name>
<publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>
<year>2015</year>
<fpage>129</fpage>
<lpage>140</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R32">
<label>32</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Xu</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Xiang</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>Q</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gilmore</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Tang</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Madabhushi</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Stacked sparse autoencoder (SSAE) for nuclei detection on breast cancer histopathology images</article-title>
<source>IEEE transactions on medical imaging</source>
<year>2016</year>
<volume>35</volume>
<fpage>119</fpage>
<lpage>130</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R33">
<label>33</label>
<element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Pratiher</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Chattoraj</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Vishwakarma</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<chapter-title>Application of stacked sparse autoencoder in automated detection of glaucoma in fundus images</chapter-title>
<source>Unconventional Optical Imaging</source>
<publisher-name>International Society for Optics and Photonics</publisher-name>
<year>2018</year>
<volume>10677</volume>
<elocation-id>106772X</elocation-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R34">
<label>34</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Xiao</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lin</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zhao</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>A semi-supervised deep learning method based on stacked sparse auto-encoder for cancer prediction using RNA-seq data</article-title>
<source>Computer methods and programs in biomedicine</source>
<year>2018</year>
<volume>166</volume>
<fpage>99</fpage>
<lpage>105</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R35">
<label>35</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Randhawa</surname>
<given-names>GS</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Soltysiak</surname>
<given-names>MP</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>El Roz</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>de Souza</surname>
<given-names>CP</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hill</surname>
<given-names>KA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kari</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Machine learning using intrinsic genomic signatures for rapid classification of novel pathogens: COVID-19 case study</article-title>
<source>Plos one</source>
<year>2020</year>
<volume>15</volume>
<elocation-id>e0232391</elocation-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R36">
<label>36</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>de M Barbosa</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Fernandes</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>
<italic>k</italic>-mers 1D and 2D representation dataset of SARS-CoV-2 nucleotide sequences</article-title>
<source>Mendeley Data</source>
<year>2020</year>
<comment>v2</comment>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.17632/f5y9cggnxy.2</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R37">
<label>37</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Mapleson</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Garcia Accinelli</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kettleborough</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wright</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Clavijo</surname>
<given-names>BJ</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>KAT: a K-mer analysis toolkit to quality control NGS datasets and genome assemblies</article-title>
<source>Bioinformatics</source>
<year>2016</year>
<volume>33</volume>
<fpage>574</fpage>
<lpage>576</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btw663</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R38">
<label>38</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Chor</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Horn</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Goldman</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Levy</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Massingham</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Genomic DNA k-mer spectra: models and modalities</article-title>
<source>Genome biology</source>
<year>2009</year>
<volume>10</volume>
<fpage>R108</fpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R39">
<label>39</label>
<element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Goodfellow</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bengio</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Courville</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<source>Deep Learning</source>
<publisher-name>MIT press</publisher-name>
<year>2016</year>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R40">
<label>40</label>
<element-citation publication-type="web">
<collab>The MathWorks</collab>
<source>Matlab</source>
<year>2020</year>
<comment>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.mathworks.com/">https://www.mathworks.com/</ext-link>
</comment>
</element-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
<floats-group>
<fig id="F1" position="float">
<label>Figure 1</label>
<caption>
<title>Genome analysis stages with deep learning.</title>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="EMS136956-f001"/>
</fig>
<fig id="F2" position="float">
<label>Figure 2</label>
<caption>
<title>Stages of viral genome analysis using deep learning.</title>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="EMS136956-f002"/>
</fig>
<fig id="F3" position="float">
<label>Figure 3</label>
<caption>
<p>Examples of <italic>k</italic>-mers images representation with <italic>k</italic> = 6. Based on <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD10">Equation 10</xref>, <italic>L</italic> = 64 and each image, matrix <bold>Φ</bold> (see <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD11">Equation 11</xref>), is composed by 64 × 64 pixels with <italic>b</italic> = 8 (see <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD12">Equation 12</xref>).</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="EMS136956-f003"/>
</fig>
<fig id="F4" position="float">
<label>Figure 4</label>
<caption>
<title>Deep learning stacked sparse autoencoder architecture (DL-SSAE).</title>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="EMS136956-f004"/>
</fig>
<fig id="F5" position="float">
<label>Figure 5</label>
<caption>
<title>Viral classification process using <italic>k</italic>-mers images representation with the DL-SSAE.</title>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="EMS136956-f005"/>
</fig>
<fig id="F6" position="float">
<label>Figure 6</label>
<caption>
<title>Confusion matrix of the validation set from the Experiment 1.</title>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="EMS136956-f006"/>
</fig>
<fig id="F7" position="float">
<label>Figure 7</label>
<caption>
<title>ROC curve of the validation set from the Experiment 1.</title>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="EMS136956-f007"/>
</fig>
<fig id="F8" position="float">
<label>Figure 8</label>
<caption>
<title>Confusion matrix of the test set from the Experiment 1.</title>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="EMS136956-f008"/>
</fig>
<fig id="F9" position="float">
<label>Figure 9</label>
<caption>
<title>Confusion matrix of the validation set from the Experiment 2.</title>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="EMS136956-f009"/>
</fig>
<fig id="F10" position="float">
<label>Figure 10</label>
<caption>
<title>ROC curve of the validation set from the Experiment 2.</title>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="EMS136956-f010"/>
</fig>
<fig id="F11" position="float">
<label>Figure 11</label>
<caption>
<title>Confusion matrix of the test set from the Experiment 2.</title>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="EMS136956-f011"/>
</fig>
<fig id="F12" position="float">
<label>Figure 12</label>
<caption>
<title>Confusion matrix of the validation set from the Experiment 3.</title>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="EMS136956-f012"/>
</fig>
<fig id="F13" position="float">
<label>Figure 13</label>
<caption>
<title>ROC curve of the validation set from the Experiment 3.</title>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="EMS136956-f013"/>
</fig>
<fig id="F14" position="float">
<label>Figure 14</label>
<caption>
<title>Confusion matrix of the test set from the Experiment 3.</title>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="EMS136956-f014"/>
</fig>
<fig id="F15" position="float">
<label>Figure 15</label>
<caption>
<title>Confusion matrix of the validation set from the Experiment 4.</title>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="EMS136956-f015"/>
</fig>
<fig id="F16" position="float">
<label>Figure 16</label>
<caption>
<title>ROC curve of the validation set from the Experiment 4.</title>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="EMS136956-f016"/>
</fig>
<fig id="F17" position="float">
<label>Figure 17</label>
<caption>
<title>Confusion matrix of the test set from the Experiment 4.</title>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="EMS136956-f017"/>
</fig>
<table-wrap id="T1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
<label>Table 1</label>
<caption>
<title>State of the art references - Part 1.</title>
</caption>
<table frame="hsides" rules="rows">
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="center" valign="middle">Biology name</th>
<th align="center" valign="middle" colspan="2">Group</th>
<th align="center" valign="middle">Aim</th>
<th align="center" valign="middle">Ref.</th>
<th align="center" valign="middle">COVID-19</th>
<th align="center" valign="middle">DNN</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="4">Genome prediction or sequence classification</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="4">Genome classification (taxonomic classification)</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="4">Viral classification</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">Viral Subtyping</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref>]</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">-</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">CNN+FC</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" valign="middle">Primer design</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref>]</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">Yes</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">CNN+FC</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" valign="middle">Identified virus sequence</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref>]</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">Yes</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">LSTM+FC<break/>CNN+FC</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" valign="middle">Taxonomic classification</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref>]<break/>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref>]</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">-<break/>-</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">CNN+FC<break/>BLSTM+FC</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="2"> </td>
<td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="2">Genome prediction</td>
<td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="2">Viral prediction</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">Identified virus sequence</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref>]<break/>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref>]</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">-<break/>-</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">CNN+FC<break/>CNN+FC</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" valign="middle">Identified phage, chromossomes, plasmid</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">23</xref>]</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">-</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">CNN+FC</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="2">Host prediction</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">Host classification</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">Viral host classification</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="2">Predicting viruses among several hosts</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref>]</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">-</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">BLSTM+CNN+FC<break/>CNN+FC</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" valign="middle">Host prediction</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">Viral host prediction</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">22</xref>]</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">Yes</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">CNN+FC</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" valign="middle">Genome segments prediction</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">Genome segments classification</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">Viral segments classification</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">Prediction specific regions in the genome</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref>]<break/>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref>]<break/>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">25</xref>]<break/>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">26</xref>]</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">-<break/>-<break/>-<break/>-</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">CNN+FC<break/>CNN+BLSTM+FC<break/>CNN+BLSTM+FC<break/>CNN+BLSTM+FC</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="T2" position="float" orientation="portrait">
<label>Table 2</label>
<caption>
<title>State of the art references - Part 2.</title>
</caption>
<table frame="hsides" rules="rows">
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="center" valign="middle">Input</th>
<th align="center" valign="middle">Output</th>
<th align="center" valign="middle">Ref.</th>
<th align="center" valign="middle">Biology fields</th>
<th align="center" valign="middle">Bioinformatics</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="6">The DNA or cDNA (RNA virus) of the virus.The whole or part of the genome is used.</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">Number of the classes</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref>]<break/>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref>]<break/>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref>]<break/>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref>]<break/>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref>]</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">Metagenomics<break/>Diagnosis of <break/>viral infections<break/> Pharmacogenomics</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="6">Free alignments techniques</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" valign="middle">Score Binary output Score</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref>]<break/>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref>]<break/>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">23</xref>]</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">Metagenomics Phylogenetic analysis</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" valign="middle">Number of the classes</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref>]</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">Metagenomics Phylogenetic analysis</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" valign="middle">Score</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">22</xref>]</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">Metagenomics</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="2">Number of the classes</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref>]<break/>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref>]</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">Transcriptome<break/>Analysis</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" valign="middle">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">25</xref>]<break/>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">26</xref>]</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">Gene expression<break/>analysis</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="T3" position="float" orientation="portrait">
<label>Table 3</label>
<caption>
<title>Examples of <italic>k</italic>-mers count 1D representation values (with <italic>k</italic> = 2) for SARS-CoV-2.</title>
</caption>
<table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="center" valign="middle">
<italic>k</italic>-mers (k = 2)</th>
<th align="center" valign="middle">China-Wuhan(ID: LR757995)</th>
<th align="center" valign="middle">USA-MA (ID: MT039888)</th>
<th align="center" valign="middle">Brazil(ID: MT126808)</th>
<th align="center" valign="middle">Italy(ID: MT066156)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="center" valign="middle">AA</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">2862</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">2859</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">2853</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">2847</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" valign="middle">AC</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">2022</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">2022</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">2022</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">2022</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" valign="middle">AG</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">1741</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">1741</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">1742</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">1742</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" valign="middle">AT</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">2306</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">2309</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">2309</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">2308</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" valign="middle">CA</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">2085</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">2082</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">2084</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">2082</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" valign="middle">CC</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">886</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">888</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">888</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">888</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" valign="middle">CG</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">439</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">439</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">440</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">439</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" valign="middle">CT</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">2080</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">2081</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">2080</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">2082</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" valign="middle">GA</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">1612</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">1612</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">1612</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">1611</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" valign="middle">GC</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">1167</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">1167</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">1169</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">1168</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" valign="middle">GG</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">1092</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">1093</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">1092</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">1092</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" valign="middle">GT</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">1990</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">1990</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">1988</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">1989</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" valign="middle">TA</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">2373</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">2378</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">2377</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">2378</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" valign="middle">TC</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">1415</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">1412</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">1413</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">1413</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" valign="middle">TG</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">2589</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">2589</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">2587</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">2587</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" valign="middle">TT</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">3212</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">3217</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">3219</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">3216</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="T4" position="float" orientation="portrait">
<label>Table 4</label>
<caption>
<title>Examples of <italic>k</italic>-mers count 2D representation values (with <italic>k</italic> = 2) for SARS-CoV-2.</title>
</caption>
<table frame="box" rules="all">
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="center" valign="middle">China-Wuhan (ID: LR757995)</th>
<th align="center" valign="middle">USA-MA (ID: MT039888)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="center" valign="middle">
<inline-formula>
<mml:math id="M18">
<mml:msub>
<mml:mtext mathvariant="bold">Λ</mml:mtext>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>17</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mspace width="0.2em"/>
<mml:mspace width="0.2em"/>
<mml:mspace width="0.2em"/>
<mml:mspace width="0.2em"/>
<mml:mspace width="0.2em"/>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>[</mml:mo>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mtable>
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>2862</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>2022</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>1741</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>1741</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>2085</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>886</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>439</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>439</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>1612</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>1167</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>1092</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>1092</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>2373</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>1415</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>2589</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>2589</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
</mml:mtable>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>]</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>
</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">
<inline-formula>
<mml:math id="M19">
<mml:msub>
<mml:mtext mathvariant="bold">Λ</mml:mtext>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>32</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mspace width="0.2em"/>
<mml:mspace width="0.2em"/>
<mml:mspace width="0.2em"/>
<mml:mspace width="0.2em"/>
<mml:mspace width="0.2em"/>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>[</mml:mo>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mtable>
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>2859</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>2022</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>1741</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>1741</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>2082</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>888</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>439</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>439</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>1612</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>1167</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>1093</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>1093</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>2378</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>1412</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>2589</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>2589</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
</mml:mtable>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>]</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" valign="middle">Brazil (ID: MT126808)</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">Italy (ID: MT066156)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" valign="middle">
<inline-formula>
<mml:math id="M20">
<mml:msub>
<mml:mtext mathvariant="bold">Λ</mml:mtext>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>52</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mspace width="0.2em"/>
<mml:mspace width="0.2em"/>
<mml:mspace width="0.2em"/>
<mml:mspace width="0.2em"/>
<mml:mspace width="0.2em"/>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>[</mml:mo>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mtable>
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>2853</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>2022</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>1742</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>1742</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>2084</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>888</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>440</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>440</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>1612</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>1169</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>1092</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>1092</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>2377</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>1413</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>2587</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>2587</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
</mml:mtable>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>]</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>
</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">
<inline-formula>
<mml:math id="M21">
<mml:msub>
<mml:mtext mathvariant="bold">Λ</mml:mtext>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>79</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:msub>
<mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
<mml:mspace width="0.2em"/>
<mml:mspace width="0.2em"/>
<mml:mspace width="0.2em"/>
<mml:mspace width="0.2em"/>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>[</mml:mo>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mtable>
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>2853</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>2022</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>1742</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>1742</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>2084</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>888</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>440</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>440</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>1612</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>1169</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>1092</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>1092</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
<mml:mtr>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>2377</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>1413</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>2587</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
<mml:mtd>
<mml:mrow>
<mml:mn>2587</mml:mn>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:mtd>
</mml:mtr>
</mml:mtable>
</mml:mrow>
<mml:mo>]</mml:mo>
</mml:mrow>
</mml:math>
</inline-formula>
</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="T5" position="float" orientation="portrait">
<label>Table 5</label>
<caption>
<title>Experiments data.</title>
</caption>
<table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="center" valign="middle">Experiments</th>
<th align="center" valign="middle">Classes</th>
<th align="center" valign="middle">Number of sequences</th>
<th align="center" valign="middle">SSAE architecture <italic>P</italic> − <italic>Q</italic>
<sub>1</sub> − <italic>Q</italic>
<sub>2</sub> − <italic>Q</italic>
<sub>3</sub> − <italic>U</italic>
</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="14">Experiment 1</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">Adenoviridae</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">195</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="14">4096 − 3000 − 1000 − 500 − 14</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" valign="middle">Anelloviridae</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">114</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" valign="middle">Caudovirales</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">500</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" valign="middle">Circoviridae</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">243</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" valign="middle">Geminiviridae</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">500</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" valign="middle">Genomoviridae</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">115</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" valign="middle">Herpesvirales</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">136</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" valign="middle">Microviridae</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">102</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" valign="middle">Ortervirales</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">214</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" valign="middle">Papillomaviridae</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">354</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" valign="middle">Parvoviridae</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">168</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" valign="middle">Polyomaviridae</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">142</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" valign="middle">Riboviria</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">500</td>
</tr>
<tr style="border-bottom: 1px solid">
<td align="center" valign="middle">Tolecusatellitidae</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">150</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="8">Experiment 2</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">Picornaviridae</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">423</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="8">4096 − 3000 − 1000 − 500 − 8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" valign="middle">Caliciviridae</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">392</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" valign="middle">Coronaviridae</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">206</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" valign="middle">Potyviridae</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">232</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" valign="middle">Flaviviridae</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">217</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" valign="middle">Rhabdoviridae</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">186</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" valign="middle">Betaflexiviridae</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">129</td>
</tr>
<tr style="border-bottom: 1px solid">
<td align="center" valign="middle">Reoviridae</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">111</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="4">Experiment 3</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">Alphacoronavirus</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">52</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="4">4096 − 3000 − 1000 − 500 − 4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" valign="middle">Betacoronavirus</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">123</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" valign="middle">Deltacoronavirus</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">20</td>
</tr>
<tr style="border-bottom: 1px solid">
<td align="center" valign="middle">Gammacoronavirus</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">9</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="4">Experiment 4</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">Embecovirus</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">47</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="4">4096 − 3000 − 1000 − 500 − 4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" valign="middle">Merbecovirus</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">17</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" valign="middle">Nobecovirus</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">9</td>
</tr>
<tr style="border-bottom: 2px solid">
<td align="center" valign="middle">Sarbecovirus</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">46</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="T6" position="float" orientation="portrait">
<label>Table 6</label>
<caption>
<title>Classification performance metrics results obtained from the validation set.</title>
</caption>
<table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="center" valign="middle">Experiment</th>
<th align="center" valign="middle">Accuracy</th>
<th align="center" valign="middle">Precision</th>
<th align="center" valign="middle">Recall</th>
<th align="center" valign="middle">F1 score</th>
<th align="center" valign="middle">Specificity</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="center" valign="middle">1</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">0.920 (92.0%)</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">0.924 (92.4%)</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">0.920 (92.0%)</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">0.931 (93.1%)</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">0.993 (99.3%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" valign="middle">2</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">0.963 (96.3%)</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">0.968 (96.8%)</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">0.971 (97.1%)</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">0.962 (96.2%)</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">0.997 (99.7%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" valign="middle">3</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">0.950 (95.0%)</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">0.979 (97.9%)</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">0.979 (97.9%)</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">0.955 (95.5%)</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">0.983 (98.3%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" valign="middle">4</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">1 (100%)</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">1 (100%)</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">1 (100%)</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">1 (100%)</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">1 (100%)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="T7" position="float" orientation="portrait">
<label>Table 7</label>
<caption>
<title>Classification performance metrics results obtained from the test set.</title>
</caption>
<table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
<thead>
<tr>
<th align="center" valign="middle">Experiment</th>
<th align="center" valign="middle">Accuracy</th>
<th align="center" valign="middle">Recall</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="center" valign="middle">1</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">1 (100%)</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">1 (100%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" valign="middle">2</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">1 (100%)</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">1 (100%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" valign="middle">3</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">0.989 (98.9%)</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">0.989 (98.9%)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center" valign="middle">4</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">0.999 (99.9%)</td>
<td align="center" valign="middle">0.999 (99.9%)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
</floats-group>
</article>
