<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="preprint">
<?all-math-mml yes?>
<?use-mml?>
<?origin ukpmcpa?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">bioRxiv</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>bioRxiv : the preprint server for biology</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub"/>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">EMS136057</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2021.09.30.462449</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="archive">PPR402754</article-id>
<article-version article-version-type="publisher-id">1</article-version>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Pyronaridine Protects Against SARS-CoV-2 in Mouse</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Puhl</surname>
<given-names>Ana C.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN1">*</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CR1">#</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Gomes</surname>
<given-names>Giovanni F.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN1">*</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Damasceno</surname>
<given-names>Samara</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Godoy</surname>
<given-names>Andre S.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Noske</surname>
<given-names>Gabriela D.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Nakamura</surname>
<given-names>Aline M.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Gawriljuk</surname>
<given-names>Victor O.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Fernandes</surname>
<given-names>Rafaela S.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Monakhova</surname>
<given-names>Natalia</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Riabova</surname>
<given-names>Olga</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lane</surname>
<given-names>Thomas R.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Makarov</surname>
<given-names>Vadim</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Veras</surname>
<given-names>Flavio P.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Batah</surname>
<given-names>Sabrina S.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">5</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Fabro</surname>
<given-names>Alexandre T.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">5</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Oliva</surname>
<given-names>Glaucius</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Cunha</surname>
<given-names>Fernando Q.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Alves-Filho</surname>
<given-names>José C.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CR1">#</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Cunha</surname>
<given-names>Thiago M.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CR1">#</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ekins</surname>
<given-names>Sean</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CR1">#</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="A1">
<label>1</label>Collaborations Pharmaceuticals, Inc., 840 Main Campus Drive, Lab 3510, Raleigh, NC 27606, USA</aff>
<aff id="A2">
<label>2</label>Center for Research in Inflammatory Diseases (CRID), Ribeirao Preto Medical School, University of Sao Paulo, Avenida Bandeirantes, 3900, Ribeirao Preto, 14049-900 ; Sao Paulo, Brazil</aff>
<aff id="A3">
<label>3</label>Institute of Physics of Sao Carlos, University of Sao Paulo, Av. Joao Dagnone, 1100 - Jardim Santa Angelina, Sao Carlos, 13563-120, Brazil</aff>
<aff id="A4">
<label>4</label>Research Center of Biotechnology RAS, 119071 Moscow, Russia</aff>
<aff id="A5">
<label>5</label>Department of Pathology and Legal Medicine, Ribeirão Preto Medical School, University of São Paulo, Ribeirão Preto, Brazil</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="CR1">
<label>#</label>To whom correspondence should be addressed: Ana C. Puhl, <email>ana@collaborationspharma.com</email>; Thiago M. Cunha <email>thicunha@fmrp.usp.br</email>; Sean Ekins, <email>sean@collaborationspharma.com</email>
</corresp>
<fn id="FN1" fn-type="equal">
<label>*</label>
<p id="P1">Both authors contribute equally</p>
</fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted">
<day>06</day>
<month>10</month>
<year>2021</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="preprint">
<day>30</day>
<month>09</month>
<year>2021</year>
</pub-date>
<permissions>
<ali:free_to_read/>
<license>
<ali:license_ref>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
<license-p>This work is licensed under a <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">CC BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license</ext-link>.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p id="P2">There are currently relatively few small-molecule antiviral drugs that are either approved or emergency approved for use against SARS-CoV-2. One of these is remdesivir, which was originally repurposed from its use against Ebola and functions by causing early RNA chain termination. We used this as justification to evaluate three molecules we had previously identified computationally with antiviral activity against Ebola and Marburg. Out of these we previously identified pyronaridine, which inhibited the SARS-CoV-2 replication in A549-ACE2 cells. Herein, the <italic>in vivo</italic> efficacy of pyronaridine has now been assessed in a K18-hACE transgenic mouse model of COVID-19. Pyronaridine treatment demonstrated a statistically significant reduction of viral load in the lungs of SARS CoV-2 infected mice. Furthermore, the pyronaridine treated group reduced lung pathology, which was also associated with significant reduction in the levels of pro-inflammatory cytokines/chemokine and cell infiltration. Notably, pyronaridine inhibited the viral PL<sup>pro</sup> activity <italic>in vitro</italic> (IC<sub>50</sub> of 1.8 μM) without any effect on M<sup>pro</sup>, indicating a possible molecular mechanism involved in its ability to inhibit SARS-CoV-2 replication. Interestingly, pyronaridine also selectively inhibits the host kinase CAMK1 (IC<sub>50</sub> of 2.4 μM). We have also generated several pyronaridine analogs to assist in understanding the structure activity relationship for PL<sup>pro</sup> inhibition. Our results indicate that pyronaridine is a potential therapeutic candidate for COVID-19.</p>
</abstract>
<kwd-group>
<kwd>Antiviral</kwd>
<kwd>SARS-CoV-2</kwd>
<kwd>Spike protein</kwd>
<kwd>pyronaridine</kwd>
</kwd-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="S1" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p id="P3">At the time of writing, we are in the midst of a major a global health crisis caused by the virus Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome Coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) that was originally reported in Wuhan, China in late 2019 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">2</xref>). Infection with this virus leads to extensive morbidity, mortality and a very broad range of clinical symptoms such as cough, loss of smell and taste, respiratory distress, pneumonia and extrapulmonary events characterized by a sepsis-like disease collectively called 2019 coronavirus disease (COVID-19) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">3</xref>). In the USA, there are currently three vaccines available, one of which has recently obtained full approval from the FDA to protect against SARS-CoV-2 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">4</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref>). There are however few small-molecule drugs approved for COVID-19 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref>) including remdesivir (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">8</xref>), which originally demonstrated activity in Vero cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>), human epithelial cells and in Calu-3 cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>) infected with SARS-CoV-2 prior to clinical testing. Remdesivir represents a repurposed drug which was originally developed for Hepatitis C virus but was then repurposed for treating Ebola and has since reached clinical trials (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref>). We therefore hypothesized that other drugs that were effective against Ebola might also be prioritized for evaluation <italic>in vitro</italic> against SARS-CoV-2. Previously, we had used a machine-learning model to identify tilorone, quinacrine and pyronaridine tetraphosphate(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref>) for testing against Ebola virus (EBOV) and subsequently these three inhibited EBOV and Marburg <italic>in vitro</italic> as well as demonstrating significant efficacy in the mouse-adapted EBOV (ma-EBOV) model (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref>). All of these molecules were identified as lysosomotropic, a characteristic that suggests these could be possible entry inhibitors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref>). Pyronaridine tetraphosphate is used as an antimalarial in several countries as part of a combination therapy with artesunate (Pyramax). Pyronaridine alone also demonstrated significant activity in the guinea pig-adapted model of EBOV infection (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref>). We and others (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">20</xref>) have recently shown that these compounds possess <italic>in vitro</italic> activity against SARS-CoV-2 and tilorone and pyronaridine are in clinical trials, the latter in combination with artesunate. The C<sub>max</sub> data for pyronaridine in our previous mouse pharmacokinetics studies (i.p. dosing) suggests that plasma levels that are above the average IC<sub>50</sub> observed for SARS-CoV-2 inhibition <italic>in vitro</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref>) can be reached with dosing well below the maximum tolerated dose. Pyronaridine also has excellent <italic>in vitro</italic> ADME properties with a long half-life that makes a single dose treatment possible (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref>). We now expand on our earlier <italic>in vitro</italic> characterization of pyronaridine (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref>) by assessing the <italic>in vivo</italic> efficacy in a mouse model of COVID-19. Finally, in an attempt to further explore molecular mechanisms, we tested the activity of pyronaridine <italic>in vitro</italic> against viral and host targets.</p>
<sec id="S2">
<title>
<italic>In vivo</italic> efficacy of Pyronaridine in a mouse model of COVID-19</title>
<p id="P4">
<italic>In vivo</italic> efficacy was assessed in K-18-hACE2 mouse model of COVID-19 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">21</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">23</xref>). Pyronaridine (75 mg/kg, i.p) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref>) was administered 1 h prior to infection. Mice that were given pyronaridine, received a single treatment. On the third day post-infection, mice were euthanized and lung viral load, cytokine levels and histopathology were evaluated (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1A</xref>). In all groups tested, mice lost weight compared to uninfected animals that received only vehicle formulation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1B</xref>). Lung viral load was evaluated by RT-qPCR and the pyronaridine treated group showed a statistically significant decrease in the lung viral load (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1C</xref>). Moreover, reduced levels of INF-1β were observed in infected mice, and pyronaridine restored the levels of INF-1β close to that found in uninfected animals (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1D</xref>). Interestingly, the increased levels of IL-6 found in the infected untreated group were not observed in animals treated with pyronaridine (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1E</xref>). In addition, pyronaridine reduced the high levels of CXCL1 and CCL4 observed in infected animals (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1D</xref>). Pyronaridine did not however reduce the high levels of IL-10, TNF-α, CCL2, and CCL3 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1F, G, K, L, M</xref>) below the elevated levels found in the infected mice.</p>
<p id="P5">To determine the severity of lung damage, histological examination of hematoxylin and eosin (H&amp;E) stained lung tissue was performed. Infected, untreated mice showed severe pathological changes with inflammatory cell infiltrates. In contrast, pyronaridine-treated animals exhibited improved morphology and milder infiltration (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2A</xref>). Histological observations were confirmed by quantitative morphometric analysis of the H&amp;E-stained slides showing a statistically significant reduction in inflammation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2B</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S3">
<title>Pyronaridine potentially targets SARS-CoV-2 PL<sup>pro</sup> but not M<sup>pro</sup>
</title>
<p id="P6">SARS-CoV-2 proteases M<sup>pro</sup> and PL<sup>pro</sup> are essential for viral replication and have been widely studied for the discovery of new direct acting antivirals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">26</xref>). Pyronaridine was therefore tested against both SARS-CoV-2 recombinant PL<sup>pro</sup> and M<sup>pro</sup> through FRET-based <italic>in vitro</italic> assays. Pyronaridine inhibited PL<sup>pro</sup> with an IC<sub>50</sub> of 1.86 ± 0.58 μM (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3A</xref>) but did not show any appreciable activity against M<sup>pro</sup> at 20 μM (data not shown). Additional analogs of pyronaridine were also synthesized and tested against PL<sup>pro</sup>. The analogs 12126038, 12126039 and 12126040 showed similar inhibitory activity when compared with pyronaridine (as well as that reported for GRL0617 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27">27</xref>)), indicating that the aminophenol moiety together with pyrrole or tertiary amine substitutions at the meta position are tolerated for PL<sup>pro</sup> inhibition (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3A</xref>). The deletion of these groups in analogs 10326099, 12126035, 12126036, 12126037 and 12126072 caused complete abolishment of the inhibitory activity of the series (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). The PL<sup>pro</sup> active site contains four subsites for peptide recognition, with a strong preference for positively charged amino acids at P3 and P4 subsites (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">26</xref>). In our molecular docking studies (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3B</xref>), the positions where the 2,6‐bis[(pyrrolidin‐1‐yl)methyl]phenol moiety of pyronaridine were docked at the P4 subsite showed a far higher score than the second highest cluster group (Glide score of −5.052 and HADDOCK score of −65.6). These positively charged amino-groups would likely satisfy the negatively charged cavity that forms the P4 subsite, forming hydrogen bounds with Asp164 and π-stacking with Tyr26 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3C</xref>). Compounds 12126038 and 12126039 also showed very similar poses after docking, indicating binding to the P4 subsite (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3B</xref>). The primary docking poses from Glide for all compounds are provided in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S1</xref>. These results indicate that the <italic>in vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic> efficacy of pyronaridine may be related to PL<sup>pro</sup> inhibition.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S4">
<title>Kinase activity profiling</title>
<p id="P7">Due to the possible effect of pyronaridine on cytokines (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>) we have also assessed the effect on host targets, as SARS-CoV-2 can cause an imbalance in the immune system that may result in a cytokine storm(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">28</xref>) as well as leading to acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS), coagulation disorders, and eventually multiple organ failure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">28</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">29</xref>). Hence targeting the cytokine storm to address hyperinflammation represents another approach to the treatment of COVID-19 patients (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">30</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33">33</xref>). In this regard, we have explored the effect of pyronaridine on human kinases which are responsible for host cell signaling (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34">34</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35">35</xref>). Screening of pyronaridine (tested at 1 μM) against 485 kinases identified only 2 as having mean percent inhibition greater than 30% including CAMK1 (35%) and MELK (31%) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table S1</xref>). Subsequently, the IC<sub>50</sub> was determined for CAMK1 (2.4 μM) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="S5" sec-type="discussion">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p id="P8">Even with vaccines becoming widely available in many countries COVID-19 continues to exact a very heavy toll on those that are unvaccinated. We are in a race against time before the virus mutates and vaccines lose their effectiveness. There is therefore an urgent need for new antivirals and in particular small-molecule treatments that are orally delivered and can be used outside of a hospital setting. Finding, developing, and progressing small molecules to the clinic is generally a slow and expensive process (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36">36</xref>), hence drug repurposing has been attempted by many groups to speed this up (either experimentally or computationally (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37">37</xref>)) by identifying already approved or clinical stage candidates used for other applications or quickly follow up the few molecules that are being used already. The traditional prioritization of compounds <italic>in vitro</italic> before animal models and then humans is still repeated and so far with few successes with many molecules not demonstrating efficacy <italic>in vivo</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38">38</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39">39</xref>).</p>
<p id="P9">Our understanding of the antiviral mechanism of pyronaridine previously shown to inhibit the Ebola virus <italic>in vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref>) via binding to the viral glycoprotein(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref>) as well as through its potent lysosomotropic activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40">40</xref>) and now the <italic>in vitro</italic> activity against SARS-CoV-2 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref>) is also further expanded. Pyronaridine was previously identified with <italic>in vitro</italic> activity against SARS-CoV-2 in A549-ACE2 cells that was on a par with remdesivir in this cell line (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref>). In the current study, we have demonstrated that pyronaridine also has antiviral activity against SARS-CoV-2 <italic>in vivo.</italic> A single prophylactic dose of pyronaridine (75 mg/kg i.p) reduced the viral load in the lung of infected mice 3 days post-infection. <italic>In vitro</italic> assays suggest that pyronaridine possesses a direct antiviral effect showing activity against PL<sup>pro</sup> (IC<sub>50</sub> 1.86 μM, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>), but did not inhibit SARS-CoV-2 M<sup>pro</sup>. Kinase profiling, resulted in determination of IC<sub>50</sub> for CAMK1 (IC<sub>50</sub> 2.4 μM, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>).</p>
<p id="P10">A single dose (75 mg/kg i.p.) of pyronaridine has an elimination half-life of 146 h in mice (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref>), comparable to the reported half-life of pyronaridine in humans of 195-251 h (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41">41</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42">42</xref>). A study of pyronaridine as a single oral dose (400 mg) given to a healthy volunteer found a C<sub>max</sub> in plasma of 495.8 ng/ml at a T<sub>max</sub> of 0.5 h (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41">41</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43">43</xref>), which gives a concentration close to 1 μM. In our study, pyronaridine inhibits Pl<sup>pro</sup> at 1.86 μM and CAMK1 at 2.4 μM, which is very close to the C<sub>max</sub> of 1 μM. Pyronaridine preferentially associates with blood cells and is highly plasma protein bound (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43">43</xref>), which suggests that it may not reach the unbound concentration necessary to have an effect on Pl<sup>pro</sup> and CAMK1 at these doses. Activation of CAMK1 has been reported to negatively impact HBV biosynthesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R44">44</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R45">45</xref>), however the mechanism has not been elucidated yet and the possible role of CAMK1 on SARS-CoV-2 infection remains to be investigated.</p>
<p id="P11">Several studies have shown a cytokine and chemokine storm as important during SARS-CoV-2 infection in patients with COVID-19, including PDGF, VEGF (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R46">46</xref>), IL-6 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R47">47</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R48">48</xref>), IL‐8, IL‐10 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R48">48</xref>), TNF‐α (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R48">48</xref>) and IFN-α and -β (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R49">49</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R53">53</xref>). Furthermore, an impaired type I interferon response has already been observed in COVID-19 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R54">54</xref>), which is followed by increased circulating levels of IL-6 and TNF-α. Many viruses, including SARS-CoV-2, subvert the immune system by inhibiting the production of interferons (INF), an important family of antiviral mediators (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R55">55</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R58">58</xref>), which results in an impaired antiviral defense and increased viral replication and infection. Here, we have demonstrated that pyronaridine restored the levels of INF-1β in infected mice. Moreover, as already discussed, this effect was associated with a reduced viral load after the treatment with pyronaridine. Notably, pyronaridine also reverted the altered levels of IL-6 and CXCL1 observed in infected mice. In addition to biochemical changes, histopathological findings are also observed in the lung of patients (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R59">59</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R61">61</xref>) and in other experimental models of COVID-19 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">21</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">23</xref>). In the present study, control animals infected with SARS-CoV-2 presented pronounced inflammatory cell infiltration and the histological examination of mouse lungs for those treated with pyronaridine showed milder infiltration, appearing comparable to that of uninfected mice. Thus, pyronaridine appears to have both antiviral and immunomodulatory effects in this experimental model of COVID-19 as used in the present study.</p>
<p id="P12">In summary, our present study provided additional data on the efficacy of pyronaridine against SARS-CoV-2 infection as well as highlighting reduced lung pathology and inflammation in a mouse model of COVID-19. Furthermore, we have shown that pyronaridine may target Pl<sup>pro</sup> as well as CAMK1. There are few inhibitors of CAMK1 that have been identified to date (such as Barettin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R62">62</xref>) or pyridine amides (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R63">63</xref>)) which has a role in inflammation targeting IL-10 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R62">62</xref>). Previous <italic>in vitro</italic> work has shown that inhibiting CAMK1 in cells reduces IL-10, the master anti-inflammatory interleukin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R64">64</xref>). In the present study there is not a significant difference in the IL-10 levels between the untreated and pyronaridine-treated infected groups so it seems unlikely that CAMK1 inhibition would be involved in the mechanism of action of inhibition of SAR-CoV-2. In conclusion, we propose that pyronaridine could be used alone as a potential therapeutic candidate for COVID-19. Finally, with the emerging virulence of novel SARS-CoV-2 strains, identifying repurposed drugs with novel mechanisms of action and whose antiviral activity translates from <italic>in vitro</italic> to <italic>in vivo</italic> are rare (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39">39</xref>), and may lead to new treatments as well as their further optimization.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S6" sec-type="materials | methods" specific-use="web-only">
<title>Materials and Methods</title>
<sec id="S7">
<title>Chemicals and reagents</title>
<p id="P13">Pyronaridine tetraphosphate [4-[(7-Chloro-2-methoxybenzo[b][1,5]naphthyridin-10-yl)amino]-2,6-bis(1-pyrrolidinylmethyl)phenol phosphate (1:4)] (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref>) was purchased from BOC Sciences (Shirley NY). The purity of this compound was greater than 95%. For pyronaridine analogs, <sup>1</sup>H and <sup>13</sup>C Spectra were measured on Bruker AC-300 (300 MHz, <sup>1</sup>H) or Bruker AC-200 (50 MHz, <sup>13</sup>C). Chemical shifts were measured in DMSO-d<sub>6</sub>or CDCl<sub>3</sub>, using tetramethylsilane as an internal standard, and reported as units (ppm) values. The following abbreviations are used to indicate the multiplicity: s, singlet; d, doublet; t, triplet; m, multiplet; dd, doublet of doublets; brs, broad singlet; brm, broad multiplet. The purity of the final compounds was analyzed on Agilent 1290 Infinity II HPLC system coupled to Agilent 6460 triple-quadrupole mass spectrometer equipped with an electrospray ionization source. The chromatographic separation was carried out on Agilent Eclipse Plus C18 RRHD column (2.1 × 50 mm, 1.8 μm) at 40 °C, sample injection volume was 0.2 μL.The mobile phase comprising 0.1 % formic acid / water (A), and 0.1 %formic acid and 85 % acetonitrile / water (B) was programmed with gradient elution (0.0-3.0 min, 60 % B; 3.0-4.0 min, 60 % to 97 % B; 4.0-6.0 min, 97 % B; 6.0-6.1 min, 97 % to 60 % B) at a flow rate of 0.4 mL/min. The mass spectrometric detection was operated in positive ion mode. Optimal parameters were: capillary voltages of 3500 V, a nebulizer pressure of 35 psi, a gas temperature of 350 °C, a gas flow rate of 12 L/min. All final compounds are &gt; 95 % pure. Melting points were determined on Electrothermal 9001 (10 °C per min) and are uncorrected. Merck KGaAsilica gel 60 F<sub>254</sub> plates were used for analytical thin-layer chromatography. Column chromatography was performed on Merck silica gel 60 (70-230 mesh). Yields refer to purified products and are not optimized. The molecules were synthesized according to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Scheme 1</xref> or <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Scheme 2</xref> and the specific methods and analytical results are described in the <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplemental Methods</xref>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S8">
<title>Test Article Preparation</title>
<p id="P14">Dose formulation for pyronaridine was prepared as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref>) under yellow light by mixing the appropriate amount of pyronaridine in melted Kolliphor HS 15 (Solutol) (20% final volume) using a vortex mixer for 30 s. The remaining sterile water (Gibco) was added, and the formulations were mixed using a vortex mixer for 30 sec – 5 min until the compound was visually dissolved and then sonication for 25 min. The final 20% Kolliphor HS 15 dose formulations was observed to be a clear, reddish solutions.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S9">
<title>Mouse studies</title>
<sec id="S10">
<title>Ethical approval</title>
<p id="P15">All the experimental procedures were performed in accordance with the guide for the use of laboratory animals of the University of Sao Paulo and approved by the institutional ethics committee under the protocol number 105/2021.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S11">
<title>SARS-CoV-2 isolate</title>
<p id="P16">SARS-CoV-2 was isolated from a COVID-19 positive-tested patient. The virus was propagated and titrated in Vero E6 cells in a biosafety level 3 laboratory (BSL3) at the Ribeirão Preto Medical school (Ribeirão Preto, Brazil). Cells were cultured in DMEM medium supplemented with 10% fetal bovine serum (FBS) and antibiotic/antimycotic (Penicillin 10,000 U/mL; Streptomycin 10,000 μg/mL). The viral inoculum was added to Vero cells in DMEM 2% FBS and incubated at 37 °C with 5% CO<sub>2</sub> for 48 h. The cytopathogenic effect (CPE) was observed under a microscope. Cell monolayer was collected, and the supernatant was stored in -70 °C. Virus titration was made by the plaque-forming units (PFU).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S12">
<title>K18-hACE2 mice</title>
<p id="P17">To evaluate the effects of Pyronaridine <italic>in vivo</italic>, we infected the K18-hACE2 humanized mice (B6.Cg-Tg(K18-ACE2)2Prlmn/J)(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">21</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R65">65</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R66">66</xref>). K18-hACE2 mice were obtained from The Jackson Laboratory and were breed in the Centro de Criação de Animais Especiais (Ribeirão Preto Medical School/University of São Paulo). This mouse model for SARS-CoV-2-induced disease has been used as it presents clinical signs, and biochemical and histopathological changes compatible with the human disease(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R65">65</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R71">71</xref>). Mice had access to water and food <italic>ad libitum</italic>. For the experimental infection, animals were transferred to the BSL3 facility.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S13">
<title>SARS-CoV-2 experimental infection and treatments</title>
<p id="P18">Female K18-hACE2 mice, 8-week-old, were infected with 2x10<sup>4</sup> PFU of SARS-CoV-2 (in 40 μL) by intranasal route. Uninfected mice (N = 5) were inoculated with equal volume of PBS (Phosphate buffered saline - 137 mM NaCl, 2.7 mM KCl, 10 mM Na<sub>2</sub>HPO<sub>4</sub>, 1.8 mM KH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub>; pH 7.4). On the day of infection, 1 h before virus inoculation, animals were treated with Pyronaridine (75 mg/kg, i.p.) (n = 6). Five infected animals remained untreated. Body weight was evaluated on the baseline and on all the days post-infection. On the day 3 post-infection animals were humanely euthanized, and lungs were collected. Right lung was collected, harvested, and homogenized in PBS with steel glass beads. The homogenate was added to TRIzol® (Invitrogen, CA, EUA) reagent (1:1), for posterior viral titration via RT-qPCR, or to lysis buffer (1:1), for ELISA assay, and stored at -70 °C. The left lung was collected in paraformaldehyde (PFA 4%) for posterior histological assessment.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S14">
<title>Absolute viral copies quantification</title>
<p id="P19">Total RNA from the right lungs were obtained using the Trizol® (Invitrogen, CA, EUA) method and quantified using NanoDrop One/Onec (ThermoFisher Scientific, USA). A total of 800 ng of RNA was used to synthesize cDNAusing the High-Capacity cDNA Reverse Transcription kit (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA, USA), following the manufacturer’s protocol. The determination of the absolute number of viral copies was made by a Taqman real-time qPCR assay with the ad of the StepOne<sup>™</sup> Real-Time PCR System (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA, USA). A standard curve was generated in order to obtain the exact number of copies in the tested sample, using an amplicon containing 944 bp cloned from a plasmid (PTZ57R/T CloneJet<sup>™</sup> Cloning Kit Thermo Fisher®), starting in the nucleotide 14 of the gene N. To quantify the number of copies, a serial dilution of the plasmid in the proportion of 1:10 was performed. Commercial primers and probes for the N1 gene and RNAse P (endogenous control) were used for the quantification (2019-nCov CDC EUA Kit, IDT), following the CDC’s instructions.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S15">
<title>ELISA assay</title>
<p id="P20">Lung homogenate was added to RIPA buffer (Radioimmunoprecipitation assay buffer – 150 mM NaCl, 1% NP-40 or Triton X-100, 0.5% sodium deoxycholate, 0.1% SDS, 50 mM Tris; pH 8.0) in proportion of 1:1, and then centrifuged at 10,000 x <italic>g</italic> at 4 °C for 10 min. Supernatant was collected and stored in -70 °C until use. The Sandwich ELISA method was performed to detect the concentration of cytokines and chemokines using kits from R&amp;D Systems (DuoSet), according to the manufacturer’s protocols. The following targets were evaluated: IL-6, IL-10, TNF-α, INF-1β, CCL2, CCL3, CCL4, CXCL1, CXCL2, and CXCL10.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S16">
<title>Lung histopathological process and analyses</title>
<p id="P21">Five micrometer lung slices were submitted to Hematoxylin and Eosin staining. A total of 10 photomicrographs in 40X magnification per animal were randomly obtained using a microscope Novel (Novel L3000 LED, China) coupled to a HDI camera for images capture. The total septal area and total area were analyzed with the aid of the Pro Plus 7 software (Media Cybernetics, Inc., MD, USA). Morphometric analysis was performed in accordance with the protocol established by the American Thoracic Society and European Thoracic Society (ATS/ERS) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R72">72</xref>).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S17">
<title>Synthesis of pyronaridine analogs</title>
<p id="P22">All reagents and solvents were purchased from commercial suppliers and used without further purification. <sup>1</sup>H and <sup>13</sup>C Spectra were measured on Bruker AC-300 (300 MHz, <sup>1</sup>H) or Bruker AC-200 (50 MHz, <sup>13</sup>C). Chemical shifts were measured in DMSO-d<sub>6</sub>or CDCl<sub>3</sub>, using tetramethylsilane as an internal standard, and reported as units (ppm) values. The following abbreviations are used to indicate the multiplicity: s, singlet; d, doublet; t, triplet; m, multiplet; dd, doublet of doublets; brs, broad singlet; brm, broad multiplet.</p>
<p id="P23">The purity of the final compounds was analyzed on Agilent 1290 Infinity II HPLC system coupled to Agilent 6460 triple-quadrupole mass spectrometer equipped with an electrospray ionization source. The chromatographic separation was carried out on Agilent Eclipse Plus C18 RRHD column (2.1 × 50 mm, 1.8 μm) at 40 °C, sample injection volume was 0.2 μL.The mobile phase comprising 0.1 % formic acid / water (A), and 0.1 %formic acid and 85 % acetonitrile / water (B) was programmed with gradient elution (0.0-3.0 min, 60 % B; 3.0-4.0 min, 60 % to 97 % B; 4.0-6.0 min, 97 % B; 6.0-6.1 min, 97 % to 60 % B) at a flow rate of 0.4 mL/min. The mass spectrometric detection was operated in positive ion mode. Optimal parameters were: capillary voltages of 3500 V, a nebulizer pressure of 35 psi, a gas temperature of 350 °C, a gas flow rate of 12 L/min. All final compounds are &gt; 95 % pure. Melting points were determined on Electrothermal 9001 (10 °C per min) and are uncorrected. Merck KGaAsilica gel 60 F<sub>254</sub> plates were used for analytical thin-layer chromatography. Column chromatography was performed on Merck silica gel 60 (70-230 mesh). Yields refer to purified products and are not optimized. The molecules were synthesized according to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Scheme 1</xref> or <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Scheme 2</xref> and the specific methods and analytical results are described in the <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplemental Methods</xref>.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S18">
<title>Molecular docking</title>
<p id="P24">Molecular docking was performed using Glide software (Schrödinger, 2017, USA) and the SARS-CoV-2 PL<sup>pro</sup> X-ray structure was downloaded from the Protein Data Bank (PDBid 7JRN). Prior to docking, ligand and protein were prepared with LigPrep (Schrödinger, 2017, USA) and Protein Preparation Wizard (Schrödinger, 2017, USA) using default parameters. Different grids were generated with Receptor Grid Generation at possible sites founded in SiteMap (Schrödinger, 2017, USA). Pyronaridine and studied analogs were docked at all sites using Glide in extra precision mode (XP mode) with default parameters (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R73">73</xref>). The site with the highest <italic>gscore</italic> was considered the binding site for each compound. A similar protocol was also performed using Haddock v2.4 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R74">74</xref>). Electrostatic potential was calculated with APBS. Figures were generated with ChimeraX.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="S19">
<title>Molecule synthesis</title>
<sec id="S20">
<title>4-[(6-chloro-2-methoxyacridin-9-yl)amino]phenol 2. (12126037)</title>
<p id="P25">Solid 2-aminophenol (0.39 g, 3.6 mmol) was added to a suspension of starting 6,9-dichloro-2-methoxyacridine 1 (0.5 g, 1.8 mmol) in 10 ml of dimethylformamide. The reaction mass was stirred at reflux for 1 hour. Cooled, the precipitate was filtered off, wash with DMF, EtOH and diethyl ether. The yield 72%. Mp 290 oC with decomposition, (DMF). Mass (EI), m / z (Irelat. (%)): 350.7981 [M]<sup>+</sup> (92). C<sub>20</sub>H<sub>15</sub>ClN<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>. <sup>1</sup>H NMR (DMSO-d<sub>6</sub>; δ, ppm): 9.98 (1H, s, NH), 8.16 (3H, m, 3CH), 7.73 (2H, m, 2CH), 7.47 (1H, d, <italic>J</italic> = 4.5, CH), 7.23 (2H, d, <italic>J</italic> = 6.5, 2CH), 6.92 (2H, d, <italic>J</italic> = 6.5, 2CH), 3.81 (3H, s, OCH<sub>3</sub>). <sup>13</sup>C NMR (DMSO-d<sub>6</sub>; δ, ppm): 156.0, 152.9, 147.8, 147.6, 145.1, 144.7, 133.7, 131.3, 131.1, 128.1, 122.8, 121.8, 121.5, 121.4, 120.9, 120.3, 120.1, 117.9, 101.0, 55.7.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S21">
<title>4-[(6-chloro-2-methoxyacridin-9-yl)amino]-2,6-bis[(dimethylamino)methyl]phenol 3. (12126038)</title>
<p id="P26">A mixture of 40% aqueous solution of dimethylamine (1.1 ml, 9.0 mmol), 1 ml of acetic acid and 37% aqueous solution of formaldehyde (0.39 ml, 5.4 mmol) were added at once to a suspension of 4-[(6-chloro-2-methoxyacridin-9-yl)amino]phenol 2 (0.9 mmol) in 10 ml of dimethylformamide. The suspension was heated to boiling and boiled for 4 hours. The reaction mixture was cooled, an aqueous solution of NaHCO<sub>3</sub> (17 mmol) is added, transferred to a separatory funnel and extracted with ethyl acetate (30 ml x 2). Combined organic layer was washed with water 2 x 100 ml and dried over sodium sulfate. The solvent was removed in vacuo and residue oil was treated by mixture of 20 ml of hexane and 1 ml of diethyl ether. The oil was ground and kept for 10 hours at 40 °C. The solid was filtered off, washed with hexane and purified by column chromatography (methanol). The yield of aim product was 25%. Mp 148-152 °C. Mass (EI), <italic>m/z</italic> (<italic>I<sub>relat</sub>.</italic>(%)): 464.9869 [M]<sup>+</sup> (88). C<sub>26</sub>H<sub>29</sub>ClN<sub>4</sub>O<sub>2</sub>. <sup>1</sup>H NMR (DMSO-d<sub>6</sub>; δ, ppm): 9.98 (1H, s, NH), 8.17 (3H, m, 3CH), 7.84 (2H, m, 2CH), 7.45 (1H, d, <italic>J</italic> = 4.5, CH), 7.06 (2H, s, 2CH), 3.81 (3H, s, OCH<sub>3</sub>), 3.61 (2H, s, 2CH<sub>2</sub>), 2.78 (12H, br s, 2N(CH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>. <sup>13</sup>C NMR (DMSO-d<sub>6</sub>; δ, ppm): 157.2, 156.0, 154.5, 147.8, 145.1, 144.6, 133.7, 131.3, 131.1, 128.0, 128.1, 125.5, 122.8, 121.4, 118.6, 114.9, 112.2, 101.0, 55.8, 55.7, 44.9.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S22">
<title>4-[(6-chloro-2-methoxyacridin-9-yl)amino]-2-(pyrrolidin-1-ylmethyl)phenol 4 and 4-[(6-chloro-2-methoxyacridin-9-yl)amino]-2,6-bis(pyrrolidin-1-ylmethyl)phenol 5</title>
<p id="P27">A mixture of pyrrolidine (0.52 ml, 6.0 mmol), 0.7 ml of acetic acid, and 37% aqueous formaldehyde solution (0.28 ml, 3.6 mmol) were added to a suspension of 4-[(6-chloro-2-methoxyacridin-9-yl)amino]phenol 2 (0.6 mmol) in 10 ml of dimethylformamide. The solution was stirred at reflux for 1 hour. The reaction mixture was cooled, an aqueous solution of NaHCO<sub>3</sub> (11 mmol) was added and extracted with ethyl acetate (2 x 30 ml). The combined organic layer was washed with water (2 x 100 ml), dried by sodium sulfate and solvent was evaporated in vacuo. The resulting oil was dissolved in chloroform and applied to a chromatography column (chloroform/methanol 9:1) and product 4 was isolated. Pure methanol was used as eluent for separation product 5.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S23">
<title>4-[(6-chloro-2-methoxyacridin-9-yl)amino]-2-(pyrrolidin-1-ylmethyl)phenol 4. (12126040)</title>
<p id="P28">The yield is 5%. Mp 178-182 °C. Mass (EI), <italic>m/z</italic> (<italic>I<sub>relat</sub>.</italic>(%)): 433.9298 [M]<sup>+</sup> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R76">76</xref>). C<sub>25</sub>H<sub>24</sub>ClN<sub>3</sub>O<sub>2</sub>. <sup>1</sup>H NMR (DMSO-d<sub>6</sub>; δ, ppm): 10.21 (1H, s, NH), 8.17 (3H, m, 3CH), 7.81 (2H, m, 2CH), 7.45 (1H, d, <italic>J</italic> = 4.5, CH), 7.06 (2H, s, 2CH), 3.83 (3H, s, OCH<sub>3</sub>), 3.60 (2H, s, 2CH<sub>2</sub>), 2.5-2.7 (8H, br m, 2N(CH<sub>2</sub>)<sub>2</sub>), 1.6-1.8 (8H, br m, 2(CH<sub>2</sub>)<sub>2</sub>). <sup>13</sup>C NMR (DMSO-d<sub>6</sub>; δ, ppm): 157.7, 156.2, 154.5, 147.8, 145.1, 144.3, 133.7, 131.3, 131.1, 125.5, 122.8, 121.4, 118.7, 114.9, 111.5, 101.1, 55.7, 54.1, 52.3, 23.4.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S24">
<title>4-[(6-chloro-2-methoxyacridin-9-yl)amino]-2,6-bis(pyrrolidin-1-ylmethyl)phenol 5. (12126039)</title>
<p id="P29">The yield is 10%. Mp 145-150 °C. Mass (EI), <italic>m/z</italic> (<italic>I<sub>relat</sub>.</italic>(%)): 517.0615 [M]<sup>+</sup> (79). C<sub>30</sub>H<sub>33</sub>ClN<sub>4</sub>O<sub>2</sub>. <sup>1</sup>H NMR (DMSO-d<sub>6</sub>; δ, ppm): 10.04 (1H, s, NH), 8.16 (3H, m, 3CH), 7.79 (2H, m, 2CH), 7.47 (1H, d, <italic>J</italic> = 4.5, CH), 7.06 (1H, d, <italic>J</italic> = 4.5, CH), 6.93 (1H, s, CH), 3.83 (3H, s, OCH<sub>3</sub>), 3.60 (2H, s, 2CH<sub>2</sub>), 2.5-2.7 (8H, br m, 2N(CH<sub>2</sub>)<sub>2</sub>), 1.6-1.8 (8H, br m, 2(CH<sub>2</sub>)<sub>2</sub>). <sup>13</sup>C NMR (DMSO-d<sub>6</sub>; δ, ppm): 156.0, 152.4, 149.3, 147.7, 145.1, 139.2, 131.2, 131.1, 128.7, 124.1, 122.8, 121.2, 120.8, 116.4, 116.1, 112.4, 101.6, 55.8, 51.9, 23.42.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S25">
<title>6-chloro-2-methoxyacridin-9-ol 6. (12126072)</title>
<p id="P30">The mixture of pyrrolidine (1.0 ml, 13.0 mmol), 1.4 ml of acetic acid and 37% aqueous formaldehyde solution (0.56 ml, 7.8 mmol) were added to a suspension of 4-[(6-chloro-2-methoxyacridin-9-yl)amino]phenol 2 (1.3 mmol) in 10 ml of ethanol. The suspension was boiled for 36 hours. The reaction mixture was cooled, an aqueous solution of NaHCO<sub>3</sub> (2.6 mmol) was added and the precipitate of aim compound was filtered off. The yield is 38%. Mp 300 °C (DMF). Mass (EI), <italic>m/z</italic> (<italic>I<sub>relat</sub>.</italic>(%)): 259.0615 [M]<sup>+</sup> (79). C<sub>14</sub>H<sub>10</sub>ClNO<sub>2</sub>. <sup>1</sup>H NMR (DMSO-d<sub>6</sub>; δ, ppm): 8.56 (1H, d, <italic>J</italic> = 9.0, CH), 7.72 (H, s, CH), 7.62 (1H, d, <italic>J</italic> = 4.5, CH), 7.44 (1H, d, <italic>J</italic> = 4.5, CH), 7.27 (1H, s, CH), 7.07 (1H, d, <italic>J</italic> = 9.0, CH), 3.86 (3H, s, OCH<sub>3</sub>). <sup>13</sup>C NMR (DMSO-d<sub>6</sub>; δ, ppm): 157.8, 148.2, 147.9, 140.6, 138.0, 136.7, 128.7, 126.9, 125.5, 124.6, 123.3, 102.9, 55.3.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S26">
<title>6-chloro-2-methoxy-9-morpholin-4-ylacridine 7. (12126036)</title>
<p id="P31">Morpholine (0.23 ml, 2.7 mmol) was added to a suspension of starting 6,9-dichloro-2-methoxyacridine 1 (0.25 g, 0.9 mmol) in 7 ml of dimethylformamide. The reaction mixture was stirred at reflux for 30 min, cooled, formed precipitate was filtered off and washed with dimethylformamide, acetone. The yield is 70%. Mp 208-212 °C (DMF). Mass (EI), <italic>m/z</italic> (<italic>I<sub>relat</sub>.</italic>(%)): 328.7926 [M]<sup>+</sup> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R74">74</xref>). C<sub>18</sub>H<sub>17</sub>ClN<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>. <sup>1</sup>H NMR (DMSO-d<sub>6</sub>; δ, ppm): 8.56 (1H, d, <italic>J</italic> = 9.0, CH), 7.72 (H, s, CH), 7.62 (1H, d, <italic>J</italic> = 4.5, CH), 7.44 (1H, d, <italic>J</italic> = 4.5, CH), 7.27 (1H, s, CH), 7.07 (1H, d, <italic>J</italic> = 9.0, CH), 3.86 (3H, s, OCH<sub>3</sub>). <sup>13</sup>C NMR (DMSO-d<sub>6</sub>; δ, ppm): 155.7, 149.8, 142.6, 134.5, 131.7, 130.9, 130.6, 127.6, 122.4, 119.7, 119.1, 114.8, 100.5, 66.8, 55.7, 50.8.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S27">
<title>(2E)-2-cyano-3-(dimethylamino)but-2-enamide 2</title>
<p id="P32">Dimethyl acetal dimethylacetamide (1 ml, 7.2 mmol) was added to a suspension of cyanoacetamide 1 (0.5 g, 6 mmol) in 15 ml of absolute alcohol. The suspension was boiled for 3 hours, cooled, obtained precipitate was filtered off, washed with alcohol and diethyl ether. Aim product 2 was obtained with a yield of 82%. Mp 188-192 °C (isopropanol).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S28">
<title>(2E)-3-anilino-2-cyanobut-2-enamide 3</title>
<p id="P33">Aniline (0.45 ml, 5 mmol) was added to a suspension of (2E)-2-cyano-3-(dimethylamino)but-2-enamide 2 (0.3 g, 2 mmol) in acetic acid (4 ml). The suspension was boiled for 3 hours, cooled, acetic acid was removed under vacuum/ The residue was treated by water, formed precipitate was filtered off and washed with water, isopropyl alcohol and diethyl ether. Aim product 3 was obtained with a yield of 87%. Mp 179-182 °C (isopropanol).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S29">
<title>A mixture of 6-[(E)-2-(dimethylamino)vinyl]-4-oxo-1-phenyl-1,4-dihydropyrimidine-5-carbonitrile 4 and (2Z,4E)-3-anilino-2-cyano-5-(dimethylamino)-N-[(1E)-(dimethylamino)methylene]penta-2,4-dienamide 5</title>
<p id="P34">Dimethylformamide diethyl acetal (1.3 ml, 7.5 mmol) was added to a suspension of (2E)-3-anilino-2-cyanobut-2-enamide 3 (0.6 g, 3 mmol) in 5 ml of absolute ethanol. The dark red solution was boiled for 6 hours. Part of the solvent was removed under vacuum until a thick suspension was obtained. The precipitate was filtered off, washed with absolute alcohol and dry diethyl ether. A mixture of compounds 4 and 5 was obtained.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S30">
<title>4-anilino-5-formyl-2-oxo-1,2-dihydropyridine-3-carbonitrile 6</title>
<p id="P35">A mixture of 6-[(E)-2-(dimethylamino)vinyl]-4-oxo-1-phenyl-1,4-dihydropyrimidine-5-carbonitrile 4 and (2Z,4E)-3-anilino-2-cyano-5-(dimethylamino)-N-[(1E)-(dimethylamino)methylene]penta-2,4-dienamide 5 (5.6 g) is dissolved in 56 ml of 90% acetic acid. A precipitate form after 30 min and reaction mixture was stirred at room temperature for 20 h. The precipitate was filtered off, washed with water, ethyl alcohol and acetone. The yield is 2.3 g of aim product 6. Mp 225-230 oC (with decomposition).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S31">
<title>3-chloro-2,3-dihydrobenzo[b]-1,6-naphthyridine-4-carbonitrile 7</title>
<p id="P36">The 4-anilino-5-formyl-2-oxo-1,2-dihydropyridine-3-carbonitrile 6 (2.3 g) was refluxed in phosphorus oxychloride (22 ml) for 1 hour. The reaction mixture was poured onto ice, stirred for 30 min. Formed precipitate was filtered off, washed with water, ethyl alcohol, diethyl ether. Aim product 7 was obtained in 80% yield. Mp 300-304 °C (DMF).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S32">
<title>3-chloro-10-oxo-5,10-dihydrobenzo[b]-1,6-naphthyridine-4-carbonitrile 8</title>
<p id="P37">To a suspension of 3-chloro-2,3-dihydrobenzo[b]-1,6-naphthyridine-4-carbonitrile 7 (0.44 g) in 15 ml of acetone was added m-chloroperbenzoic acid 55% (1.45 g) in small portions and refluxed for 9 hours. The reaction mixture was cooled, obtained precipitate was filtered off and washed with acetone, toluene, acetone. The aim product 8 was obtained with a yield 50%. Mp 305 °C.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S33">
<title>3-morpholin-4-ylbenzo[b]-1,6-naphthyridine-4-carbonitrile 9. (12126035)</title>
<p id="P38">Morpholine (0.16 ml, 1.8 mmol) was added to a suspension of 3-chloro-2,3-dihydrobenzo[b]-1,6-naphthyridine-4-carbonitrile 7 (0.15 g, 0.6 mmol) in 4 ml of dry dimethylformamide. The solution was boiled for 1 hour. Cooled, poured into 40 ml of water, extracted 2 times with 30 ml of ethyl acetate. The organic fractions were additionally washed with water 2 times. Ethyl acetate was removed under vacuum, ethyl alcohol was added to the dry residue, and the precipitate was filtered off. Washed with diethyl ether. The aim product 9 was obtained with a yield of 78%.Mp 222-225 °C (EtOH:DMF 2:1). Mass (EI), <italic>m/z</italic> (<italic>I<sub>relat</sub>.</italic>(%)): 290.3194 [M]<sup>+</sup> (79). C<sub>17</sub>H<sub>14</sub>N<sub>4</sub>O. <sup>1</sup>H NMR (DMSO-d<sub>6</sub>; δ, ppm): 9.46 (1H, s, CH), 9.13 (1H, s, CH), 8.16 (1H, d, <italic>J</italic> = 6.5, CH), 7.91 (1H, s, CH), 7.44 (1H, d, <italic>J</italic> = 6.5, CH), 4.16 (4H, m, O(CH<sub>2</sub>)<sub>2</sub>), 3.78 (4H, m, N(CH<sub>2</sub>)<sub>2</sub>). <sup>13</sup>C NMR (DMSO-d<sub>6</sub>; δ, ppm): 144.9, 143.5, 137.8, 136.4, 136.0, 133.1, 129.5, 128.4, 126.8, 126.1, 114.5, 101.4, 66.7, 53.8.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S34">
<title>3-morpholin-4-yl-10-oxo-5,10-dihydrobenzo[b]-1,6-naphthyridine-4-carbonitrile 10. (10326099)</title>
<p id="P39">Morpholine (0.14 ml, 1.6 mmol) was added to a solution of 3-chloro-10-oxo-5,10-dihydrobenzo[b]-1,6-naphthyridine-4-carbonitrile 8 (0.2 g, 0.8 mmol) in 5 ml of dry dimethylformamide. Formed suspension was stirred at reflux for 1 hour, cooled, the precipitate was filtered off, washed with dimethylformamide and acetone. Mp 290 °C (из DMF). The yield is 38%. Mass (EI), <italic>m/z</italic> (<italic>I<sub>relat</sub>.</italic>(%)): 306.3188 [M]<sup>+</sup> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R68">68</xref>). C<sub>17</sub>H<sub>14</sub>N<sub>4</sub>O<sub>2</sub>. <sup>1</sup>H NMR (DMSO-d<sub>6</sub>; δ, ppm): 8.02 (1H, s, CH), 7.91 (1H, d, <italic>J</italic> = 6.5, CH), 7.59 (1H, s, CH), 7.09 (1H, d, <italic>J</italic> = 6.5, CH), 4.08 (4H, m, O(CH<sub>2</sub>)<sub>2</sub>), 3.72 (4H, m, N(CH<sub>2</sub>)<sub>2</sub>). <sup>13</sup>C NMR (DMSO-d<sub>6</sub>; δ, ppm): 182.5, 146.4, 146.1, 139.7, 139.1, 138.7, 137.0, 124.9, 122.7, 118.3, 115.4, 108.8, 94.9, 66.8, 53.7.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="S35">
<title>PL<sup>pro</sup> cloning, expression, purification and assays</title>
<p id="P40">The viral cDNA template (GenBank MT126808.1) was kindly provided by Dr. Edison Durigon. Amplification of the nucleotide sequence coding for the PL<sup>pro</sup> domain (residues 1564-1879 of SARSCoV-2) was performed by Polymerase Chain Reaction (PCR) using forward (5'- ATTCCATGGGCGAAGTGAGGACTATTAAGGTGTTTAC -3') and reverse (5'- ATTGCTCGAGTGGTTTTATGGTTGTTGTGTAACT -3') primers, with restriction sites for <italic>NcoI</italic> and <italic>XhoI</italic>. PCR product was digested with <italic>NcoI</italic> and <italic>XhoI</italic> and cloned into pET28a (Novagen) in frame with a C-terminal his-tag coding sequence <italic>E. coli</italic> BL21 transformed with plasmids were grown in LB to an optical density (OD<sub>600</sub>) of 0.6 at 37 °C and 200 RPM. Protein expression was induced adding 0.5 mM IPTG and 1 mM Zinc Chloride and grown overnight at 18°. The cell pellet was resuspended in lysis buffer (50 mM Tris, 150 mM NaCl, 10 mM imidazole, 1 mM DTT, pH 8.5), disrupted by sonication and centrifuged at 12,500 rpm for 40 min at 4° C. Protein was isolated from the lysate using 5 mL Ni-NTA resin (Qiagen) pre-equilibrated with lysis buffer and then washed with 15 column volumes (CV) with the same buffer. The his-tagged protein was eluted 4 CV of elution buffer (lysis buffer supplemented with 250 mM imidazole) and further purified by size exclusion chromatography in a Superdex 200 10/30 (GE Healthcare) equilibrated with 20 mM Tris pH 7.4, 100 mM NaCl, 2 mM DTT.</p>
<p id="P41">PL<sup>pro</sup> inhibition assay was performed using the FRET-based fluorescent peptide substrate Abz-TLKGG↓APIKEDDPS-EDDnp, kindly provided by Dr. Maria Aparecida Juliano (Federal University of São Paulo, Brazil). The assay was standardized with enzyme concentration of 70 nM and 27 μM of fluorescent substrate in PL<sup>pro</sup> assay buffer (50 mM HEPES pH 7.5, 0.01 % Triton X-100 and 5 mM DTT), at 37°C for 30 min. Activity was measured in the plate reader system Spectramax Gemini EM (Molecular devices), with λ<sub>ex</sub>= 320 nm and λ<sub>em</sub>= 420 nm, in presence of different inhibitors and 1% DMSO.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S36">
<title>M<sup>pro</sup> cloning, expression, purification and assays</title>
<p id="P42">The M<sup>pro</sup> cloning is described elsewhere (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R75">75</xref>). For expression, BL21 cells transformed with plasmid were grown in ZYM-5052 to an OD<sub>600</sub> of 0.6-0.8 at 37°C and 200 RPM. Protein expression was induced lowering the temperature to 18 °C, cells were then grown for 16h and harvested by centrifugation. The cell pellet was resuspended in lysis buffer (20 mM Tris pH 7.8, 150 mM NaCl, 1 mM DTT), disrupted by sonication and centrifuged at 12,000 x g for 40 min at 4 °C. Uncleaved protein with 6xHisTag were isolated from the lysate using Ni-NTA resin (Qiagen). The flow-through (FT) was then used to purify cleaved protein with ammonium sulfate precipitation. Ammonium sulfate was added into the FT to a final concentration of 1M, incubated on ice for 10 min and centrifuged at 12,000 x g for 30 min at 4 °C. The precipitated protein was resuspended in gel filtration buffer (20 mM Tris pH 7.8, 150 mM NaCl, 1 mM EDTA, 1 mM DTT) and purified by size-exclusion chromatography in a HiLoad 26/100 Superdex 200 column (GE Healthcare) pre-equilibrated with gel filtration buffer. Afterwards, the protein was buffer exchanged to 20 mM Tris pH 8.0, 1.0 mM DTT and loaded into a Mono-Q 5/50 GL column (GE Healthcare) in the same buffer, and eluted with a linear gradient of a buffer containing 20 mM Tris pH 8.0, 1.0 M NaCl and 1.0 mM DTT. Proteins were concentrated at 1.0 mg/mL, flash-frozen and stored at -80°C for inhibition assays.</p>
<p id="P43">M<sup>pro</sup> inhibition assay was performed using the FRET-based fluorescent peptide substrate DABCYL-KTSAVLQ↓SGFRKM-E(EDANS)-NH2 (purchased from Genscript). The assay was standardized with enzyme concentration of 140 nM and 30 μM of fluorescent substrate in M<sup>pro</sup> assay buffer containing (20 mM Tris pH 7.3, 1 mM EDTA, 1 mM DTT), at 37°C for 30 min. Activity was detected in the spectrofluorometer system Spectramax Gemini EM (Molecular devices), with λ<sub>ex</sub>= 360 nm and λ<sub>em</sub> 460 nm, in presence of different inhibitors and 1% DMSO.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S37">
<title>Kinase profiling of pyronaridine</title>
<p id="P44">Kinase profiling was performed for pyronaridine (1 μM) in duplicate by ThermoFisher (Life Technologies Corporation, Chicago, IL 60693) using Z’Lyte (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R76">76</xref>), Adapta (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R77">77</xref>) and LanthaScreen (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R78">78</xref>) assays for 485 purified kinases.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="S38">
<title>CAMK1 inhibition</title>
<p id="P45">Pyronaridine inhibition of CAMK1 was performed by Selected Services (Thermo Fisher) using the the Adapta universal kinase assay, which is a homogenous, fluorescent-based immunoassay for the detection of ADP. The 2X CAMK1 (CaMK1) and ZIPtide mixture was prepared in 50 mM HEPES pH 7.5, 0.01% BRIJ-35, 10 mM MgCl2, 1 mM EGTA, 4 mM CaCl2, 800 U/ml Calmodulin, 0.02% NaN3. The final 10 μL Kinase Reaction consists of 0.25 - 1.2 ng CAMK1 (CaMK1) and 200 μM ZIPtide in 32.5 mM HEPES pH 7.5, 0.005% BRIJ-35, 5 mM MgCl2, 500 μM EGTA, 2 mM CaCl2, 400 U/ml Calmodulin, 0.01% NaN3. After the 1 h kinase reaction incubation, 5 μL of Detection Mix is added.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="SM">
<title>Supplementary Material</title>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1">
<label>Supplemental Material</label>
<media xlink:href="EMS136057-supplement-Supplemental_Material.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" id="N67529" position="anchor"/>
</supplementary-material>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack id="S39">
<title>Acknowledgments</title>
<p>The authors would like to kindly acknowledge their many collaborators around the world who have assisted in our various COVID-19 projects. The authors gratefully acknowledge the technical assistance of Marcella Daruge Grando, Ieda Regina dos Santos, Juliana Trench Abumansur, and Felipe Souza.</p>
<sec id="S40">
<title>Grant information</title>
<p>We kindly acknowledge NIH funding: SE kindly acknowledges NIH funding R44GM122196-02A1 from NIH NIGMS 1R43AT010585-01 from NIH/NCCAM, AI142759 and AI108197 to RSB. Dr. Glaucius Oliva and colleagues acknowledge Coordenação de Aperfeiçoamento de Pessoal de Nível Superior (CAPES – project 88887.516153/2020-00) and Fundação de Amparo à Pesquisa do Estado de São Paulo (FAPESP project 2013/07600-3). TMC, JCAF and FQC received funding from the São Paulo Research Foundation (FAPESP) under grant agreement 2013/08216-2 (Center for Research in Inflammatory Disease) and 2020/04860-8 and from Coordenação de Aperfeiçoamento de Pessoal de Nível Superior (project 88887.507155/2020-00). NM, OR and VM acknowledge RFBR (project 20-54-80006).</p>
</sec>
</ack>
<glossary>
<title>Abbreviations Used</title>
<def-list>
<def-item>
<term>ACE2</term>
<def>
<p>Angiotensin converting enzyme 2</p>
</def>
</def-item>
<def-item>
<term>BMP</term>
<def>
<p>Bis(monoacylglycero)phosphate</p>
</def>
</def-item>
<def-item>
<term>COVID-19</term>
<def>
<p>Coronavirus disease</p>
</def>
</def-item>
<def-item>
<term>MERS-CoV</term>
<def>
<p>Middle East Respiratory Syndrome coronavirus</p>
</def>
</def-item>
<def-item>
<term>SARS-CoV-2</term>
<def>
<p>Severe Acute Respiratory coronavirus 2</p>
</def>
</def-item>
</def-list>
</glossary>
<fn-group>
<fn id="FN2" fn-type="conflict">
<p id="P46">
<bold>Competing interests:</bold>
</p>
<p id="P47">SE is CEO of Collaborations Pharmaceuticals, Inc. ACP is an employee at Collaborations Pharmaceuticals, Inc. Collaborations Pharmaceuticals, Inc. has obtained FDA orphan drug designations for pyronaridine, tilorone and quinacrine for use against Ebola. CPI have also filed a provisional patent for use of these molecules against Marburg and other viruses. Other authors have no conflicts.</p>
<p id="P48">SE is CEO of Collaborations Pharmaceuticals, Inc. ACP and TRL are employees at Collaborations Pharmaceuticals, Inc.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="FN3" fn-type="con">
<p id="P49">
<bold>Author contributions:</bold>
</p>
<p id="P50">A.C.P, T.M.C, S.E. conceived and codirected the study. A.C.P., G.F.G, A.S.G., V.M., G.O., F.Q.C., J.C.A.F, T.C designed the experiments; A.C.P, S.D., G.D.N., A.M.N, V.O.G, R.S.F, N.M., O.R, S.S.B and A.T.F performed <italic>in vitro</italic> experiments. G.F.G, S.D. F.P.V, performed <italic>in vivo</italic> experiments. A.C.P, S.E., G.F.G, A.S.G. and T.M.C, and T.L. wrote the manuscript. All authors read and accept the manuscript.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<ref id="R1">
<label>1</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>Author Correction: A new coronavirus associated with human respiratory disease in China</article-title>
<source>Nature</source>
<year>2020</year>
<volume>580</volume>
<fpage>E7</fpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R2">
<label>2</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<collab>V. Coronaviridae Study Group of the International Committee on Taxonomy of</collab>
<article-title>The species Severe acute respiratory syndrome-related coronavirus: classifying 2019-nCoV and naming it SARS-CoV-2</article-title>
<source>Nat Microbiol</source>
<year>2020</year>
<volume>5</volume>
<fpage>536</fpage>
<lpage>544</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R3">
<label>3</label>
<element-citation publication-type="web">
<collab>WHO</collab>
<source>Naming the coronavirus disease (COVID-2019) and the virus that causes it</source>
<year>2020</year>
<comment>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/technical-guidance/naming-the-coronavirus-disease-(covid-2019)-and-the-virus-that-causes-it">https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/technical-guidance/naming-the-coronavirus-disease-(covid-2019)-and-the-virus-that-causes-it</ext-link>
</comment>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R4">
<label>4</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Rehman</surname>
<given-names>MFU</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>Novel coronavirus disease (COVID-19) pandemic: A recent mini review</article-title>
<source>Comput Struct Biotechnol J</source>
<year>2021</year>
<volume>19</volume>
<fpage>612</fpage>
<lpage>623</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R5">
<label>5</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kyriakidis</surname>
<given-names>NC</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>López-Cortés</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>González</surname>
<given-names>EV</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Grimaldos</surname>
<given-names>AB</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Prado</surname>
<given-names>EO</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>SARS-CoV-2 vaccines strategies: a comprehensive review of phase 3 candidates</article-title>
<source>NPJ Vaccines</source>
<year>2021</year>
<volume>6</volume>
<elocation-id>28</elocation-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R6">
<label>6</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Huang</surname>
<given-names>HY</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>Landscape and progress of global COVID-19 vaccine development</article-title>
<source>Hum Vaccin Immunother</source>
<year>2021</year>
<fpage>1</fpage>
<lpage>5</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R7">
<label>7</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hall</surname>
<given-names>MD</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>Report of the National Institutes of Health SARS-CoV-2 Antiviral Therapeutics Summit</article-title>
<source>J Infect Dis</source>
<year>2021</year>
<volume>224</volume>
<fpage>S1</fpage>
<lpage>S21</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R8">
<label>8</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Eastman</surname>
<given-names>RT</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>Remdesivir: A Review of Its Discovery and Development Leading to Emergency Use Authorization for Treatment of COVID-19</article-title>
<source>ACS Cent Sci</source>
<year>2020</year>
<volume>6</volume>
<fpage>672</fpage>
<lpage>683</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R9">
<label>9</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>Remdesivir and chloroquine effectively inhibit the recently emerged novel coronavirus (2019-nCoV) in vitro</article-title>
<source>Cell Res</source>
<year>2020</year>
<volume>30</volume>
<fpage>269</fpage>
<lpage>271</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R10">
<label>10</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Pruijssers</surname>
<given-names>AJ</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>Remdesivir Inhibits SARS-CoV-2 in Human Lung Cells and Chimeric SARS-CoV Expressing the SARS-CoV-2 RNA Polymerase in Mice</article-title>
<source>Cell Rep</source>
<year>2020</year>
<volume>32</volume>
<elocation-id>107940</elocation-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R11">
<label>11</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Mulangu</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>A Randomized, Controlled Trial of Ebola Virus Disease Therapeutics</article-title>
<source>N Engl J Med</source>
<year>2019</year>
<volume>381</volume>
<fpage>2293</fpage>
<lpage>2303</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R12">
<label>12</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ekins</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>Machine learning models identify molecules active against Ebola virus in vitro</article-title>
<source>F1000Res</source>
<year>2015</year>
<volume>4</volume>
<elocation-id>1091</elocation-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R13">
<label>13</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lane</surname>
<given-names>TR</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>Repurposing the antimalarial pyronaridine tetraphosphate to protect against Ebola virus infection</article-title>
<source>PLoS Negl Trop Dis</source>
<year>2019</year>
<volume>13</volume>
<elocation-id>e0007890</elocation-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R14">
<label>14</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lane</surname>
<given-names>TR</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Comer</surname>
<given-names>JE</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Freiberg</surname>
<given-names>AN</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Madrid</surname>
<given-names>PB</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ekins</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Repurposing Quinacrine Against Ebola Virus Infection In vivo</article-title>
<source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source>
<year>2019</year>
<volume>63</volume>
<elocation-id>e01142-01119</elocation-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R15">
<label>15</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ekins</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>Efficacy of Tilorone Dihydrochloride against Ebola Virus Infection</article-title>
<source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source>
<year>2018</year>
<volume>62</volume>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R16">
<label>16</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lane</surname>
<given-names>TR</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ekins</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Towards the Target: Tilorone, Quinacrine and Pyronaridine Bind to Ebola Virus Glycoprotein</article-title>
<source>ACS Med Chem Lett</source>
<year>2020</year>
<volume>11</volume>
<fpage>1653</fpage>
<lpage>1658</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R17">
<label>17</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lane</surname>
<given-names>TR</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>Efficacy of Oral Pyronaridine Tetraphosphate and Favipiravir Against Ebola Virus Infection in Guinea Pig</article-title>
<source>Antiviral Research</source>
<year>2020</year>
<volume>181</volume>
<elocation-id>104863</elocation-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R18">
<label>18</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Puhl</surname>
<given-names>AC</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>Repurposing the Ebola and Marburg Virus Inhibitors Tilorone, Quinacrine, and Pyronaridine: In Vitro Activity against SARS-CoV-2 and Potential Mechanisms</article-title>
<source>ACS Omega</source>
<year>2021</year>
<volume>6</volume>
<fpage>7454</fpage>
<lpage>7468</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R19">
<label>19</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Jeon</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>Identification of antiviral drug candidates against SARS-CoV-2 from FDA-approved drugs</article-title>
<source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source>
<year>2020</year>
<volume>64</volume>
<elocation-id>e00819-00820</elocation-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R20">
<label>20</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bae</surname>
<given-names>J-Y</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>Pyronaridine and artesunate are potential antiviral drugs against COVID-19 and influenza</article-title>
<source>bioRxiv</source>
<year>2020</year>
<elocation-id>2020.2007.2028.225102</elocation-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R21">
<label>21</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>McCray</surname>
<given-names>PB</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>Lethal infection of K18-hACE2 mice infected with severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus</article-title>
<source>J Virol</source>
<year>2007</year>
<volume>81</volume>
<fpage>813</fpage>
<lpage>821</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R22">
<label>22</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Oladunni</surname>
<given-names>FS</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>Lethality of SARS-CoV-2 infection in K18 human angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 transgenic mice</article-title>
<source>Nat Commun</source>
<year>2020</year>
<volume>11</volume>
<elocation-id>6122</elocation-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R23">
<label>23</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bao</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>The pathogenicity of SARS-CoV-2 in hACE2 transgenic mice</article-title>
<source>Nature</source>
<year>2020</year>
<volume>583</volume>
<fpage>830</fpage>
<lpage>833</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R24">
<label>24</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Jin</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>Structure of M</article-title>
<source>Nature</source>
<year>2020</year>
<volume>582</volume>
<fpage>289</fpage>
<lpage>293</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R25">
<label>25</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Shin</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>Papain-like protease regulates SARS-CoV-2 viral spread and innate immunity</article-title>
<source>Nature</source>
<year>2020</year>
<volume>587</volume>
<fpage>657</fpage>
<lpage>662</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R26">
<label>26</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Qiao</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>SARS-CoV-2 M</article-title>
<source>Science</source>
<year>2021</year>
<volume>371</volume>
<fpage>1374</fpage>
<lpage>1378</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R27">
<label>27</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Fu</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>The complex structure of GRL0617 and SARS-CoV-2 PLpro reveals a hot spot for antiviral drug discovery</article-title>
<source>Nat Commun</source>
<year>2021</year>
<volume>12</volume>
<elocation-id>488</elocation-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R28">
<label>28</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Costela-Ruiz</surname>
<given-names>VJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Illescas-Montes</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Puerta-Puerta</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ruiz</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Melguizo-Rodríguez</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>SARS-CoV-2 infection: The role of cytokines in COVID-19 disease</article-title>
<source>Cytokine Growth Factor Rev</source>
<year>2020</year>
<volume>54</volume>
<fpage>62</fpage>
<lpage>75</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R29">
<label>29</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>Cytokine Storm: The Primary Determinant for the Pathophysiological Evolution of COVID-19 Deterioration</article-title>
<source>Front Immunol</source>
<year>2021</year>
<volume>12</volume>
<elocation-id>589095</elocation-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R30">
<label>30</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Felsenstein</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Herbert</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>McNamara</surname>
<given-names>PS</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hedrich</surname>
<given-names>CM</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>COVID-19: Immunology and treatment options</article-title>
<source>Clin Immunol</source>
<year>2020</year>
<volume>215</volume>
<elocation-id>108448</elocation-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R31">
<label>31</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Peter</surname>
<given-names>AE</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sandeep</surname>
<given-names>BV</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rao</surname>
<given-names>BG</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kalpana</surname>
<given-names>VL</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Calming the Storm: Natural Immunosuppressants as Adjuvants to Target the Cytokine Storm in COVID-19</article-title>
<source>Front Pharmacol</source>
<year>2020</year>
<volume>11</volume>
<elocation-id>583777</elocation-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R32">
<label>32</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Roshanravan</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Seif</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ostadrahimi</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Pouraghaei</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ghaffari</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Targeting Cytokine Storm to Manage Patients with COVID-19: A Mini-Review</article-title>
<source>Arch Med Res</source>
<year>2020</year>
<volume>51</volume>
<fpage>608</fpage>
<lpage>612</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R33">
<label>33</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Moradian</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>Cytokine release syndrome: inhibition of pro-inflammatory cytokines as a solution for reducing COVID-19 mortality</article-title>
<source>Eur Cytokine Netw</source>
<year>2020</year>
<volume>31</volume>
<fpage>81</fpage>
<lpage>93</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R34">
<label>34</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Beerli</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>Vaccinia virus hijacks EGFR signalling to enhance virus spread through rapid and directed infected cell motility</article-title>
<source>Nat Microbiol</source>
<year>2019</year>
<volume>4</volume>
<fpage>216</fpage>
<lpage>225</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R35">
<label>35</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Pleschka</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>Influenza virus propagation is impaired by inhibition of the Raf/MEK/ERK signalling cascade</article-title>
<source>Nat Cell Biol</source>
<year>2001</year>
<volume>3</volume>
<fpage>301</fpage>
<lpage>305</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R36">
<label>36</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Paul</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>How to improve R&amp;R productivity: the pharmaceutical industry's grand challenge</article-title>
<source>Nat Rev Drug Discov</source>
<year>2010</year>
<volume>9</volume>
<fpage>203</fpage>
<lpage>214</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R37">
<label>37</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Muratov</surname>
<given-names>EN</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>A critical overview of computational approaches employed for COVID-19 drug discovery</article-title>
<source>Chem Soc Rev</source>
<year>2021</year>
<volume>50</volume>
<fpage>9121</fpage>
<lpage>9151</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R38">
<label>38</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Tummino</surname>
<given-names>TA</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>Drug-induced phospholipidosis confounds drug repurposing for SARS-CoV-2</article-title>
<source>Science</source>
<year>2021</year>
<volume>373</volume>
<fpage>541</fpage>
<lpage>547</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R39">
<label>39</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lane</surname>
<given-names>TR</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ekins</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Defending Antiviral Cationic Amphiphilic Drugs That May Cause Drug-Induced Phospholipidosis</article-title>
<source>J Chem Inf Model</source>
<year>2021</year>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R40">
<label>40</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lane</surname>
<given-names>TR</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>Repurposing Pyramax® for the Treatment of Ebola Virus Disease: Additivity of the Lysosomotropic Pyronaridine and Non-Lysosomotropic Artesunate</article-title>
<source>Antiviral Research</source>
<year>2020</year>
<volume>182</volume>
<elocation-id>104908</elocation-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R41">
<label>41</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Jayaraman</surname>
<given-names>SD</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ismail</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Nair</surname>
<given-names>NK</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Navaratnam</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Determination of pyronaridine in blood plasma by high-performance liquid chromatography for application in clinical pharmacological studies</article-title>
<source>J Chromatogr B Biomed Sci Appl</source>
<year>1997</year>
<volume>690</volume>
<fpage>253</fpage>
<lpage>257</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R42">
<label>42</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ramanathan</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>A new and simple solid-phase extraction method for LC determination of pyronaridine in human plasma</article-title>
<source>J Chromatogr B Analyt Technol Biomed Life Sci</source>
<year>2005</year>
<volume>824</volume>
<fpage>45</fpage>
<lpage>50</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R43">
<label>43</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Croft</surname>
<given-names>SL</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>Review of pyronaridine anti-malarial properties and product characteristics</article-title>
<source>Malar J</source>
<year>2012</year>
<volume>11</volume>
<elocation-id>270</elocation-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R44">
<label>44</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bouchard</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Puro</surname>
<given-names>RJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Schneider</surname>
<given-names>RJ</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Activation and inhibition of cellular calcium and tyrosine kinase signaling pathways identify targets of the HBx protein involved in hepatitis B virus replication</article-title>
<source>J Virol</source>
<year>2003</year>
<volume>77</volume>
<fpage>7713</fpage>
<lpage>7719</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R45">
<label>45</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bouchard</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>LH</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Schneider</surname>
<given-names>RJ</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Calcium signaling by HBx protein in hepatitis B virus DNA replication</article-title>
<source>Science</source>
<year>2001</year>
<volume>294</volume>
<fpage>2376</fpage>
<lpage>2378</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R46">
<label>46</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Huang</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>Clinical features of patients infected with 2019 novel coronavirus in Wuhan, China</article-title>
<source>Lancet</source>
<year>2020</year>
<volume>395</volume>
<fpage>497</fpage>
<lpage>506</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R47">
<label>47</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Herold</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>Elevated levels of IL-6 and CRP predict the need for mechanical ventilation in COVID-19</article-title>
<source>J Allergy Clin Immunol</source>
<year>2020</year>
<volume>146</volume>
<fpage>128</fpage>
<lpage>136</lpage>
<elocation-id>e124</elocation-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R48">
<label>48</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>Specific cytokines in the inflammatory cytokine storm of patients with COVID-19-associated acute respiratory distress syndrome and extrapulmonary multiple-organ dysfunction</article-title>
<source>Virol J</source>
<year>2021</year>
<volume>18</volume>
<elocation-id>117</elocation-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R49">
<label>49</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>Q</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>Inborn errors of type I IFN immunity in patients with life-threatening COVID-19</article-title>
<source>Science</source>
<year>2020</year>
<volume>370</volume>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R50">
<label>50</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Xia</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>Evasion of Type I Interferon by SARS-CoV-2</article-title>
<source>Cell Rep</source>
<year>2020</year>
<volume>33</volume>
<elocation-id>108234</elocation-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R51">
<label>51</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Yuen</surname>
<given-names>CK</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>SARS-CoV-2 nsp13, nsp14, nsp15 and orf6 function as potent interferon antagonists</article-title>
<source>Emerg Microbes Infect</source>
<year>2020</year>
<volume>9</volume>
<fpage>1418</fpage>
<lpage>1428</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R52">
<label>52</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Molony</surname>
<given-names>RD</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>Aging impairs both primary and secondary RIG-I signaling for interferon induction in human monocytes</article-title>
<source>Sci Signal</source>
<year>2017</year>
<volume>10</volume>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R53">
<label>53</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hu</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Xia</surname>
<given-names>CQ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Butfiloski</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Clare-Salzler</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Effect of high glucose on cytokine production by human peripheral blood immune cells and type I interferon signaling in monocytes: Implications for the role of hyperglycemia in the diabetes inflammatory process and host defense against infection</article-title>
<source>Clin Immunol</source>
<year>2018</year>
<volume>195</volume>
<fpage>139</fpage>
<lpage>148</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R54">
<label>54</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hadjadj</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>Impaired type I interferon activity and inflammatory responses in severe COVID-19 patients</article-title>
<source>Science</source>
<year>2020</year>
<volume>369</volume>
<fpage>718</fpage>
<lpage>724</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R55">
<label>55</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Teijaro</surname>
<given-names>JR</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Type I interferons in viral control and immune regulation</article-title>
<source>Curr Opin Virol</source>
<year>2016</year>
<volume>16</volume>
<fpage>31</fpage>
<lpage>40</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R56">
<label>56</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>McNab</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mayer-Barber</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Sher</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wack</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>O'Garra</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Type I interferons in infectious disease</article-title>
<source>Nat Rev Immunol</source>
<year>2015</year>
<volume>15</volume>
<fpage>87</fpage>
<lpage>103</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R57">
<label>57</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Katze</surname>
<given-names>MG</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>He</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gale</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
<suffix>Jr</suffix>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Viruses and interferon: a fight for supremacy</article-title>
<source>Nat Rev Immunol</source>
<year>2002</year>
<volume>2</volume>
<fpage>675</fpage>
<lpage>687</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R58">
<label>58</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>JS</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Shin</surname>
<given-names>EC</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>The type I interferon response in COVID-19: implications for treatment</article-title>
<source>Nat Rev Immunol</source>
<year>2020</year>
<volume>20</volume>
<fpage>585</fpage>
<lpage>586</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R59">
<label>59</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Caramaschi</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>Histopathological findings and clinicopathologic correlation in COVID-19: a systematic review</article-title>
<source>Mod Pathol</source>
<year>2021</year>
<volume>34</volume>
<fpage>1614</fpage>
<lpage>1633</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R60">
<label>60</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Pannone</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>Lung histopathological findings in COVID-19 disease - a systematic review</article-title>
<source>Infect Agent Cancer</source>
<year>2021</year>
<volume>16</volume>
<elocation-id>34</elocation-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R61">
<label>61</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hariri</surname>
<given-names>LP</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>Lung Histopathology in Coronavirus Disease 2019 as Compared With Severe Acute Respiratory Sydrome and H1N1 Influenza: A Systematic Review</article-title>
<source>Chest</source>
<year>2021</year>
<volume>159</volume>
<fpage>73</fpage>
<lpage>84</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R62">
<label>62</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Lind</surname>
<given-names>KF</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Osterud</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hansen</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Jorgensen</surname>
<given-names>TO</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Andersen</surname>
<given-names>JH</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>The immunomodulatory effects of barettin and involvement of the kinases CAMK1alpha and RIPK2</article-title>
<source>Immunopharmacol Immunotoxicol</source>
<year>2015</year>
<volume>37</volume>
<fpage>458</fpage>
<lpage>464</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R63">
<label>63</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Fromont</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>Discovery of Highly Selective Inhibitors of Calmodulin-Dependent Kinases That Restore Insulin Sensitivity in the Diet-Induced Obesity in Vivo Mouse Model</article-title>
<source>J Med Chem</source>
<year>2020</year>
<volume>63</volume>
<fpage>6784</fpage>
<lpage>6801</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R64">
<label>64</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>Calcium/calmodulin-dependent protein kinase (CaMK) Ialpha mediates the macrophage inflammatory response to sepsis</article-title>
<source>J Leukoc Biol</source>
<year>2011</year>
<volume>90</volume>
<fpage>249</fpage>
<lpage>261</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R65">
<label>65</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Oladunni</surname>
<given-names>FS</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>Lethality of SARS-CoV-2 infection in K18 human angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 transgenic mice</article-title>
<source>Nat Commun</source>
<year>2020</year>
<volume>11</volume>
<elocation-id>6122</elocation-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R66">
<label>66</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bao</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>The pathogenicity of SARS-CoV-2 in hACE2 transgenic mice</article-title>
<source>Nature</source>
<year>2020</year>
<volume>583</volume>
<fpage>830</fpage>
<lpage>833</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R67">
<label>67</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Yinda</surname>
<given-names>CK</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>K18-hACE2 mice develop respiratory disease resembling severe COVID-19</article-title>
<source>PLoS Pathog</source>
<year>2021</year>
<volume>17</volume>
<elocation-id>e1009195</elocation-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R68">
<label>68</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Arce</surname>
<given-names>VM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Costoya</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>SARS-CoV-2 infection in K18-ACE2 transgenic mice replicates human pulmonary disease in COVID-19</article-title>
<source>Cell Mol Immunol</source>
<year>2021</year>
<volume>18</volume>
<fpage>513</fpage>
<lpage>514</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R69">
<label>69</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Moreau</surname>
<given-names>GB</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>Evaluation of K18-</article-title>
<source>Am J Trop Med Hyg</source>
<year>2020</year>
<volume>103</volume>
<fpage>1215</fpage>
<lpage>1219</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R70">
<label>70</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Winkler</surname>
<given-names>ES</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>Publisher Correction: SARS-CoV-2 infection of human ACE2-transgenic mice causes severe lung inflammation and impaired function</article-title>
<source>Nat Immunol</source>
<year>2020</year>
<volume>21</volume>
<fpage>1470</fpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R71">
<label>71</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zheng</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>COVID-19 treatments and pathogenesis including anosmia in K18-hACE2 mice</article-title>
<source>Nature</source>
<year>2021</year>
<volume>589</volume>
<fpage>603</fpage>
<lpage>607</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R72">
<label>72</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hsia</surname>
<given-names>CC</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hyde</surname>
<given-names>DM</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ochs</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Weibel</surname>
<given-names>ER</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<collab>A. E. J. T. F. o. Q. A. o. L. Structure</collab>
<article-title>An official research policy statement of the American Thoracic Society/European Respiratory Society: standards for quantitative assessment of lung structure</article-title>
<source>Am J Respir Crit Care Med</source>
<year>2010</year>
<volume>181</volume>
<fpage>394</fpage>
<lpage>418</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R73">
<label>73</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Friesner</surname>
<given-names>RA</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>Extra Precision Glide:  Docking and Scoring Incorporating a Model of Hydrophobic Enclosure for Protein−Ligand Complexes</article-title>
<source>Journal of Medicinal Chemistry</source>
<year>2006</year>
<volume>49</volume>
<fpage>6177</fpage>
<lpage>6196</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R74">
<label>74</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Dominguez</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Boelens</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Bonvin</surname>
<given-names>AMJJ</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>HADDOCK: A Protein-Protein Docking Approach Based on Biochemical or Biophysical Information</article-title>
<source>Journal of the American Chemical Society</source>
<year>2003</year>
<volume>125</volume>
<fpage>1731</fpage>
<lpage>1737</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R75">
<label>75</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Noske</surname>
<given-names>GD</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>A Crystallographic Snapshot of SARS-CoV-2 Main Protease Maturation Process</article-title>
<source>J Mol Biol</source>
<year>2021</year>
<volume>433</volume>
<elocation-id>167118</elocation-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R76">
<label>76</label>
<element-citation publication-type="web">
<collab>ThermoFisher</collab>
<source>Z′-LYTE Screening Protocol and Assay Conditions</source>
<year>2018</year>
<comment>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://assets.thermofisher.com/TFS-Assets/BID/Methods-&amp;-Protocols/20180123_SSBK_Customer_Protocol_and_Assay_Conditions.pdf">http://assets.thermofisher.com/TFS-Assets/BID/Methods-&amp;-Protocols/20180123_SSBK_Customer_Protocol_and_Assay_Conditions.pdf</ext-link>
</comment>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R77">
<label>77</label>
<element-citation publication-type="web">
<collab>ThermoFisher</collab>
<source>Adapta Screening Protocol and Assay Conditions</source>
<year>2018</year>
<comment>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://assets.thermofisher.com/TFS-Assets/BID/Methods-&amp;-Protocols/20180123_SSBK_Adapta_Customer_Protocol_and_Assay_Conditions.pdf">http://assets.thermofisher.com/TFS-Assets/BID/Methods-&amp;-Protocols/20180123_SSBK_Adapta_Customer_Protocol_and_Assay_Conditions.pdf</ext-link>
</comment>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R78">
<label>78</label>
<element-citation publication-type="web">
<collab>ThermoFisher</collab>
<source>LanthaScreen Eu Kinase Binding Assay Screening Protocol and Assay Conditions</source>
<year>2018</year>
<comment>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://assets.thermofisher.com/TFS-Assets/BID/Methods-&amp;-Protocols/20180123_SSBK_LanthaScreen_Binding_Customer_Protocol_and_Assay_Conditions.pdf">http://assets.thermofisher.com/TFS-Assets/BID/Methods-&amp;-Protocols/20180123_SSBK_LanthaScreen_Binding_Customer_Protocol_and_Assay_Conditions.pdf</ext-link>
</comment>
</element-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
<floats-group>
<boxed-text id="BX1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
<caption>
<title>One sentence summary</title>
</caption>
<p>There is currently intense interest in discovering small molecules with direct antiviral activity against the severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-Cov-2). Pyronaridine, an antiviral drug with in vitro activity against Ebola, Marburg and SARS-CoV-2 has now statistically significantly reduced the viral load in mice along with IL-6, TNF-α, and IFN-β ultimately demonstrating a protective effect against lung damage by infection to provide a new potential treatment for testing clinically.</p>
</boxed-text>
<fig id="F1" position="float">
<label>Figure 1</label>
<caption>
<title>
<italic>In vivo</italic> efficacy of pyronaridine in a mouse model of COVID-19.</title>
<p>A) Experimental timeline: K18-hACE2 mice were infected with SARS-CoV-2 (2 X 10<sup>4</sup> PFU/40 μL saline, intranasal) or mock. One group of mice was treated with pyronaridine (75 mg/kg i.p.) 1 h before virus inoculation. B) Body weight was evaluated daily. C) At 3 DPI, mice were euthanized and the lung viral load, and D-M) Lung cytokines and chemokines levels were determined. * p&lt;0.05, ** p&lt;0.01, and *** p&lt;0.001 as compared with mock group after one-way ANOVA followed by Tukey post-hoc test. # p&lt;0.05 as compared with infected group after one-way ANOVA followed by Tukey post-hoc test. Pyr – Pyronaridine.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="EMS136057-f001"/>
</fig>
<fig id="F2" position="float">
<label>Figure 2</label>
<caption>
<p>Lung histopathological analyses of COVID-19 mice treated with pyronaridine. K18-hACE2 mice were infected with SARS-CoV-2 (2 X 10<sup>4</sup> PFU/40 μL, intranasal) or mock. One group of mice was treated with pyronaridine (75 mg/kg i.p.) 1 h before virus inoculation. At 3 DPI, mice were euthanized, and the lungs were harvested and processed for histopathological analyses. A - Representative images of lung slices stained with hematoxylin and eosin (H&amp;E). B- Quantitative morphometric analyses. *** p&lt;0.001 as compared with mock group after one-way ANOVA followed by Tukey post-hoc test. # p&lt;0.05 and ## p&lt;0.01 as compared with infected group after one-way ANOVA followed by Tukey post-hoc test. Pyr – Pyronaridine. Scale bars: 20X = 125 μm; 40X = 50 μm.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="EMS136057-f002"/>
</fig>
<fig id="F3" position="float">
<label>Figure 3</label>
<caption>
<p>A. Dose-response curves of pyronaridine and active analogs against SARS-CoV-2 PL<sup>pro</sup> B. Docking pose of pyronaridine (yellow) and analogs 12126039 (blue) and 12126038 (purple) in PL<sup>pro</sup> active site (PDB 7JRN). Electrostatic potential projected as surface charge. C. 2D ligand interaction diagram. Hydrogen bonds are depicted in pink, while pi-stackings are depicted in green.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="EMS136057-f003"/>
</fig>
<fig id="F4" position="float">
<label>Figure 4</label>
<caption>
<title>Pyronaridine CAMK1 dose response.</title>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="EMS136057-f004"/>
</fig>
<fig id="F5" position="float">
<label>Scheme 1</label>
<caption>
<title>Synthetic route for 6-chloro-2-methoxyacridine derivatives</title>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="EMS136057-f005"/>
</fig>
<fig id="F6" position="float">
<label>Scheme 2</label>
<caption>
<title>Synthetic route for benzo[b]-1,6-naphthyridine derivatives</title>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="EMS136057-f006"/>
</fig>
<table-wrap id="T1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
<label>Table 1</label>
<caption>
<title>Pl<sup>pro</sup> IC<sub>50</sub> inhibition data for pyronaridine analogs.</title>
</caption>
<table frame="box" rules="all">
<thead>
<tr>
<th valign="top" align="left">Molecule</th>
<th valign="top" align="left">Structure</th>
<th valign="top" align="left">Mol wt</th>
<th valign="top" align="left">IC<sub>50</sub> (μM)</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td valign="top" align="left">Pyronaridine</td>
<td valign="top" align="left">
<inline-graphic xlink:href="EMS136057-i001.jpg"/>
</td>
<td valign="top" align="left">518.05</td>
<td valign="top" align="left">1.86 ± 0.58</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td valign="top" align="left">12126038</td>
<td valign="top" align="left">
<inline-graphic xlink:href="EMS136057-i002.jpg"/>
</td>
<td valign="top" align="left">465.00</td>
<td valign="top" align="left">3.28 ± 0.4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td valign="top" align="left">12126039</td>
<td valign="top" align="left">
<inline-graphic xlink:href="EMS136057-i003.jpg"/>
</td>
<td valign="top" align="left">517.08</td>
<td valign="top" align="left">2.44 ± 0.53</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td valign="top" align="left">12126040</td>
<td valign="top" align="left">
<inline-graphic xlink:href="EMS136057-i004.jpg"/>
</td>
<td valign="top" align="left">433.94</td>
<td valign="top" align="left">2.56 ± 0.28</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td valign="top" align="left">10326099</td>
<td valign="top" align="left">
<inline-graphic xlink:href="EMS136057-i005.jpg"/>
</td>
<td valign="top" align="left">306.33</td>
<td valign="top" align="left">&gt;20</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td valign="middle" align="left">12126035</td>
<td valign="top" align="left">
<inline-graphic xlink:href="EMS136057-i006.jpg"/>
</td>
<td valign="top" align="left">290.33</td>
<td valign="top" align="left">&gt;20</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td valign="middle" align="left">12126036</td>
<td valign="top" align="left">
<inline-graphic xlink:href="EMS136057-i007.jpg"/>
</td>
<td valign="top" align="left">328.80</td>
<td valign="top" align="left">&gt;20</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td valign="middle" align="left">12126037</td>
<td valign="top" align="left">
<inline-graphic xlink:href="EMS136057-i008.jpg"/>
</td>
<td valign="top" align="left">350.81</td>
<td valign="top" align="left">&gt;20</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td valign="top" align="left">12126072</td>
<td valign="top" align="left">
<inline-graphic xlink:href="EMS136057-i009.jpg"/>
</td>
<td valign="top" align="left">259.69</td>
<td valign="top" align="left">&gt;20</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</table-wrap>
</floats-group>
</article>
