<!DOCTYPE article
 PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" article-type="preprint"><?all-math-mml yes?><?use-mml?><?origin ukpmcpa?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">bioRxiv</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>bioRxiv : the preprint server for biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub"/></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">EMS144201</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2021.11.30.470647</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="archive">PPR427937</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Crowding changes appearance systematically in peripheral, amblyopic, and developing vision</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kalpadakis-Smith</surname><given-names>A.V.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tailor</surname><given-names>V.K.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Dahlmann-Noor</surname><given-names>A.H.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Greenwood</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Experimental Psychology, University College London, London, UK</aff><aff id="A2"><label>2</label>NIHR Biomedical Research Centre @ Moorfields Eye Hospital, London, UK</aff><aff id="A3"><label>3</label>Moorfields Eye Hospital NHS Foundation Trust, London, UK</aff><author-notes><corresp id="CR1">Corresponding author: John A. Greenwood <email>john.greenwood@ucl.ac.uk</email> <italic>Website:</italic> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://eccentricvision.com">http://eccentricvision.com</ext-link></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted"><day>07</day><month>04</month><year>2022</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="preprint"><day>06</day><month>04</month><year>2022</year></pub-date><permissions><ali:free_to_read/><license><ali:license_ref>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is licensed under a <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0 International license</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p id="P1">Visual crowding is the disruptive effect of clutter on object recognition. Although most prominent in adult peripheral vision, crowding also disrupts foveal vision in typically-developing children and those with strabismic amblyopia. Do these crowding effects share the same mechanism? Here we exploit observations that crowded errors in peripheral vision are not random: target objects appear either averaged with the flankers (assimilation), or replaced by them (substitution). If amblyopic and developmental crowding share the same mechanism then their errors should be similarly systematic. We tested foveal vision in children aged 3-8 years with typical vision or strabismic amblyopia, and peripheral vision in typical adults. The perceptual effects of crowding were measured by requiring observers to adjust a reference stimulus to match the perceived orientation of a target ‘Vac-Man’ element. When the target was surrounded by flankers that differed by ±30°, all three groups (adults and children with typical or amblyopic vision) reported orientations between the target and flankers (assimilation). Errors were reduced with ±90° differences, but primarily matched the flanker orientation (substitution) when they did occur. A population pooling model of crowding successfully simulated this pattern of errors in all three groups. We conclude that the perceptual effects of amblyopic and developing crowding are systematic and resemble the near periphery in adults, suggesting a common underlying mechanism.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Crowding</kwd><kwd>amblyopia</kwd><kwd>development</kwd><kwd>peripheral vision</kwd><kwd>orientation</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="S1" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p id="P2">Clutter can significantly disrupt the recognition of objects that are otherwise readily identified in isolation – a phenomenon known as visual crowding (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R56">Levi, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R98">Whitney &amp; Levi, 2011</xref>). In the typical adult visual system, crowding is most pronounced in peripheral vision, where the recognition of a target can be hindered by flanking objects separated by as much as half the target eccentricity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">Bouma, 1970</xref>). Although this disruption is usually minimal in the fovea (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R92">Toet &amp; Levi, 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">Danilova &amp; Bondarko, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">Coates, Levi, Touch, &amp; Sabesan, 2018</xref>), elevations occur in amblyopia, a developmental disorder of vision characterised by reduced acuity in one eye despite optical correction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R65">McKee, Levi, &amp; Movshon, 2003</xref>). When amblyopia is associated with strabismus (ocular misalignment), foveal vision in the affected eye is strongly impaired by the presence of nearby flankers in both adults (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">Flom, Weymouth, &amp; Kahneman, 1963</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R59">Levi &amp; Klein, 1985</xref>) and children (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38">Greenwood et al., 2012</xref>). Foveal elevations in crowding have also been found in children with typical vision up to the age of 11 years (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R49">Jeon, Hamid, Mauer, &amp; Lewis, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38">Greenwood et al., 2012</xref>). These elevations have a range of functional consequences, given for instance the correlation between crowding and reading ability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R64">Martelli, Di Filippo, Spinelli, &amp; Zoccolotti, 2009</xref>). However, although it is clear that crowding occurs in these three instances – typical peripheral vision, the amblyopic fovea, and the developing fovea – it is unclear whether the underlying mechanism is the same.</p><p id="P3">In the typical adult periphery, crowding strongly disrupts target identification when flankers are near the target. The spatial extent of crowding can be defined as the target-flanker separation required to remove this disruptive effect (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">Bouma, 1970</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R92">Toet &amp; Levi, 1992</xref>). These values are typically far larger than what would be predicted by the level of acuity or blur in peripheral vision (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R86">Song, Levi, &amp; Pelli, 2014</xref>) and do not vary with target size (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R58">Levi, Hariharan, &amp; Klein, 2002b</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R94">Tripathy &amp; Cavanagh, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R74">Pelli, Palomares, &amp; Majaj, 2004</xref>). Peripheral crowding is also selective for the similarity between the target and flankers in visual dimensions such as orientation and contrast polarity, with target identification more strongly disrupted when flankers are similar to the target than when they are dissimilar (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R52">Kooi, Toet, Tripathy, &amp; Levi, 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R99">Wilkinson, Wilson, &amp; Ellemberg, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">Chung, Levi, &amp; Legge, 2001</xref>). In the amblyopic fovea, crowding is similarly reduced by an increase in target-flanker separation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R57">Levi, Hariharan, &amp; Klein, 2002a</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39">Hariharan, Levi, &amp; Klein, 2005</xref>), with an extent that is also well in excess of limits imposed by acuity or blur (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R86">Song, Levi, &amp; Pelli, 2014</xref>) and largely invariant to target size (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R57">Levi, Hariharan, &amp; Klein, 2002a</xref>). Amblyopic crowding may however be less dependent on target-flanker similarity – flankers dissimilar to the target in polarity, contrast, and orientation have been found to be equally disruptive as flankers similar to the target along these dimensions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R57">Levi, Hariharan, &amp; Klein, 2002a</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39">Hariharan, Levi, &amp; Klein, 2005</xref>). These variations in the characteristics of crowding cast doubt on the possibility of a common mechanism for peripheral vision and the amblyopic fovea. Although crowding in the typically developing fovea is also dependent on target-flanker separation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38">Greenwood et al., 2012</xref>), the effects of acuity/blur, target size, and target-flanker similarity are unclear.</p><p id="P4">Much of our understanding of the mechanisms underlying crowding in the typical adult periphery derives from measurements of the errors that observers make when reporting the identity of a crowded target. Observers have been found to report either the identity of one of the flankers surrounding the target (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R88">Strasburger, Harvey, &amp; Rentschler, 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R87">Strasburger, 2005</xref>), or an intermediate identity close to the target-flanker average (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R70">Parkes et al., 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34">Greenwood, Bex, &amp; Dakin, 2009</xref>). The finding that target patches of noise can similarly adopt the perceived orientation of the flankers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">Greenwood, Bex, &amp; Dakin, 2010</xref>) suggests that these errors are not simply the result of decisional bias. Rather, they represent a change in the perceived identity of the target to more closely resemble the flankers, indicating that peripheral crowding has systematic perceptual effects.</p><p id="P5">A range of models can account for this systematic shift in the identity of crowded targets. Substitution models (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">Ester, Klee, &amp; Awh, 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">Ester, Zilber, &amp; Serences, 2015</xref>) argue that errors emerge due to the substitution of a flanker into the target location, leading observers to report the flanker identity. This substitution is either attributed to the increased positional uncertainty of peripheral vision (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R101">Wolford, 1975</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R53">Krumhansl &amp; Thomas, 1977</xref>), or unfocussed spatial attention (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R88">Strasburger, Harvey, &amp; Rentschler, 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R87">Strasburger, 2005</xref>). On the other hand, ‘pooling’ or averaging models (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R70">Parkes et al., 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34">Greenwood, Bex, &amp; Dakin, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">Dakin, Cass, Greenwood, &amp; Bex, 2010</xref>) posit that crowding is the compulsory integration of target and flanker signals, resulting in observers perceiving an average or intermediate feature (e.g. orientation) of the target and flankers. Each of these model types focuses on distinct types of errors: either flanker reports (‘substitution errors’) or reports of intermediate identities between the target and flankers (‘assimilation errors’).</p><p id="P6">Population pooling models (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R95">van den Berg, Roerdink, &amp; Cornelissen, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40">Harrison &amp; Bex, 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36">Greenwood &amp; Parsons, 2020</xref>) propose a more general framework for the perceptual effects of peripheral crowding. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40">Harrison and Bex (2015)</xref> used an orientation-matching task where observers matched the orientation of a reference Landolt-C to that of a crowded target in the periphery. When the target was surrounded by flankers that differed by 45° or less, observers reported orientations between the target and flanker values (assimilation errors). When the difference from the target was 90° or above, errors more closely matched the flanker orientation (substitution errors). Rather than invoking separate substitution or averaging mechanisms, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40">Harrison and Bex (2015)</xref> account for both error types using a population pooling model that takes a weighted combination of population responses to the target and flankers. Similar approaches have been applied more generally to explain crowding with letters (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31">Freeman, Chakravarthi, &amp; Pelli, 2012</xref>) and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R50">faces (Kalpadakis-Smith, Goffaux, &amp; Greenwood, 2018</xref>). Higher-dimensional pooling approaches have also been developed, which depict crowding as an over-application of summary statistics across the periphery (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">Balas, Nakano, &amp; Rosenholtz, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32">Freeman &amp; Simoncelli, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R51">Keshvari &amp; Rosenholtz, 2016</xref>). Their generality allows the consideration of these crowding effects in a range of naturalistic tasks (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R78">Rosenholtz, Yu, &amp; Keshvari, 2019</xref>), though quantitative predictions of these high-dimensional models are more difficult to discern for specific paradigms.</p><p id="P7">Although population pooling models can account for peripheral crowding, their applicability to amblyopia is unknown. Given the plethora of deficits in visual function observed in the affected eye (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R65">McKee, Levi, &amp; Movshon, 2003</xref>), the basis of amblyopic crowding could in fact differ substantially from that of peripheral vision. In addition to the definitive acuity deficit, vision in the affected eye of observers with amblyopia is characterised by increased positional uncertainty (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R59">Levi &amp; Klein, 1985</xref>). This uncertainty could produce confusions of the flanker for the target, making a predominance of substitution errors. Alternatively, crowded errors may arise due to perceptual distortions that affect the amblyopic eye. Observers with strabismic amblyopia show considerable distortions when reproducing visual stimuli, including shrinkage, expansion, and torsion of specific regions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R77">Pugh, 1958</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R83">Sireteanu, Lagreze, &amp; Constantinescu, 1993</xref>). Although these distortions are consistent over time, they vary across observers and visual field location (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">Barrett et al., 2003</xref>). If these distortions underlie the perceptual effects of amblyopic crowding, then errors would not be systematic but random (depending on the particular conjunction of the distortion type and stimulus), suggesting a distinct mechanism from peripheral crowding.</p><p id="P8">Even less is known about the mechanism of foveal crowding during development. Although the extent of foveal crowding has been found to be greater in typically developing children than in adults (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">Atkinson &amp; Braddick, 1983</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">Atkinson, Anker, Evans, &amp; McIntyre, 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R49">Jeon et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38">Greenwood et al., 2012</xref>), the perceptual effects of developing crowding have not been investigated. Studies have however demonstrated that children make a disproportionate amount of random errors in psychophysical tasks relative to adults (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R100">Witton, Talcott, &amp; Henning, 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R62">Manning, Jones, Dekker, &amp; Pellicano, 2018</xref>). These errors are frequently made in low difficulty “catch” trials (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R93">Treutwein, 1995</xref>) and have been attributed to attentional lapses and under-developed short-term memory. Both of these factors would produce random errors that could dominate responses to the identity of a target object in crowding paradigms. The same could be true of children with amblyopia. In both cases, the observed elevations in foveal crowding could therefore reflect quite distinct processes to the systematic perceptual effects observed in peripheral vision.</p><p id="P9">To investigate the perceptual effects of amblyopic and developing crowding, we tested the foveal vision of children aged 3-8 years with either strabismic amblyopia or typical vision, with comparison to peripheral vision in typical adults. Though many studies of amblyopic crowding have used adult observers, we felt it important to test these deficits in children, given that both the onset and treatment of this condition typically occurs in early childhood (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R45">Holmes et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R90">Tailor, Bossi, Greenwood, &amp; Dahlmann-Noor, 2016</xref>). To this end, we adapted the orientation-matching task used by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40">Harrison and Bex (2015</xref>), with stimuli presented foveally to children with and without amblyopia, and in peripheral vision to adults. Given the timing constraints in testing children (due to shorter attention spans), we tested ±30° and ±90° target-flanker orientation differences. The ±30° flanker differences were selected to test whether children show the same systematic shift of responses to orientations between the target and flankers (assimilation errors) as in the periphery. Because orientation differences below 90° are less able to distinguish between assimilation and substitution errors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40">Harrison &amp; Bex, 2015</xref>), we chose ±90° flanker differences to further constrain the underlying mechanisms. These ±90° orientation differences have also been shown to reduce the effect of crowding in the periphery relative to smaller orientation differences (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39">Hariharan, Levi, &amp; Klein, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40">Harrison &amp; Bex, 2015</xref>), allowing us to examine the selectivity for target-flanker similarity in amblyopic and developing crowding. We further probed the possibility of a common mechanism by simulating the observed perceptual effects with a population pooling model of crowding, with comparison to a model that simply added noise to the orientation judgements.</p><p id="P10">If there is a common mechanism that underlies amblyopic, developing, and peripheral crowding, each of these instances should show the same systematic effects on target appearance as observed in the adult periphery. That is, children with amblyopia and typical vision should make either assimilation or substitution errors, depending on the target-flanker orientation difference. In contrast, distinct mechanisms for crowding in strabismic amblyopia and developing vision may produce random errors, either because crowding affects the appearance of the target in a non-systematic manner or due to attentional lapses.</p></sec><sec id="S2" sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec id="S3"><title>Design</title><p id="P11">Both children and adults completed three tasks. Acuity was measured first to determine the minimum target size at which each observer could judge the orientation of the target element. Crowded acuity was then measured to determine the extent of the spatial zone of crowding around the target location. These tasks, adapted from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38">Greenwood et al. (2012)</xref>, were used to set stimulus sizes for the orientation-matching task, in particular to ensure both that the target size was above acuity limits and that flankers were within the spatial region of crowding. The third orientation-matching task, adapted from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40">Harrison &amp; Bex (2015)</xref>, allowed us to measure the perceptual effects of crowding.</p></sec><sec id="S4"><title>Observers</title><sec id="S5"><title>Children</title><p id="P12">40 children between 3-8 years of age were tested, divided into two groups: those with typical vision (<italic>n</italic>= 20, mean= 73.2 months, range= 36-94 months), and those with strabismic amblyopia (<italic>n</italic>= 20, mean= 70.7 months, range= 37-100 months). Sample sizes were derived from prior work (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38">Greenwood et al., 2012</xref>), with children tested at the Children’s Eye Centre at Moorfields Eye Hospital (London, UK).</p><p id="P13">Prior to the study, children underwent a full orthoptic assessment to ensure they met our inclusion and exclusion criteria. Typically developing children were selected to have a best-corrected visual acuity of 0.1 logMAR (logarithm of the minimum angle of resolution) or better in both eyes, as measured by Thomson V2000 acuity charts, in the absence of any pre-existing visual or neurological deficits. For children with strabismic amblyopia, inclusion was based on the presence of amblyopia, as indicated by a two-line difference in best-corrected logMAR acuity between the eyes, as well as heterotropia (deviation of the optical axes) that could be either esotropia (inward deviation) or exotropia (outward). Children with additional visual deficits (e.g. macular dystrophies) and developmental or neurological conditions (e.g. autism) were excluded. We did not exclude cases of joint anisometropia and strabismus. Clinical details for all children are shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Appendix A</xref>.</p><p id="P14">Three children with amblyopia did not complete all experimental tasks and were excluded from the analysis. They are not included in the tallies above. The experimental procedures were performed with the informed consent of children and their parents and were approved by the Health Research Authority of the UK National Health Service.</p></sec><sec id="S6"><title>Adults</title><p id="P15">10 adults were tested (4 males, mean= 28.7 years, range= 24-35 years), including two of the authors (AKS and JAG). All had a best-corrected visual acuity of 0 logMAR or better. None had amblyopia or strabismus, nor any history of binocular dysfunction, as indicated by self-report.</p></sec></sec><sec id="S7"><title>Apparatus</title><sec id="S8"><title>Children</title><p id="P16">Experiments were programmed using MATLAB (The Mathworks, Ltd., Cambridge, UK) and run on a Dell PC using PsychToolbox (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">Brainard, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R72">Pelli, 1997</xref>). Stimuli were presented on an ASUS VG278HE LCD monitor, with 1920 × 1080 resolution and 120 Hz refresh rate. The monitor was calibrated using a Minolta photometer and linearised in software, to give a maximum luminance of 150 cd/m<sup>2</sup>. A second Dell UltraSharp 2208WFP LCD monitor, with 1680 × 1050 resolution and 75 Hz refresh rate, was positioned above the first. In the acuity and crowding-extent tasks, this second monitor was used to display a running tally of points children received by playing the games. In the orientation-matching task it displayed the response stimulus.</p><p id="P17"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1A</xref> shows the experimental setup for the children. Children wore stereo-shutter glasses (nVidia Corp., Santa Clara, CA) alternating at 120 Hz, custom-fit into a ski-mask frame to allow a comfortable fit over their optical correction. These glasses were used to present the stimuli monocularly. Children were seated 3 m from the screen. For the acuity and crowding-extent tasks, the experimenter recorded the children’s responses using the keyboard. For the orientation-matching task, a Griffin Powermate response dial was used by the children to rotate the response element and register their responses.</p></sec><sec id="S9"><title>Adults</title><p id="P18">Adults completed the same three tasks as children, run on a Viglen PC and presented on a Sony GDM-FW900 CRT monitor with 2304 × 1440 resolution and 80 Hz refresh rate. The monitor was calibrated and linearised to give a maximum luminance of 122 cd/m<sup>2</sup>. For the acuity and crowding-extent tasks, observers registered their response using a keyboard. Responses in the orientation-matching task were made with a Griffin Powermate dial. Observers were seated 50 cm from the monitor, with a head-and-chin rest used to minimise movement. Stimuli were presented monocularly to the dominant eye, with an eye-patch covering the non-dominant eye. Eye-dominance was established using the Miles test (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R66">Miles, 1928</xref>). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1B</xref> depicts this experimental setup.</p></sec></sec><sec id="S10"><title>Stimuli and Procedures</title><sec id="S11"><title>Children</title><p id="P19">The three tasks involved five video-game characters adapted from a previous study (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38">Greenwood et al., 2012</xref>): Vac-Man (Visual Acuity Man) and four ghosts. Vac-Man was a circle with a horizontal gap for a “mouth”, resembling a filled-in Landolt-C. Prior to rotation, the mouth extended from the stimulus midpoint to the rightwards edge, with a vertical width (which we refer to as the “gap size”) that was one-fifth of the stimulus diameter, similar to the proportions in Sloan letters (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R85">Sloan, 1959</xref>). Vac-Man was the centrally located target stimulus in all three tasks, viewed foveally and rendered in black at 90% Weber contrast against a mid-grey (45 cd/m<sup>2</sup>) background. Vac-Man also served as flanker and response stimuli in the orientation-matching task. The ghost characters acted either as colour aids for the identification of Vac-Man’s orientation in the acuity task (as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1A</xref>), or achromatic flanker stimuli in the crowding-extent task (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1D</xref>). The gap for each of the ghosts’ “legs” was also one-fifth of the stimulus diameter.</p><p id="P20">All children began with the acuity task, where they were asked to report which of the ghosts Vac-Man was facing (4 Alternative Forced Choice, 4AFC). Each ghost had a distinct colour (green above, red to the right, orange below, and blue to the left) and moved slowly along the monitor edges at a large separation from the target (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1A</xref>) to minimise the chance of any crowding with the target. Children could report either the colour of the ghost or its location, verbally or by pointing. Pictures of the ghosts were placed at the monitor edges to aid children’s reports. Normal colour-naming abilities were checked using the stimuli prior to participation. Feedback was given after each trial through brief animations, with Vac-Man smiling for correct responses and frowning when incorrect. A longer “reward” animation was presented after 3 correct responses in which Vac-Man ate a ghost (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1C</xref>). Children had unlimited response time.</p><p id="P21">In the subsequent crowding-extent task, the four ghosts became flankers surrounding Vac-Man, each achromatic in order to match the target and increase the strength of crowding through target-flanker similarity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R52">Kooi et al., 1994</xref>). Flanker ghosts were located above, below, left, and right of Vac- Man, with each ghost randomly oriented in 1 of 4 cardinal orientations. Children made the same 4AFC judgement as the acuity task, aided by the reference cards of the ghosts on the monitor edges.</p><p id="P22">Acuity thresholds were measured by varying the overall size of Vac-Man, and thus the visibility of the mouth gap to indicate its orientation. Size was varied using a QUEST staircase procedure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R97">Watson &amp; Pelli, 1983</xref>) set to converge at 62.5% correct performance. These gap-size thresholds set the lower bound for the size used in the orientation-matching task. The spatial extent of crowding was also measured by varying Vac-Man size, with QUEST converging at a higher level of 80% correct performance. Flanker ghosts were scaled similarly, with the centre-to-centre separation between the target and flankers scaled at 1.1× target diameter, a value recommended as efficient for the measurement of crowding extent (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R86">Song, Levi, &amp; Pelli, 2014</xref>). Although this method confounds size and separation by varying both, the extent of amblyopic and peripheral crowding are limited by centre-to-centre separation and not target size (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39">Hariharan, Levi, &amp; Klein, 2005</xref>). As such, it is only the variations in centre-to-centre separation that should affect the strength of crowding, and thus the measurement of its extent (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R61">Levi, Song, &amp; Pelli, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R86">Song, Levi, &amp; Pelli, 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">Coates, Ludowici, &amp; Chung, 2021</xref>). The resulting threshold gave the upper bound for the sizes and target-flanker separations used in the orientation-matching task, ensuring that stimuli were placed within the spatial extent of crowding.</p><p id="P23">The QUEST routine used for both acuity and crowding-extent tasks was tailored to suit children in three ways. First, to begin the task children were given 3 practice trials with a target gap-size set at twice their acuity level measured during orthoptic testing. Second, easier trials were presented on every fifth trial by selecting a gap size at twice the current QUEST threshold estimate. This minimised the frustration that numerous trials near threshold can produce. Third, an exit criterion was used to reduce testing time: if the standard deviation of the threshold estimated by QUEST for the preceding 8 trials was below 0.03 log units, the experimenter was given the option to exit the task. Otherwise, the experiment terminated after 60 trials (30 for each eye). The average number of trials needed to estimate threshold, excluding practice trials, was 44 for acuity and 46 for the crowding-extent task. Both eyes were tested in one experimental run, with separate QUEST staircases for each eye running simultaneously and selected at random on each trial. The output of each QUEST staircase gave the threshold size of Vac-Man’s mouth in degrees of visual angle.</p><p id="P24">The final orientation-matching task measured the perceptual effects of crowding. Four achromatic “imposter” Vac-Men surrounded the “real” target Vac-Man in each cardinal direction (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1E</xref>). Both target and flanker Vac-Men were at 90% Weber contrast. Here, a second response Vac-Man was presented on the response screen, twice the size of the target to ensure visibility. Children used the response dial to rotate the Vac-Man on the response screen until it appeared the same as the real Vac-Man on the main monitor. They had unlimited time to respond. On each trial, the orientation of the target varied randomly between ±45° from vertical. The four flankers were matched in orientation, all of them differing from the target by either ±30° or ±90°. This resulted in five flanker conditions: unflanked (target in isolation) or surrounded by flankers with a difference of either +30° (counter-clockwise), -30° (clockwise), +90°, or -90° from the target. 12 trials were tested for each condition, resulting in 60 trials in total for the orientation-matching task. When children’s responses deviated from the orientation of the target by more than ±35°, they received feedback in the form of a frowning Vac-Man, whereas when they responded within that range, Vac-Man smiled. This was done to maintain children’s engagement in the task and reward them for participating.</p><p id="P25">Stimulus sizes in the matching task were determined individually for each child, both to ensure that Vac-Man was visible (i.e. above the acuity limit) and crowded (i.e. with flankers within the spatial extent of crowding). A multiple of the gap-size acuity threshold was thus used, constrained by the crowding-extent values. We aimed to present stimuli with a gap size of 3× the acuity threshold, though lower values were used where this gave target-flanker separations that exceeded the crowding extent for that child (either 2.5, 2, or 1.5× acuity). For the amblyopic children, three were tested with sizes 3× acuity thresholds, seven with 2.5×, five with 2×, and five with 1.5×. For those with typical vision, one child was tested with 2.5×, six with 2×, and thirteen with 1.5×.</p></sec><sec id="S12"><title>Adults</title><p id="P26">Adults completed the same three tasks as the children with the same stimuli (minus reward animations), with the addition of a Gaussian fixation point near the bottom of the monitor. Stimuli were presented monocularly to the dominant eye and viewed peripherally at four eccentricities: 2.5°, 5°, 10°, and 15° in the upper visual field.</p><p id="P27">On each trial of the acuity and crowding-extent tasks, the fixation point first appeared for 500ms. This was followed by the target, either in isolation (acuity task) or surrounded by the ghost flankers (crowding-extent task) for 500ms. A circular 1/f noise mask with a diameter of 1/3 the target eccentricity was then presented for 250ms. A different mask was presented on each trial. After the presentation of the mask, observers had unlimited time to make a 4AFC response on the target orientation. A 500ms inter-trial interval followed, with the fixation dot on screen. Each staircase consisted of 45 trials, with observers completing two staircases per eccentricity. For each observer, acuity and crowding-extent values were taken from the average gap-size threshold across the two staircases at each eccentricity.</p><p id="P28">The orientation-matching task was largely identical to the children’s version (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1E</xref>). Stimuli were presented with a gap size of 3× the acuity threshold. With a target-flanker separation of 1.1× the target diameter, this gave absolute target-flanker separations that increased with eccentricity, averaging 0.64° at 2.5° eccentricity (range= 0.57-0.72°), 1.01° at 5° (range= 0.93-1.12°), 1.91° at 10° (range= 1.39-2.28°), and 3.13° at 15° (range= 2.39-4.41°). These values fell within the crowding extent measured for each observer. Average values were also close to being a constant proportion of the target eccentricity, corresponding to 0.26×, 0.20×, 0.19×, and 0.21× the target eccentricity, respectively. Besides the slight elevation at 2.5° eccentricity, the strength of crowding should therefore have been similar at all eccentricities.</p><p id="P29">The trial presentation sequence was similar to the acuity and crowding tasks, with a fixation dot appearing for 500ms, followed by the target for 500ms. The target was either presented in isolation or surrounded by flankers of a ±30° or ±90° orientation difference. A 1/f noise mask was then presented for 250ms, at which point a reference stimulus identical to the target appeared at fixation at a random orientation. The size of the reference matched the target. Observers had unlimited time to adjust the reference stimulus to match the orientation of the previously presented target. Adults completed 5 blocks of 100 trials per eccentricity, resulting in a total of 2000 trials per observer. In each block, 20 trials were included for each of the 5 flanker conditions. Blocks for each eccentricity were interleaved to counter any practice effects. Observers received auditory feedback in the form of a beep when their estimate of the target orientation was offset by more than ±35°. All other parameters were identical to the children’s version of the tasks.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="S13" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="S14"><title>Acuity and Crowding Extent</title><p id="P30">The acuity and crowding-extent tasks each gave a measure of the gap size of the Vac-Man target required for performance to reach a particular point (62.5% for acuity; 80% for crowding). For acuity, the gap size was the value of interest. For crowding, the spatial extent value was calculated as the radius from the centre of the target to the centre of one flanker. This centre-to-centre separation was equal to the target diameter (which was five times the gap size) multiplied by 1.1 (the relative separation between elements). Here we consider the adult results first, followed by the children.</p><sec id="S15"><title>Adult Periphery</title><p id="P31">Gap-size (acuity) thresholds for the four eccentricities can be seen in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2A</xref>. Thresholds increased with eccentricity, with 2.32±0.07 arcmins (mean±SEM) at 2.5° eccentricity, 3.68±0.07 arcmins at 5°, 6.95±0.34 arcmins at 10°, and 11.36±0.72 arcmins at 15°. A one-way ANOVA revealed a significant effect of eccentricity, (F[1.47, 13.20] = 110.34, <italic>P</italic>&lt; .0001, Greenhouse-Geisser corrected), demonstrating the well-known reduction of acuity in the periphery.</p><p id="P32">The spatial extent of crowding at each eccentricity is presented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2B</xref>. Crowding also increased with eccentricity, though with a vast difference in scale from acuity, with 0.82±0.04° (mean±SEM) at 2.5°, 1.88±0.11° at 5°, 3.81±0.17° at 10°, and 6.83±0.44° at 15° eccentricity. A one-way ANOVA accordingly revealed a significant effect of eccentricity (F[1.23, 11.07] = 146.20, <italic>P</italic>&lt; .0001, Greenhouse-Geisser corrected).</p></sec><sec id="S16"><title>Typically Developing and Amblyopic Fovea</title><p id="P33">Acuity values for children with typical vision and amblyopia are plotted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3A</xref>. Gap-size thresholds for the left and right eyes of children with typical vision averaged 1.07±0.07 and 0.94±0.06 arcmins respectively (close to a Snellen acuity of 6/6). There was no significant difference between these values (paired samples t-test: t[19]=2.37, <italic>P</italic>= .5), indicating no interocular differences in acuity. Reduced acuity levels were evident in the amblyopic eye of the amblyopic group, with an average of 4.03±0.67 arcmins compared to 1.14±0.14 arcmin for the unaffected fellow fixating eye (equivalent to Snellen acuities of 6/24 and 6/6). This interocular difference was significant (paired samples t-test: t[19] =4.13, <italic>P</italic>&lt; .0001), consistent with the characteristic acuity deficit in amblyopia. Acuity in the fellow eye did not differ from the acuity of the children with typical vision (unpaired t-test between the fellow fixating eye and the mean of both eyes in children with typical vision: t[38]= -0.88, <italic>P</italic>= .38).</p><p id="P34">Values for the spatial extent of crowding for children are in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3B</xref>. For children with typical vision, the extent of crowding averaged 0.17±0.01° for the left eye and 0.15±0.02° for the right eye, with no significant interocular difference (paired samples t-test: t[19]=1.58, <italic>P</italic>= .13). For the amblyopic group, the extent of crowding was greater in the amblyopic eye, averaging 0.79±0.13° compared to 0.16±0.01° for the fellow fixating eye (paired samples t-test: t[19]=4.85, <italic>P</italic>&lt; .0001). There was no difference in the extent of crowding between the fellow fixating eye of the children with amblyopia and the mean of both eyes in children with typical vision (unpaired t-test: t[38]=-0.21, <italic>P</italic>= .83).</p></sec></sec><sec id="S17"><title>Orientation-Matching Task</title><p id="P35">Responses in the matching task were recorded as the perceived orientation of the target on each trial, which were subtracted from the veridical target value to give error values. Frequency histograms were constructed to tally the errors from ±180° in 10° bins, separately for each flanker condition. For children, this gave five distributions of response errors per observer. For adults, responses were combined across the five repeat blocks to give five distributions for each eccentricity. Both children and adults produced error distributions that were mirror-symmetric in conditions with target-flanker differences of opposite sign (-30°and 30°, -90° and 90°). As a result, the sign of the response errors was reversed in conditions with negative differences in order to sum the distributions. For each group, this gave three response-error distributions per observer (and per eccentricity for adults): unflanked, ±30° target-flanker difference, and ±90° target-flanker difference.</p><sec id="S18"><title>Adult Periphery</title><p id="P36"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref> plots response-error histograms for each eccentricity in the adult periphery. For unflanked targets (left column), the distribution of response errors was unimodal across all eccentricities (panels A-D), with a peak at 0° and a narrow width. As such, when the target was presented in isolation, observers reported its orientation with good accuracy and precision, with increasing eccentricity having no effect on these estimates.</p><p id="P37">With flankers that differed by 30° (middle column), response-error distributions were also unimodal at all four eccentricities, though distributions shifted towards the flankers, with a peak at orientations between the target and flanker values (shown as dashed lines). There was also an increase in the spread of response errors relative to the unflanked condition. In other words, crowding had a disruptive effect on both accuracy and response precision.</p><p id="P38">When flankers differed by 90° from the target, response-error distributions became bimodal (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>, right column). The first peak was concentrated at 0°, indicating responses near to the veridical target value, with the second at 90°, near to the flanker orientation. The location of these peaks did not change with eccentricity, though the height of the peaks did. At lower eccentricities, the frequency of responses near the target was greater (i.e. the peak centred on 0° was highest), whereas at larger eccentricities responses near the flanker orientation became more frequent. In other words, observers were increasingly likely to report orientations near to the flankers as eccentricity increased.</p><p id="P39">These response-error distributions allow us to draw a number of conclusions regarding the perceptual effects of crowding in the adult periphery. Observers were both accurate and precise when reporting the orientation of unflanked targets. With ±30° target-flanker differences, crowding primarily led observers to indicate intermediate orientations between the target and flankers. These responses can be classified as assimilation errors. Crowding with ±90° target-flanker differences led to a mixture of responses near to either the target or flanker orientations. The latter can be classified as substitution errors, which increased in frequency with eccentricity.</p></sec><sec id="S19"><title>Typically Developing and Amblyopic Fovea</title><p id="P40"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref> shows histograms of the response errors for children. When the target was unflanked, children with typical vision (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5A, left</xref>) gave a unimodal distribution of response errors centred near 0°, with a slightly broader width than that found with adults in the periphery (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>). The group with amblyopia (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5B, left</xref>) showed a similar pattern of errors when stimuli were presented in the fovea of their amblyopic eye, with the peak centred on 0° and a similar bandwidth to children with typical vision. In other words, both groups could accurately report the orientation of the isolated target element with good precision.</p><p id="P41">When flankers differed from the target by 30°, both groups of children showed unimodal response-error distributions with a peak shifted to fall between the veridical target and flanker orientations. Both groups showed an increase in response-error variability compared to the unflanked condition, with greater variability in the amblyopic group. This shift in the peak of response errors, combined with reduced response precision relative to unflanked performance, is similar to that observed in the adult periphery.</p><p id="P42">When flankers differed by 90°, response-error distributions for both groups of children became bimodal. In each case, responses were most frequently near to the target orientation, with a secondary peak in responses close to 90°, indicative of flanker reports. These flanker responses were more frequent in children with amblyopia. There was also an increase in the variability of responses relative to unflanked performance, but to a lesser extent than when the flankers differed by 30°. These response-error distributions were highly similar to those of adults in the near periphery (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4 A&amp;B</xref>).</p><p id="P43">Taken together, children performed well when required to judge the orientation of unflanked targets, giving responses that were both accurate and precise. With ±30° target-flanker differences, errors were primarily reports of intermediate orientations between the target and flankers. As with adults in this condition, these can be classified as assimilation errors. With ±90° target-flanker differences, children primarily reported values near to the target orientation, with a secondary rate of responses to the flanker orientation. The latter can be classified as substitution errors, which arose at a similar rate to the errors made by adults in the near periphery. Therefore, on a group level, children with typical vision and amblyopia made the same systematic errors with stimuli viewed foveally as did adults with stimuli viewed peripherally.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="S20"><title>Modelling</title><p id="P44">Given the common pattern of crowded errors made by adults and children with both typical vision and amblyopia, we next sought to examine the basis of these systematic perceptual outcomes with a computational model. Our approach was inspired by the models of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R95">van den Berg, Roerdink, and Cornelissen (2010</xref>) and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40">Harrison and Bex (2015)</xref>, and similar to recent models of crowding for colour and motion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36">Greenwood &amp; Parsons, 2020</xref>). The model had three stages, summarised in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>.</p><p id="P45"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6 A</xref> shows example stimuli for each condition. For ease of modelling, response errors were directly simulated using the orientation difference from the target as inputs (rather than absolute orientations). As in the results presented above, 0° indicated no error. In the first stage of the model (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6B</xref>), the response of a population of detectors selective for orientation was simulated, similar to neurons in primary visual cortex (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R79">Schiller, Finlay, &amp; Volman, 1976</xref>). Each detector responded to a range of orientations, according to a Gaussian tuning function with a peak sensitivity centred on a particular orientation, as in <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD1">equation 1</xref>: <disp-formula id="FD1"><label>(1)</label><mml:math id="M1"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:msup><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="P46">Here, <italic>r(θ)</italic> is the population response at a given orientation (θ), ranging from α180°. The value a set the height of the detector sensitivity (set to 1), μ set the orientation producing the peak response, and σ gave the bandwidth, set to 30° to match the selectivity of neurons in cortical area V1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">De Valois, Yund, &amp; Hepler, 1982</xref>). Gaussian noise <italic>n</italic> was added with a magnitude of γ (the first free parameter). This ‘early noise’ allowed us to fit sensitivity to unflanked orientations in particular, though the same noise parameter was used across all conditions.</p><p id="P47">Based on the principles of population coding (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R76">Pouget, Dayan, &amp; Zemel, 2000</xref>), the resulting population-response distribution is a Gaussian function centred on the orientation of the Landolt-C stimulus, with a bandwidth equivalent to the underlying sensitivity bandwidth of the detectors. On trials when the input to the model was a target presented in isolation (unflanked), the resulting population responses were centred near 0°. Responses from an example unflanked trial are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6B</xref> (top panel). For illustration, in this example trial the early noise is set to 0.1.</p><p id="P48">In the 30° and 90° flanker difference conditions, population responses were generated for both the target <bold><italic>θ<sub>t</sub></italic></bold> and the flanker orientation <bold><italic>θ<sub>f</sub></italic></bold> on each trial. Flanker responses were generated using <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD1">equation 1</xref>, though with a second free parameter for the noise term (‘late noise’), which allowed us to determine the degree of performance impairment induced by the flankers. The resulting population responses to the flanker orientation were centred either near 30° or 90°, respectively. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6B</xref> shows population responses from an example trial for each of the two flanker conditions (middle and bottom rows), with the late noise parameter set to 0.2.</p><p id="P49">The second stage of the model simulated the effects of crowding as the pooling of population responses to the target and flanker elements. A weighted sum of the population response to the target and flankers was taken that allowed modulation of the precise combination of these responses. The weighted combination of responses to the target and flankers was given as: <disp-formula id="FD2"><label>(2)</label><mml:math id="M2"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="P50">Here, <bold><italic>w<sub>t</sub></italic></bold> and <bold><italic>w<sub>f</sub></italic></bold> were the weights for the population responses to the target and flankers, respectively. The flanker weight ranged from 0-1, with the weight of the target being one minus the flanker weight. As the data from all groups indicated that response-error distributions in the 30° flanker difference condition differed from those in the 90° flanker difference condition, the flanker weight was independent in these conditions. This gave two additional free parameters: the flanker weight for the 30° condition (<bold><italic>w<sub>f</sub></italic><sub>30</sub></bold>)and that for the 90° condition (<bold><italic>w<sub>f</sub></italic><sub>90</sub></bold>) to give four free parameters in total.</p><p id="P51"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6C</xref> shows the second stage for each flanker condition on an example trial. With a 30° target-flanker difference and a flanker weight of 0.5, both target and flanker distributions contribute equally to the pooled response. Their breadth means that the combined population response distribution is broadly unimodal, with a peak that shifts away from 0° towards the 30° flanker orientation. With a 90° target-flanker difference and the same 0.5 flanker weight, the combined population response distribution becomes bimodal, with peaks near the target and flanker orientations.</p><p id="P52">In the third and final stage of the model, a ‘decision’ on the perceived target orientation was made by extracting the maximum response from the population on each trial. For unflanked targets (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6D</xref>), the population response to the target carried through to the final stage, and the peak of the response is near the target at 8°. For the 30° and 90° flanker difference conditions, the peak of the combined target and flanker population responses was taken. In the 30° flanker condition, this example trial gave a shift in the peak towards the flankers (at 18°) – an assimilation error. A decrease in the flanker weight here would shift the peak back towards the target orientation (0°), and vice versa. In the 90° flanker condition, the combination of the bimodal distribution and noise results in a peak closer to the flankers (at 87°) – a flanker substitution error. A decrease in the flanker weight here would increase the likelihood of responses laying around the 0° target value, rather than around the 90° flanker.</p><p id="P53">Our model simulation included 1000 trials per flanker condition. For comparison between these simulated responses and the measured error distributions, the output of the model was binned in 10° increments. This binning did not alter the output of the model in a qualitative fashion. The best-fitting parameters for all groups were determined using a two-stage fitting procedure. The initial coarse fit involved a grid search through the parameter space in pre-defined steps. From this we derived the parameters that best fit the data in the grid using the least-squared error (LSE) between response-error distributions and the simulated distributions from 1000 trials, summed across all 3 conditions. In the second-stage fine fit, the best parameters from the coarse fit were used to seed the analysis, with the best-fitting parameters determined by minimising the LSE using <italic>fminsearch</italic> in Matlab, again taking the summed difference between data and simulated distributions from 1000 trials. We then ran 1000 iterations of the model with the best-fitting parameters for each dataset.</p><p id="P54">We also considered the response errors that would arise if crowding does not have a systematic effect on target appearance, but rather distorts or adds noise to the target orientation. To do so, we tested an additional model that did not contain the second pooling stage, but rather simply added noise to the population response when flankers were present. Although distortions may be locally systematic (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R77">Pugh, 1958</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R83">Sireteanu, Lagreze, &amp; Constantinescu, 1993</xref>), in the present task this would cause errors when the target and/or flanker gaps were rotated to appear in some visual field locations and not others. The variety of orientations and target-flanker combinations in our task would then produce a random distribution of errors across the experiment as a whole, particularly when errors were aligned to the target orientation rather than their absolute orientation (since distortions should depend on the retinotopic location of the gap in each element), and even more so once errors were pooled at the group level given the idiosyncrasy of these distortions. Errors due to attentional lapses or developmental issues with short-term memory (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R100">Witton, Talcott, &amp; Henning, 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R62">Manning et al., 2018</xref>) should similarly manifest as random errors.</p><p id="P55">The noise model had three stages, the first of which was identical to the population pooling model, using <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD1">equation 1</xref> above to produce a population response to the target. Early noise was again the first free parameter. Population responses to the flankers were not simulated. Rather, the second stage differed in that the population response to the target was simply subjected to an additional noise parameter: <disp-formula id="FD3"><label>(3)</label><mml:math id="M3"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mi>η</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="P56">Here, y<sub>t</sub> is the population response to the target, <bold>σ<sub>η</sub></bold> the added random noise and <bold><italic>β</italic></bold> was the magnitude of this late noise (the second and final free parameter in the noise model). The third stage of the model was then identical to the final stage of the pooling model, with the maximum response taken as the ‘decision’ of the model on each trial. As with the population pooling model, we ran 1000 trials of this 3-stage model for each condition, using the procedure described above. MATLAB code for both models is available online<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN1">i</xref></sup>.</p><sec id="S21"><title>Model Simulations of Group Data</title><sec id="S22"><title>Adults</title><p id="P57"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref> shows the result of 1000 iterations of the best-fitting population pooling model for the adult mean data at each eccentricity. For unflanked targets, the model almost perfectly captures the response errors, with early noise values that were similar across all eccentricities (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table A4</xref>, and plotted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref> as white triangles). When the target was crowded, response distributions became noisier and more broadly distributed, with a lower peak response. The model captured this through the addition of late noise to the flanker population response, which added further disruption to the pooling stage. Values for the late noise parameter showed a slight decrease with eccentricity, from values of 1.22 at 2.5° to 0.73 at 15° eccentricity.</p><p id="P58">The systematic nature of the response errors induced by flankers were driven by the flanker weight parameters. With ±30° target-flanker differences, the model clearly replicates the response-error distribution in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref> (middle column) where the majority of the errors were between the target and flanker orientations. These flanker weights increased with eccentricity from 0.52 at 2.5° eccentricity to 0.64 at 15°. With ±90° target-flanker differences, there was a marked effect of eccentricity, with the proportion of flanker responses increasing with eccentricity. This was captured well by the model, which followed this pattern of increasing flanker responses with an increase in the flanker weights from 0.34 at 2.5° to 0.52 at 15° eccentricity. On the whole, the model follows the profile of response errors in all conditions.</p><p id="P59">In contrast, the noise model generally performed poorly, as shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure A1</xref> of <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Appendix B</xref>. Although the model was able to capture errors around the target in the unflanked condition, it failed to produce the shift towards the flankers in the 30° condition and the bimodal pattern of errors in the 90° condition. Clearly the addition of noise alone, ignoring the identity of the flankers, is insufficient to account for these errors. To determine which of the two models best fit the response distributions, we computed Akaike Information Criterion (AIC) values (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">Akaike, 1974</xref>) which take the least squared error (LSE), and correct for the number of parameters included in each model (since the pooling model had four free parameters while the noise model had two). Despite this correction, the superior performance of the population pooling model is clear from the AIC values, shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figure 8A</xref> (and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Tables A3</xref> &amp; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">A4</xref>), where lower AIC values indicate better model fits to the data. In adults, the pooling model outperformed the noise model at all eccentricities. As such, the group response errors could not be accounted for by a process that merely adds random noise to the target orientation.</p><p id="P60">To reproduce the systematic shifts in these error distributions, the pooling model used two additional free parameters for flanker weights in the ±30° and ±90° flanker conditions. In <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Appendix C</xref> we compare this with the performance of a three-parameter version of the pooling model, where the same weight was applied in both flanker conditions. Although this three-parameter model performed better than the noise model (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table A5</xref>), it was less effective at capturing the systematic pattern of crowded errors than the four-parameter pooling model (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure A2</xref>). It is thus important that these models incorporate variations in the strength of crowding with target-flanker differences in orientation.</p></sec><sec id="S23"><title>Children</title><p id="P61"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref> shows the simulated distributions for the group data of children with typical vision (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5A</xref>) and amblyopia (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5B</xref>), each computed as the mean of 1000 model iterations. In the unflanked condition, the model captures the Gaussian distribution of response errors well for both groups, with early noise values higher for both groups than those of adults (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table A4</xref>). When the target was crowded, the combined population response again became noisier and more broadly distributed, with a lower peak response. This was again captured by the model with the addition of late noise, values of which were again higher than those used for adults.</p><p id="P62">To reproduce the shift in response error distributions for the crowding condition with ±30° target-flanker differences, flanker weights in the model were similar to those of the two closest eccentricities in adults. With ±90° target-flanker differences, the model successfully captured both peaks of the bimodal distribution of response errors in each of the two groups, again using weights similar to adult values in the parafovea. Overall, the model successfully captured the pattern of systematic errors observed for both groups of children. The noise model again provided a substantially poorer fit to the data (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Appendix B</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure A1</xref>), demonstrating that the errors of children with typical and amblyopic vision cannot be accounted for by a process that merely adds random noise to the target orientation. The four-parameter pooling model was similarly better able to characterise response errors than the three-parameter pooling model (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Appendix C</xref>), again demonstrating the need for variations in flanker weights with target-flanker similarity.</p></sec></sec><sec id="S24"><title>Model Simulations of Individual Data</title><p id="P63">Having demonstrated that the population pooling model can reproduce the observed response-error distributions using group data, we next consider how well the model can account for individual data. The model was fit using the same procedure as above, this time to data from individual observers. Because children had so few trials per condition (24 in each crowded condition), smoothing was applied to the response-error histograms using a three-point boxcar average prior to model fitting. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref> shows the best-fitting values for all free parameters of the model for each adult at the four eccentricities tested, and for each child in the groups with typical vision and amblyopia.</p><p id="P64">For the early noise parameter (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7A</xref>), values were again similar across the four eccentricities tested in adults, with mean values (shown as bars) between 0.44-0.47 and individual values from 0.32-0.64. These values were generally larger in children with typical vision (mean 0.80, range 0.40-1.68) and amblyopia (mean 0.92, range 0.40-2.54). For the late noise parameter (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7B</xref>), adult values again showed a slight decrease with eccentricity on average, with means (and ranges) of 1.47 (0.61-3.67) at 2.5°, 1.16 (0.51-2.49) at 5°, 1.01 (0.59-2.19) at 10°, and 1.12 (0.41-2.15) at 15°. Children in both groups again tended to require higher late noise values, with a mean of 1.62 (range 0.4-3.04) for those with typical vision and 2.13 (range 0.79-4.14) for those with amblyopia.</p><p id="P65">When flankers differed by ±30° from the target (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7C</xref>), flanker weights again tended to increase with eccentricity for adults, with means (ranges) of 0.48 (0.20-0.93), 0.46 (0.03-0.85), 0.58 (0.35-0.91) and 0.55 (0.33-0.94) from 2.5-15° eccentricity, though substantial individual differences are clearly apparent in the ranges. For children with typical vision and amblyopia, best-fitting flanker weights gave mean (range) values of 0.52 (0.10-0.85) and 0.53 (0.00-0.91), respectively, again corresponding to values in the adult periphery that were between those of the near periphery and the farthest eccentricities. When flankers differed by ±90° from the target (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7D</xref>), flanker weights in the adult periphery showed a clear increase with eccentricity, with means of 0.32 (0.05-0.79) at 2.5°, 0.43 (0.15-0.65) at 5°, 0.51 (0.21-0.88) at 10°, and 0.55 (0.18-0.94) at 15°. The range was again broad, indicative of individual differences. In children, the range of flanker weight values was similarly broad, with means of 0.32 (0.05-0.67) and 0.33 (0.05-0.86) that were again most similar to the closer eccentricities in adults.</p><p id="P66">A number of conclusions can be drawn from the model fits to the individual data. First, children generally required larger early noise values than adults in order for the model to simulate their response error distributions. This indicates a broad difference in the general properties of foveal vision in children and the adult periphery. Children from both groups also required greater late noise values than adults, suggesting greater difficulties in clutter that may go beyond the stimulus, perhaps into decisional processes. Flanker weights in the children were however similar to values for adults in the parafovea,particularly for the 90° flanker condition, consistent with the commonalities observed in the pattern of response errors between adults and children.</p><p id="P67">In order to determine the success of these fits to individual data, the noise model was also fit to individual response-error distributions. Comparisons of these fits are shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure A3</xref> of <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Appendix D</xref> for adults and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure A4</xref> for children. Generally, as with the fits to the group data, the noise model failed to account for the systematic shift in the pattern of response errors towards the flanker orientations. However, for some individuals the noise model approached the success of the pooling model, and in others the noise model outperformed the pooling model.</p><p id="P68">AIC values for individual fits are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figure 8B</xref>. In the adult periphery, the pooling model had lower AIC values than the noise model in 9 of 10 adults at 2.5° and 5°, and for all 10 adults at 10° and 15°. Accordingly, AIC values were significantly lower (indicating better fits) for the pooling model at all eccentricities: t[9]= -3.83, <italic>P</italic>= .004 at 2.5°; t[9]= -3.92, <italic>P</italic>= .004 at 5°; t[9]= -7.35, <italic>P</italic>&lt; .001 at 10° and t[9]= -6.20, <italic>P</italic>&lt; .001 at 15°. Those for whom the pooling model failed tended to have low error rates (as shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure A3</xref>), making it hard to discriminate between the models.</p><p id="P69">For children, all 20 of those with typical vision showed lower AIC values for the pooling model, indicating better fits, while 18 of 20 amblyopic children were better fit by the pooling model. Here too the AIC values were significantly lower for the pooling model, with t[19]= -5.96, <italic>P</italic>&lt; .001 for those with typical vision and t[19]= -3.67, <italic>P=</italic> .002 for those with amblyopia. Amongst the amblyopic children, those for whom the pooling model failed tended to have highly noisy responses (as shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure A4</xref>), which again gave similar fits for the two models. Although this tendency was present in some of the children with typical vision, this was never to the extent that the noise model outperformed the pooling model.</p><p id="P70">On the whole, the pooling model outperforms the noise model in describing the response errors of all three groups. It is particularly striking that the pooling model is able to outperform the noise model with fits to individual data, given that these distributions relied on only 24 trials for children in each crowded condition. We conclude that the errors made by adults in peripheral vision cannot be accounted for by a process that merely adds random noise to the target orientation. The same is true for children with both typical and amblyopic vision. Rather, systematic changes in the target orientation are required to capture the systematic errors in these patterns of performance.</p></sec></sec><sec id="S25" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p id="P71">Our aim was to examine the perceptual effects of crowding in the fovea of children with typical vision and amblyopia, and to assess its similarity with crowding in the typical adult periphery. In all three groups, errors in the perceived orientation of a crowded Landolt-C target systematically followed the appearance of the flanker elements. With crowded targets, children made errors that predominantly matched either intermediate orientations between the target and flankers (assimilation) with 30° target-flanker orientation differences, or the orientation of the flankers (substitution) with 90° target-flanker differences (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>). These errors matched those observed in adult peripheral vision (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>), consistent with previous studies of adults (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R70">Parkes et al., 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34">Greenwood, Bex, &amp; Dakin, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">Dakin et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">Ester, Zilber, &amp; Serences, 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40">Harrison &amp; Bex, 2015</xref>). The frequency of both assimilation and substitution errors increased with eccentricity in the typical periphery, with the errors made by children with typical vision and those with amblyopia most closely resembling the errors found at para-foveal eccentricities. In other words, children with typical vision and those with amblyopia make the same crowded errors as adults in the visual periphery. The commonality of these errors, in conjunction with other properties shared between these instances of crowding (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R57">Levi, Hariharan, &amp; Klein, 2002a</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38">Greenwood et al., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R86">Song, Levi, &amp; Pelli, 2014</xref>) leads us to conclude that a common mechanism underlies crowding in these three instances.</p><p id="P72">We further demonstrate that a weighted population pooling model can reproduce this pattern of crowded errors in the typically developing and amblyopic fovea, as well as in the adult periphery. Similar to prior approaches (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R95">van den Berg, Roerdink, &amp; Cornelissen, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40">Harrison &amp; Bex, 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36">Greenwood &amp; Parsons, 2020</xref>), we simulated crowding via the weighted pooling of population responses to the target and flanker orientations. The weights determined the relative contribution of the target/flanker population responses to the pooled response distribution, from which decisions were drawn. With this approach, assimilation errors arose with 30° target-flanker differences because the combination of the target and flanker population responses gave a unimodal distribution with a peak response at intermediate orientations. Substitution errors arose with 90° target-flanker differences due to the bimodal distribution of the pooled response – although correct target responses were usually most common, noise in the bimodal pooled response gave a secondary rate of reports near the flanker orientation. Flanker population responses also added noise to the pooled population response, in line with previous models of peripheral crowding (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34">Greenwood, Bex, &amp; Dakin, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">Ester, Klee, &amp; Awh, 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">Ester, Zilber, &amp; Serences, 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36">Greenwood &amp; Parsons, 2020</xref>). However, noise alone was insufficient to account for the errors made by either group of children or in the adult periphery (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figure 8</xref>). Indeed, the success of the population pooling model was apparent not only in the fits to group data, but also with individual distributions of response errors. As a result, we suggest that pooling models provide a likely candidate for the common mechanism in these three instances of crowding.</p><p id="P73">In order to test the viability of the population pooling model, we have of course restricted our stimuli to simple target-flanker configurations (e.g. with identical flankers in a given trial). Nonetheless, given the success of pooling models in accounting for crowding with more complex stimuli in peripheral vision, including letters (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31">Freeman, Chakravarthi, &amp; Pelli, 2012</xref>) and faces (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R50">Kalpadakis-Smith, Goffaux, &amp; Greenwood, 2018</xref>), it is likely that these approaches could similarly account for the crowding of complex stimuli in the developing and amblyopic fovea. The pooling process used herein is also consistent with higher-dimensional ‘texture’ pooling models, which can simulate crowding in natural scenes through the extraction of image statistics across large regions of the peripheral field (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">Balas, Nakano, &amp; Rosenholtz, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32">Freeman &amp; Simoncelli, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R51">Keshvari &amp; Rosenholtz, 2016</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R78">Rosenholtz, Yu, &amp; Keshvari, 2019</xref>). Both assimilation and substitution errors have indeed been simulated with this approach in the adult periphery (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R51">Keshvari &amp; Rosenholtz, 2016</xref>), making it likely that a similar process could work in the developing and amblyopic fovea, though it is unclear whether these models could also predict the increase in random responses found in children, as well as the individual differences observed.</p><p id="P74">The systematic effects of crowding that we observe are difficult to reconcile with higher-level models of crowding. For instance, attentional models (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R88">Strasburger, Harvey, &amp; Rentschler, 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R87">Strasburger, 2005</xref>) predict a predominance of substitution errors due to an inability to accurately focus spatial attention. The assimilation errors that we observe with 30° target-flanker differences are difficult to explain within this framework. Similarly, grouping theories propose that crowding is determined by Gestalt principles in a top-down fashion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43">Herzog, Sayim, Chicherov, &amp; Manassi, 2015</xref>). These models fail to account for our data in two ways. First, they make no prediction regarding the systematic perceptual outcomes of crowding, focusing instead on the performance decrements induced by clutter. Second, their top-down operation is inconsistent with the monocular elevations in foveal crowding found in amblyopia – the same stimulus can cause crowding effects when presented to one eye, but not the other.</p><p id="P75">Consistent with prior reports of individual differences in the spatial extent of crowding (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R92">Toet &amp; Levi, 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R75">Petrov &amp; Meleshkevich, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37">Greenwood, Szinte, Sayim, &amp; Cavanagh, 2017</xref>), our results also reveal substantial individual differences in the perceptual effects of crowding in both adults and children. For instance, with the 30° target-flanker difference, some typically developing children reported clearly intermediate orientations, whereas others reported orientations more similar to the flankers (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure A4</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Appendix D</xref>). The pooling model was nonetheless able to account for these individual differences through variations in the four free parameters. Although children showed substantial variations in these parameters relative to adults, some of this variation may be due to differences in age, given the developmental trajectory of crowding (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R49">Jeon et al., 2010</xref>), as well as variations in the extent of disruption from amblyopia.</p><p id="P76">Further evidence for a common mechanism for peripheral, developing, and amblyopic crowding comes from its featural selectivity. Both children and adults (in the near periphery) gave more responses near to the correct target orientation when target and flankers differed by ±90° than when they differed by ±30°. Our pooling model reproduced these differences with lower flanker weights for ±90° vs. ±30° flankers, which gave better fits to the data for all groups than a pooling model with a single weighting parameter for both conditions (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Appendix C</xref>). This finding is consistent with the selectivity of peripheral crowding for target-flanker similarity in orientation, whereby errors decrease when elements are less similar (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">Andriessen &amp; Bouma, 1976</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R54">Leat, Li, &amp; Epp, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R58">Levi, Hariharan, &amp; Klein, 2002b</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39">Hariharan, Levi, &amp; Klein, 2005</xref>). Here we show that target-flanker similarity also matters in developing and amblyopic crowding. This is inconsistent with prior reports that amblyopic crowding in adults disrupts target recognition regardless of target-flanker similarity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R44">Hess, Dakin, Tewfik, &amp; Brown, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39">Hariharan, Levi, &amp; Klein, 2005</xref>). Interestingly variations in featural selectivity are also evident in our results. At higher eccentricities in the adult periphery, the frequency of substitution errors increased with 90° target-flanker differences, suggesting that the selectivity for target-flanker similarity may decrease with eccentricity. This is also evident in the parameters of the pooling model (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7</xref>), where flanker weights for the two conditions converged at higher eccentricities. Following suggestions that foveal crowding in amblyopia can be linked with an equivalent eccentricity in the typical periphery (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R60">Levi, Klein, &amp; Aitsebaomo, 1985</xref>), we note that the developing and amblyopic fovea resemble para-foveal eccentricities more than the far periphery in terms of both the selectivity for target-flanker similarity and the systematicity of crowded errors.</p><p id="P77">Given the consistency of the response-error distributions in peripheral, amblyopic, and developing crowding, and the success of the population pooling model in reproducing them, we suggest that a common neural basis could underlie these effects. Because the weights in our pooling model are central to the crowding process, the question becomes: what determines the variations in these flanker weights? We suggest two possible factors. First, the increase in the extent of crowding with eccentricity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">Bouma, 1970</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R92">Toet &amp; Levi, 1992</xref>) has been attributed to increases in receptive field size (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R70">Parkes et al.,2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R67">Motter, 2009</xref>) and/or the overlap between receptive fields (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">Dayan &amp; Solomon, 2010</xref>). Individual differences in crowding are indeed correlated with population receptive field (pRF) size in V2 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42">He, Wang, &amp; Fang, 2019</xref>), with increased pRF sizes observed in the amblyopic fovea in areas V1-V3 compared to the typical fovea (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">Clavagnier, Dumoulin, &amp; Hess, 2015</xref>). The role of receptive field size in developmental crowding is less clear, with neuroimaging studies suggesting that pRFs reach adult-like sizes by 6 years of age (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">Dekker et al., 2019</xref>), despite foveal crowding being elevated until as late as 12 years (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">Atkinson &amp; Braddick, 1983</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">Atkinson et al., 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R49">Jeon et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38">Greenwood et al., 2012</xref>). It is possible however that the spatial selectivity of visual neurons may change in later childhood, given for instance the maturation of connections in primary visual cortex (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R48">Huttenlocher, de Courten, Garey, &amp; Van der Loos, 1982</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R47">Huttenlocher &amp; Dabholkar, 1997</xref>), and the later maturation of centre-surround receptive fields in extrastriate cortex (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R103">Zhang et al., 2005</xref>).</p><p id="P78">Alternatively, the rise in crowding with eccentricity has also been attributed to decreases in the cortical distance between target and flanker elements (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R68">Motter &amp; Simoni, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R73">Pelli, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R63">Mareschal, Morgan, &amp; Solomon, 2010</xref>) driven by cortical magnification (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">Daniel &amp; Whitteridge, 1961</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R96">Van Essen, Newsome, &amp; Maunsell, 1984</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R80">Sereno et al., 1995</xref>). Individual differences in cortical magnification may then explain variations in crowding, similar to proposals regarding variations in acuity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27">Duncan &amp; Boynton, 2003</xref>) and perceived object size (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R69">Moutsiana et al., 2016</xref>). As well as spatial variations, the featural selectivity of crowding has also been argued to follow cortical distance – changes in orientation may shift target and flanker signals along orientation columns in visual cortex (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R63">Mareschal, Morgan, &amp; Solomon, 2010</xref>), which could cause a reduction in weights in a similar manner to changes in target-flanker separation. Because amblyopia is known to produce a reduction in neurons responding to the amblyopic eye in areas V1 and V2 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">Crawford &amp; von Noorden, 1979</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">Bi et al., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R81">Shooner et al., 2015</xref>), the increased crowding with this condition could also derive from a reduction in cortical magnification. However, neuroimaging studies have thus far failed to observe differences in cortical magnification in either amblyopia (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">Clavagnier, Dumoulin, &amp; Hess, 2015</xref>) or in the course of typical development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">Dekker et al., 2019</xref>). Of course, our current data cannot distinguish between these effects of receptive field size/overlap and cortical distance. We suggest that one or both of these factors might drive the variations in weights that determine both the strength of crowding and its effect on the appearance of crowded objects.</p><p id="P79">An alternative explanation for these variations in crowding is that they may reflect differences in the positional uncertainty regarding the target element. Positional uncertainty could create source confusion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R101">Wolford, 1975</xref>) either through the mislocalisation of features or whole letters (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R89">Strasburger, Rentschler, &amp; Jüttner, 2011</xref>). A rise in positional uncertainty with eccentricity could in particular explain the rise in substitution-type errors found in the ±90° flanker condition. Indeed, both peripheral vision and amblyopic foveal vision are characterised by increased positional uncertainty (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R46">Hussain et al., 2015</xref>). Similarly, positional uncertainty may recede in the course of development, given the observation that Vernier acuity does not reach adult levels until the early teens (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">Carkeet, Levi, &amp; Manny, 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R84">Skoczenski &amp; Norcia, 2002</xref>). As such, some proportion of the substitution errors found with 90° target-flanker differences may be attributable to position uncertainty in the adult periphery, as well as in children with amblyopia and typical vision. This is not necessarily inconsistent with pooling models of crowding, and indeed some have incorporated both processes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31">Freeman, Chakravarthi, &amp; Pelli, 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41">Harrison &amp; Bex, 2017</xref>). Our model also captures the increase in errors with ±90° flankers across eccentricity via an increase in the flanker weights for this condition, which could derive from positional uncertainty. This would however speak against the idea raised above that a common factor could drive all of the variations in crowding, as some have suggested (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">Agaoglu &amp; Chung, 2016</xref>). Importantly however, position uncertainty alone cannot explain all of our results, given the predominance of assimilation errors observed with 30° target-flanker differences.</p><p id="P80">Despite the above-noted similarities between groups, differences are also evident. The model fits to data from both sets of children required higher levels of early noise in order to match performance, consistent with the broader elevations in low-level vision such as acuity and contrast sensitivity, both in amblyopia (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R65">McKee, Levi, &amp; Movshon, 2003</xref>) and during development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R82">Simons, 1983</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R55">Leat, Yadav, &amp; Irving, 2009</xref>). This could also be driven by attention lapses or limitations of either short-term memory, motor coordination, or decision-making factors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R100">Witton, Talcott, &amp; Henning, 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R62">Manning et al., 2018</xref>). A small subset of children with amblyopia were further noted to have made a disproportionate number of random reports (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure A4</xref>), giving orientations that did not correspond to either the target or the flankers. For these cases, a model that simply adds noise to the target population response performed best (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figure 8</xref>). This increased response variability could be due to attentional lapses, or to perceptual distortions that characterise amblyopic vision (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R77">Pugh, 1958</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R83">Sireteanu, Lagreze, &amp; Constantinescu, 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">Barrett et al., 2003</xref>). More broadly however, these random factors cannot account for the systematic effects of crowding on target appearance, though it is possible that they acted as an additional source of errors, particularly for some children.</p><p id="P81">We have presented a population pooling model that can characterise the perceptual effects of crowding in three instances: the amblyopic fovea, the typically developing fovea, and the adult periphery. On the basis of this common mechanism, we can make predictions for a diverse range of conditions where elevated crowding has been observed, including Posterior Cortical Atrophy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">Crutch &amp; Warrington, 2007</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">2009</xref>), dyslexia (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33">Geiger &amp; Lettvin, 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">Atkinson, 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R64">Martelli et al., 2009</xref>), and infantile nystagmus (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">Chung &amp; Bedell, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R71">Pascal &amp; Abadi, 1995</xref>). Several of these conditions report similar properties to those observed herein. For instance, crowding in Posterior Cortical Atrophy exhibits a selectivity for target-flanker similarity that matches that observed in typical peripheral vision (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R102">Yong et al., 2014</xref>). In these instances, we would expect to see the same systematic pattern of errors as in the present study. In other cases, the properties of crowding appear to differ. For instance, the spatial extent of interference zones are elongated horizontally in idiopathic infantile nystagmus, unlike the radially symmetric zones observed in typical vision and the amblyopic fovea (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R91">Tailor et al., 2021</xref>). In these cases, the pattern of response errors may differ substantially. By examining the nature of the errors produced in these distinct conditions, we can thus determine the generality of this common mechanism for crowding.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="SM"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1"><label>Appendices</label><media xlink:href="EMS144201-supplement-Appendices.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" id="d5aAeFbB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack id="S26"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>This work was funded by the Moorfields Eye Charity (ST1411F) and the UK Medical Research Council (MR/K024817/1). Thanks to Dina Prapa from Moorfields Eye Hospital for help with participant recruitment.</p></ack><fn-group><fn id="FN1"><label>i</label><p id="P82">Code available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://github.com/eccentricvision/KidsCrowdModels">http://github.com/eccentricvision/KidsCrowdModels</ext-link></p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><ref id="R1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Agaoglu</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name><name><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>STL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Can (should) theories of crowding be unified?</article-title><source>Journal of Vision</source><year>2016</year><volume>16</volume><issue>15</issue><fpage>10</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Akaike</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A new look at the statistical model identification</article-title><source>IEEE Transactions on Automatic Control</source><year>1974</year><volume>19</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>716</fpage><lpage>723</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Andriessen</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bouma</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Eccentric vision: Adverse interactions between line segments</article-title><source>Vision Research</source><year>1976</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>71</fpage><lpage>78</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Atkinson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Review of human visual development: Crowding and dyslexia</chapter-title><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Stein</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group><source>Vision and visual dysfunction</source><publisher-name>Macmillan Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc><year>1991</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>44</fpage><lpage>57</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><element-citation publication-type="confproc"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Atkinson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Anker</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>McIntyre</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><source>The Cambridge Crowding Cards for preschool visual acuity testing</source><conf-name>Paper presented at the Transactions of the 6th International Orthoptic Congress</conf-name><conf-loc>Harrogate, UK</conf-loc><year>1987</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Atkinson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Braddick</surname><given-names>OJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assessment of visual acuity in infancy and early childhood</article-title><source>Acta Ophthalmologica Scandinavica</source><year>1983</year><volume>157</volume><fpage>18</fpage><lpage>26</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Balas</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakano</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosenholtz</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A summary-statistic representation in peripheral vision explains visual crowding</article-title><source>Journal of Vision</source><year>2009</year><volume>9</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>13</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barrett</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></name><name><surname>Pacey</surname><given-names>IE</given-names></name><name><surname>Bradley</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Thibos</surname><given-names>LN</given-names></name><name><surname>Morrill</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nonveridical visual perception in human amblyopia</article-title><source>Investigative Ophthalmology &amp; Visual Science</source><year>2003</year><volume>44</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1555</fpage><lpage>1567</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Tao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Harwerth</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name><name><surname>Chino</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Neuronal responses in visual area V2 (V2) of macaque monkeys with strabismic amblyopia</article-title><source>Cerebral Cortex</source><year>2011</year><volume>21</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>2033</fpage><lpage>2045</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bouma</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Interaction effects in parafoveal letter recognition</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1970</year><volume>226</volume><issue>241</issue><fpage>177</fpage><lpage>178</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brainard</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Psychophysics Toolbox</article-title><source>Spatial Vision</source><year>1997</year><volume>10</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>433</fpage><lpage>436</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carkeet</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Levi</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Manny</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Development of Vernier acuity in childhood</article-title><source>Optometry and Vision Science</source><year>1997</year><volume>74</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>741</fpage><lpage>750</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name><name><surname>Levi</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Legge</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Spatial frequency and contrast properties of crowding</article-title><source>Vision Research</source><year>2001</year><volume>41</volume><issue>14</issue><fpage>1833</fpage><lpage>1850</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>STL</given-names></name><name><surname>Bedell</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of retinal image motion on visual acuity and contour interaction in congenital nystagmus</article-title><source>Vision Research</source><year>1995</year><volume>35</volume><issue>21</issue><fpage>3071</fpage><lpage>3082</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clavagnier</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Dumoulin</surname><given-names>SO</given-names></name><name><surname>Hess</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Is the cortical deficit in amblyopia due to reduced cortical magnification, loss of neural resolution, or neural disorganisation?</article-title><source>The Journal of Neuroscience</source><year>2015</year><volume>35</volume><issue>44</issue><fpage>14740</fpage><lpage>14755</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coates</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Levi</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Touch</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Sabesan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Foveal Crowding Resolved</article-title><source>Scientific Reports</source><year>2018</year><volume>8</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>9177</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coates</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Ludowici</surname><given-names>CJH</given-names></name><name><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>STL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The generality of the critical spacing for crowded optotypes: From Bouma to the 21st century</article-title><source>Journal of Vision</source><year>2021</year><volume>21</volume><issue>11:18</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>22</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crawford</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>von Noorden</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effects of short-term experimental strabismus on the visual system in Macaca mulatta</article-title><source>Investigative Ophthalmology &amp; Visual Science</source><year>1979</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>496</fpage><lpage>505</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crutch</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Warrington</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Foveal crowding in posterior cortical atrophy: A specific early-visual-processing deficit affecting word reading</article-title><source>Cognitive Neuropsychology</source><year>2007</year><volume>24</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>843</fpage><lpage>866</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crutch</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Warrington</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The relationship between visual crowding and letter confusability: Towards an understanding of dyslexia in posterior cortical atrophy</article-title><source>Cognitive Neuropsychology</source><year>2009</year><volume>26</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>471</fpage><lpage>498</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dakin</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Cass</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Greenwood</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bex</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Probabilistic, positional averaging predicts object-level crowding effects with letter-like stimuli</article-title><source>Journal of Vision</source><year>2010</year><volume>10</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>16</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Daniel</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Whitteridge</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The representation of the visual field on the cebral cortex in monkeys</article-title><source>Journal of Physiology</source><year>1961</year><volume>159</volume><fpage>203</fpage><lpage>221</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Danilova</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name><name><surname>Bondarko</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Foveal contour interaction and crowding effects at the resolution limit of the visual system</article-title><source>Journal of Vision</source><year>2007</year><volume>7</volume><issue>2</issue></element-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dayan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Solomon</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Selective Bayes: Attentional load and crowding</article-title><source>Vision Research</source><year>2010</year><volume>50</volume><issue>22</issue><fpage>2248</fpage><lpage>2260</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>De Valois</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Yund</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></name><name><surname>Hepler</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The orientation and direction selectivity of cells in macaque visual cortex</article-title><source>Vision Research</source><year>1982</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>531</fpage><lpage>544</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dekker</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwarzkopf</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>de Haas</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Nardini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sereno</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Population receptive field tuning properties of visual cortex during childhood</article-title><source>Developmental Cognitive Neuroscience</source><year>2019</year><volume>37</volume><elocation-id>100614</elocation-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Duncan</surname><given-names>RO</given-names></name><name><surname>Boynton</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cortical magnification within human primary visual cortex correlates with acuity thresholds</article-title><source>Neuron</source><year>2003</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>659</fpage><lpage>671</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ester</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></name><name><surname>Klee</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Awh</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Visual crowding cannot be wholly explained by feature pooling</article-title><source>Journal of Experimental Psychology: Human Perception &amp; Performance</source><year>2014</year><volume>40</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>1022</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ester</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></name><name><surname>Zilber</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Serences</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Substitution and pooling in visual crowding induced by similar and dissimilar distractors</article-title><source>Journal of Vision</source><year>2015</year><volume>15</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>4</fpage><comment>4</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Flom</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Weymouth</surname><given-names>FW</given-names></name><name><surname>Kahneman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Visual resolution and contour interaction</article-title><source>Journal of the Optical Society of America</source><year>1963</year><volume>53</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>1026</fpage><lpage>1032</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Freeman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Chakravarthi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Pelli</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Substitution and pooling in crowding</article-title><source>Attention, Perception, &amp; Psychophysics</source><year>2012</year><volume>74</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>379</fpage><lpage>396</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Freeman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Simoncelli</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Metamers of the ventral stream</article-title><source>Nature Neuroscience</source><year>2011</year><volume>14</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>1195</fpage><lpage>1201</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Geiger</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Lettvin</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Peripheral vision in persons with dyslexia</article-title><source>New England Journal of Medicine</source><year>1987</year><volume>316</volume><issue>20</issue><fpage>1238</fpage><lpage>1243</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Greenwood</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bex</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Dakin</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Positional averaging explains crowding with letter-like stimuli</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source><year>2009</year><volume>106</volume><fpage>12130</fpage><lpage>13135</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Greenwood</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bex</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Dakin</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Crowding changes appearance</article-title><source>Current Biology</source><year>2010</year><volume>20</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>496</fpage><lpage>501</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Greenwood</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Parsons</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dissociable effects of visual crowding on the perception of color and motion</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source><year>2020</year><volume>117</volume><issue>14</issue><fpage>8196</fpage><lpage>8202</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R37"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Greenwood</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Szinte</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sayim</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Cavanagh</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Variations in crowding, saccadic precision, and spatial localisation reveal the shared topology of spatial vision</article-title><source>Procedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source><year>2017</year><volume>114</volume><issue>17</issue><fpage>E3573</fpage><lpage>E3582</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R38"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Greenwood</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Tailor</surname><given-names>VK</given-names></name><name><surname>Sloper</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Simmers</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bex</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Dakin</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Visual acuity, crowding and stereo-vision are linked in children with and without amblyopia</article-title><source>Investigative Ophthalmology &amp; Visual Science</source><year>2012</year><volume>53</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>7655</fpage><lpage>7665</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R39"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hariharan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Levi</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>“Crowding” in normal and amblyopic vision assessed with Gaussian and Gabor C’s</article-title><source>Vision Research</source><year>2005</year><volume>45</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>617</fpage><lpage>633</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R40"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harrison</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bex</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A Unifying Model of Orientation Crowding in Peripheral Vision</article-title><source>Current Biology</source><year>2015</year><volume>25</volume><issue>24</issue><fpage>3213</fpage><lpage>3219</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R41"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harrison</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bex</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Visual crowding is a combination of an increase of positional uncertainty, source confusion, and featural averaging</article-title><source>Scientific Reports</source><year>2017</year><volume>7</volume><elocation-id>45551</elocation-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R42"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The critical role of V2 population receptive fields in visual orientation crowding</article-title><source>Current Biology</source><year>2019</year><volume>29</volume><issue>13</issue><fpage>2229</fpage><lpage>2236</lpage><elocation-id>e2223</elocation-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R43"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Herzog</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Sayim</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Chicherov</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Manassi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Crowding, grouping, and object recognition: A matter of appearance</article-title><source>Journal of Vision</source><year>2015</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>18</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R44"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hess</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><name><surname>Dakin</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Tewfik</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Contour interaction in amblyopia: Scale selection</article-title><source>Vision Research</source><year>2001</year><volume>41</volume><issue>17</issue><fpage>2285</fpage><lpage>2296</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R45"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lazar</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name><name><surname>Melia</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>Astle</surname><given-names>WF</given-names></name><name><surname>Dagi</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name><name><surname>Donahue</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effect of age on response to amblyopia treatment in children</article-title><source>Archives of Ophthalmology</source><year>2011</year><volume>129</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>1451</fpage><lpage>1457</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R46"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hussain</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Svensson</surname><given-names>C-M</given-names></name><name><surname>Besle</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Webb</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><name><surname>Barrett</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></name><name><surname>McGraw</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Estimation of cortical magnification from positional error in normally sighted and amblyopic subjects</article-title><source>Journal of Vision</source><year>2015</year><volume>15</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>25</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R47"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huttenlocher</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name><name><surname>Dabholkar</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regional differences in synaptogenesis in human cerebral cortex</article-title><source>The Journal of Comparative Neurology</source><year>1997</year><volume>387</volume><fpage>167</fpage><lpage>178</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R48"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huttenlocher</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name><name><surname>de Courten</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Garey</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Van der Loos</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Synaptogenesis in human visual cortex-Evidence for synapse elimination during normal development</article-title><source>Neuroscience Letters</source><year>1982</year><volume>33</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>247</fpage><lpage>252</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R49"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jeon</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamid</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mauer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Developmental changes during childhood in single-letter acuity and its crowding by surrounding contours</article-title><source>Journal of Experimental Child Psychology</source><year>2010</year><volume>107</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>423</fpage><lpage>437</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R50"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kalpadakis-Smith</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name><name><surname>Goffaux</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Greenwood</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Crowding for faces is determined by visual (not holistic) similarity: Evidence from judgements of eye position</article-title><source>Scientific Reports</source><year>2018</year><volume>8</volume><issue>1</issue><elocation-id>12556</elocation-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R51"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Keshvari</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosenholtz</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pooling of continuous features provides a unifying account of crowding</article-title><source>Journal of Vision</source><year>2016</year><volume>16</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>39</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R52"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kooi</surname><given-names>FL</given-names></name><name><surname>Toet</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Tripathy</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Levi</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effect of similarity and duration on spatial interaction in peripheral vision</article-title><source>Spatial Vision</source><year>1994</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>255</fpage><lpage>279</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R53"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krumhansl</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of level of consfusability on reporting letters from briefly presented visual displays</article-title><source>Perception &amp; Psychophysics</source><year>1977</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>269</fpage><lpage>279</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R54"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leat</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Epp</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Crowding in central and eccentric vision: The effects of contour interaction and attention</article-title><source>Investigative Ophthalmology &amp; Visual Science</source><year>1999</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>504</fpage><lpage>512</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R55"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leat</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Yadav</surname><given-names>NK</given-names></name><name><surname>Irving</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Development of visual acuity and contrast sensitivity in children</article-title><source>Journal of Optometry</source><year>2009</year><volume>2</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>19</fpage><lpage>26</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R56"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Levi</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Crowding - An essential bottleneck for object recognition: A mini-review</article-title><source>Vision Research</source><year>2008</year><volume>48</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>635</fpage><lpage>654</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R57"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Levi</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hariharan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Suppressive and facilitatory spatial interactions in amblyopic vision</article-title><source>Vision Research</source><year>2002a</year><volume>42</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>1379</fpage><lpage>1394</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R58"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Levi</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hariharan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Suppressive and facilitatory spatial interactions in peripheral vision: Peripheral crowding is neither size invariant nor simple contrast masking</article-title><source>Journal of Vision</source><year>2002b</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>3</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R59"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Levi</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Vernier acuity, crowding and amblyopia</article-title><source>Vision Research</source><year>1985</year><volume>25</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>979</fpage><lpage>991</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R60"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Levi</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Aitsebaomo</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name></person-group><source>Vernier acuity, crowding and cortical magnification</source><year>1985</year><volume>25</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>963</fpage><lpage>977</lpage><comment>1985</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="R61"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Levi</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Pelli</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Amblyopic reading is crowded</article-title><source>Journal of Vision</source><year>2007</year><volume>7</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>17</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R62"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Manning</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name><name><surname>Dekker</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Pellicano</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Psychophysics with children: Investigating the effects of attentional lapses on threshold estimates</article-title><source>Attention, Perception, &amp; Psychophysics</source><year>2018</year><volume>80</volume><fpage>1311</fpage><lpage>1324</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R63"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mareschal</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Solomon</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cortical distance determines whether flankers cause crowding or the tilt illusion</article-title><source>Journal of Vision</source><year>2010</year><volume>10</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>13</fpage><comment>1-14</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="R64"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martelli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Di Filippo</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Spinelli</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Zoccolotti</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Crowding, reading, and developmental dyslexia</article-title><source>Journal of Vision</source><year>2009</year><volume>9</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>18</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R65"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McKee</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Levi</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Movshon</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The pattern of visual deficits in amblyopia</article-title><source>Journal of Vision</source><year>2003</year><volume>3</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>5</fpage><comment>5</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="R66"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miles</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ocular dominance: Methods and results</article-title><source>Psychological Bulletin</source><year>1928</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>155</fpage><lpage>156</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R67"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Motter</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Central V4 Receptive Fields Are Scaled by the V1 Cortical Magnification and Correspond to a Constant-Sized Sampling of the V1 Surface</article-title><source>Journal of Neuroscience</source><year>2009</year><volume>29</volume><issue>18</issue><fpage>5749</fpage><lpage>5757</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R68"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Motter</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><name><surname>Simoni</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The roles of cortical image separation and size in active visual search performance</article-title><source>Journal of Vision</source><year>2007</year><volume>7</volume><issue>2(6)</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>15</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R69"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moutsiana</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>de Haas</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Papageorgiou</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>van Dijk</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Balraj</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Greenwood</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cortical idiosyncrasies predict the perception of object size</article-title><source>Nature Communications</source><year>2016</year><volume>7</volume><issue>12110</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>12</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R70"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parkes</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Lund</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Angelluci</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Solomon</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Compulsory averaging of crowded orientation signals in human vision</article-title><source>Nature Neuroscience</source><year>2001</year><volume>4</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>6</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R71"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pascal</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Abadi</surname><given-names>RV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Contour interaction in the presence of congenital nystagmus</article-title><source>Vision Research</source><year>1995</year><volume>35</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>1785</fpage><lpage>1789</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R72"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pelli</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The VideoToolBox software for visual psychophysics: Transforming numbers into movies</article-title><source>Spatial Vision</source><year>1997</year><volume>10</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>437</fpage><lpage>442</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R73"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pelli</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Crowding: A cortical constraint on object recognition</article-title><source>Current Opinion in Neurobiology</source><year>2008</year><volume>18</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>445</fpage><lpage>451</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R74"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pelli</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Palomares</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Majaj</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Crowding is unlike ordinary masking: Distinguishing feature integration from detection</article-title><source>Journal of Vision</source><year>2004</year><volume>4</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>1136</fpage><lpage>1169</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R75"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Petrov</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Meleshkevich</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Asymmetries and idiosyncratic hot spots in crowding</article-title><source>Vision Research</source><year>2011</year><volume>51</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>1117</fpage><lpage>1123</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R76"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pouget</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Dayan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Zemel</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Information processing with population codes</article-title><source>Nature Reviews Neuroscience</source><year>2000</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>125</fpage><lpage>132</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R77"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pugh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Visual distortion in amblyopia</article-title><source>The British Journal of Ophthalmology</source><year>1958</year><volume>42</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>449</fpage><lpage>460</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R78"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rosenholtz</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Keshvari</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Challenges to pooling models of crowding: Implications for visual mechanisms</article-title><source>Journal of Vision</source><year>2019</year><volume>19</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>15</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R79"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schiller</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name><name><surname>Finlay</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name><name><surname>Volman</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quantitative studies of single-cell properties in monkey striate cortex ||. Orientation specificity and ocular dominance</article-title><source>Journal of Neurophysiology</source><year>1976</year><volume>38</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1320</fpage><lpage>1333</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R80"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sereno</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name><name><surname>Dale</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Reppas</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Kwong</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name><name><surname>Belliveau</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Brady</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Borders of multiple visual areas in humans revealed by functional magnetic resonance imaging</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1995</year><volume>268</volume><fpage>889</fpage><lpage>893</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R81"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shooner</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Hallum</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumbhani</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Ziemba</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Garcia-Marin</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Population representation of visual information in areas V1 and V2 of amblyopic macaques</article-title><source>Vision Research</source><year>2015</year><volume>114</volume><fpage>56</fpage><lpage>67</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R82"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Simons</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Visual acuity norms in young children</article-title><source>Survey of Ophthalmology</source><year>1983</year><volume>28</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>84</fpage><lpage>92</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R83"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sireteanu</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Lagreze</surname><given-names>W-D</given-names></name><name><surname>Constantinescu</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Distortions in two-dimensional visual space perception in strabismic observers</article-title><source>Vision Research</source><year>1993</year><volume>33</volume><issue>5-6</issue><fpage>677</fpage><lpage>690</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R84"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Skoczenski</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Norcia</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Late maturation of visual hyperacuity</article-title><source>Psychological Science</source><year>2002</year><volume>13</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>537</fpage><lpage>541</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R85"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sloan</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>New test charts for the measurement of visual acuity at far and near distances</article-title><source>American Journal of Ophthalmology</source><year>1959</year><volume>48</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>807</fpage><lpage>813</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R86"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Levi</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Pelli</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A double dissociation of the acuity and crowding limits to letter identification, and the promise of improved visual screening</article-title><source>Journal of Vision</source><year>2014</year><volume>14</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>37</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R87"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Strasburger</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Unfocused spatial attention underlies the crowding effect in indirect form vision</article-title><source>Journal of Vision</source><year>2005</year><volume>5</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>1024</fpage><lpage>1037</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R88"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Strasburger</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Harvey</surname><given-names>LOJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Rentschler</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Contrast thresholds for identification of numeric characters</article-title><source>Perception &amp; Psychophysics</source><year>1991</year><volume>49</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>495</fpage><lpage>508</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R89"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Strasburger</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Rentschler</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Jüttner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Peripheral vision and pattern recognition: A review</article-title><source>Journal of Vision</source><year>2011</year><volume>11</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>82</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R90"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tailor</surname><given-names>VK</given-names></name><name><surname>Bossi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Greenwood</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Dahlmann-Noor</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Childhood amblyopia: Current management and new trends</article-title><source>British Medical Bulletin</source><year>2016</year><volume>119</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>75</fpage><lpage>86</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R91"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tailor</surname><given-names>VK</given-names></name><name><surname>Theodorou</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dahlmann-Noor</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>Dekker</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Greenwood</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Eye movements elevate crowding in idiopathic infantile nystagmus syndrome</article-title><source>Journal of Vision</source><year>2021</year><volume>21</volume><issue>13:9</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>23</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R92"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Toet</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Levi</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The two-dimensional shape of spatial interaction zones in the parafovea</article-title><source>Vision Research</source><year>1992</year><volume>32</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>1349</fpage><lpage>1357</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R93"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Treutwein</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Adaptive psychophysical procedures</article-title><source>Vision Research</source><year>1995</year><volume>35</volume><issue>17</issue><fpage>2503</fpage><lpage>2522</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R94"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tripathy</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Cavanagh</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The extent of crowding in peripheral vision does not scale with target size</article-title><source>Vision Research</source><year>2002</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>2357</fpage><lpage>2369</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R95"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van den Berg</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Roerdink</surname><given-names>JBTM</given-names></name><name><surname>Cornelissen</surname><given-names>FW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A Neurophysiologically Plausible Population Code Model for Feature Integration Explains Visual Crowding</article-title><source>PLoS Computational Biology</source><year>2010</year><volume>6</volume><issue>1</issue><elocation-id>e1000646</elocation-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R96"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van Essen</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Newsome</surname><given-names>WT</given-names></name><name><surname>Maunsell</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The visual field representation in the striate cortex of the macaque monkey: Asymmetries, anisotropies, and individual variability</article-title><source>Vision Research</source><year>1984</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>429</fpage><lpage>448</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R97"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Pelli</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quest: A Bayesian adaptive psychometric method</article-title><source>Perception &amp; Psychophysics</source><year>1983</year><volume>33</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>113</fpage><lpage>120</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R98"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Whitney</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Levi</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Visual crowding: A fundamental limit on conscious perception and object recognition</article-title><source>Trends in Cognitive Sciences</source><year>2011</year><volume>15</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>160</fpage><lpage>168</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R99"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wilkinson</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name><name><surname>Ellemberg</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lateral interactions in peripherally viewed texture arrays</article-title><source>Journal of the Optical Society of America A</source><year>1997</year><volume>14</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>2057</fpage><lpage>2068</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R100"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Witton</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Talcott</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Henning</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Psychophysical measurements in children: Challenges, pitfalls, and considerations</article-title><source>PeerJ</source><year>2017</year><volume>5</volume><elocation-id>e3231</elocation-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R101"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wolford</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Perturbation model for letter identification</article-title><source>Psychological Review</source><year>1975</year><volume>82</volume><fpage>184</fpage><lpage>199</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R102"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yong</surname><given-names>KXX</given-names></name><name><surname>Shakespeare</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Cash</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Henley</surname><given-names>SMD</given-names></name><name><surname>Nicholas</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ridgway</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Prominent effects and neural correlates of visual crowding in a neurodegenerative disease population</article-title><source>Brain</source><year>2014</year><volume>137</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>3284</fpage><lpage>3299</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R103"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Maruko</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Bi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Delayed maturation of receptive field center/surround mechanisms in V2</article-title><source>Procedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source><year>2005</year><volume>102</volume><issue>16</issue><fpage>5862</fpage><lpage>5867</lpage></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><boxed-text id="BX1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Precis</title></caption><p>Crowding strongly disrupts peripheral vision, as well as the foveal vision of children with typical vision and amblyopia. We show that typically developing and amblyopic children make the same crowded errors as adults in the visual periphery, consistent with a common mechanism in all three cases.Introduction</p></boxed-text><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Apparatus and stimuli.</title><p><bold>A.</bold>For children, stimuli were viewed through stereoscopic shutter glasses mounted in a ski mask and presented on a 3D-compatible monitor at 3 m distance. An example trial of the acuity task is depicted, where children reported the colour of the ghost that Vac-Man was facing. Coloured cards of the ghosts on the monitor edges helped children select the ghost. <bold>B.</bold> Adults viewed the monitor from 50 cm, wearing an eye patch over their non-dominant eye. <bold>C.</bold> An example frame from the “reward animation”, presented every three correct trials. <bold>D.</bold> Illustration of the stimuli in the crowding-extent task. Ghost flankers were presented at random orientations at a fixed relative separation (1.1× stimulus diameter), with their absolute separation varied by QUEST. <bold>E.</bold> Illustration of stimuli in the orientation matching task. Here, flankers were filled-in Landolt-Cs, similar to the target, presented with the same orientation difference at a fixed separation.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS144201-f001"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Acuity and crowding in the adult periphery.</title><p><bold>A.</bold>Acuity measured as gap-size thresholds (in minutes of arc) for adult observers at four eccentricities in peripheral vision. Light grey dots plot values for each observer (n=10), shifted along the x-axis where required for visibility, with the mean for each eccentricity overlaid as a transparent black dot. <bold>B.</bold> The spatial extent of crowding, measured as the centre-to-centre separation between the target and flankers in degrees of visual angle, plotted as in panel A.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS144201-f002"/></fig><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Acuity and crowding in the typically developing and amblyopic fovea.</title><p>A. Acuity measured as gap-size thresholds (in minutes of arc) for children with typical vision and amblyopia (n=20 each). Dots indicate values for each eye of individuals (shifted on the x-axis for visibility); bars indicate the mean. LE = left eye, RE= right eye, AME= amblyopic eye, FFE = fellow fixating eye, n.s. = no significant difference, ***P&lt;.001. <bold>B.</bold> The extent of crowding (in degrees of visual angle) measured as the centre-to-centre separation between the target and flankers, plotted as in panel A.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS144201-f003"/></fig><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Distributions of mean response error from the orientation-matching task for the adult periphery.</title><p>
<bold>A.</bold> Response error distributions at 2.5° eccentricity, with mean values presented as light-grey dots. The black solid line plots the mean distribution of the population pooling model, with grey shaded areas plotting the 95% range of simulated distributions for 1000 model iterations. Dashed grey lines indicate the target location (‘T’), and for the conditions in which flankers were present, the flanker location (‘F’). <bold>B-D.</bold> Response error distributions at 5°-15° eccentricity, plotted as in panel A.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS144201-f004"/></fig><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>Mean response-error distributions for children with typical vision and amblyopia in the orientation-matching task.</title><p><bold>A.</bold> Response-error distributions for children with typical vision, with mean values shown as dots. The black solid line indicates the mean distribution of the population pooling model, with grey shaded areas plotting the range of simulated distributions for 1000 model iterations. Dashed grey lines indicate the target orientation (T), and when present, the flankers (F). <bold>B.</bold> Response-error distributions for children with amblyopia, plotted as in panel A. Note that all data here is for the amblyopic eye.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS144201-f005"/></fig><fig id="F6" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title>Illustration of the 3 stages of the weighted population pooling models.</title><p><bold>A.</bold> Example stimulus input for each of the 3 flanker conditions (unflanked, and flankers with a 30° or 90° difference from the target). <bold>B.</bold> Early population response to the target (upper panel), and the target and flankers (middle and bottom panels). Arrows indicate the response to the target orientation (‘T’; purple distributions) and the response to the orientation of the flankers (‘F’; blue distributions). <bold>C.</bold> The pooling stage, modelled as the weighted combination of population responses to the target and flankers. <bold>D.</bold> The decision stage, where the perceptual outcome is read out as the peak of the combined population response. The grey dashed line indicates this peak, with the value shown numerically.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS144201-f006"/></fig><fig id="F7" position="float"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><title>Best-fitting model parameters in the adult periphery and for children with typical vision and amblyopia.</title><p><bold>A</bold>. Best-fitting values for the early noise parameter. Dots indicate individual observers (shifted on the x-axis for clarity), and bars the mean of the individual observers. White triangles show the parameters for fits to the averaged group data. <bold>B</bold>. Best-fitting values for the late noise parameter, plotted with conventions as in A. <bold>C-D.</bold> Best-fitting values for the flanker weights when the flankers differed by 30° from the target (C),and when flankers differed by 90° (D).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS144201-f007"/></fig><fig id="F8" position="float"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><title>Akaike Information Criterion (AIC) values to assess goodness-of-fit for the pooling and noise models.</title><p><bold>A</bold>. AIC values for the fits to the averaged group data, plotted separately for the pooling (dark grey) and noise (light grey) models. Note that more negative values indicate better fits to the data. <bold>B</bold>. AIC values for model fits to individual data. Bars here represent the mean of the fits to individual data for the pooling and noise models, with individual values superimposed as circles. Individuals are joined with bars to show the direction of effect.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS144201-f008"/></fig></floats-group></article>