<!DOCTYPE article
 PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" article-type="preprint"><?all-math-mml yes?><?use-mml?><?origin ukpmcpa?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">bioRxiv</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>bioRxiv : the preprint server for biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2692-8205</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">EMS207660</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2025.07.28.666086</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="archive">PPR1056724</article-id><article-version-alternatives><article-version article-version-type="status">preprint</article-version><article-version article-version-type="number">1</article-version></article-version-alternatives><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>A spinal origin for the obligate flexor synergy in the non-human primate: Implications for control of reaching</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Glover</surname><given-names>Isabel S.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>Anne M.E.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Krakauer</surname><given-names>John W.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>Stuart N.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Faculty of Medical Sciences, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/01kj2bm70</institution-id><institution>Newcastle University</institution></institution-wrap>, <city>Newcastle upon Tyne</city>, <postal-code>NE2 4HH</postal-code>, <country country="GB">UK</country></aff><aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Department of Neurology and Neurosciences, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/00za53h95</institution-id><institution>Johns Hopkins University</institution></institution-wrap>, <city>Baltimore</city>, <state>MD</state>, <country country="US">USA</country></aff><author-notes><corresp id="CR1"><bold>Corresponding Author:</bold> Prof. Stuart Baker, Faculty of Medical Sciences, Newcastle upon Tyne, NE2 4HH, UK. <email>stuart.baker@ncl.ac.uk</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted"><day>31</day><month>07</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="preprint"><day>30</day><month>07</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><permissions><ali:free_to_read/><license><ali:license_ref>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is licensed under a <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0 International license</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p id="P1">Stroke survivors frequently develop the flexor synergy, an obligate co-contraction of shoulder abductors and elbow flexors; the neural substrate has proven elusive. Here we trained healthy monkeys to generate isometric elbow and shoulder torques to move an on-screen cursor, and recorded neuron firing from motor cortical areas and the reticular formation. In all regions we found cells correlated with activity around a single joint. Neurons coding co-contractions showed a bias towards combinations orthogonal to the post-stroke flexor synergy, e.g. shoulder abduction with elbow extension. Threshold microstimulation in the spinal cord but not in either motor cortex or the reticular formation generated coactivation aligned to the flexor synergy. We suggest the evolution of prehension required descending systems either to control or bypass locomotion-dedicated spinal circuits. Loss of descending input after stroke constrains the upper limb to spinal synergies best suited to primitive locomotor functions.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec id="S1" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p id="P2">After a stroke involving motor cortex and its corticofugal outputs, patients typically pass through a defined sequence towards recovery<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">2</xref></sup>. There is an initial flaccid paralysis, caused by the loss of descending input to motoneurons. This is then replaced by weak and awkward movements characterized by synergies – obligate co-contractions of muscles acting around different joints. The most common is the flexor synergy, in which abduction around the shoulder joint is coupled with flexion around the elbow, wrist and digits<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">3</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref></sup>. With further recovery, a patient may be able to escape the constraint of synergies and make more normal movements. However, this is not always possible; for the most severely affected stroke survivors, synergies remain a permanent feature of their movements and a major contributor to disability<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref></sup>. They are therefore an important target for rehabilitation.</p><p id="P3">Why should damage to the motor cortex lead to synergies? One plausible idea is that they are a release phenomenon, produced by a motor circuit which naturally generates the observed co-activation and which is normally suppressed in healthy individuals. For example, in the newborn, Twitchell <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">8</xref></sup> described the traction response which has a similar pattern of muscle activation to the flexor synergy; it is usually lost over the first four months of life. This dormant circuit could reemerge post-stroke and cause synergies. It is also possible that the underlying circuit plays an everyday role in movements of the healthy adult, being activated for movements which require muscle patterns coincident with the synergy. In health, this circuit would be activated or inhibited by cortical systems as appropriate to the task at hand. However, the loss of cortical control after a stroke could lead to a failure of inhibitory control, and the inappropriate intrusion of synergy coactivations into movements where they are unwanted. For example, activation of the flexor synergy during reaching away from the body leads to a severe limitation of available workspace<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref></sup>, because coactivation of elbow flexion with shoulder abduction is the opposite of the elbow extension and shoulder abduction required.</p><p id="P4">Where in the central nervous system is the circuit for synergies? The available evidence suggests a role for the contralesional motor cortex, and its indirect connections to the paretic limb via the reticular formation in the brainstem and the reticulospinal tract<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref></sup>. It is known that the reticulospinal tract is less able to activate muscles selectively than the corticospinal tract<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref></sup>. Neurons in the reticular formation become more active after a corticospinal lesion<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref></sup>, and reticulospinal connections strengthen<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref></sup>. Increased reliance on this pathway is therefore a plausible route to produce the obligate muscle co-activations seen after stroke. This hypothesis makes two predictions: the reticular formation should be naturally activated mainly for movements that compose the flexor synergy, and its outputs should coactivate muscles in a flexor-synergy-like pattern.</p><p id="P5">In this study performed in two healthy macaque monkeys, we set out to test whether neurons were preferentially activated for movements aligned to the flexor synergy. Importantly, we not only recorded from all major motor cortical regions, but also from the reticular formation. Surprisingly, we found that all brain regions studied – including the reticular formation – contained cells which could code independent contraction around elbow or shoulder joints. In addition, where cells were activated for co-contraction around these joints, the majority fired with movements orthogonal to the flexor synergy (e.g. shoulder abduction with elbow extension). Finally, juxta-threshold microstimulation of motor cortex or reticular formation never led to co-activation of muscles needed to produce shoulder abduction with elbow flexion; this was only seen when stimulating the spinal cord. Our results suggest post-stroke synergies do not arise because of inherent flexor biases in upregulated reticulospinal pathways. Instead, they point instead towards spinal circuits as the source of these biases. We propose that after stroke, contralateral corticospinal control is lost to varying degrees leaving no option but to route residual descending commands via these biased spinal pathways. This necessarily produces the flexor synergy.</p></sec><sec id="S2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="S3"><title>Behavioral Task</title><p id="P6">Monkeys performed a task requiring isometric contractions around the shoulder and elbow joints. The animal sat with the right forearm in a close-fitting cast attached to a six-axis force-torque transducer (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1A</xref>). Output from the transducer was used to calculate torques exerted by the shoulder and elbow joints. A cursor on a screen in front of the monkey was moved left-right by the shoulder abduction/adduction torque, and up-down by the elbow flexion/extension torque (white circle, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1B</xref>). After a period at rest, a single target appeared in one of 16 locations (squares, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1B</xref>); the monkey moved the cursor to the target and held to obtain a food reward. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1CD</xref> show average shoulder and elbow torques from a single behavioral session, aligned to the start of the 0.4 s-long hold period (grey shading in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1CD</xref>). The different plots are arranged according to different target locations; for example, the top right plot reflects the target requiring a combination of shoulder abduction and elbow flexion. The torques were highly tuned by the nature of the task. For comparison, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1EF</xref> presents the average of rectified EMG from the shoulder abductor muscle posterior deltoid, and the elbow flexor biceps. As expected, these show very similar directional tuning to the shoulder and elbow torques (see polar plots in the middle of each panel, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1CDEF</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S4"><title>Single Unit Recordings</title><p id="P7">Peri-event time histograms (PETHs) were compiled of spikes relative to either the beginning of the task hold period, or to the onset of contraction. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2A</xref> shows such PETHs for one neuron recorded in the reticular formation of monkey C, relative to the onset of contraction. PETHs are arranged similarly to the plots of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>. This neuron was strongly directionally tuned, preferring targets requiring shoulder adduction and elbow flexion; firing was slightly larger for the high vs low torque targets (black and green lines in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2A</xref>).</p><p id="P8">Mean firing rate was measured after the torque initiation (grey shading, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2A</xref>; values plotted using polar plot in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2A</xref>) and subject to regression analysis with torque as described in Methods, yielding regression coefficients. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2B</xref> gives a scatter plot of these coefficients across all cells recorded in monkey C reticular formation. Firstly, we determined whether the coefficients relating firing to shoulder and elbow torque were significantly different from zero. This allowed classification of cells into those that were related to shoulder torque only, elbow only, both or neither. For the cells which were related to both shoulder and elbow torques (filled circles in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2B</xref>), further classification could be made based on what combination of torques they responded to (i.e. which quadrant they lay in on <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2B</xref>). We designated cells related to shoulder abduction with elbow flexion, or shoulder adduction with elbow extension, as coding <italic>in synergy</italic> contractions (red colors in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2B</xref>). These cells had preferred combinations of torques which aligned to the pathological synergies seen after stroke. By contrast, cells which were related to shoulder abduction with elbow extension, or shoulder adduction with elbow extension, were designated <italic>out of synergy</italic> cells (blue colors in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2B</xref>) – because their preferred torque combinations were orthogonal to what is seen in stroke survivors.</p></sec><sec id="S5"><title>Neural Coding of Shoulder and Elbow Contractions</title><p id="P9"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref> presents the number of cells which were placed into the different categories outlined above on the basis of regression analysis, for firing during the contraction phase of the task, where PETHs were aligned to onset of torque increase. Data from each animal are shown separately (left and right columns), and results are separated by the brain region (rows). The purple/green histograms show the numbers of cells coding for shoulder only, elbow only, both together or neither. The red/blue histograms show further details about the cells identified as coding for both elbow and shoulder torques (purple slices in the left pie charts), indicating whether they fired <italic>in</italic> or <italic>out of synergy</italic> as defined above.</p><p id="P10">One hypothesis for the cause of post-stroke synergies is that they are produced when the loss of M1 circuits leads to control being taken over by another area – for example the ipsilateral M1 and/or the reticular formation. If that area were unable to produce independent control of the shoulder and elbow joints, but instead was constrained to produce synergistic co-contractions, this would lead to pathological synergies. Such synergies would not be seen in healthy individuals because M1 is able to counteract this tendency. Two aspects of the data in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref> argue against such a hypothesis.</p><p id="P11">Firstly, in all regions examined, there were many cells which coded only for elbow or shoulder torque (green sections in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>). Indeed, in all areas except M1 in monkey C, the cells coding for independent joint contraction outnumbered those coding for co-contraction (compare purple vs green sections). If any of these regions were to take over control following M1 damage, there is no reason to expect that they could not subserve fractionated joint control.</p><p id="P12">Secondly, when examining cells which do code for co-contractions, there were many cells which coded for out-of-synergy contractions – in all cases, these were in the majority. If synergies resulted from the release of a pre-existing bias in one of these regions, we would expect stroke survivors to show shoulder abduction coupled with elbow extension, or shoulder adduction coupled with elbow flexion – a pattern orthogonal to that actually seen. The bias in all areas was similar to that in M1. Comparing the proportions of <italic>in synergy</italic> to <italic>out of synergy</italic> cells in all areas relative to M1, only ipsiM1 and RF in monkey M were significantly different (chi-squared P=0.012 and P=0.0054 respectively; both significant after Benjamini-Hochberg correction for multiple comparisons). These differences were in opposite directions – ipsiM1 had fewer, and RF more <italic>in synergy</italic> cells, although the number of cells in the sample for RF was very low. However, importantly the majority of cells coding for co-contraction were aligned to <italic>out of synergy</italic> contractions in all areas.</p><p id="P13">Some previous work has suggested that the neural control of holding (maintaining fixed state) may engage different circuits from the control of movement (producing a change of state)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref></sup>. Accordingly, it is possible that different results could be seen when analyzing holding versus movement components of a task. However, for the present study that does not seem to be the case. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref> presents proportions of neurons from different areas in the same format as <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>, but now for analysis of firing in the hold phase of the task. Very similar results are seen: all regions have cells coding for single joint contraction as well as for co-contraction, and of the latter cells are usually more numerous coding for <italic>out of synergy</italic> than <italic>in synergy</italic> co-contraction. When comparing the distribution of <italic>in synergy</italic> vs <italic>out of synergy</italic> cells for each monkey and area to that seen in M1, only ipsiM1 in monkey M was significantly different (chi-squared test P=0.0049, significant at P&lt;0.05 after correction for multiple comparisons using Benjamini-Hochberg procedure) – and this difference was in the direction that ipsiM1 was even more biased than M1 to <italic>out of synergy</italic> movements. There was a strong correlation between the coefficients determined from torque initiation and those from the hold phase of the task (mean correlation r=0.69, range 0.42-0.9).</p><p id="P14">The analyses of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 3</xref>&amp;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref> grouped cells into gross anatomical areas; we were interested to see whether similar results were seen with more nuanced sub-divisions. This is presented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref>; here results have been combined across animals; left and right columns present data for contraction and hold parts of the task respectively.</p><p id="P15">In M1, we divided cells according to whether they were antidromically identified as PTNs which project to the corticospinal tract, or not so identified (unidentified cells, UID). Similar results were seen for both classes, although a higher proportion of PTNs were task related than UIDs (sum of purple and green segments).</p><p id="P16">The RF is a bilaterally organized structure. Reticulospinal cells receive bilateral input from the cortex<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">20</xref></sup>, and projections target both sides of the spinal cord<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">21</xref></sup>. In this study our penetrations targeted RF both ipsilateral and contralateral to the limb performing the task (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Figure 1</xref>). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref> presents the results separately for each side; the findings are very similar. Finally, we separated cells depending on their estimated location within the brainstem, assigning them either to the pontine nucleus PnC or the medullary nucleus Gi. Once again, the results were very similar between the two nuclei: both contained cells coding for independent joint movement as well as for co-contraction, and more cells coding for co-contraction were activated <italic>out of synergy</italic> compared to <italic>in synergy</italic>.</p></sec><sec id="S6"><title>Muscle Responses to Microstimulation</title><p id="P17">Examination of cell discharge patterns during voluntary movement is a powerful approach, but conclusions are always based on correlation. This does not necessarily reflect the causal effect a cell has on muscles. A complementary approach is to measure muscle responses following weak electrical stimulation within a given area. This indicates the outputs sent from the stimulated site to spinal motoneurons, either via direct or indirect pathways. Here we analyzed responses evoked by microsimulation of M1, RF and also the intermediate zone of the spinal cord, focusing on whether regions were capable of supporting the pathological synergies seen post-stroke.</p><p id="P18">From all sites stimulated, at all tested intensities, we first selected only the instances where responses were produced in shoulder abductor or elbow flexor muscles. Responses were then classified according to whether they activated only one of these muscle groups, or both. The results are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref> separately for M1, RF and spinal cord (SC) (rows). The left column includes all instances of recorded responses, regardless of stimulus intensity. Here, a concern could be that stronger stimuli spread and activated multiple outputs, making co-activation appear more common. The right column therefore includes only the smaller number of responses elicited at threshold, defined as the lowest intensity which elicited a response in any muscle.</p><p id="P19">The overwhelming majority of sites within M1 and RF produced independent activation of either shoulder abductors or elbow flexors, but not both – at threshold, no sites were seen which produced co-activation of these muscle groups. By contrast, in the spinal cord at threshold only 2/172 sites produced independent shoulder abduction. The great majority of spinal sites (27/29, 93%) capable of activating shoulder abductors did so in consort with elbow flexion.</p></sec></sec><sec id="S7" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><sec id="S8"><title>Possible Sources of Post-Stroke Synergies</title><p id="P20">In this study, we show that cells within M1 can encode contractions around either the elbow or shoulder joint, or for co-contractions around both joints simultaneously. Furthermore, the cells which encode co-contractions have a bias: most cells code for contractions orthogonal to the synergies typically seen in a human stroke survivor. Considering these results from M1 in isolation leads to an obvious proposal for the source of post-stroke synergies: an M1 lesion removes drive for independent and <italic>out of synergy</italic> movements, leaving <italic>in synergy</italic> co-contractions as the only remaining option. However, critically here we recorded not just from M1, but from other cortical motor areas as well as the reticular formation. We show that all other brain centers tested had similar activity patterns to M1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>–<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>). Whichever one of these areas might take over function after M1 lesion, it should also be capable of providing drive for independent movements around single joints, and for across joint co-contractions the dominant drive should still be for <italic>out of synergy</italic> movements. Given these results, it is hard to propose that synergies arise because a pre-existing preference for <italic>in synergy</italic> co-contractions is unmasked in any surviving brain area. This is contrary to current ideas in the field, which suggest that after a severe lesion control is subsumed by ipsilateral motor areas and the reticular formation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">22</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref></sup>. These are proposed to be unable to encode fractionated independent contractions of elbow and shoulder joints<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref></sup>. Yet in our data, findings from ipsilateral M1 and the reticular formation were very similar to those from the contralateral M1, PMd and SMA.</p><p id="P21">Even if a brain region can accurately code for independent contractions across shoulder and elbow joints, these cannot be executed unless output projections are sufficiently well separated between different muscle groups. We investigated this by examining muscle responses to stimulation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref>). Juxta-threshold stimuli in both M1 and RF activated either elbow flexors or shoulder abductors, never the two groups together. M1 and RF not only have the ability to code for independent muscle contractions, but also to generate this independent activity via their output projections.</p><p id="P22">How then do post-stroke synergies arise? It is clear that something must change after the lesion. In health M1 corticospinal output probably does not provide the majority of drive to motoneurons<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">25</xref></sup>, but its input is still substantial. Part of this is via direct cortico-motoneuronal connections, as well as through oligosynaptic routes involving spinal cord interneurons<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">26</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">28</xref></sup>. Loss of M1 after a stroke therefore produces loss of motoneuron drive. Other pathways must then race to make good this deficit, sprouting terminals to strengthen their outputs. For the RF, electrophysiological recordings have shown that the majority of this additional input is disynaptic<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref></sup>. Anatomical studies also suggest that most increased corticospinal drive to the spinal cord after a lesion goes to lamina VI/VII, where interneurons are located; these provide a disynaptic route to influence motoneurons (from SMA bilaterally<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">29</xref></sup> and from ipsilateral M1<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">30</xref></sup>). As <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref> shows, in healthy animals spinal circuits almost always activated shoulder abductor muscles together with elbow flexors. A command attempting independent shoulder abduction from surviving ipsilateral cortex or the reticular formation would necessarily have to pass through these spinal interneurons, producing the undesired co-contractions characteristic of post-stroke synergies.</p><p id="P23">In many stroke survivors, synergies are only a transient phenomenon. With time, the ability to generate independent activity around shoulder and elbow joints can recover<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref></sup>. There are multiple possible ways in which this could occur. Monosynaptic connections to motoneurons, both from surviving cortical areas and from the RF, could increase, allowing fractionated control over muscles. Alternatively, spinal interneurons could refine their connections to target motor nuclei acting around only one joint. These options are not mutually exclusive. Importantly, some people are never able to go through this process, and remain stuck with unwanted synergies. These tend to be individuals with more severe lesions. We know that cortico-motoneuronal axons from M1 are exquisitely finely targeted, connecting to just a few motor nuclei<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31">31</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32">32</xref></sup>. It is possible that the survival of even a small number of these cortico-motoneuronal connections from the lesioned hemisphere could provide a ‘teaching’ signal, which allows spinal circuits to be gradually sculpted towards improved fractionation via activity-dependent processes. A severe stroke produces a near-complete lesion of these critical cells, and could therefore render it impossible to pass beyond <italic>in synergy</italic> movements.</p></sec><sec id="S9"><title>Cell Activity is Biased Towards <italic>Out of Synergy</italic> Movements</title><p id="P24">In this study, we provide evidence for a remarkable bias in cell firing patterns over regions within the cortex, as well as in the reticular formation. For neurons encoding contractions around both elbow and shoulder joints, the majority was related to shoulder abduction/elbow extension or shoulder adduction/elbow flexion (<italic>out of synergy</italic>)– the opposite of the obligate <italic>in synergy</italic> co-contractions seen post-stroke.</p><p id="P25">Somewhat different biases in cortical directional activity have previously been reported. In the classic study of Georgopoulos et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33">33</xref></sup> using a center-out reaching task in two dimensions, cell preferred directions were not uniformly distributed across the possible reach directions: reaches away from the body and to the right were over-represented. This would correspond to shoulder abduction with elbow extension (an <italic>out of synergy</italic> contraction); however, the opposite direction (towards body and left) was under-represented, which would require shoulder adduction and elbow flexion (also <italic>out of synergy</italic>). Such cell activity biases depend on the posture of the upper limb; with the shoulder abducted, reaches both towards and away from the body are over-represented<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34">34</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35">35</xref></sup>. This M1 preference is similar to that seen in muscle activity. It has been suggested based on limb biomechanics that towards/away movements require more power to produce a constant hand velocity than those to the left or right, leading to M1 distributing more resources to enable such movements<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35">35</xref></sup>. By contrast, a study using three dimensional reaching found that preferred directions were approximately uniformly distributed<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36">36</xref></sup>. None of these results are directly comparable to the present work, where we tested isometric contractions. Our task isolates motor control from any requirements imposed by limb kinematics. By focusing on the coordination of shoulder adduction/abduction and elbow flexion/extension, we tried to reveal control processes especially relevant to the development of obligate synergies post-stroke.</p></sec><sec id="S10"><title>Spinal Circuits are Biased towards <italic>In Synergy</italic> Movements</title><p id="P26">In contrast to our neural recording results from the cortex and RF, stimulation of the spinal cord showed a clear bias towards activating shoulder abductors with elbow flexors – an <italic>in synergy</italic> contraction. The spinal cord is known to play an important role in locomotion<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37">37</xref></sup>, which muscles are activated in stereotyped synergies<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38">38</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40">40</xref></sup>. In quadrupedal macaques, both climbing and walking require shoulder abductors to be contracted with elbow flexors. The preference of spinal circuits for an <italic>in synergy</italic> movement may reflect a role best suited for producing locomotion. Descending control of a voluntary <italic>in synergy</italic> movement could be easily accomplished simply by activating the relevant spinal interneuron populations. By contrast, if the spinal cord cannot coordinate the relevant motor pools for an <italic>out of synergy</italic> movement, control would rely on more direct input from descending pathways. This could explain why more resources are devoted in cortical areas and the RF to control <italic>out of synergy</italic> vs <italic>in synergy</italic> movements. On this view, the development of descending pathways has been driven by the need to break away from the stereotyped co-contractions which subserve locomotion to a more flexible motor repertoire capable of supporting prehension. For any given movement, the relative contributions of primitive spinal circuits versus more selective descending pathways will depend on how well aligned the movement is to the capabilities of the spinal machinery alone.</p><p id="P27">To some extent, the widespread similarity between biases across the regions recorded from is unsurprising, as they are heavily interconnected. SMA and PMd both provide cortico-cortical input to M1<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41">41</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43">43</xref></sup> and ipsiM1<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R44">44</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R45">45</xref></sup>. The RF receives highly convergent bilateral cortico-reticular input<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R46">46</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R47">47</xref></sup>. These interconnections should mean that the system is robust to damage; we would not expect, for example, that preferences of the RF would change extensively after damage to M1, as inputs to it from the SMA with the same biases would survive. These results, in addition to the novelty of suggesting that the post-stroke flexor synergy arises in spinal cord, also suggest that the cortex and brainstem evolved a control system to uncouple the arm from spinal circuits dedicated to locomotion, thus allowing prehension.</p></sec></sec><sec id="S11" sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><p id="P28">Experiments were conducted on two female macaque monkeys (monkeys M, 7 years, 5.7 kg and C, 6 years, 6.1 kg). All procedures were approved by the Newcastle University Animal Welfare and Ethical Review Board, and were conducted under appropriate licenses from the UK Home Office.</p><sec id="S12"><title>Behavioral Task</title><p id="P29">Animals were trained to perform a task requiring precise control of torque around the elbow and shoulder joints, which was measured using methods described previously<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R48">48</xref></sup> adapted to be suitable for use in monkey. During training sessions, the monkey sat in a training cage, and was lightly restrained by a collar around the neck. A 3D scan of the right forearm was taken (EinScan Pro HD, SHINING 3D, Hangzhou, China), and used to construct a customized plastic cast by 3D printing. This was in two pieces which could be assembled around the forearm and then fitted into a circular clamp, providing a tight-fitting attachment which was without uncomfortable pressure points. The clamp was connected to a six axis transducer (model 45E15A4-I63-EF-200N, JR3 Inc, Woodland, CA, USA) which measured force and torque exerted by the animal (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1A</xref>). The transducer and neck restraints were placed in the same locations on the training cage each day. Taking the center of the transducer as the origin of the coordinate system, we measured the 3D locations of the elbow and shoulder relative to this origin, and expressed these as vectors <italic><underline>r<sub>e</sub></underline></italic> and <italic><underline>r<sub>s</sub></underline></italic>. The force and torques measured in 3D by the transducer are the vectors <italic><underline>F</underline></italic> and <italic><underline>M</underline></italic> respectively. Analyzing the arm as a rigid body in equilibrium<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R49">49</xref></sup>, in which forces and torques are only applied at the shoulder and forearm attachment to the transducer, showed that the shoulder torque could be calculated as: <disp-formula id="FD1"><mml:math id="M1"><mml:munder accentunder="true"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">_</mml:mo></mml:munder><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:munder accentunder="true"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">_</mml:mo></mml:munder><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:munder accentunder="true"><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">_</mml:mo></mml:munder><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:munder accentunder="true"><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">_</mml:mo></mml:munder></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="P30">Where × denotes the vector cross product. The upper arm and forearm were then analyzed as two rigid bodies in equilibrium, in which the upper arm was acted on only by shoulder and elbow joints, and the forearm by the elbow and transducer attachment. This showed that the elbow torque could be calculated as: <disp-formula id="FD2"><mml:math id="M2"><mml:munder accentunder="true"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">_</mml:mo></mml:munder><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:munder accentunder="true"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">_</mml:mo></mml:munder><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:munder accentunder="true"><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">_</mml:mo></mml:munder><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:munder accentunder="true"><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">_</mml:mo></mml:munder></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="P31">Voltage signals proportional to <italic><underline>F</underline></italic> and <italic><underline>M</underline></italic> were sampled by a PC with data acquisition card (National Instruments model USB6343, Austin, TX, USA), and the calculations described above performed in real time by a custom computer program. This displayed a cursor on screen. Movement of the cursor in the x axis was controlled by shoulder abduction-adduction torque. Movement in the y axis was controlled by elbow flexion-extension torque (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1B</xref>).</p><p id="P32">Each trial of the task began with the cursor hidden. To proceed, the six force-torque signals from the transducer had to have a standard deviation (measured over a 1.3 s window for monkey C; 1.8 s for monkey M) below a threshold value (0.45 N for force, 0.05 Nm for torque); we found that this was a reliable indicator that the monkey was at rest. The force-torque signals were then zeroed; this compensated for slow drifts in the outputs which otherwise occurred over the course of a one-hour long training or recording session. The cursor then appeared, along with a target. Targets were spaced radially around two circles at 45° intervals, with the circle radius corresponding to a torque of 0.35 and 0.7 Nm. Targets were rectangular, with a half-width of 0.1 and 0.08 Nm in the shoulder abduction/adduction and elbow flexion/extension direction respectively (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1B</xref>). The monkey was required to place the cursor into the target, and to hold for 0.4 s in monkey C, and 1 s in monkey M. The target and cursor then disappeared, and the animal was given a food reward. Placement of the cursor into target, and the successful completion of a trial, were indicated with auditory tones in addition to the on-screen information. The 16 different targets were presented in pseudorandom order in blocks of five.</p><p id="P33">The monkeys became highly skilled at performing this task. Monkeys C and M completed an average of 564 and 575 successful trials per recording session (range 236-880).</p></sec><sec id="S13"><title>Surgical Implants</title><p id="P34">After behavioral training was complete, the animals underwent an implant surgery. This implanted a headpiece, which permitted atraumatic head fixation and incorporated chambers to give access to brain regions with microelectrodes. The headpiece was an anulus generated by 3D printing in titanium, using a digital model derived from an MRI scan of the head; this ensured a good fit between the headpiece underside and the bone. The headpiece was attached to the skull using a system of expanding bolt assemblies as described previously<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R50">50</xref></sup>. Both the headpiece and bolt assemblies were coated in hydroxyapatite, to improve osteointegration. In the same surgery, fine stainless-steel wires insulated with Teflon (part number AS632, Cooner Wire Co, Chatsworth, CA, USA) were implanted in the following 12 muscles acting on the upper limb: extensor digitorum communis, extensor carpi radialis, flexor digitorum superficialis, flexor carpi radialis, triceps, brachioradialis, biceps, brachialis, posterior deltoid, anterior deltoid, supraspinatus, pectoralis major. These wires ran sub-cutaneously to connectors on the headpiece, allowing EMG recordings.</p><p id="P35">In a subsequent surgery, two fine electrodes (LF501, Microprobes Inc, Gaithersburg, MD, USA) were implanted in the pyramidal tract in the medulla, using a double angle stereotaxic approach<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R51">51</xref></sup>. Electrodes were advanced while stimulating (up to 500 μA isolated biphasic constant-current stimuli, 0.1 ms per phase); they were fixed in place at the location with the lowest threshold to produce an antidromic response in a recording made from the dural surface overlying the primary motor cortex (M1; thresholds at final location were between 15 and 145 μA).</p><p id="P36">All surgeries were conducted under general anesthesia. After induction with ketamine (7 mg/kg), medetomidine (3 μg/kg) and midazolam (0.3 mg/kg; all IM), anesthesia was continued with sevoflurane inhalation (2-2.25%) and alfentanil continual intravenous infusion (24 μg/kg/hr). The animal was intubated, and ventilated using positive pressure ventilation. Temperature was maintained with a supply of warm air, and a thermostatic heating blanket. Meloxicam (300 μg/kg) was given for added analgesia. Methylpregnisolone (loading dose 30mg/kg followed by 5.4 mg/kg/hr) was given to reduce cerebral oedema. Hartmann’s solution was infused to prevent dehydration (5 ml/kg/hr). Prophylactic antibiotic was administered (cefotaxamine, 20mg/kg every 4 hours). Monitoring included pulse oximetry, heart rate, core and peripheral temperature and non-invasive blood pressure. At the end of the surgery buprenorphine (20 μg/kg), amoxy-clavulanate (12.5mg/kg), dexamethasone (0.5 mg/kg), maropitant (1mg/kg) and paracetamol (23 mg/kg) were given.</p></sec><sec id="S14"><title>Neural Recordings</title><p id="P37">After recovery from the implant surgeries was complete, a craniotomy was opened under the recording chamber overlying M1 and the dorsal pre-motor cortex (PMd) in a further brief surgery, and recording sessions commenced. Electrodes were introduced through the dura, and moved to find single unit recordings. In monkey C, recordings initially used up to five glass-insulated platinum microelectrodes, positioned using an Eckhorn microdrive<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R52">52</xref></sup>; we searched particularly for antidromically-identified pyramidal tract neurons (PTNs). In later recordings, silicon probes with 32 contacts were used (Atlas Neuroengineering, Leuven, Belgium), followed by 1024 contact SiNAPS active neural probes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R53">53</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R54">54</xref></sup>. In monkey M, only 1024 channel SiNAPS electrodes were used in M1/PMd. For the multiple contact probes, recordings following pyramidal tract stimulation were made at the start and end of each recording session; this allowed us to identify antidromically identified PTNs<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R53">53</xref></sup>. Recordings were also made from SMA contralateral to the arm performing the task, from RF bilaterally, and (in monkey M only) from M1 ipsilateral to the task. All cortical recordings used SiNAPS probes, other than some sessions in M1 for monkey C as noted above. All RF recordings used 32 channel U probes (Plexon Inc, Dallas, Texas, USA).</p></sec><sec id="S15"><title>Histology and Cell Localization</title><p id="P38">At the end of neural recordings, the animals were used in an unrelated study under terminal anesthesia, and then killed by overdose of anesthetic and transcardial perfusion. The brain was removed and processed for histology. Parasagittal sections of the cortex surrounding the central sulcus and the brainstem were cut on a freezing microtome (50 μm thickness) and stained using cresyl violet. For the cortical sections, the boundary between M1 and PMd was determined as the point where large Betz cells ceased. This was used together with the coordinates of cortical penetrations to classify recorded neurons as lying within M1 or PMd. For the brainstem, a parasagittal section was digitized, and the reticular nucleus gigantocellularis (Gi) and caudal pontine reticular nucleus (PnC) were identified relative to landmarks which were marked on a traced drawing<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R55">55</xref></sup>. The drawing was aligned with the MRI of the brain taken at the start of the study; this allowed us to register the histological tracing to stereotaxic coordinates, and thereby to reconstruct electrode penetrations using manipulator readings taken each day. Brainstem recording sites were classified as lying on either the left or right side of the brain, and within the Gi or PnC nuclei.</p><p id="P39"><xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Figure 1</xref> shows the reconstructed location of reticular formation cells which were significantly related to some aspect of the task. Localizing our recordings was made more straightforward because we identified the abducens nucleus in some penetrations, from its characteristic discharge during voluntary lateral eye movements and the small lateral deviations of the eye caused during microstimulation. Sites where abducens was identified are marked on the reconstruction in blue. Based on previously-described divisions of the primate reticular formation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R55">55</xref></sup>, we marked a boundary line between the nucleus gigantocellularis (Gi) and the caudal pontine nucleus (PnC). This allowed cells to be classified according to their estimated nuclear location; we also noted the side of the brainstem on which neurons were recorded, allowing classification as ipsilateral or contralateral to the arm performing the task (red vs black dots, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Suppl. Fig. 1</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S16"><title>Data Analysis</title><sec id="S17"><title>Torque Analysis</title><p id="P40">For each trial, the shoulder and elbow torques were smoothed with a Gaussian kernel (50 ms width parameter), and binned into 10ms bins. The torque path (position of cursor on the screen) for each trial was then plotted from the trial start until the end of the hold period. Target distance was defined as the straight-line distance between the cursor position at the trial start and trial end. A threshold for movement onset was calculated for each trial by taking 5% or 10% of the target distance, for targets furthest or nearest the center position respectively. Movement onset was then defined as the last point where the distance from trial start was less than this threshold. Trials were only included in the analysis if this point was in the correct direction, defined as being within ±90° of the target direction.</p><p id="P41">To facilitate a comparison between torques and cell firing rates, a mean torque value was calculated for the movement period (400ms window starting at movement onset, as defined above) and the hold period (400ms window starting at start of the hold period). Baseline torque was subtracted from each of these values (mean torque across first 50ms of each trial, when the cursor was held on the central target). Mean values were calculated separately for shoulder torque and elbow torque.</p></sec><sec id="S18"><title>Spike Discrimination</title><p id="P42">Neural recordings were first separated into the discharge times of clean single units. For single microelectrode recordings, this used a custom cluster-cutting program (Getspike, SN Baker). For 32 channel silicon probes and 1024 channel SiNAPS probes, this used KiloSort4<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R56">56</xref></sup>. Clusters identified by Kilosort were further processed by the program Bombcell<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R57">57</xref></sup>; only units classified as ‘good’ by both Kilosort and Bombcell were used in further analysis. For SiNAPS probe recordings, an additional more time-consuming analysis extracted the spike times of identified PTNs, using filters matched to the identified spike shape<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R53">53</xref></sup>. Kilosort clusters which matched these spikes were deleted to avoid duplication. Finally, brainstem recordings using 32 channel linear probes (U probes) were clustered using Mountainsort<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R58">58</xref></sup>; a custom program further processed these clusters to remove those likely to be artifacts, and to combine clusters likely to originate from the same cell.</p></sec><sec id="S19"><title>Single Unit Analysis – Cell Selection</title><p id="P43">Spike times were converted into a continuous estimate of firing rate by convolution with a Gaussian kernel<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R59">59</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R60">60</xref></sup> (width 50 ms). Cells were occasionally lost during recording. To prevent these periods with no spikes from artifactually reducing estimates of task-related firing, we identified blocks of ten consecutive trials with no spikes recorded; these trials were removed from the analysis for that cell. Peri-event time histograms (PETHs) were then constructed by averaging across all trials for each condition. A bin width of 50 ms was used, and PETHs were smoothed by convolution with a Gaussian kernel (width 50 ms). PETHs were constructed separately aligned to torque onset and the start of the hold period, and all subsequent analyses were performed separately for these ‘move’ and ‘hold’ PETHs.</p><p id="P44">Cells were only included in the analysis if they met the following three criteria. Firstly, there had to be a minimum of five trials for each condition. Secondly, baseline firing had to be consistent across all conditions. This was assessed by averaging firing rate for each condition for a baseline period from -1.5s to -1.0s, relative to the trial marker (move onset or start of the hold period). Cells were excluded if any of these baseline firing values lay outside ±5 median absolute deviations from the median of baseline firing for that cell. Thirdly, cells were only included in the analysis if their firing was task related. This was determined using a Monte Carlo method. For each trial, the inter-spike intervals were shuffled and the PETH recomputed. This process was repeated to produce 100 PETHs with shuffled data. The latency of peak firing was calculated from the unshuffled PETH by finding the latency of peak firing for each condition and taking the median of these values. For each condition, firing rate at this peak latency was compared between the real PETH and the shuffled PETHs. The firing of a cell was considered task-related if the real peak firing was greater than at least 95 of 100 of the peak firing rates from shuffled PETHs, for at least half of the conditions. Note that since these analyses were performed separately for PETHs aligned to movement and the hold period, different populations of cells were included in the ‘move’ and ‘hold’ analyses.</p></sec><sec id="S20"><title>Correlation of Torque and Firing Rate</title><p id="P45">Although the window of interest for torque was fixed, corresponding to either the first 400ms after movement onset, or the first 400ms of the hold period, cell firing rate presumably modulates prior to this to drive the contraction. Furthermore, it is likely that the latency between firing rate modulation and torque output varies for each cell. We therefore identified a window of firing rate for each cell that best correlated to torque and used this in our analysis.</p><p id="P46">For each cell, we calculated the mean firing rate for each 400ms window starting -200ms to 0ms relative to the movement onset, progressing in 10ms steps. We then performed a regression between each of these firing rates and mean shoulder/elbow torque during the initial movement period (0-400ms after movement onset). We selected the firing rate window with the highest regression coefficient to include in the subsequent analysis, representing the period of cell activity that best correlated with torque. Firing rate, shoulder torque and elbow torque values were all normalized by their respective standard deviations, prior to performing a Tobit regression<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R61">61</xref></sup>. This method was chosen here to accommodate the left-censoring of the firing rate data - rate values cannot be negative. Confidence intervals were calculated for the regression coefficients. This analysis was repeated for the hold period.</p><p id="P47">The coefficients from the Tobit regression were used to classify the relation of the cell activity to torque. A cell was defined as having a significant correlation between firing rate and shoulder torque if the confidence intervals of the regression coefficients did not cross zero. This analysis was repeated for elbow torque, thereby allowing classification of cells as ‘shoulder only’ (significant relationship between firing rate and shoulder torque, but not elbow torque), ‘elbow only’, ‘both’, or ‘neither’. Examination of the sign of the correlation coefficients for ‘both’ cells allowed a further classification according to the type of co-contraction which the cell responded to. <italic>In synergy</italic> co-contractions were those aligned to post-stroke synergies: elbow flexion with shoulder abduction, or elbow extension with shoulder adduction. <italic>Out of synergy</italic> co-contractions were those orthogonal to post-stroke synergies: elbow flexion with shoulder adduction, or elbow extension with shoulder abduction.</p><p id="P48">To compare coefficients between data aligned to torque onset and the hold phase of the task, for each monkey, area and joint a cell was included if the Tobit regression coefficient was significantly different from zero for either task phase. We then calculated the correlation between torque onset and hold coefficients.</p></sec></sec><sec id="S21"><title>Analysis of Published Data on Responses to Microstimulation</title><p id="P49">To complement results from the new experiments described above, we also carried out some re-analysis of a previously published study<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref></sup>. Full experimental details are given in the publication. Briefly, EMG was recorded from many muscles acting around the shoulder, elbow, wrist and digits in one arm. Microelectrodes were advanced into M1, RF and the spinal cord intermediate zone (SC). Experiments in M1 and RF were carried out in the awake state, with access to the brain provided with recording chambers as described above. For SC, the recordings were made in a terminal experiment under propofol, an anesthetic which we have found leaves spinal excitability relatively intact. Single-pulse stimuli were given through the microelectrode, and responses in EMGs recorded. For each site, and for each stimulus intensity, the post-stimulus averaged rectified EMG was tested for statistical significance relative to the baseline, and the muscle was classified as responding or not responding. Where a response was seen, the intensity was progressively reduced until it was abolished. The threshold intensity was then defined as the lowest intensity which produced a response in at least one muscle. In the post-hoc analysis carried out here, sites were only included if they activated at least one muscle out of posterior deltoid, anterior deltoid, biceps, brachioradialis and brachialis. Sites were then classified according to whether they activated shoulder abductors alone, elbow flexors alone, or both (i.e. at least one muscle in each category).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="SM"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1"><label>Supplementary Figures</label><media xlink:href="EMS207660-supplement-Supplementary_Figures.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" id="d27aAcEbB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack id="S22"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The authors wish to thank Terri Jackson and Andrew Atkinson for animal training, Norman Charlton for engineering support, Rocio Palacios O’Connor for veterinary assistance, and Michelle Waddle for surgical theatre nursing.</p><sec id="S23"><title>Funding</title><p>This work was supported by NIH grant 5R01NS119319. Development of SiNAPS probes used in this study was supported by BBSRC grant BB/V00896X/1.</p></sec></ack><ref-list><ref id="R1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Brunnstrom</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><source>Movement therapy in hemiplegia</source><publisher-name>Harper &amp; Row</publisher-name><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc><year>1970</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Twitchell</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The restoration of motor fucntion following hemiplegia in man</article-title><source>Brain</source><year>1951</year><volume>74</volume><fpage>443</fpage><lpage>480</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14895765</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Avni</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The Kinematics of 3D Arm Movements in Sub-Acute Stroke: Impaired Inter-Joint Coordination is Attributable to Both Weakness and Flexor Synergy Intrusion</article-title><source>Neurorehabil Neural Repair</source><year>2024</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>646</fpage><lpage>658</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/15459683241268535</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11403926</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39113590</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dewald</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Beer</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Abnormal joint torque patterns in the paretic upper limb of subjects with hemiparesis</article-title><source>Muscle Nerve</source><year>2001</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>273</fpage><lpage>283</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11180211</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dewald</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Pope</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name><surname>Given</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Buchanan</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name><name><surname>Rymer</surname><given-names>WZ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Abnormal muscle coactivation patterns during isometric torque generation at the elbow and shoulder in hemiparetic subjects</article-title><source>Brain</source><year>1995</year><volume>118</volume><fpage>495</fpage><lpage>510</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7735890</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ellis</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Schut</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Dewald</surname><given-names>JPA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Flexion synergy overshadows flexor spasticity during reaching in chronic moderate to severe hemiparetic stroke</article-title><source>Clin Neurophysiol</source><year>2017</year><volume>128</volume><fpage>1308</fpage><lpage>1314</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.clinph.2017.04.028</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5507628</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28558314</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zackowski</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Dromerick</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><name><surname>Sahrmann</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Thach</surname><given-names>WT</given-names></name><name><surname>Bastian</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>How do strength, sensation, spasticity and joint individuation relate to the reaching deficits of people with chronic hemiparesis?</article-title><source>Brain</source><year>2004</year><volume>127</volume><fpage>1035</fpage><lpage>1046</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14976070</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Twitchell</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Normal Motor Development</article-title><source>Phys Ther</source><year>1965</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>419</fpage><lpage>423</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14327864</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beer</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><name><surname>Ellis</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Holubar</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name><name><surname>Dewald</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Impact of gravity loading on post-stroke reaching and its relationship to weakness</article-title><source>Muscle Nerve</source><year>2007</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>242</fpage><lpage>250</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/mus.20817</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2866301</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17486581</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McPherson</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Progressive recruitment of contralesional cortico-reticulospinal pathways drives motor impairment post stroke</article-title><source>J Physiol</source><year>2018</year><volume>596</volume><fpage>211</fpage><lpage>1225</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1113/JP274968</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5878212</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29457651</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McPherson</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Dewald</surname><given-names>JPA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Abnormal synergies and associated reactions post-hemiparetic stroke reflect muscle activation patterns of brainstem motor pathways</article-title><source>Front Neurol</source><year>2022</year><volume>13</volume><elocation-id>934670</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fneur.2022.934670</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9588949</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36299276</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zaaimi</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Dean</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name><name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Different contributions of primary motor cortex, reticular formation, and spinal cord to fractionated muscle activation</article-title><source>J Neurophysiol</source><year>2018</year><volume>119</volume><fpage>235</fpage><lpage>250</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/jn.00672.2017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5866475</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29046427</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></name><name><surname>Maunz</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Pitts</surname><given-names>NG</given-names></name><name><surname>Mackel</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Patterns of projection and branching of reticulospinal neurons</article-title><source>Exp Brain Res</source><year>1975</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>333</fpage><lpage>351</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1183508</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zaaimi</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Soteropoulos</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Riddle</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name><name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Classification of Neurons in the Primate Reticular Formation and Changes After Recovery From Pyramidal Tract Lesion</article-title><source>Journal of Neuroscience</source><year>2018</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>6190</fpage><lpage>6206</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.3371-17.2018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6031583</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29793974</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zaaimi</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Edgley</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Soteropoulos</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Changes in descending motor pathway connectivity after corticospinal tract lesion in macaque monkey</article-title><source>Brain</source><year>2012</year><volume>135</volume><fpage>2277</fpage><lpage>2289</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/brain/aws115</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3381720</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22581799</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Albert</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Postural control of arm and fingers through integration of movement commands</article-title><source>eLife</source><year>2020</year><volume>9</volume><elocation-id>e52507</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.52507</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7062460</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32043973</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hadjiosif</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Separating the control of moving and holding in post-stroke arm paresis</article-title><source>eLife</source><year>2022</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shalit</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Zinger</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Joshua</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Prut</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Descending systems translate transient cortical commands into a sustained muscle activation signal</article-title><source>Cereb Cortex</source><year>2012</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>1904</fpage><lpage>1914</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21965441</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shadmehr</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Distinct neural circuits for control of movement vs. holding still</article-title><source>J Neurophysiol</source><year>2017</year><volume>117</volume><fpage>1431</fpage><lpage>1460</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/jn.00840.2016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5376603</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28053244</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Zaaimi</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Edgley</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Extensive cortical convergence to primate reticulospinal pathways</article-title><source>Journal of Neuroscience</source><year>2021</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>1005</fpage><lpage>1018</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.1379-20.2020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7880280</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33268548</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Davidson</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Buford</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bilateral actions of the reticulospinal tract on arm and shoulder muscles in the monkey: stimulus triggered averaging</article-title><source>Exp Brain Res</source><year>2006</year><volume>173</volume><fpage>25</fpage><lpage>39</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16506008</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Owen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ingo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Dewald</surname><given-names>JPA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Upper Extremity Motor Impairments and Microstructural Changes in Bulbospinal Pathways in Chronic Hemiparetic Stroke</article-title><source>Front Neurol</source><year>2017</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>257</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fneur.2017.00257</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5468392</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28659855</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Motor system activation after subcortical stroke depends on corticospinal system integrity</article-title><source>Brain</source><year>2006</year><volume>129</volume><fpage>809</fpage><lpage>819</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/brain/awl002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3717515</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16421171</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>YT</given-names></name><name><surname>Francisco</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Rymer</surname><given-names>WZ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A Unifying Pathophysiological Account for Post-stroke Spasticity and Disordered Motor Control</article-title><source>Front Neurol</source><year>2019</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>468</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fneur.2019.00468</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6524557</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31133971</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tapia</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Tohyama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Poll</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The existence of the StartReact effect implies reticulospinal, not corticospinal, inputs dominate drive to motoneurons during voluntary movement</article-title><source>Journal of Neuroscience</source><year>2022</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>7634</fpage><lpage>7647</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.2473-21.2022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9546468</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36658461</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morecraft</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Terminal distribution of the corticospinal projection from the hand/arm region of the primary motor cortex to the cervical enlargement in rhesus monkey</article-title><source>J Comp Neurol</source><year>2013</year><volume>521</volume><fpage>4205</fpage><lpage>4235</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cne.23410</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3894926</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23840034</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yoshino-Saito</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishimura</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Oishi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Isa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quantitative inter-segmental and inter-laminar comparison of corticospinal projections from the forelimb area of the primary motor cortex of macaque monkeys</article-title><source>Neuroscience</source><year>2010</year><volume>171</volume><fpage>1164</fpage><lpage>1179</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20933586</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alstermark</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Isa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Saito</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Disynaptic pyramidal excitation in forelimb motoneurons mediated via C(3)-C(4) propriospinal neurons in the Macaca fuscata</article-title><source>J Neurophysiol</source><year>1999</year><volume>82</volume><fpage>3580</fpage><lpage>3585</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10601484</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McNeal</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Selective long-term reorganization of the corticospinal projection from the supplementary motor cortex following recovery from lateral motor cortex injury</article-title><source>J Comp Neurol</source><year>2010</year><volume>518</volume><fpage>586</fpage><lpage>621</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cne.22218</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3765018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20034062</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morecraft</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Frontal and frontoparietal injury differentially affect the ipsilateral corticospinal projection from the nonlesioned hemisphere in monkey (Macaca mulatta)</article-title><source>J Comp Neurol</source><year>2016</year><volume>524</volume><fpage>380</fpage><lpage>407</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cne.23861</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4675697</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26224429</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shinoda</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Yokota</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name><name><surname>Futami</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Divergent projection of individual corticospinal axons to motoneurons of multiple muscles in the monkey</article-title><source>Neurosci Lett</source><year>1981</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>7</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6164967</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Buys</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lemon</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name><name><surname>Mantel</surname><given-names>GWH</given-names></name><name><surname>Muir</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Selective facilitation of different hand muscles by single corticospinal neurones in the conscious monkey</article-title><source>J Physiol</source><year>1986</year><volume>381</volume><fpage>529</fpage><lpage>549</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1113/jphysiol.1986.sp016342</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1182994</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3625544</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Georgopoulos</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalaska</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Caminiti</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Massey</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>On the relations between the direction of two-dimensional arm movements and cell discharge in primate motor cortex</article-title><source>J Neurosci</source><year>1982</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>1527</fpage><lpage>1537</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.02-11-01527.1982</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6564361</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7143039</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Gribble</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Cabel</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dissociation between hand motion and population vectors from neural activity in motor cortex</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2001</year><volume>413</volume><fpage>161</fpage><lpage>165</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11557980</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kurtzer</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Herter</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nonuniform distribution of reach-related and torque-related activity in upper arm muscles and neurons of primary motor cortex</article-title><source>J Neurophysiol</source><year>2006</year><volume>96</volume><fpage>3220</fpage><lpage>3230</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17005623</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Kettner</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Georgopoulos</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Primate motor cortex and free arm movements to visual targets in three-dimensional space. I. Relations between single cell discharge and direction of movement</article-title><source>J Neurosci</source><year>1988</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>2913</fpage><lpage>2927</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.08-08-02913.1988</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6569414</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3411361</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kiehn</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Decoding the organization of spinal circuits that control locomotion</article-title><source>Nat Rev Neurosci</source><year>2016</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>224</fpage><lpage>238</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrn.2016.9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4844028</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26935168</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Higurashi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Locomotor kinematics and EMG activity during quadrupedal versus bipedal gait in the Japanese macaque</article-title><source>J Neurophysiol</source><year>2019</year><volume>122</volume><fpage>398</fpage><lpage>412</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31116630</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Courtine</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Kinematic and EMG determinants in quadrupedal locomotion of a non-human primate (Rhesus)</article-title><source>J Neurophysiol</source><year>2005</year><volume>93</volume><fpage>3127</fpage><lpage>3145</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15647397</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krouchev</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalaska</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Drew</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sequential activation of muscle synergies during locomotion in the intact cat as revealed by cluster analysis and direct decomposition</article-title><source>J Neurophysiol</source><year>2006</year><volume>96</volume><fpage>1991</fpage><lpage>2010</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16823029</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R41"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shima</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanji</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Involvement of NMDA and non-NMDA receptors in the neuronal responses of the primary motor cortex to input from the supplementary motor area and somatosensory cortex: studies of task-performing monkeys</article-title><source>Jpn J Physiol</source><year>1998</year><volume>48</volume><fpage>275</fpage><lpage>290</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9757144</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R42"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Muakkassa</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name><name><surname>Strick</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Frontal lobe inputs to primate motor cortex: evidence for four somatotopically organized ‘premotor’ areas</article-title><source>Brain Res</source><year>1979</year><volume>177</volume><fpage>176</fpage><lpage>182</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">115545</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R43"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dum</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name><surname>Strick</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Frontal lobe inputs to the digit representations of the motor areas on the lateral surface of the hemisphere</article-title><source>J Neurosci</source><year>2005</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>1375</fpage><lpage>1386</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.3902-04.2005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6726000</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15703391</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R44"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rouiller</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Transcallosal connections of the distal forelimb representations of the primary and supplementary motor cortical areas in macaque monkeys</article-title><source>Exp Brain Res</source><year>1994</year><volume>102</volume><fpage>227</fpage><lpage>243</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7705502</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R45"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boussaoud</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanne-Gariepy</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wannier</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Rouiller</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Callosal connections of dorsal versus ventral premotor areas in the macaque monkey: a multiple retrograde tracing study</article-title><source>BMC Neurosci</source><year>2005</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>67</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2202-6-67</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1314896</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16309550</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R46"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fregosi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Contestabile</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamadjida</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rouiller</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Corticobulbar projections from distinct motor cortical areas to the reticular formation in macaque monkeys</article-title><source>Eur J Neurosci</source><year>2017</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>1379</fpage><lpage>1395</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28394483</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R47"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Darling</surname><given-names>WG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Hand Motor Recovery Following Extensive Frontoparietal Cortical Injury Is Accompanied by Upregulated Corticoreticular Projections in Monkey</article-title><source>J Neurosci</source><year>2018</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>6323</fpage><lpage>6339</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.0403-18.2018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6041795</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29899028</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R48"><label>48</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beer</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><name><surname>Given</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Dewald</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Task-dependent weakness at the elbow in patients with hemiparesis</article-title><source>Arch Phys Med Rehabil</source><year>1999</year><volume>80</volume><fpage>766</fpage><lpage>772</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10414760</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R49"><label>49</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beer</surname><given-names>FP</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name><name><surname>Mazurek</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name><name><surname>Eisenberg</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name></person-group><source>Vector mechanics for engineers: Statics</source><publisher-name>McGraw-Hill</publisher-name><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc><year>2010</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R50"><label>50</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lemon</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name></person-group><source>Methods for Neuronal recording in Conscious Animals</source><publisher-name>Wiley</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc><year>1984</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R51"><label>51</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Soteropoulos</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bilateral representation in the deep cerebellar nuclei</article-title><source>J Physiol</source><year>2008</year><volume>586</volume><fpage>1117</fpage><lpage>1136</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1113/jphysiol.2007.144220</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2268981</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18187463</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R52"><label>52</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Multiple single unit recording in the cortex of monkeys using independently moveable microelectrodes</article-title><source>J Neurosci Methods</source><year>1999</year><volume>94</volume><fpage>5</fpage><lpage>17</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10638811</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R53"><label>53</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Angotzi</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>High-density, Identified Cell Recordings from Motor Cortex of Awake Behaving Macaques using 1024-channel SiNAPS Probes</article-title><source>BioRxiv</source><year>2025</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R54"><label>54</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Angotzi</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>SiNAPS: An implantable active pixel sensor CMOS-probe for simultaneous large-scale neural recordings</article-title><source>Biosensors &amp; bioelectronics</source><year>2019</year><volume>126</volume><fpage>355</fpage><lpage>364</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30466053</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R55"><label>55</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sakai</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name><name><surname>Davidson</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Buford</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reticulospinal neurons in the pontomedullary reticular formation of the monkey (Macaca fascicularis)</article-title><source>Neuroscience</source><year>2009</year><volume>163</volume><fpage>1158</fpage><lpage>1170</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroscience.2009.07.036</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2760615</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19631726</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R56"><label>56</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pachitariu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sridhar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Pennington</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Stringer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Spike sorting with Kilosort4</article-title><source>Nature methods</source><year>2024</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>914</fpage><lpage>921</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41592-024-02232-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11093732</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38589517</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R57"><label>57</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fabre</surname><given-names>JMJ</given-names></name><name><surname>van Beest</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name><name><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Carandini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bombcell: automated curation and cell classification of spike-sorted electrophysiology data</article-title><source>Zenodo</source><year>2023</year><elocation-id>8172822</elocation-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R58"><label>58</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A Fully Automated Approach to Spike Sorting</article-title><source>Neuron</source><year>2017</year><volume>95</volume><fpage>1381</fpage><lpage>1394</lpage><elocation-id>e1386</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2017.08.030</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5743236</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28910621</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R59"><label>59</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nawrot</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Aertsen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rotter</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Single-trial estimation of neuronal firing rates: from single-neuron spike trains to population activity</article-title><source>J Neurosci Methods</source><year>1999</year><volume>94</volume><fpage>81</fpage><lpage>92</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10638817</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R60"><label>60</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Silverman</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></name></person-group><source>Density estimation</source><publisher-name>Chapman &amp; Hall</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc><year>1986</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R61"><label>61</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tobin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Estimation of Relationships for Limited Dependent Variables</article-title><source>Econometria</source><year>1958</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>24</fpage><lpage>36</lpage></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Behavioral Task.</title><p>A, drawing of the experimental arrangement. The monkey’s arm was placed in a closely fitting cast linked to a six-axis force-torque transducer. B, screen arrangement viewed by the monkey. The central cursor (white) was moved left-right by shoulder abduction-adduction torques, and up-down by elbow flexion-extension torques. Squares show targets (only one appeared at a time). Green/black color marks targets close to/further away from the center (rest) position. C, shoulder, D, elbow torques. Each plot is positioned according to the location of targets on the screen. Traces are an average of all trials performed in one session in monkey C, aligned to the start of the hold period (shaded grey). Line colors indicate targets closer or further from the center, as in (B). Inner polar plot shows the torque as a function of target angle: solid lines indicate elbow flexion or shoulder abduction, dotted lines elbow extension or shoulder adduction. E, dependence on task of EMG from the posterior deltoid muscle, F, same for biceps muscle. Same arrangement of plots as (C,D).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS207660-f001"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Example of Single Unit Activity.</title><p>A, firing rate of a single unit recorded from the reticular formation in monkey C, using similar display conventions as <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>. Alignment is to the onset of torque. B, scatter plot of regression coefficients for task-related cells recorded in monkey C from the reticular formation, for firing rates during the period shaded grey in A. Filled circles mark cells which were significantly related to both shoulder and elbow torques; open circles were only significantly related to torque from one joint. Colors indicate the four quadrants, corresponding to different combinations of elbow and shoulder torques. Red colors are <italic>in synergy</italic>, blue <italic>out of synergy</italic> as defined in the text. Arrow marks the cell illustrated in (A).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS207660-f002"/></fig><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Distribution of Cells with Different Characteristics Related to Onset of Torque.</title><p>Each row relates to a different region of the brain. Purple/green pie charts show the number of cells detected via regression analysis to be coding for torques around both shoulder and elbow joints (purple), only a single joint (different shades of green), or not coding for torque (white). Red/blue pie charts take cells included in the purple sector, and further classify them according to the type of co-contraction which they represent. Red colors indicate <italic>in synergy</italic> combinations; blue colors indicate <italic>out of synergy</italic> combinations. Results are shown separately for each monkey.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS207660-f003"/></fig><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Distribution of Cells with Different Characteristics Related to Hold Period of Task.</title><p>Similar display as <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>, but for cells classified using firing measured during hold period.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS207660-f004"/></fig><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>Distribution of Cells with Different Characteristics Separated by Cell Type.</title><p>Results presented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figs 4</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref> for M1 and RF are separated by the class of cell. For M1, results are presented for identified pyramidal tract neurons (PTNs) or unidentified cells (UID). For RF, cells have been classified in two ways. IpsiRF/Contra RF separates the neurons according to which side of the brainstem they were recorded on (red vs black dots in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>). Gi/PnC separates cells according to their estimated rostro-caudal location, in nucleus gigantocellularis or the caudal part of the pontine reticular formation (see maps in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>). Results are combined across the two monkeys; data from contraction onset (Move) and Hold phases of the task are presented on the left and right side of the figure respectively.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS207660-f005"/></fig><fig id="F6" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title>Effects Produced by Microstimulation.</title><p>Each pie chart shows the distribution of effects produce by microstimulation in M1, RF or the spinal cord (SC). Effects are classified according to whether they activated elbow flexors only, shoulder abductors only, or both. Left column plots results for all available data, recorded at a range of stimulus intensities. Right column shows results only for sites stimulated at juxta-threshold stimulus intensity.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS207660-f006"/></fig></floats-group></article>