<!DOCTYPE article
 PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" article-type="preprint"><?all-math-mml yes?><?use-mml?><?origin ukpmcpa?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">bioRxiv</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>bioRxiv : the preprint server for biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2692-8205</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">EMS206389</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2025.06.06.658321</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="archive">PPR1033413</article-id><article-version-alternatives><article-version article-version-type="status">preprint</article-version><article-version article-version-type="number">1</article-version></article-version-alternatives><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Identification and Validation of a Previously Missed Mutational Signature in Colorectal Cancer</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kazachkova</surname><given-names>Mariya</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Otlu</surname><given-names>Burçak</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Díaz-Gay</surname><given-names>Marcos</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Abbasi</surname><given-names>Ammal</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A6">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Moody</surname><given-names>Sarah</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A7">7</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Perdomo</surname><given-names>Sandra</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A8">8</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wedge</surname><given-names>David C.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A9">9</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Brennan</surname><given-names>Paul</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A8">8</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Stratton</surname><given-names>Michael R.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A7">7</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Alexandrov</surname><given-names>Ludmil B.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A6">6</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A10">10</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CR1">*</xref></contrib><aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Biomedical Sciences Graduate Program, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/0168r3w48</institution-id><institution>University of California San Diego</institution></institution-wrap>, <city>La Jolla</city>, <state>CA</state>, <country country="US">USA</country></aff><aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Department of Cellular and Molecular Medicine, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/0168r3w48</institution-id><institution>University of California San Diego</institution></institution-wrap>, <city>La Jolla</city>, <state>CA</state>, <country country="US">USA</country></aff><aff id="A3"><label>3</label>Moores Cancer Center, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/0168r3w48</institution-id><institution>University of California San Diego</institution></institution-wrap>, <city>La Jolla</city>, <state>CA</state>, <country country="US">USA</country></aff><aff id="A4"><label>4</label>Department of Health Informatics, Graduate School of Informatics, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/014weej12</institution-id><institution>Middle East Technical University</institution></institution-wrap>, <city>Ankara</city>, <country country="TR">Turkey</country></aff><aff id="A5"><label>5</label>Digital Genomics Group, Structural Biology Program, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/00bvhmc43</institution-id><institution>Spanish National Cancer Research Center (CNIO)</institution></institution-wrap>, <city>Madrid</city>, <country country="ES">Spain</country></aff><aff id="A6"><label>6</label>Department of Bioengineering, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/0168r3w48</institution-id><institution>University of California San Diego</institution></institution-wrap>, <city>La Jolla</city>, <state>CA</state>, <country country="US">USA</country></aff><aff id="A7"><label>7</label>Cancer, Ageing and Somatic Mutation, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/05cy4wa09</institution-id><institution>Wellcome Sanger Institute</institution></institution-wrap>, <city>Cambridge</city>, <country country="GB">UK</country></aff><aff id="A8"><label>8</label>Genomic Epidemiology Branch, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/00v452281</institution-id><institution>International Agency for Research on Cancer (IARC/WHO)</institution></institution-wrap>, <city>Lyon</city>, <country country="FR">France</country></aff><aff id="A9"><label>9</label>Manchester Cancer Research Centre, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/027m9bs27</institution-id><institution>University of Manchester</institution></institution-wrap>, <city>Manchester</city>, <country country="GB">UK</country></aff><aff id="A10"><label>10</label>Sanford Stem Cell Institute, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/0168r3w48</institution-id><institution>University of California San Diego</institution></institution-wrap>, <city>La Jolla</city>, <state>CA</state>, <country country="US">USA</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="CR1"><label>*</label>Correspondence should be addressed to <email>L2alexandrov@health.ucsd.edu</email>.</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted"><day>14</day><month>06</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="preprint"><day>09</day><month>06</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><permissions><ali:free_to_read/><license><ali:license_ref>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is licensed under a <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0 International license</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p id="P1">Mutational signature analysis has greatly enhanced our understanding of the mutagenic processes found in cancer and normal tissues. As part of a recent study, we analyzed 802 treatment-naïve, microsatellite-stable colorectal cancers (CRC) and identified a <italic>de novo</italic> signature, SBS_D, which was conservatively decomposed into SBS18, a signature associated with reactive oxygen species. Here, we re-evaluate this decomposition and provide evidence that SBS_D represents a distinct mutational process from that of SBS18.</p><p id="P2">Through an independent analysis of 2,616 whole-genome sequenced microsatellite-stable CRCs across three distinct cohorts, we demonstrate that SBS_D is consistently present at a similar prevalence, suggesting that this signature may have been previously overlooked. Using a naïve decomposition approach, we demonstrate that the pattern of SBS_D better aligns with signatures previously associated with deficiencies in DNA polymerase delta (POLD1) proofreading and mismatch repair. However, multiple lines of evidence, including the absence of pathogenic mutations in the exonuclease domain of <italic>POLD1</italic> or in mismatch repair-associated genes, indicate that SBS_D is not driven by canonical defects in these DNA repair pathways.</p><p id="P3">Overall, this study identifies a previously unrecognized mutational signature in microsatellite-stable CRC and proposes that its etiology may be linked to DNA repair infidelity emerging late in tumor development in samples without canonical defects in DNA repair pathways.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec id="S1" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p id="P4">Over the past decade, mutational signature analysis has become a standard component of genomics research<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">2</xref></sup>, greatly enhancing our understanding of the extrinsic and intrinsic mutagenic factors that influence the genomes of both cancer<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">3</xref></sup> and normal somatic cells<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">4</xref></sup>. This has resulted in the development of global reference sets of mutational signatures, including those maintained by the Catalogue of Somatic Mutations in Cancer (COSMIC) database<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref></sup>.</p><p id="P5">In principle, mutational signature analysis can be performed in at least two ways: by assigning known reference signatures from databases like COSMIC to individual samples<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref></sup> or by conducting <italic>de novo</italic> extraction of mutational signatures<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">8</xref></sup>. This latter approach is commonly employed in the analysis of large datasets containing at least several hundred samples, enabling the identification of novel mutational signatures by detecting <italic>de novo</italic> signatures that do not correspond to known references<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">8</xref></sup>. Specifically, all <italic>de novo</italic> extracted signatures are either directly matched to known reference signatures or, more frequently, decomposed into a combination of multiple reference signatures. Given the extensive catalog of known reference signatures, the decomposition process can be optimized to prioritize biologically relevant signatures, minimizing the risk of overfitting<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref></sup>. For example, a mutational signature associated with ultraviolet (UV) light exposure would typically be excluded from the decomposition of <italic>de novo</italic> signatures detected in colorectal or brain tumors as UV-induced mutations are not expected in these contexts<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref></sup>. Following decomposition, any signature that cannot be accurately reconstructed using a combination of known signatures with a cosine similarity of at least 0.90 is generally considered novel<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref></sup>.</p><p id="P6">In most cases, it is straightforward to determine whether a mutational signature is known or novel. Many <italic>de novo</italic> extracted signatures are easily decomposed into known reference signatures with high similarity. Conversely, some signatures exhibit patterns that cannot be fully reconstructed with substantial similarity, indicating the presence of a novel signature absent from the current reference set. Nevertheless, borderline cases exist where it remains uncertain whether a signature represents a truly distinct mutational process or merely a complex combination of previously known signatures. Scientifically, there is always a temptation to report a new signature, as it suggests the discovery of a potentially novel mutagenic process. However, validating such a discovery requires robust evidence in independent cohorts, particularly for signatures with unknown etiology, to ensure their validity. As a result, studies may adopt a conservative approach, potentially leading to the underreporting of genuinely novel mutational signatures.</p><p id="P7">Here, we revisit a recent <italic>de novo</italic> mutational signature analysis of 802 whole-genome sequenced microsatellite-stable colorectal cancers (CRC) from the Mutographs project<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref></sup>. In the original analysis, we identified a <italic>de novo</italic> single base substitution (SBS) signature, designated SBS_D, which had a cosine similarity of 0.90 when decomposed into known COSMICv3.4 reference signatures. At the time, we adopted a conservative approach and did not classify SBS_D as a novel signature<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref></sup>. Instead, we reported its decomposition into known COSMIC signatures, including SBS18, which has been associated with reactive oxygen species<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref></sup>. Here, we demonstrate that SBS_D represents a distinct mutational process from SBS18. Furthermore, we successfully extract SBS_D from three independent, previously published CRC cohorts<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref></sup>, none of which had identified or reported it. Finally, based on associations with known molecular phenotypes in CRC, we propose that SBS_D may result from POLD1 proofreading and mismatch repair infidelity occurring late in the evolution of tumors without detectable canonical defects in either pathway. Collectively, our findings reveal the existence of a previously unrecognized mutational signature in microsatellite-stable CRC samples and underscore the challenges associated with identifying novel mutational signatures.</p></sec><sec id="S2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="S3"><title>Mutational Signatures and Their Predefined Schemas</title><p id="P8">All analyses of mutational signatures intrinsically rely on a predefined schema for classifying somatic mutations<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref></sup>. For somatic single base substitutions, the SBS-96 context is the most widely used classification schema and serves as the foundation for the current set of COSMIC reference SBS signatures<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref></sup>. In the SBS-96 framework, somatic mutations are classified into six base substitution types (C&gt;A, C&gt;G, C&gt;T, T&gt;A, T&gt;C, and T&gt;G) based on the pyrimidine base change within the mutated Watson-Crick base pair (<italic>e.g</italic>., C&gt;T representing a C:G&gt;T:A mutation). Each of the six types is further subdivided into 16 subtypes by incorporating the trinucleotide context, which accounts for the adjacent 5′ and 3′ bases of the mutated pyrimidine. While SBS-96 is the most used schema for SBSs, higher-resolution schemas like SBS-288 and SBS-1536 have been applied in recent large-scale analyses, including in previous Mutographs studies<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref></sup>. These schemas enhance resolution by incorporating additional features, such as transcriptional strand information in SBS-288 or an extended pentanucleotide context in SBS-1536<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref></sup> (<xref ref-type="sec" rid="S11">Methods</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S4"><title>Original Mutographs <italic>De Novo</italic> Signature Analysis</title><p id="P9">In the original analysis of 802 treatment-naïve, microsatellite-stable, DNA repair-proficient CRC samples from Mutographs, <italic>de novo</italic> extraction was performed using the SBS-288 classification schema<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref></sup>. This resulted in the identification of 16 <italic>de novo</italic> mutational signatures, labeled SBS_A through SBS_P (note that the use of letters distinguishes these from COSMIC reference signatures, which typically use numbers, <italic>e.g</italic>., SBS18). Of these, 12 signatures were decomposed into COSMIC reference signatures, with the decomposition optimized to exclude signatures associated with defective DNA repair, as the cohort included only DNA repair-proficient samples. The remaining four signatures represented mutational patterns not previously cataloged in COSMICv3.4 and were, as such, classified as novel. One of the 12 <italic>de novo</italic> signatures that was decomposed into COSMIC signatures, SBS_D, achieved a borderline reconstruction cosine similarity of 0.90. However, there was insufficient evidence to classify it as a novel signature, as no other large CRC mutational signature study had previously reported it. Adopting a conservative approach and given insufficient evidence at the time, we reported SBS_D as a mixture of previously known signatures while acknowledging the possibility that it may represent a novel signature<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref></sup>. Importantly, SBS_D was found in 428/802 microsatellite-stable CRC samples, contributing 8.5% of all mutations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1a</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S5"><title>Reevaluating the Pattern of SBS_D</title><p id="P10">The pattern of SBS_D was decomposed into COSMICv3.4 signatures SBS1 (14.5%), SBS5 (40.9%), SBS18 (32.6%), and SBS34 (12.0%) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1a</xref>). SBS1 and SBS5 are ubiquitous clock-like mutational signatures present in all types of cancer<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref></sup> and normal tissues<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref></sup>. Due to their pervasive nature, some degree of SBS1 and SBS5 contamination is expected in the decomposition of any <italic>de novo</italic> signature<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">8</xref></sup>, and, as anticipated, these signatures were found in many <italic>de novo</italic> signatures extracted from the Mutographs CRC cohort<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref></sup>. As such, if the decomposition was accurate, SBS_D would represent a combination of the reactive oxygen species-associated signature SBS18, the unknown etiology signature SBS34, and contributions from ubiquitous clock-like signatures (SBS1 and SBS5), with SBS18 being the predominant non-clock-like contributor. However, another <italic>de novo</italic> signature extracted from this cohort, SBS_B, exhibited a near perfect match to SBS18 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1b</xref>). Moreover, the C&gt;A component, which constitutes the majority of SBS18 mutations, showed substantial differences between SBS18 and SBS_D (cosine similarity [CS]=0.80; Spearman correlation [CORR]=0.72) but was nearly identical between SBS18 and SBS_B (CS=0.98; CORR=0.97; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1c</xref>). Considering the extremely high similarity between SBS18 and SBS_B, we will henceforth refer to SBS_B as SBS18^. Additionally, as part of the Mutographs study, additional extractions were performed using the SBS-96 and SBS-1536 classification schemas. Both approaches yielded two signatures closely resembling SBS18^ and SBS_D (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Figure 1</xref>). This consistency across different mutational schemas highlights the robustness of the patterns for these signatures, irrespective of the underlying classification framework. Overall, these findings raised doubts about the assignment of SBS18 as a contributor to SBS_D and suggested that SBS_D could represent a distinct mutational process.</p></sec><sec id="S6"><title>SBS_D Represents a Mutational Process Distinct from SBS18</title><p id="P11">To enhance our understanding of SBS_D and its relationship with SBS18^, we performed molecular timing on the microsatellite-stable, DNA repair proficient Mutographs CRC samples where copy number information was available (774 of 802 samples; 96.5%) by categorizing SBS mutations based on their timing relative to copy number gains during cancer development into two groups: early clonal and late clonal (<xref ref-type="sec" rid="S11">Methods</xref>). This stratification allowed us to analyze the contributions of SBS_D and SBS18^ across distinct stages of tumor evolution. Our analysis revealed that SBS_D was preferentially active in late clonal mutations compared to early clonal mutations (p-value&lt;0.0001; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2a</xref>). In contrast, SBS18^ was typically active exclusively early or both early and late but was rarely observed exclusively in late clonal mutations (p-value&lt;0.0001, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2b</xref>). Notably, prior studies have similarly demonstrated that SBS18 is either preferentially early or constant in CRC development<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">20</xref></sup>. These findings indicate that SBS_D is an evolutionarily late signature, likely representing a mutational process distinct from that of SBS18^.</p><p id="P12">Additionally, we performed topography analysis on the Mutographs CRC data to elucidate the topographical characteristics of SBS_D and SBS18^ (<xref ref-type="sec" rid="S11">Methods</xref>). Although the two mutational signatures were similar in replication timing and strand asymmetry analyses (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Figure 2</xref>), they displayed a notable difference in nucleosome occupancy (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2c</xref>). Specifically, SBS_D mutations were depleted near nucleosomes and did not exhibit any periodicity. In contrast, SBS18^ mutations were enriched near nucleosomes and demonstrated clear periodicity as expected and previously reported<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">21</xref></sup> for COSMIC signature SBS18 in CRC and across all cancer types (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2d</xref>). These observations further highlight the clear similarity between SBS18^ and SBS18, and they suggest that SBS_D represents a mutational process dissimilar to the one captured by SBS18.</p></sec><sec id="S7"><title>Signatures SBS_D and SBS18^ are Validated in Independent Cohorts</title><p id="P13">Although several large mutational signature extraction studies in CRC have been recently conducted<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref></sup>, none have reported a <italic>de novo</italic> signature resembling SBS_D. These prior studies analyzed DNA repair−proficient and repair−deficient samples together, which may have masked the presence of an SBS_D-like signature. Consistent with this, when we performed signature extraction on all Mutographs CRC samples without stratifying by DNA-repair status (<italic>n</italic>=981), no signature bearing resemblance to SBS_D was observed (CS&lt;0.85 across all 27 <italic>de novo</italic> signatures; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Figure 3</xref>).</p><p id="P14">To validate SBS_D and confirm its distinction from SBS18^, we performed <italic>de novo</italic> signature extraction on treatment-naïve, microsatellite-stable, DNA repair−proficient samples from three independent whole-genome sequenced CRC cohorts, including: <italic>(i)</italic> 390 recently whole-genome re-sequenced samples from The Cancer Genome Atlas (TCGA) project, representing patients predominantly from the United States<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref></sup>; <italic>(ii)</italic> 694 samples from a recently published study<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref></sup>, representing patients from Sweden; and <italic>(iii)</italic> 1,532 samples from the Genomics England (GEL) project<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref></sup>, representing patients from the United Kingdom (<xref ref-type="sec" rid="S11">Methods</xref>). <italic>De novo</italic> extractions for the Swedish and TCGA cohorts were conducted using the SBS-288 classification schema, consistent with the approach used in the Mutographs CRC project<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref></sup>. In contrast, the GEL cohort was analyzed using the SBS-96 schema, as it is the only publicly available mutational context for these cancers<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">22</xref></sup>. Despite differences in classification schemas, SBS_D and SBS18^ were identified across all three cohorts with high cosine similarity to their original Mutographs CRC signatures, reinforcing their distinction and confirming the reproducibility of SBS_D extraction in independent DNA repair proficient cohorts (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3a-b</xref>). Moreover, aside from the GEL cohort—which showed lower signature prevalence—the total number of mutations and the proportion of samples attributed to these two signatures were very similar across the cohorts, further supporting their robustness and consistency (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3a</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S8"><title>Naïve Decomposition of SBS_D</title><p id="P15">The Mutographs CRC study utilized an optimized decomposition method when decomposing <italic>de novo</italic> signatures to COSMICv3.4 signatures<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref></sup>. Specifically, since the analyzed samples were treatment-naïve, microsatellite-stable, and DNA repair-proficient, the decomposition process was designed to exclude mutational signatures associated with chemotherapy exposure or DNA repair deficiencies. In the naïve decomposition approach, which allows the use of all known COSMIC signatures, SBS_D decomposed to a mixture of SBS10c (44%), SBS15 (12%), SBS34 (7%), and the clock-like signatures (37%) with cosine similarity of 0.98 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4a</xref>). SBS10c has been shown to strictly come from samples harboring germline or somatic <italic>POLD1</italic> exonuclease domain mutations<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">23</xref></sup>, and SBS15 has been attributed to defective DNA mismatch repair in microsatellite-unstable samples<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref></sup>.</p><p id="P16">At first glance, these results suggest that SBS_D is associated with POLD1 deficiency or microsatellite instability. However, there are at least three lines of evidence that argue strongly against this result. <italic>First</italic>, all <italic>POLD1</italic>-mutant and microsatellite-unstable CRC samples—confirmed by droplet digital PCR—were excluded from the 802-sample cohort prior to signature extraction. We also thoroughly reviewed all samples for any previously missed pathogenic or potentially pathogenic mutations in <italic>POLD1</italic> or the mismatch repair-associated genes. Given that SBS10c has only been observed in tumors with pathogenic germline or somatic mutations in <italic>POLD1</italic>’s exonuclease domain<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">23</xref></sup>, the absence of such mutations in the 802 samples argues against POLD1 deficiency as the cause of SBS_D (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary Table 1−2</xref>). Although 12 samples carried non-pathogenic <italic>POLD1</italic> mutations, none showed elevated SBS_D activity (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Figure 4a</xref>). Similarly, among the 38 samples with mutations in known mismatch repair genes, SBS_D activity was not elevated (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Figure 4b</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary Table 1−2</xref>). Only one CRC sample was found to carry a pathogenic <italic>MSH6</italic> nonsense mutation, but it lacked both SBS_D activity and a mutational profile consistent with microsatellite instability (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Figure 5</xref>). Similarly, we observed no difference in SBS_D activity between samples with and without loss of heterozygosity in <italic>POLD1</italic> or DNA mismatch repair genes (<italic>POLD1</italic>: 103/774; DNA mismatch repair: 420/774; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Figure 4c-d</xref>). <italic>Second</italic>, while samples with known <italic>POLD1</italic> mutations or microsatellite instability showed 10- to 100-fold higher substitution and indel rates, this elevated mutational burden was not observed in microsatellite-stable samples positive for SBS_D (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4b</xref>). <italic>Third</italic>, tumors with pathogenic <italic>POLD1</italic> mutations or microsatellite instability typically have stable, diploid genomes with aberrations affecting less than 20% of the genome, which is in stark contrast to the substantial genomic instability observed in most tumors with SBS_D activity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4b</xref>). While microsatellite instability—but not POLD1 deficiency—can also arise from epigenetic events, mainly the hypermethylation of the <italic>MLH1</italic> promoter<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref></sup>, such data were not available for the Mutographs cohort. However, epigenetically driven cases also exhibit high levels of substitutions and indels<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">25</xref></sup>, which were not observed in SBS_D-positive samples. Together, this supports the conclusion that SBS_D is not driven by canonical defects in POLD1 or mismatch repair.</p></sec><sec id="S9"><title>Exploring the Potential Etiology of SBS_D</title><p id="P17">Although SBS_D does not appear to result from canonical defects in <italic>POLD1</italic> or mismatch repair genes, the similarity in mutational patterns suggests that POLD1—and possibly mismatch repair—may still contribute to its underlying mutational processes. This hypothesis is further supported by three key observations in the Mutographs CRC cohort. <italic>First</italic>, although SBS_D-positive samples lacked the characteristic features of POLD1 or DNA repair deficiency—such as hypermutation and low genome aberration (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4b</xref>)—they exhibited strikingly higher indel burden compared to SBS_D-negative samples (1.3-fold increase; q-value of 2.50 × 10<sup>-12</sup> after adjusting for known covariates), whereas negligible differences were observed for SBS burden and genome aberration (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5a</xref>). A markedly higher indel burden was also observed in SBS_D positive samples across the TCGA, Swedish, and GEL cohorts (q-values&lt;10<sup>-10</sup>; 1.3-fold increase in TCGA; 1.3-fold increase in the Swedish cohort; 1.4-fold increase in GEL; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Figure 6</xref>). <italic>Second</italic>, a prior study<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">23</xref></sup> showed that POLD1-deficient tumors are hypermutated specifically for indel signature ID1, which arises from replication slippage of the newly synthesized strand. Notably, SBS_D was the SBS signature most strongly correlated with ID1 activity (CORR=0.66; q-value&lt;0.0001; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5b</xref>). <italic>Third</italic>, SBS10c in POLD1-defective tumors exhibits a distinct nucleosome occupancy pattern, marked by strong depletion at nucleosome-bound regions, and a similar depletion pattern was observed for SBS_D in the DNA repair proficient samples (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5c</xref>). While we can be confident that SBS_D is not driven by established genomic aberrations in <italic>POLD1</italic> and mismatch repair genes, our results suggest that there may be a link between SBS_D and infidelity in these DNA repair processes.</p></sec></sec><sec id="S10" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p id="P18">In this study, we revisited the Mutographs CRC mutational signature analysis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref></sup>, where mutational signature SBS_D was previously decomposed into the reactive oxygen species-associated signature SBS18. Although our results do not alter the main finding from the Mutographs CRC project, they do indicate that the conservative approach taken by Mutographs has missed that SBS_D represents a distinct mutational process from SBS18. Furthermore, although SBS_D is consistently present at similar prevalence across multiple independent microsatellite-stable CRC cohorts, it was not previously reported in these studies.</p><p id="P19">As multiple large-scale colorectal cancer cohorts<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref></sup> have previously undergone mutational signature analysis, it is surprising that SBS_D has not been reported. This seems to be due to previous studies not separating DNA repair deficient and DNA repair proficient cancers prior to performing <italic>de novo</italic> signature extraction. DNA repair deficient tumors typically harbor at least an order of magnitude more single base substitutions—around 10<sup>5</sup> compared to ~10<sup>4</sup> in microsatellite-stable cases—which can obscure weaker signals that overlap with signatures of DNA repair deficiency. Since SBS_D shares features with signatures commonly found in hypermutated, DNA repair−deficient tumors, it is particularly prone to being masked during extraction from mixed cohorts. This challenge is further amplified by the fact that SBS_D typically accounts for only 5 to 10% of all mutations in microsatellite-stable tumors. Indeed, without stratifying DNA repair−proficient and DNA repair−deficient samples, the orders-of-magnitude-higher mutation rates from hypermutated microsatellite-unstable or polymerase proofreading-deficient tumors can mask the more subtle contribution of SBS_D.</p><p id="P20">To address this, the original Mutographs CRC study<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref></sup> implemented a key strategy by analyzing microsatellite-stable and unstable samples separately. However, the study also adopted a conservative stance and did not classify SBS_D as a novel signature. At the time, its decomposition into known reference signatures was borderline, and without the additional evidence presented in this study, SBS_D was interpreted as a composite rather than a distinct entity. The results in this study underscore the need to further investigate signatures with borderline decompositions, including analyses of additional cohorts and evaluation of naïve signature decomposition approaches that incorporate all known reference signatures.</p><p id="P21">Overall, despite extensive studies on CRC mutational landscapes, our findings reveal a previously unrecognized mutational signature in microsatellite-stable CRC that may reflect DNA repair infidelity during the late stages of CRC evolution. However, to conclusively determine the etiology of SBS_D, further <italic>in vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic> experiments will be required. Notably, recent advances in polymerase error rate sequencing (PER-seq) have provided new insights into polymerase epsilon fidelity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">26</xref></sup>, and similar approaches will be needed to experimentally validate the potential role of POLD1 infidelity in this newly identified mutational signature.</p></sec><sec id="S11" sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec id="S12"><title>Mutational Contexts</title><p id="P22">Briefly, the SBS-96 mutational context organizes somatic mutations into six base substitution types: C&gt;A, C&gt;G, C&gt;T, T&gt;A, T&gt;C, and T&gt;G (according to the pyrimidine base of the Watson-Crick base-pair). Each type is divided into 16 subtypes based on the trinucleotide context, which accounts for the bases immediately preceding and following the mutation (4 possible bases at the 5′ position × 4 at the 3′ position × 6 substitution types = 96 categories)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref></sup>. The SBS-1536 classification extends the SBS-96 schema by incorporating the pentanucleotide context, resulting in 1,536 mutational channels (256 per each of the six base substitution types). While its complexity has limited its widespread use, SBS-1536 has previously provided insights into mutational processes such as APOBEC-mediated cytidine deamination<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27">27</xref></sup>. The SBS-288 classification builds upon SBS-96 by introducing three additional subcategories for each mutation: <italic>(i)</italic> non-transcribed, <italic>(ii)</italic> transcribed, and <italic>(iii)</italic> un-transcribed. This schema differentiates mutations occurring in non-transcribed (<italic>i.e</italic>., non-genic) regions of the genome from those in transcribed regions of the genome. Mutations within transcribed regions are further divided based on the transcriptional strand orientation relative to the pyrimidine mutated base<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref></sup>, resulting in the <italic>transcribed</italic> and <italic>un-transcribed</italic> classifications. This enhanced framework enables more detailed investigations of transcription-coupled DNA damage and repair processes, for example, transcription-coupled nucleotide excision repair. Importantly, both the SBS-288 and SBS-1536 schemas are fully collapsible to SBS-96, allowing extracted signatures to be converted back to the SBS-96 schema for direct comparison with COSMIC reference signatures. The mutational context enables the transformation of mutational catalogs from cancer genomes into a mutational matrix, where each row represents a specific mutation type and each column corresponds to a tumor sample.</p></sec><sec id="S13"><title>Mutational Signature Extraction and Decomposition</title><p id="P23">Mutational signature extraction and decomposition results from the Mutographs CRC Project<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref></sup> were utilized in this study. Briefly, we previously used SigProfilerExtractor<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">8</xref></sup>, which involves performing nonnegative matrix factorization (NMF) on a mutational matrix, to identify the underlying mutational signatures in the cohort. Extractions were performed using the SBS-96, SBS-288, and SBS-1536 contexts, and the signatures from the SBS-288 extraction were decomposed and used for the Mutographs CRC study. Decomposition of the <italic>de novo</italic> signatures, which means identifying which known reference signatures best explain each of the <italic>de novo</italic> signatures, was performed using an optimized approach where the following signature subsets were removed from the decomposition: artifact signatures, ultraviolet signatures, lymphoid signatures, mismatch repair deficiency signatures, polymerase deficiency signatures, base excision repair deficiency signatures, and treatment signatures. This was done using SigProfilerAssignment<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref></sup> and utilizing the exclude_signature_subgroups parameter.</p></sec><sec id="S14"><title>Identification of Mutational Signature Activity in Each Sample</title><p id="P24">As in the original Mutographs CRC project<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref></sup>, Mutational Signature Attribution<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">28</xref></sup> (MSA) was used to attribute each of the <italic>de novo</italic> mutational signatures to each sample. MSA was run using the same parameters used for the original Mutographs CRC study, including setting the no_CI_for_penalties parameter to false for penalty selection. Analyses were performed using the pruned attributions produced by the tool. Somatic mutations attributed to each mutational signature after mapping to COSMICv3.4—along with SBS_D, which is now classified as a novel signature—are provided in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary Table 3</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="S15"><title>Molecular Timing of SBS18^ and SBS_D</title><p id="P25">Copy number profiles, generated using Battenberg<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">29</xref></sup>, and somatic variant calls, generated using a consensus between the CaVEMan<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">30</xref></sup> and Strelka2<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31">31</xref></sup> callers, were generated as part of the Mutographs CRC project. These data were used to run DPClust3p<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">29</xref></sup> and DPClust<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">29</xref></sup> to identify the cancer cell fraction (CCF) of each somatic mutation and estimated number of chromosomes carrying each somatic mutation. The following logic was applied: in areas with copy number amplifications, if a mutation appeared on more than one chromosome copy, it was labeled as early clonal, and if a mutation appeared on one or less chromosome copies when a gain had occurred on the major allele in that location, it was labeled as likely late clonal; this logic was only applied to clonal mutations (those with CCF&gt;0.95).</p><p id="P26">Samples with at least 256 early clonal and 256 late clonal mutations were retained for analysis (684/774), as has been done in previous studies<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref></sup>. MSA was then used to identify the activity of each <italic>de novo</italic> mutational signature in each early clonal and late clonal set of mutations. A McNemar test was used to assess if the frequencies of samples with SBS_D activity and SBS18^ activity were different between late clonal and early clonal mutations.</p></sec><sec id="S16"><title>Topography Analysis</title><p id="P27">SigProfilerTopography<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32">32</xref></sup> was used to analyze the topographical features of SBS_D, SBS18^, and SBS10c. Probability files and activity files were generated using MSA as part of the Mutographs CRC project. For the SBS_D and SBS18^ analysis, MSA was run with the SBS-288 <italic>de novo</italic> signatures and the 802 DNA repair proficient samples. For the SBS10c analysis, MSA was run using the COSMICv3.4 reference signatures and the three <italic>POLD1</italic>-mutant samples from the full Mutographs CRC cohort. Both runs of SigProfilerTopography<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32">32</xref></sup> used 0.75 for the average_probability parameter. For replication timing and replication strand asymmetry analyses, the HCT116 colon carcinoma cell line was used as the reference. For nucleosome occupancy, the K562 cell line was used as the reference.</p></sec><sec id="S17"><title>Somatic Variant Calling in Three Independent Cohorts</title><p id="P28">For the Swedish Cohort, somatic mutation calls were publicly available and had been identified using Mutect<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33">33</xref></sup>, Mutect2<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34">34</xref></sup>, and TNscope<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35">35</xref></sup>. For GEL, only the SBS-96 mutational matrix was available; somatic mutations for GEL were identified using Strelka<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31">31</xref></sup>. Because mutation calls are not yet available for the TCGA whole-genome sequenced CRC samples, we identified mutations using Mutect2<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34">34</xref></sup> with the pcr-indel-model parameter set to HOSTILE and all other parameters set to default values; the standard PASS filter was the applied.</p></sec><sec id="S18"><title>Sample Filtering in Three Independent Cohorts</title><p id="P29">Samples in each independent cohort were filtered to mimic the DNA repair proficient sample set used in the Mutographs CRC project. For all three cohorts, samples with over 100,000 single base substitution (SBS) mutations or over 7,000 indel mutations were removed. In addition, any samples with less than 1,000 SBS mutations were removed. To account for mutations in <italic>MUTYH, NTLH1</italic>, and <italic>OGG1</italic>, samples with cosine similarity greater than 0.80 to any of the respective signatures (SBS36 from COSMIC<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36">36</xref></sup>, SBS30 from COSMIC<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36">36</xref></sup>, and SBS108 from SIGNAL<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37">37</xref></sup>) were removed. Like in the Mutographs CRC project, two samples from the Swedish cohort were removed for suspected microsatellite instable activity (high levels of SBS15) despite not being hypermutators.</p></sec><sec id="S19"><title>Mutational Signature Extraction in Three Independent Cohorts</title><p id="P30">After filtering, SBS matrices were generated for the TCGA and Swedish cohort using SigProfilerMatrixGenerator<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref></sup>. For the GEL cohort, the publicly available SBS-96 mutational matrix was filtered and used for downstream analysis as the variant calling files are not publicly available. SigProfilerExtractor<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">8</xref></sup> with default parameters was then used to extract mutational signatures from each cohort, and the suggested solution was used for each extraction.</p></sec><sec id="S20"><title>Characterizing Pathogenicity of Mutations in <italic>POLD1</italic> and DNA Mismatch Repair Genes</title><p id="P31">Ensembl Variant Effect Predictor (VEP)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38">38</xref></sup> was previously used to annotate mutations in the Mutographs CRC cohort. All mutations with the MODIFIER annotation (lowest impact) were filtered out. All protein-altering single base substitution and indel mutations from the 802 DNA repair proficient samples in <italic>POLD1</italic> and DNA mismatch repair genes (<italic>MLH1, MLH3, MSH2, MSH3, MSH6, PMS1</italic>, and <italic>PMS2</italic>) were examined using CLINVAR<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39">39</xref></sup>. Results were reported in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary Table 1</xref> (single base substitutions) and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary Table 2</xref> (indels).</p></sec><sec id="S21"><title>Linear Models for Comparing Genomic Features</title><p id="P32">A generalized linear model (Python version 3.9.7; statsmodels version 0.13.2) was used to identify the association between SBS_D status and total number of single base substitutions, total number of indel mutations, and fraction genome aberrant. Fraction genome aberrant values came from the original Mutographs CRC study<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref></sup>. A single model was used for each feature, and sex, age, tumor subsite, country, and purity were all included as covariates. This same approach was used to identify associations between SBS_D status and total number of indel mutations in the Swedish and TCGA cohorts<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref></sup>. No linear modeling was performed for the Genomics England (GEL) cohort<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref></sup> due to the lack of publicly available metadata.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="SM"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1"><label>Supplementary Figures</label><media xlink:href="EMS206389-supplement-Supplementary_Figures.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" id="d15aAcEbB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD2"><label>Supplementary Tables</label><media xlink:href="EMS206389-supplement-Supplementary_Tables.xls" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel" id="d15aAcEcB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD3"><label>Supplementary Figure Legends</label><media xlink:href="EMS206389-supplement-Supplementary_Figure_Legends.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" id="d15aAcEdB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack id="S22"><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>M.K. was supported by the Cancer Biology, Informatics, and Omics Training Grant (T32CA067754) and the Merkin Fellowship through the University of California San Diego. This work was delivered as part of the Mutographs team supported by the Cancer Grand Challenges partnership funded by Cancer Research UK (C98/A24032). M.R.S. and S.M. are also supported by the Wellcome Trust core grant (206194). M.D.-G. was awarded with a fellowship within the “Generación D” initiative, Red.es, Ministerio para la Transformación Digital y de la Función Pública, for talent attraction (C005/24-ED CV1), funded by the European Union NextGenerationEU funds, through PRTR. D.C.W. is co-funded by Cancer Research UK RadNet Manchester (grant no. C1994/A28701), NIHR Manchester BRC (grant no. NIHR203308), The University of Manchester and the Christie NHS Foundation Trust. This work was supported by the US National Institute of Health grants R01ES032547, R01ES036931, R01CA269919, R01CA296974, P01CA281819, and U01CA290479 to L.B.A. as well as by L,B.A.’s Packard Fellowship for Science and Engineering and the UC San Diego Sanford Stem Cell Institute. The computational analyses reported in this manuscript have utilized the Triton Shared Computing Cluster at the San Diego Supercomputer Center of UC San Diego. The funders had no roles in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="con" id="FN1"><p id="P33"><bold>Contributions</bold></p><p id="P34">This study was conceived by M.K. and supervised by L.B.A., D.C.W., M.R.S., and P.B. Analysis of data was performed by M.K. and B.O. with guidance from L.B.A., D.C.W., S.M., M.D.-G, A.A., and S.P. The Cancer Genome Atlas (TCGA) data was downloaded and processed by M.K. and A.A. The manuscript was written by M.K. and L.B.A. with contributions from all other authors. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></fn><fn fn-type="conflict" id="FN2"><p id="P35"><bold>Competing Interests</bold></p><p id="P36">M.R.S. is a founder, stockholder and consultant for Quotient Therapeutics. L.B.A. is a co-founder, CSO, scientific advisory member, and consultant for io9 (now Acurion), has equity and receives income. The terms of this arrangement have been reviewed and approved by the University of California, San Diego in accordance with its conflict of interest policies. L.B.A. is also a compensated member of the scientific advisory board of Inocras. L.B.A.’s spouse is an employee of Hologic, Inc. L.B.A. declares U.S. provisional applications filed with UCSD with serial numbers: 63/269,033; 63/289,601; 63/483,237; 63/412,835; and 63/492,348. L.B.A. and A.A. declare US provisional patent application filed with UCSD with serial number 63/366,392. L.B.A. is also an inventor of a US Patent 10,776,718 for source identification by non-negative matrix factorization. L.B.A., M.D.-G., M.R.S., P.B., S.P., and S.M. further declare a European patent application with application number EP25305077.7. All other authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><ref id="R1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Mutational signatures: From methods to mechanisms</article-title><source>Annu Rev Biomed Data Sci</source><year>2021</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>189</fpage><lpage>206</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34465178</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koh</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Degasperi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Momen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nik-Zainal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mutational signatures: emerging concepts, caveats and clinical applications</article-title><source>Nat Rev Cancer</source><year>2021</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>619</fpage><lpage>637</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34316057</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boysen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Investigating the origins of the mutational signatures in cancer</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2025</year><volume>53</volume><elocation-id>gkae1303</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11707540</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39778866</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkae1303</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fiala</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Diamandis</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mutations in normal tissues-some diagnostic and clinical implications</article-title><source>BMC Med</source><year>2020</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>283</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7594459</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33115454</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12916-020-01763-y</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alexandrov</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The repertoire of mutational signatures in human cancer</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2020</year><volume>578</volume><fpage>94</fpage><lpage>101</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7054213</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32025018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41586-020-1943-3</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sondka</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>COSMIC: a curated database of somatic variants and clinical data for cancer</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2024</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>D1210</fpage><lpage>D1217</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10767972</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38183204</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkad986</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Díaz-Gay</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Assigning mutational signatures to individual samples and individual somatic mutations with SigProfilerAssignment</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2023</year><volume>39</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10746860</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38096571</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btad756</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Islam</surname><given-names>SMA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Uncovering novel mutational signatures by de novo extraction with SigProfilerExtractor</article-title><source>Cell Genom</source><year>2022</year><volume>2</volume><comment>None</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9646490</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36388765</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.xgen.2022.100179</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Díaz-Gay</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Geographic and age variations in mutational processes in colorectal cancer</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2025</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>2</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40267983</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Senkin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Geographic variation of mutagenic exposures in kidney cancer genomes</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2024</year><volume>629</volume><fpage>910</fpage><lpage>918</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11111402</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38693263</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41586-024-07368-2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Torrens</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The complexity of tobacco smoke-induced mutagenesis in head and neck cancer</article-title><source>Nature Genetics</source><year>2024</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>884</fpage><lpage>896</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11985354</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40164736</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41588-025-02134-0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alexandrov</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Signatures of mutational processes in human cancer</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2013</year><volume>500</volume><fpage>415</fpage><lpage>421</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3776390</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23945592</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature12477</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>Cancer Genome Atlas Network</collab><article-title>Comprehensive molecular characterization of human colon and rectal cancer</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2012</year><volume>487</volume><fpage>330</fpage><lpage>337</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3401966</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22810696</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature11252</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nunes</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Prognostic genome and transcriptome signatures in colorectal cancers</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2024</year><volume>633</volume><fpage>137</fpage><lpage>146</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11374687</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39112715</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41586-024-07769-3</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cornish</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The genomic landscape of 2,023 colorectal cancers</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2024</year><volume>633</volume><fpage>127</fpage><lpage>136</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11374690</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39112709</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41586-024-07747-9</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moody</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Mutational signatures in esophageal squamous cell carcinoma from eight countries with varying incidence</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><year>2021</year><volume>53</volume><fpage>1553</fpage><lpage>1563</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34663923</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bergstrom</surname><given-names>EN</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>SigProfilerMatrixGenerator: a tool for visualizing and exploring patterns of small mutational events</article-title><source>BMC Genomics</source><year>2019</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>685</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6717374</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31470794</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12864-019-6041-2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Vijg</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Somatic mutations in aging and disease</article-title><source>GeroScience</source><year>2024</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>5171</fpage><lpage>5189</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11336144</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38488948</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11357-024-01113-3</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gerstung</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The evolutionary history of 2,658 cancers</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2020</year><volume>578</volume><fpage>122</fpage><lpage>128</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7054212</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32025013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41586-019-1907-7</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dentro</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Characterizing genetic intra-tumor heterogeneity across 2,658 human cancer genomes</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2021</year><volume>184</volume><fpage>2239</fpage><lpage>2254</lpage><elocation-id>e39</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8054914</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33831375</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2021.03.009</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Otlu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Topography of mutational signatures in human cancer</article-title><source>Cell Rep</source><year>2023</year><volume>42</volume><elocation-id>112930</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10507738</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37540596</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.celrep.2023.112930</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Degasperi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Substitution mutational signatures in whole-genome-sequenced cancers in the UK population</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2022</year><volume>376</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7613262</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35949260</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.abl9283</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Increased somatic mutation burdens in normal human cells due to defective DNA polymerases</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><year>2021</year><volume>53</volume><fpage>1434</fpage><lpage>1442</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8492474</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34594041</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41588-021-00930-y</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Niv</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Microsatellite instability and MLH1 promoter hypermethylation in colorectal cancer</article-title><source>World J Gastroenterol</source><year>2007</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>1767</fpage><lpage>1769</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4149951</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17465465</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3748/wjg.v13.i12.1767</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Microsatellite instability and high tumor mutational burden detected by next generation sequencing are concordant with loss of mismatch repair proteins by immunohistochemistry</article-title><source>Cancer Genet</source><year>2025</year><volume>290–291</volume><fpage>44</fpage><lpage>50</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39700818</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tomková</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Human DNA polymerase ε is a source of C&gt;T mutations at CpG dinucleotides</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><year>2024</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>2506</fpage><lpage>2516</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11549043</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39390083</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41588-024-01945-x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>JKL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Association of mutation signature effectuating processes with mutation hotspots in driver genes and non-coding regions</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2022</year><volume>13</volume><elocation-id>178</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8748499</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35013316</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-021-27792-6</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Senkin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MSA: reproducible mutational signature attribution with confidence based on simulations</article-title><source>BMC Bioinformatics</source><year>2021</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>540</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8567580</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34736398</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12859-021-04450-8</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nik-Zainal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The life history of 21 breast cancers</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2012</year><volume>149</volume><fpage>994</fpage><lpage>1007</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3428864</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22608083</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2012.04.023</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>CgpCaVEManWrapper: Simple execution of CaVEMan in order to detect somatic single nucleotide variants in NGS data</article-title><source>Curr Protoc Bioinformatics</source><year>2016</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>15101</fpage><lpage>151018</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6097605</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27930805</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cpbi.20</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Strelka2: fast and accurate calling of germline and somatic variants</article-title><source>Nat Methods</source><year>2018</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>591</fpage><lpage>594</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30013048</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Otlu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Alexandrov</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluating topography of mutational signatures with SigProfilerTopography</article-title><source>Genome Biol</source><year>2025</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>134</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12093824</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40394581</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13059-025-03612-8</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cibulskis</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Sensitive detection of somatic point mutations in impure and heterogeneous cancer samples</article-title><source>Nat Biotechnol</source><year>2013</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>213</fpage><lpage>219</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3833702</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23396013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nbt.2514</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Benjamin</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Calling Somatic SNVs and Indels with Mutect2</article-title><source>bioRxiv</source><year>2019</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/861054</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Freed</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Aldana</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>TNscope: Accurate detection of somatic mutations with haplotype-based variant candidate detection and machine learning filtering</article-title><source>bioRxiv</source><year>2018</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/250647</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tate</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>COSMIC: The Catalogue Of Somatic Mutations In Cancer</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2019</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>D941</fpage><lpage>D947</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6323903</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30371878</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gky1015</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Degasperi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A practical framework and online tool for mutational signature analyses show inter-tissue variation and driver dependencies</article-title><source>Nat Cancer</source><year>2020</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>249</fpage><lpage>263</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7048622</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32118208</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s43018-020-0027-5</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McLaren</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The Ensembl Variant Effect Predictor</article-title><source>Genome Biol</source><year>2016</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>122</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4893825</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27268795</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13059-016-0974-4</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Landrum</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>ClinVar: improving access to variant interpretations and supporting evidence</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2018</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>D1062</fpage><lpage>D1067</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5753237</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29165669</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkx1153</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>SBS_D and SBS_B from the Mutographs colorectal cancer cohort.</title><p><bold><italic>(a)</italic></bold> Optimized decomposition of SBS_D showing the total number of mutations attributed to the signature and the proportion of samples in which it is detected. <bold><italic>(b)</italic></bold> Optimized decomposition of SBS_B showing the total number of mutations attributed to the signature and the proportion of samples in which it is detected. <bold><italic>(c)</italic></bold> Comparison of the C&gt;A contexts among COSMIC signature SBS18, <italic>de novo</italic> signature SBS_B, and <italic>de novo</italic> signature SBS_D. SBS_B and SBS_D were collapsed to the SBS-96 mutation classification schema, and normalization was performed within the C&gt;A contexts. Cosine similarity (cs) and Spearman correlation (corr) are shown relative to the C&gt;A contexts for SBS18.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS206389-f001"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>SBS_D and SBS18^ reflect distinct mutational processes.</title><p><bold><italic>(a)</italic></bold> <italic>(Left)</italic> Relative SBS_D activity in early and late clonal mutations. Each line represents one sample: gray lines indicate SBS_D activity in both early and late clonal mutations, blue lines indicate activity only in early clonal mutations, and red lines indicate activity only in late clonal mutations. <italic>(Right)</italic> Number of samples with SBS_D activity in each category. Samples lacking SBS_D activity in both early and late clonal mutations are excluded from the plots. P-value is based on a McNemar test. <bold><italic>(b)</italic></bold> Same format as panel <italic>(a)</italic>, but for SBS18^, showing a different pattern of activity across early and late clonal mutations. <bold><italic>(c)</italic></bold> Nucleosome occupancy pattern for SBS_D (<italic>left</italic>) and SBS18^ (<italic>right</italic>), as identified by SigProfilerTopography. Each plot is centered on the mutation site, with 1,000 base pairs upstream (5’) and downstream (3’). Solid lines represent the average nucleosome signal for observed mutations; dashed lines show the signal for simulated mutations. <bold><italic>(d)</italic></bold> Nucleosome occupancy patterns for COSMIC signature SBS18 across all cancer types (<italic>left</italic>) and restricted to colorectal cancer (CRC) samples (<italic>right</italic>) from the COSMIC website. Plot features and layout match those in panel <italic>(c)</italic>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS206389-f002"/></fig><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Independent colorectal cancer cohorts support reproducibility of SBS_D and SBS18^.</title><p><bold><italic>(a)</italic></bold> SBS18^ (<italic>left</italic>) and SBS_D (<italic>right</italic>) signatures extracted from the Mutographs, The Cancer Genome Atlas (TCGA), Swedish, and Genomics England (GEL) colorectal cancer (CRC) cohorts. Signature extraction for the Mutographs, TCGA, and Swedish cohorts was performed using the SBS-288 context and then collapsed to SBS-96 for visualization; the GEL cohort was directly analyzed in the SBS-96 context. The number of mutations and positive samples reflects results from mutational signature attribution (MSA) using <italic>de novo</italic> signatures identified by SigProfilerExtractor. <bold><italic>(b)</italic></bold> Heatmap showing cosine similarities among SBS18^-like and SBS_D-like signatures extracted from the four CRC cohorts.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS206389-f003"/></fig><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Naïve decomposition of SBS_D and its distinction from <italic>POLD1</italic>-mutant and MSI tumors.</title><p><bold><italic>(a)</italic></bold> Naïve decomposition of SBS_D using the complete COSMIC reference signature set. <bold><italic>(b)</italic></bold> Comparison of microsatellite-stable samples with SBS_D activity (MSS SBS_D+), <italic>POLD1</italic>-mutant samples, and samples harboring microsatellite instability (MSI) in terms of total number of single base substitutions (SBSs; <italic>left</italic>), small insertions and deletions (indels; <italic>middle</italic>), and fraction genome aberrant (<italic>right</italic>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS206389-f004"/></fig><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>SBS_D exhibits mutational features suggestive of DNA repair infidelity.</title><p><bold><italic>(a)</italic></bold> Comparison of SBS_D-positive (SBS_D<sup>+</sup>) and SBS_D-negative (SBS_D<sup>−</sup>) samples across total number of single base substitution mutations (<italic>left</italic>), total number of indel mutations (<italic>middle</italic>), and fraction of the genome with copy number aberrations (<italic>right</italic>). P-values were calculated using linear models adjusted for age, sex, tumor subsite, country, and tumor purity, followed by Benjamini-Hochberg multiple testing correction to yield q-values. <bold><italic>(b)</italic></bold> Spearman correlation between the activity of each <italic>de novo</italic> SBS signature and ID1 activity. Asterisks indicate significant correlations with q-value&lt;0.001 after Benjamini-Hochberg multiple testing correction. <bold><italic>(c)</italic></bold> Nucleosome occupancy pattern for SBS10c in the three <italic>POLD1</italic>-mutant samples from the Mutographs colorectal cancer cohort (<italic>top</italic>); nucleosome occupancy for SBS_D in the microsatellite-stable Mutographs colorectal cancers. Each plot is centered on the mutation site, with 1,000 base pairs upstream (5’) and downstream (3’). Solid lines represent the average nucleosome signal for observed mutations; dashed lines show the signal for simulated mutations.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS206389-f005"/></fig></floats-group></article>