<!DOCTYPE article
 PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" article-type="preprint"><?all-math-mml yes?><?use-mml?><?origin ukpmcpa?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">bioRxiv</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>bioRxiv : the preprint server for biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2692-8205</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">EMS207556</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2025.07.22.666027</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="archive">PPR1055286</article-id><article-version-alternatives><article-version article-version-type="status">preprint</article-version><article-version article-version-type="number">1</article-version></article-version-alternatives><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Human ribosome interactions reframe neomycin toxicity</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Xinyi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Lingfan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>Changfeng</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Keqin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>Yuanjie</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Shuangli</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Zhe</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Lei</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>Xuben</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CR1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Meng</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CR1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Amunts</surname><given-names>Alexey</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">5</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CR1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Wenfei</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CR1">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1"><label>1</label>School of Basic Medical Sciences, Cheeloo College of Medicine, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/0207yh398</institution-id><institution>Shandong University</institution></institution-wrap>, <city>Jinan, Shandong</city>, <country country="CN">China</country></aff><aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Children’s Hospital Affiliated to <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/0207yh398</institution-id><institution>Shandong University</institution></institution-wrap>, <city>Jinan, Shandong</city>, <country country="CN">China</country></aff><aff id="A3"><label>3</label>Department of Medicinal Chemistry, Shandong Key Laboratory of Druggability Optimization and Evaluation for Lead Compounds, School of Pharmaceutical Sciences, Cheeloo College of Medicine, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/0207yh398</institution-id><institution>Shandong University</institution></institution-wrap>, <city>Jinan, Shandong</city>, <country country="CN">China</country></aff><aff id="A4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/00pd74e08</institution-id><institution>University of Münster</institution></institution-wrap>, <addr-line>Schlossplatz 8</addr-line>, <postal-code>48143</postal-code><city>Münster</city>, <country country="DE">Germany</country></aff><aff id="A5"><label>5</label>Department of Structural Biochemistry, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/03vpj4s62</institution-id><institution>Max Planck Institute of Molecular Physiology</institution></institution-wrap>, <addr-line>Otto-Hahn-Str. 11</addr-line>, <postal-code>44227</postal-code><city>Dortmund</city>, <country country="DE">Germany</country></aff><author-notes><corresp id="CR1">
<label>*</label> Correspondence to: <email>wenfeili@sdu.edu.cn</email>; <email>alexey.amunts@gmail.com</email>
</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted"><day>27</day><month>07</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="preprint"><day>26</day><month>07</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><permissions><ali:free_to_read/><license><ali:license_ref>https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work has been placed in the Public Domain.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p id="P1">Aminoglycosides like neomycin are widely used but clinically limited due to toxicity, traditionally attributed to mitoribosome inhibition. Here, we demonstrate that this assumption requires re-evaluation by comparing neomycin’s interactions with human ribosomes <italic>in vitro</italic> and in cells. While cryo-EM and biochemical assays reveal strong <italic>in vitro</italic> binding to both mitoribosomes and cytosolic ribosomes, especially at conserved regions such as the helix 44 (h44) decoding center despite sequence divergence, and H69. Cellular analyses show minimal impact on global translation, reduced occupancy on cytosolic ribosomes, and a complete absence of neomycin on mitoribosomes. These discrepancies suggest limited mitochondrial permeability rather than direct mitoribosome inhibition underlies neomycin’s toxicity. Our findings redefine the mechanistic basis of aminoglycosides side effects and call for a reassessment of their cellular targets.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec id="S1" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p id="P2">Precise control of protein synthesis is fundamental to cellular life, and its disruption is a common target for antibiotics<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">4</xref></sup>. Although aminoglycosides are highly effective against bacteria, their systemic clinical use is constrained by significant oto- and nephrotoxicity in patients<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref></sup>. While selectivity of aminoglycosides for bacterial ribosomes is often attributed to structural variations within h44 decoding site compared to their eukaryotic counterparts<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">8</xref></sup>, the structural similarity between bacterial and mitochondrial translation apparatus suggests a potential for off-target effects may underlie the observed human toxicities<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref></sup>. Aminoglycosides have been reported to interact with eukaryotic ribosomes, influencing translation fidelity or inducing premature termination codon readthrough<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">20</xref></sup>. Derivatives of aminoglycosides could further enhance specificity to eukaryotic ribosome for therapeutic purposes, such as leishmania targeting<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">21</xref></sup> or nonsense mutation suppression for genetic diseases<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">22</xref></sup>.</p><p id="P3">Neomycin is a 4,5-linked aminoglycoside antibiotic<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">23</xref></sup> that inhibits bacterial translation primarily by binding to the decoding A site<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">25</xref></sup>. This involves binding to h44 of the small subunit (SSU) and H69 of the large subunit (LSU), thereby causing codon misreading and translation inhibition<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">26</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">28</xref></sup>. Molecular dynamics simulations of the decoding site showed that the catalytic activity also depends on rRNA A-site dynamics<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">29</xref></sup>. Despite the assumption that mitochondrial translation is the primary site of aminoglycoside toxicity, neomycin has also been shown to disrupt mitochondrial lipid metabolism, and promote pathological interactions with lipid droplets, leading to oxidative stress and impaired fatty acid utilization<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">30</xref></sup>. Thus, the understanding of neomycin's impact for guiding the development of safer therapeutic strategies warrants critical re-evaluation. A detailed investigation of neomycin's interaction with both human mitochondrial and cytosolic ribosomes is crucial for a complete picture of its cellular impact and for guiding the development of safer therapeutic strategies.</p><p id="P4">Previous studies successfully used addition of antibiotics streptomycin<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31">31</xref></sup> and quinupristin/dalfopristin<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32">32</xref></sup> directly to the cell culture to define their structures in the mitoribosome-bound form. In this study, we systematically investigate neomycin's action on mitoribosomes and cytosolic ribosomes from HEK (human embryonic kidney) 293-derived cells. We determined the cryo-EM structures of human mitoribosomes and cytosolic ribosomes bound to neomycin <italic>in vitro</italic>, then analyzed native ribosomes isolated from drug-treated cells to assess neomycin’s occupancy <italic>in vivo</italic>. Our results reveal striking discrepancies between <italic>in vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic> drug behavior, including limited engagement and selective loss of binding at key functional sites, such as h44, in the cellular environment. These findings challenge the conventional views of neomycin's mitochondrial toxicity and indicate that additional factors, including cellular bioavailability barriers, redox-dependent binding plasticity, and ribosomal dynamics should be taken into account when considering therapeutic strategies.</p></sec><sec id="S2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="S3"><title>Distinct neomycin-binding landscape on human mitoribosome</title><p id="P5">To investigate the molecular basis of neomycin's interaction with human mitoribosomes, we performed cryo-EM on mitoribosomes rapidly isolated from HEK293F cells<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33">33</xref></sup> and incubated with 50 μM neomycin. This yielded six maps with nominal resolutions ranging from 2.9−3.3 Å. These states were designated as “non-rotated A/A-P/P”, “non-rotated A/A-P/P-E/E”, “partially rotated A/A-P/P-E/E”, “partially rotated hybrid A/P-P/E”, “rotated empty”, “rotated hybrid A/P-P/E” (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 1</xref>, Supplementary Table 1). The map quality allowed us to consistently identify cofactors, including polyamines and Fe-S clusters, associated with rRNA and proteins, in agreement with previous reports<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31">31</xref></sup> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 1c-d</xref>). Neomycin composed of four linked monosaccharide rings (I-IV), including a central 2-deoxystreptamine (ring II), and three amino-modified sugars (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1a</xref>). Across the six states, we identified nine distinct densities corresponding to neomycin molecules: three on the mitochondrial small ribosomal subunit (mtSSU) (Neo1-3) and six on the mitochondrial large ribosomal subunit (mtLSU) (Neo4-9) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1b</xref>, Supplementary Table 2).</p><p id="P6">Specifically, Neo1 displayed well-defined density for all four rings (I-IV) and bound to h44 adjacent to the A-tRNA binding site within the decoding center (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1c</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 2</xref>). This binding effectively blocks proper pairing of tRNA with mRNA, consistent with observations in bacterial ribosomes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">25</xref></sup> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 3a</xref>). Neo1 establishes potential hydrogen bonds with several nucleotides from the mtSSU including G1489, U1490, C1491, A1555, A1557, A1558, G1559 and U1560 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1c</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 2d</xref>). Notably, ring I of Neo1 forms stable π-π stacking with the nucleobase C1556 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1c</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 2d</xref>). Furthermore, two conserved nucleotides, A1447 and A1558 (equivalent to A1492/A1493 in bacteria), are observed to flip out of h44 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1c</xref>), a characteristic of sampling the codon-anticodon interaction that facilitates near cognate tRNA incorporation of incorrect amino acid during protein synthesis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34">34</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36">36</xref></sup>.</p><p id="P7">The Neo2 molecule, situated in a pocket formed by h1 and h44, displayed well-identified density for all four rings (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1d</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 3c</xref>). It establishes potential hydrogen bonds with the nucleobase of C1481 and sugar-phosphate backbone of U656, G657, G658 and G899 from the mtSSU (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1d</xref>). Similarly, the Neo3 molecule binds to h28 near the P-tRNA, stabilized by hydrogen bonds with nucleotides from the mtSSU (specifically, the phosphate group of G1469 and A1470; and the nucleobases from G1472, C1473, G1474, G1178, U1180 and C1182 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1e</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 3c</xref>). Neo4 binds to the terminal hairpin of H69, stabilized by nucleotides from both the mtSSU (G1079 U1081 and G1582) and mtLSU (C2583 and U2586) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1f</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 2e</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 3c</xref>). H69 is recognized as another critical binding pocket for aminoglycosides. Consistent with previous bacterial structural data<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">25</xref></sup>, Neo1 and Neo4 represent conserved neomycin binding sites in human mitoribosomes, located within the h44 and H69 regions, respectively (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 3a-b</xref>).</p><p id="P8">The engagement of neomycin, particularly h44 and H69, was found to be dependent on the rotational state of the mitoribosome (Supplementary Table 2). Specifically, Neo1 binds to h44, exhibited well-defined density for all four of its rings across various non-rotated and partially rotated states (Supplementary Table 2). However, it was notably absent in the functional rotated state containing A/P and P/E tRNAs (Supplementary Table 2). This suggests that neomycin binding to h44 preferentially stabilizes non-rotated or partially rotated conformations, thereby preventing the mitoribosome from fully entering the functional rotated state. This observation aligns with findings in bacterial systems, where neomycin binding to h44 is known to restrict subunit rotation and maintain a non-rotated state, providing a structural basis for its inhibitory mechanism<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27">27</xref></sup>.</p><p id="P9">For H69, discernible densities for rings I to III of neomycin were observed in both rotated and non-rotated states only when tRNAs occupied the A and P sites (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1f</xref>, Supplementary Table 2). Intriguingly, H69 binding was absent in partially rotated states (Supplementary Table 2). This indicates that H69 binding is contingent upon specific tRNA occupancy and ribosomal conformation, favoring either the non-rotated or fully rotated states with engaged tRNAs. Collectively, this conformational state-dependent binding of neomycin to both h44 and H69 on the mitoribosome suggests a dynamic interplay between drug association and the ribosome's structural landscape, paralleling similar mechanisms observed in bacterial ribosomes.</p></sec><sec id="S4"><title>Structural analysis reveals canonical and novel neomycin-binding sites on the human cytosolic ribosome</title><p id="P10">To understand the impact of neomycin on human cellular translation and its potential toxicity, we assessed its interaction with human cytosolic ribosomes (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 4</xref>, Supplementary Table 3). While previous studies have indicated sequence differences in the critical h44 region of human ribosomes compared to their bacterial counterparts (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 2a-c</xref>), potentially affecting aminoglycoside binding<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">26</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">28</xref></sup>, our <italic>in vitro</italic> translation (IVT) assays revealed that neomycin significantly inhibits cytosolic ribosomes activity, with a half-maximal inhibitory concentration (IC<sub>50</sub>) of approximately 50 μM (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2a</xref>). This finding suggests that neomycin can effectively target human cytosolic ribosomes and inhibit its translation.</p><p id="P11">To further elucidate the molecular mechanism of this inhibition and the specific binding modes of neomycin on the cytosolic ribosome, we subsequently performed cryo-EM analysis of cytosolic ribosome complexes incubated with 50 μM neomycin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 4</xref>, Supplementary Table 3). Our single-particle analysis yielded structures of ribosomes in three distinct translational states: non-rotated, partially rotated and rotated (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 4a</xref>). Across these maps, we identified neomycin molecules bound at 17 distinct pockets: three on the small ribosomal subunit (SSU) (Neo1, Neo10 and Neo11) and fourteen on the large ribosomal subunit (LSU) (Neo12-Neo25) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2b</xref>, Supplementary Table 4). Notably, the majority of these binding pockets were consistently occupied by neomycin across the different ribosomal states (Supplementary Table 4).</p><p id="P12">A well-established mechanism for aminoglycoside action in bacteria involves binding to the decoding center, primarily formed by h44 of the small subunit<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">26</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">28</xref></sup>. We observed analogous binding in the human cytosolic ribosome despite sequence differences (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 2a-c</xref>). Our structures of the neomycin-bound human cytosolic ribosome revealed Neo1 at the universally conserved aminoglycoside binding pocket within h44 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2b-c</xref>, Supplementary Table 4). While the overall binding mode is conserved, superimposition of human and bacterial h44 structures indicated slight conformational changes and subtle differences in the precise neomycin binding pose (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 5a-c</xref>). Neo1 interacts with U1821-U1827 of h44, with A1824 and A1825 (equivalent to A1492/A1493 in bacteria) flipped out from the helix, consistent with observations in bacteria and mitoribosomes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1c</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2c</xref>).</p><p id="P13">Intriguingly, we also identified a second neomycin molecule (Neo11) bound to a novel, distinct pocket located centrally on h44, away from the canonical A-site tRNA binding region (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2d-e</xref>). The conformation of Neo11 within this pocket exhibited significant differences between the partially rotated and rotated states (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2d-e</xref>). Specifically, in the rotated ribosome, ring I of Neo11 directly interacts with G437 from the SSU via a hydrogen bond, while ring IV forms hydrogen bonds with h44 residues, including G1726, G1727 and A1806 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2d</xref>). In contrast, in the partially rotated state (characterized by an approximate 5° rotation of the SSU relative to the one from the rotated state), this pocket undergoes a spatial displacement of approximately 3 Å. Meanwhile, Neo11 undergoes a 180° flip with its ring I approaching the A1806 direction (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2e</xref>). This conformational rearrangement leads to entirely distinct interactions between Neo11 and h44: ring I forms a hydrogen bond with C1807, ring II interacts with U1730 and G1805 (proximal of A1806), and ring IV engages with the phosphate group of G1726 and G1727 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2e</xref>). These latter interactions, where nucleobases stabilize neomycin, occur specifically in the rotated state. These dynamic binding characteristics suggest a potential link between the novel Neo11 binding site and ribosome dynamics. Notably, unlike in bacterial ribosomes and mitoribosomes where H69 is a conserved aminoglycoside pocket, no neomycin binding was observed to H69 of the human cytosolic ribosome, likely due to sequence differences in human H69 causing a relatively smaller pocket and potential steric clash (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 5d</xref>).</p><p id="P14">Beyond these h44-proximal sites, we identified a large, previously uncharacterized pocket, formed by helices H89 and H72 of the LSU rRNA and a conserved rRNA loop (C1928-C2053) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2f</xref>). This pocket simultaneously accommodates three neomycin molecules (Neo13, Neo14, and Neo18) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2f</xref>). Upon neomycin binding within this pocket, we observed a distinct conformational change in nucleotide G1940 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2f</xref>). This specific conformational alteration of G1940 was consistently present across all structural classes of neomycin-bound ribosomes. Analyzing the identified binding pockets revealed significant differences compared to those observed in mitoribosomes, with the exception of the universally conserved Neo1 site (Supplementary Tables 2 and 4). Several neomycin-binding pockets appeared to be specific to the human cytosolic ribosome, occupying regions that correspond to different ribosomal proteins in the bacterial ribosome or mitoribosome (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2g-h</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 5e-g</xref>). For example, Neo19 binds to a pocket formed by LSU nucleotides, a pocket absents in mitoribosomes as it is occupied by the mL30 protein (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2g-h</xref>). These differences highlight the distinct structural landscapes of various ribosomes. Collectively, these multiple binding interactions, particularly at the h44 decoding center, provide a structural rationale for the neomycin-induced inhibition of cytosolic translation observed in our IVT assays (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S5"><title>Absence of neomycin binding to mitoribosomes in cells</title><p id="P15">While our cryo-EM data analysis revealed multiple binding of neomycin to both mitoribosomes and cytosolic ribosomes <italic>in vitro</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs. 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>), its effects on cellular translation were mild. Cell viability assays (CCK8) indicated limited cytotoxicity upon short-term neomycin exposure with an IC<sub>50</sub> of approximately 1.2 mM after prolonged (72 h) treatment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3a</xref>). Consistent with this, L-azidohomoalanine (L-AHA) labeling assay (a method for detecting newly synthesized nascent chains)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37">37</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39">39</xref></sup> showed no significant change of global mitochondrial translation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3b</xref>).</p><p id="P16">To investigate this discrepancy between <italic>in vitro</italic> potency and <italic>in vivo</italic> cellular effects, we conducted comprehensive structural, biochemical and computational analysis of the native ribosome (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Figs. 6-10</xref>). We isolated the native translation complexes from the kidney-derived HEK293F cells treated with 1 mM neomycin. This concentration, while higher than typical plasma levels (up to ∼0.13 mM), is clinically relevant as neomycin accumulates to millimolar concentrations in the kidney—a primary site of its toxicity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40">40</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41">41</xref></sup>. As previously shown<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31">31</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42">42</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43">43</xref></sup> this approach implies that the antimicrobial would have to be imported into mitochondria, preserving more native states. Mitoribosomes were then isolated and subjected to a cryo-EM analysis (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig 6</xref>, Supplementary Table 5).</p><p id="P17">The cryo-EM analysis of mitoribosomes from treated cells yielded six distinct translational states characterized by varying SSU rotations and associated translation factors (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3c</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 6</xref>). Consistent with our biochemical data showing limited cellular toxicity and effect on mitochondrial translation upon neomycin treatment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3a-b</xref>), our structural analysis revealed a striking absence of bound neomycin molecules on human mitoribosomes isolated from these treated cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3c</xref>, Supplementary Table 2). This indicates that under the cellular conditions, neomycin does not stably associate with or significantly inhibit human mitoribosomes <italic>in vivo</italic>.</p><p id="P18">At physiological temperatures, biomolecules can access a broader range of conformations, and the rates of conformational switching are generally faster than at lower temperatures<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R44">44</xref></sup>. Although rapid cooling during cryo-EM sample preparation can kinetically trap molecules in states representative of the room-temperature ensemble<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R44">44</xref></sup>. It remains crucial to assess if the binding pocket for neomycin adopts a non-binding-competent conformation specifically at physiological cellular temperatures <italic>in vivo</italic>. To investigate this, we performed all-atom explicit-solvent molecular dynamics (MD) simulations of the mtSSU with bound neomycin, focusing on the decoding center (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3d-e</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 9</xref>). Molecular dynamics (MD) simulations were initiated from the cryo-EM structure and performed across a range of temperatures up to physiological conditions. For each temperature, five independent replicates were conducted, accumulating a total simulation time of 0.5 μs. As anticipated, the fluctuation of the antibiotic's atomic positions, quantified by root mean square deviation (RMSD) analysis, increased with rising temperature (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 9b</xref>). Despite these thermal fluctuations, the neomycin molecules remained stably associated with their binding sites within the mitoribosome, and the average conformations of the bound drugs were consistent with those observed in the cryo-EM structure (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3d</xref>). The consistent association of neomycin with its mitoribosomal binding sites even at physiological temperatures effectively rules out temperature-driven conformational changes as the sole reason for its observed absence <italic>in vitro</italic>. Furthermore, comparative analysis of the MD trajectories revealed enhanced binding stability of neomycin at the Neo1 site relative to Neo2 and Neo3, evidenced by lower ligand RMSD values and reduced calculated linear interaction energy (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3e</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S6"><title>Reduced engagement of neomycin with human cytosolic ribosomes <italic>in vivo</italic></title><p id="P19">Despite strong <italic>in vitro</italic> inhibition of cytosolic ribosomes and observed binding to the key h44 site in <italic>in vitro</italic> incubated structures (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>), neomycin treatment did not markedly inhibit nanoluciferase expression in cells, even at high concentrations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4a</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 8a and c</xref>). This suggests a limited overall effect on cellular translation. Although L-AHA labeling assay showed no significant change of global cytosolic translation, we did observe an increase in stop codon readthrough in a reporter cell line upon neomycin treatment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4b-c</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 8b</xref>). This suggests that neomycin can influence cytosolic translation fidelity, even with minimal overall inhibition. To further understand neomycin’s cellular effect on cytosolic translation, we isolated cytosolic ribosomes from the same batch of neomycin-treated cells used for mitoribosome analysis. Our analysis revealed ribosomes in four different states, with the rotated state being the most prevalent (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 7</xref>, Supplementary Table 5). We detected 15 neomycin molecules bound to the ribosomes, occupying some of the same pockets identified in our <italic>in vitro</italic> incubation experiments (Supplementary Table 4). Notably, densities for some sites such as Neo21 and Neo19 were diminished or absent in the cellular samples compared to the <italic>in vitro</italic> incubated ribosomes (Supplementary Table 4). Strikingly, the Neo1 site within the canonical h44 decoding center, a key binding site <italic>in vitro</italic>, was completely devoid of neomycin in the cellular dataset (Supplementary Table 4, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4d</xref>). This absence occurred despite no significant conformational changes in the h44 pocket or novel post-translational modifications in the decoding center (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 8e</xref>). We performed temperature-dependent MD simulations on the SSU was conducted for the SSU with its bound neomycin molecules, including Neo1. Although the neomycin molecules and their binding pocket displayed conformational change with increasing temperatures (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig 9d and f</xref>), their binding relative to their pockets remained stable with minor RMSD during simulations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4e</xref>), excluding temperature-driven conformational changes as the sole cause for its <italic>in vitro</italic> absence. Additionally, neomycin binding at Neo1 site exhibited significantly stronger affinity than at Neo10 or Neo11 from the SSU, evidenced by much lower interaction energies (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4f</xref>), indicating that the lack of h44 bound neomycin is not due to weak binding affinity.</p><p id="P20">Our <italic>in vivo</italic> structural findings, particularly the reduced occupancy on cytosolic ribosomes (Supplementary Table 4), suggest that the cellular environment critically modulates neomycin's interactions, contrasting with direct incubation experiments. One notable difference is the cellular redox state, maintained by glutathione (GSH), which is altered upon cell lysis for <italic>in vitro</italic> studies. Our <italic>in vitro</italic> translation assays showed that the reducing agent TCEP or GSH provided a protective effect against neomycin's inhibitory action at certain concentrations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4g</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 8d</xref>), consistent with research that GSH can reduce neomycin toxicity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R45">45</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R46">46</xref></sup>. This suggests that the reducing intracellular environment may diminish its binding for this site <italic>in vivo</italic> (Supplementary Table 4). Moreover, at higher concentrations (3 mM) and prolonged exposure, neomycin binding became restricted to only two pockets (Supplementary Tables 4-5, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 10</xref>), suggesting that cellular mechanisms, such as drug efflux, may actively limit neomycin's interaction with its targets.</p></sec></sec><sec id="S7" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p id="P21">This study provides insights into neomycin's interaction with human ribosomes by uncovering the differences between its <italic>in vitro</italic> binding properties and in-cell behavior. We show that neomycin’s activity is modulated by the cellular environment, which can diminish or prevent its engagement with key ribosomal targets. Our findings highlight a clear divergence between <italic>in vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic> neomycin-ribosome interactions. <italic>In vitro</italic>, neomycin robustly binds conserved sites on both mitoribosomes and cytosolic ribosomes, including the bacterial-like decoding center at h44 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figs. 1</xref>-<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>, Supplementary Tables 2 and 4). Crucially, however, in cells neomycin fails to occupy these sites, most notably h44 in cytosolic ribosomes, and is undetectable on mitoribosomes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>-<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>, Supplementary Table 2). These observations correlate with minimal inhibition of global translation, suggesting intracellular factors, such as limited mitochondrial permeability and redox balance may restrict neomycin's effective access. We propose that the cellular reducing environment alters neomycin’s binding affinity, a hypothesis supported by translation assays showing redox-dependent modulation of neomycin activity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 8</xref>). Moreover, restricted engagement at higher drug concentrations implies additional resistance mechanisms, further limiting neomycin’s impact. Beyond direct ribosomal inhibition, other potential toxicity mechanisms exist, as exemplified by a recent finding that neomycin induces toxicity by mediating PGC-1α imbalance of mitochondria-lipid droplet homeostasis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">30</xref></sup>.</p><p id="P22">Expanding on these insights into cellular accessibility, our observations reveal that neomycin binds the decoding center (h44 and H69) in a ribosomal state-dependent manner. This suggests that its interactions with both mitoribosomes and cytosolic ribosomes are influenced by subunit rotation, aligning with the known mechanism by which 4,5-linked aminoglycosides antibiotics stabilize the non-rotated state and thereby inhibit translocation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27">27</xref></sup>. Furthermore, while the binding of neomycin to mitoribosomes and cytosolic ribosomes differs overall, except for Neo1 in the canonical h44 pocket, the fundamental contact modules of neomycin remain conserved. To investigate this in detail, we quantified the interacting frequency of each neomycin atom across previously reported bacterial ribosome structures and human ribosome structures (mitoribosome and cytosolic ribosome) determined in our study. Our analysis revealed that, consistent with prior bacterial studies, rings I and II of neomycin are the most frequently utilized moieties for ribosomal interaction<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27">27</xref></sup>, playing a crucial role in neomycin's binding (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 9g-i</xref>). Specifically, these two -NH<sub>2</sub> groups from ring II (2-DOS ring, the core of aminoglycosides) exhibit the highest frequency of interactions across all three ribosome types, closely followed by the -OH and 6’-NH<sub>2</sub> groups from ring I (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 9g-i</xref>). The strong binding capabilities of these amino groups stem from their ability to form hydrogen bonds with phosphate oxygen atoms within the ribosome's rRNA backbone or with nucleotide hydroxyl groups. Furthermore, their typical positive charge enables robust electrostatic interactions with the negatively charged phosphate backbone of the ribosome.</p><p id="P23">Collectively, our study demonstrates that neomycin-ribosome interactions are not static but highly sensitive to various factors like the ribosomal state and cellular redox environment, indicating an additional level of complexity in the ribosome-antibiotic binding studies. Moreover, our findings challenge the prevailing assumption that mitochondrial translation inhibition is the primary cause of neomycin toxicity, as neomycin was notably absent on native mitoribosomes <italic>in vivo</italic>. Instead, toxicity may involve metabolic disturbances or drug accumulation under pathological conditions. The resilience of mitoribosomes to neomycin may also arise from an adaptive cellular response, inherent insensitivity to certain threshold levels, or a limited import into mitochondria. However, the specific mechanistic processes essential for neomycin binding warrant further investigation. In the future, the structural studies of native samples will help to better understand the related pathological dysfunctions.</p></sec><sec id="S8" sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec id="S9"><title>Cell lines and cell culture</title><p id="P24">HEK293T cells were cultured at 37 °C and 5% CO<sub>2</sub> in Dulbecco’s Modified Eagle’s Medium (DMEM, Gibco, C11995500BT) supplemented with 10% fetal bovine serum (FBS, Excell Bio, FSP500). HEK293F cells were cultured in SMM 293-TII expression medium (Sino Bio, M293TII) in shake flasks at 37 °C, 5% CO<sub>2</sub> and 110 rpm.</p></sec><sec id="S10"><title>Plasmid construction and generation of stable cell lines</title><p id="P25">Clonal stable cell lines expressing NanoLuciferase (NLuc) or Cystic Fibrosis Transmembrane Conductance Regulator (CFTR) were generated as previously described<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R47">47</xref></sup>. The NLuc expression construct was generated by PCR amplification of NLuc-Flag fragments, subsequently assembled into a linearized vector (originally derived from Jamie H. D. Cate’s laboratory) via Gibson Assembly. For the <italic>CFTR</italic> plasmid, <italic>CFTR-G542X (UGA)</italic> along with the G542X context (seven codons upstream and downstream) was fused to mEGFP and NLuc. This recombinant fragment was cloned into the same laboratory-derived backbone vector using Gibson Assembly. The CFTR-G542X mutant was created through site-directed mutagenesis of wild-type <italic>CFTR</italic> cDNA templates. The plasmid construct was subsequently transfected into HEK293T cells and stable transfectants were selected using 1 μg/ml puromycin for two weeks.</p></sec><sec id="S11"><title><italic>In vivo</italic> translation assays</title><p id="P26">The effect of neomycin on cytosolic translation was evaluated using the NLuc cell lines, which were exposed to different concentrations of neomycin (0.5, 1, 2 and 3 mM) or DMEM as a control. Luciferase activity was quantified after 1, 4, and 24 h using microplate luminometer (BERTHOLD, Centro XS3 LB 960). To access the impact of the redox environment on neomycin toxicity, 0.3mM H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> was co-administered with varying concentrations of neomycin (0.1, 1, and 3 mM) for 1 h. Additionally, to determine the readthrough effect of neomycin, the CFTR cell lines were treated with different concentrations of neomycin (0.5, 1, 2, and 3 mM) for 24 h and 48 h respectively.</p></sec><sec id="S12"><title><italic>In vitro</italic> transcription and translation assays</title><p id="P27">The DNA template for <italic>in vitro</italic> transcription was PCR-amplified from plasmid pGM_EMCV-NLuc using primers encoding T7 RNA polymerase promoter and poly-A tail sequences. The <italic>in vitro</italic> transcription reaction was performed as previously described<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R47">47</xref></sup>. mRNA transcripts were assessed for quality and size by gel electrophoresis, quantified spectrophotometrically (Implen spectrophotometer, Nanophotometer NP80), diluted to 1 μg/μL, aliquoted, and preserved at -80 °C prior to <italic>in vitro</italic> translation reactions.</p><p id="P28">HEK293T cells were harvested at ∼80% confluency and resuspended in ice-cold lysis buffer (10 mM HEPES-KOH pH 7.5, 10 mM KOAc, 0.5 mM Mg(OAc)<sub>2</sub>, 5 mM DTT) at a 1:1 (v/v) ratio. The HEK293T cell lysates and IVT reaction systems were prepared as described previously<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R48">48</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R49">49</xref></sup>. Neomycin (MCE, HY-17624A) was introduced at different concentrations as experimental variables in the reaction system at final concentrations of 1 μM, 5 μM, 10 μM, 15 μM, 25 μM, 30 μM, 40 μM, 50 μM and 100 μM. Reactions were equilibrated at 30 °C for 25 min prior to luciferase activity measurement using a microplate luminometer (BERTHOLD, Centro XS3 LB 960). Lysates and mRNA aliquots from identical preparation lots were used for comparative assays within individual experimental series to control batch variability.</p></sec><sec id="S13"><title>Cell counting kit-8 (CCK-8) cell growth assay</title><p id="P29">The cytotoxicity of neomycin was measured in HEK293T cell lines using the CCK-8 assay. Approximately 8000 cells per well were seeded in a 96-well plate in DMEM medium supplemented with 10% FBS. After 24 h of adhesion, the cells were treated with different concentrations of neomycin dilutions versus DMEM vehicle control. After 72 h of incubation, culture medium was replaced with fresh DMEM medium supplemented with CCK-8 (10% v/v reagent: medium ratio) for an additional 2 h of light-protected incubation. Cellular viability was determined by measuring at 450 nm using a microplate reader. The cytotoxic concentration that inhibits 50% viability (IC<sub>50</sub>) of neomycin was calculated by fitting the dose-response curve using GraphPad Prism software. All experiments were performed in biological triplicates (n = 3).</p></sec><sec id="S14"><title>L-AHA labeling of nascent polypeptides</title><p id="P30">L-AHA labeling of mitochondrial-encoded nascent polypeptides was performed as described previously<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39">39</xref></sup>. Briefly, the cells were treated with different concentrations of neomycin and 50 μg/mL cycloheximide (CHX, MCE, HY-12320), which selectively inhibits eukaryotic cytosolic ribosome activity by blocking translational elongation. Fluorescence signals were analyzed using an Amersham Typhoon 5 (Cytiva).</p><p id="P31">For the cytosolic nascent polypeptide labeling, the procedure mirrored that used for mitochondrial-encoded nascent polypeptides, with cells treated with 50 μg/mL CHX as a positive control. Following the labeling, cells were harvested and resuspended in buffer containing 60 mM Tris-HCl pH 8.0, 50 mM NaCl, 2 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 40 mM KCl, 5% glycerol, 0.1% NP-40 and 1× protease inhibitor and were subsequently homogenized on ice using a glass dounce homogenizer. The resulting cell lysate was cleared by centrifugation at 15,000 <italic>×g</italic> for 15 min at 4 °C, and the supernatant was transferred to new 1.5 mL tubes. The click reaction and the following protein signal detection were performed as described above. All experiments were performed in triplicate (n = 3 independent experiments).</p></sec><sec id="S15"><title>Isolation of mitochondria and purification of mitoribosomes</title><p id="P32">Mitochondria isolation was performed as described previously<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42">42</xref></sup>. A final volume of 1L HEK293F cells at a density of 3× 10<sup>6</sup> cells/ml was harvested, washed with Phosphate Buffered Saline (PBS) buffer, and resuspended in 60mL mitochondrial isolation buffer (50 mM HEPES-KOH pH 7.5, 10 mM KCl, 1.5 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 1 mM EDTA, 1 mM EGTA, 1 mM DTT, protease inhibitors). Cells were lysed by grinding in a glass dounce homogenizer and lysate was clarified by centrifugation at 1000 <italic>×g</italic> for 15 min, then 10,000 <italic>×g</italic> for 15min at 4°C to get the crude mitochondria in the pellet. The resulting pellet was resuspended in 10 mL resuspension buffer (50 mM HEPES-KOH pH 7.5, 10 mM KCl, 1.5 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 1 mM EDTA, 1 mM EGTA, 1 mM DTT, 70 mM sucrose, 210 mM mannitol, and 1× protease inhibitor). Genomic DNA was removed by adding of 100 U RNase-free DNase I and centrifugation at 10,000 <italic>×g</italic> for 15 min at 4 °C. The crude mitochondria were gently resuspended in 1 mL buffer containing 20 mM HEPES-KOH pH 7.5, 1 mM EDTA, 250 mM sucrose and loaded onto sucrose gradients comprising 1.5 mL 60% (w/v), 4 mL 32% (w/v), 1.5 mL 23% (w/v) and 1.5 mL 15% (w/v) sucrose solutions in 20mM HEPES-KOH pH 7.5, 1mM EDTA. The gradients were centrifuged at 28,000 rpm for 1h at 4 °C using an SW41Ti rotor (Beckman Coulter). The brown band containing mitochondria migrating to the interface of 32% and 60% sucrose was collected.</p><p id="P33">The fresh isolated mitochondria were resuspended in lysis buffer (25 mM HEPES-KOH pH 7.5, 100 mM KCl, 10 mM Mg(OAc)<sub>2</sub>, 1.7% Triton X-100, 2 mM DTT, 1× protease inhibitor) at a mitochondria-to-buffer ratio of 1:2 (v/v). The mixture was homogenized with a glass dounce homogenizer. The lysate was cleared by centrifugation at 30,000 <italic>×g</italic> for 20 min at 4 °C. The supernatant was then loaded onto the top of sucrose cushion (1 M sucrose in 20 mM HEPES-KOH pH 7.5, 100 mM KCl, 20 mM Mg(OAc)<sub>2</sub>, 1% TX-100, 2 mM DTT) and centrifuged at 339,200 <italic>×g</italic> for 45 minutes at 4°C using an MLA130 rotor (Beckman Coulter). The pellet was rinsed and resuspended in Grid buffer (20 mM HEPES-KOH pH 7.5, 100 mM KCl, 10 mM Mg(OAc)<sub>2</sub>, 0.02% DDM, 1 mM DTT). Mitoribosomes (280 nM) were incubated with 50 μM neomycin (∼178-fold excess) for 30 min at 4 °C prior to the cryo-EM sample preparation (molar ratio of ribosome to neomycin around 1:170).</p></sec><sec id="S16"><title>Human cytosolic ribosome purification</title><p id="P34">The human cytosolic ribosome was isolated using a modified protocol adapted from a previously published paper<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R50">50</xref></sup>. HEK293T cells were harvested at ∼80% confluency, centrifuged at 1000 <italic>×g</italic> for 10 minutes at 4 °C, and washed twice with ice-cold PBS. The cell pellet was resuspended in an equal volume of lysis buffer (10 mM HEPES-KOH pH 7.5, 10 mM KOAc, 0.5 mM Mg(OAc)<sub>2</sub>, 5 mM DTT). Following 20 min incubation on ice, the resuspended cells were mechanically lysed by grinding in a glass homogenizer. Lysates were centrifuged at 1,000 <italic>×g</italic> for 10 min to remove cell debris, and cleared by centrifugation at 10,000 <italic>×g</italic> for 15 min at 4 °C. The supernatant was then loaded onto a sucrose cushion (10mM HEPES-KOH pH 7.5, 50mM KCl, 5mM Mg(OAc)<sub>2</sub>, 0.02% DDM, 1mM DTT, 1M sucrose) and centrifuged at 603,000 <italic>×g</italic> for 45 min at 4 °C in an MLA130 Rotor (Beckman Coulter). The pellets obtained were washed and sequentially resuspended in Grid buffer (20 mM HEPES-KOH pH 7.5, 50 mM KCl, 5 mM Mg(OAc)<sub>2</sub>, 0.02% DDM) and measured using an Implen spectrophotometer. Cytosolic ribosomes (294 nM) were incubated with 50 μM neomycin (∼170-fold excess) for 30 min at 4 °C prior to the cryo-EM sample preparation (molar ratio of ribosome to neomycin around 1:170).</p></sec><sec id="S17"><title>Isolation of mitoribosome and cytosolic ribosome from neomycin treated cells</title><p id="P35">HEK293F was scaled up sequentially, by inoculating at 1×10<sup>6</sup> cells/mL and subsequently splitting at a cell density of 3.0×10<sup>6</sup> cells/mL until achieving 300 mL final culture volume. Neomycin was added to HEK293F cells to a final concentration of 1 mM for 1 hour prior to utilization. Native human mitoribosomes purification was performed as described for the “Isolation of mitochondria and purification of mitoribosomes” part. And no extra neomycin was added during the purification. The same batch of cells were used for cytosolic ribosome isolation to make strict comparison, meaning we have native mitoribosomes and cytosolic ribosomes from the same cells. After cells harvest and lysis, the supernatant was applied for cytosolic ribosome isolation and the pellet was for crude mitochondria isolation. The protocol for purification of cytosolic ribosomes is the same as described in “Human cytosolic ribosome purification”. For the high concentration neomycin treated cells, we treated the cells with 3mM neomycin for 3 h and then conducted the cytosolic ribosomes isolation as described.</p></sec><sec id="S18"><title>Cryo-EM grids preparation</title><p id="P36">The concentration of the mitoribosomes and cytosolic ribosomes used for cryo-EM grid preparation was 280nM and 160 nM. Approximately, 3.2 μL aliquots were applied to a plasma-cleaned holey carbon grid (R1.2/1.3, 300 mesh, Quantfoil) for 1 min, on which a homemade continuous carbon film was precoated. Grids were blotted for 2.5 s under 100% humidity at 4 °C and plunge-frozen in liquid ethane using Vitrobot Mark IV (Thermo Fisher Scientific).</p></sec><sec id="S19"><title>Cryo-EM data collection and processing</title><p id="P37">Cryo-EM micrographs of all samples were collected on a Titan Krios transmission electron microscope (Thermo Fisher Scientific) operated at 300 kV using a slit width of 20 eV on a GIF quantum energy filter (Gatan). The micrographs were recorded using a Falcon 4i direct electron detector at a pixel size of 0.81 Å. A total electron dose of 50 electrons per Å<sup>2</sup> was fractionated over 40 frames with a total exposure time of 5.9 s. Data were acquired using EPU software<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R50">50</xref></sup> with a defocus ranging from 1.0 to 2.0 μm.</p><p id="P38">All datasets were processed using cryoSPARC v.4.2.1<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R51">51</xref></sup>. The movie stacks were first corrected for motion using the patch motion correction tool of cryoSPARC. Contrast transfer function (CTF) parameters were estimated using the patch CTF estimation tool. Manual curation was performed to exclude suboptimal micrographs. From the curated micrographs, particles were initially identified through blob-based template-free picking, followed by iterative template-based particle picking using averaging projections selected from 2D classification. The extracted particles underwent multiple rounds of 2D classification to remove non-ribosomal contaminants and ice artifacts. Particles were then used for 3D auto-refinement yielding a map for further classification.</p><p id="P39">Focused 3D classification was carried out using a mask on the SSU to facilitate conformational sorting, enabling separation of rotated versus non-rotated ribosome states. Another round of focused 3D classification using a spherical mask on the tRNA binding sites was performed, separating the particles into different tRNA binding states. H69 and h44 are key binding sites of aminoglycoside antibiotics. Therefore, a spherical mask of radius 23 Å was generated for H69 and h44, respectively, for 3D classification to improve the local resolution. Masks with smoothed edges were generated with the "relion_mask_create" tool in RELION4.0.0<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R52">52</xref></sup>. After one round of CTF refinement, particles of each class were further processed by focused refinements with different masks applied. All reported map resolutions were determined by the FSC = 0.143 cutoff criterion.</p></sec><sec id="S20"><title>Model building and refinement</title><p id="P40">In general, the structures of cytosolic ribosomes (PDB:8QOI<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R53">53</xref></sup>) and mitoribosome (PDB: 7QI5<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref></sup>) were used for rigid body docking into the cryo-EM density map using UCSF ChimeraX v1.8<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R54">54</xref></sup>. The docked coordinates were realigned to match map orientation and saved as models for manual building and adjustment in Coot v0.9.8.1<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R55">55</xref></sup>. The neomycin ligand was fetched from the Coot ligand library using the three-letter code: NMY and manually positioned according to the density maps. Conformational changes induced by neomycin binding were also manually adjusted. And the unknown continuous density was analyzed using CryFold<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R56">56</xref></sup> to predict the sequence and three-dimensional structure, which was subsequently added into the model. Final models were further subjected to refinement with Phenix.real_space_refine v1.13_2998<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R57">57</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R58">58</xref></sup>. The figures were prepared with ChimeraX<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R54">54</xref></sup>. Figures were compiled using Adobe Illustrator.</p></sec><sec id="S21"><title>Computational methods</title><p id="P41">mtSSU molecular dynamics (MD) simulations were performed using the AMBER package. The system comprised ribosomal proteins, rRNA, and three neomycin molecules (Neo1, Neo2, Neo3) solvated in an orthorhombic TIP3P water box extending 12 Å beyond the solute. The ff19SB force field was applied to proteins, OL3 to RNA, and GAFF2 parameters with AM1-BCC charges to ligands. After energy minimization and stepwise heating, production runs were conducted at 90 K, 280 K, 290 K, 300 K, and 310 K under NPT conditions using a 2-fs timestep with SHAKE constraints. Five independent 100-ns replicates per temperature were acquired. Binding free energies were calculated via the linear interaction energy method using the <italic>cpptraj</italic> module in Ambertools. And the MD of the SSU of the cytosolic ribosome with three neomycin molecules (Neo1, Neo10, and Neo11) were performed as described for the mtSSU.</p></sec><sec id="S22"><title>Reporting summary</title><p id="P42">Further information on research design is available in the Nature Research Reporting Summary linked to this paper.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="SM"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1"><label>Supplemental figures</label><media xlink:href="EMS207556-supplement-Supplemental_figures.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" id="d5aAcEbB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack id="S23"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank Zhengkun Xie from the Center of Advanced Analysis &amp; Gene Sequencing of Zhengzhou University for technical support; Jamie Doudna Cate and Jingdong Cheng for helpful discussions. This work was supported by grants from the National Natural Science Foundation of China (32171291 and 32371351 to W.L., 82302100 to M.W.), National Key Research and Development Program of China (2022YFA0807100 to W.L., 2023YFC2308900 to M.W.), Nature Science Foundation of Shandong Province (ZR2021QC002 to W.L.) the Shandong Excellent Young Scientists Fund Program (2022HWYQ-025), Taishan Scholars Program (tsqnz20221104), Cutting Edge Development Fund of Advanced Medical Research Institute (GYY2023QY01) and the Cheeloo Youth Program of Shandong University to W.L., European Research Council (805230) to A.A..</p></ack><sec id="S24" sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p id="P43">The data that support the findings of this study are available from the corresponding authors upon reasonable request. The cryo-EM maps have been deposited in the Electron Microscopy Data Bank under the following accession numbers, respectively: EMD-65426 (<italic>in vitro</italic> dataset, mitoribosomes in non-rotated state with A/A P/P E/E-site tRNA), EMD-65433 (<italic>in vitro</italic> dataset, mitoribosomes in non-rotated state with A/A P/P-site tRNA), EMD-65428 (<italic>in vitro</italic> dataset, mitoribosome in partially rotated state with A/P P/E-site tRNA), EMD-65427 (<italic>in vitro</italic> dataset, mitoribosome in partially rotated state with A/A P/P E/E-site tRNA), EMD-65431 (<italic>in vitro</italic> dataset, mitoribosome in rotated state with A/P P/E-site tRNA), EMD-65429 (<italic>in vitro</italic> dataset, mitoribosome in rotated); EMD-65419 (<italic>in vitro</italic> dataset, cytosolic ribosome in non-rotated state with P/P E/E-site tRNA), EMD-65412 (<italic>in vitro</italic> dataset, cytosolic ribosome in partially rotated state with eEF2, SERBP1 and E/E-site tRNA), EMD-65434 (<italic>in vitro</italic> dataset, cytosolic ribosome in rotated state with A/P P/E-site tRNA), EMD-65411 (1mM native dataset, cytosolic ribosome in non-rotated state with P/P E/E-site tRNA), EMD-65413 (1mM native dataset, cytosolic ribosome in partially-rotated state with eEF2, SERBP1 and E/E-site tRNA), EMD-65415 (1mM native dataset, cytosolic ribosome in rotated state with A/P P/E-site tRNA), EMD-65414 (1mM native dataset, cytosolic ribosome in rotated state with A/A P/E-site tRNA); EMD-65416 (3mM native dataset, cytosolic ribosome in non-rotated state with P/P E/E-site tRNA), EMD-65417 (3mM native dataset, cytosolic ribosome in partially-rotated state with eEF2, SERBP1 and E/E-site tRNA), EMD-65418 (3mM native dataset, cytosolic ribosome in rotated state with A/P P/E-site tRNA); EMD-65421 (1mM native dataset, mitoribosome in non-rotated state with P/P E/E-site tRNA), EMD-65422 (1mM native dataset, mitoribosome in non-rotated state with A/A P/P E/E-site tRNA), EMD-65423 (1mM native dataset, mitoribosome in partially rotated state with A/A P/P-site tRNA); EMD-65424 (native dataset, mitoribosome in partially rotated state with A/P P/E-site tRNA), EMD-65425 (native dataset, mitoribosome in rotated state with P/E-site tRNA), EMD-65420 (native dataset, LSU of the mitoribosome). The corresponding atomic coordinates have been deposited in the Protein Data Bank with accession codes 9VXM (mitoribosome in non-rotated state with A/A P/P -site tRNA, corresponding map EMD-65433) and 9VXN (cytosolic ribosome in rotated state with A/P P/E-site tRNA, corresponding map EMD-65434). Source data are provided with this paper.</p></sec><fn-group><fn fn-type="con" id="FN1"><p id="P44"><bold>Contributions</bold></p><p id="P45">X.Z., L.Z., C.J. and M.W. performed the sample preparation, acquired cryo-EM data, and carried out image processing and structure refinement. L.Z., C.J., W.M. and W.L. did the model building and structural analysis. X.Z., L.Z. and K.W. conducted biochemistry and cell-based experiments. X.H. performed the MD experiment. L.Z., W.L., C.J., W.M. and A.A. prepared the figures. W.L. and A.A. wrote the initial draft of the paper. All authors analyzed the data and edited the paper.</p></fn><fn fn-type="conflict" id="FN2"><p id="P46"><bold>Competing interests</bold></p><p id="P47">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><ref id="R1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kohanski</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Dwyer</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>How antibiotics kill bacteria: from targets to networks</article-title><source>Nat Rev Microbiol</source><year>2010</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>423</fpage><lpage>435</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrmicro2333</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2896384</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20440275</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Steitz</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Polikanov</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name><name><surname>Gagnon</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ribosome-targeting antibiotics: Modes of action, mechanisms of resistance, and implications for drug design</article-title><source>Annu Rev Biochem</source><year>2018</year><volume>87</volume><fpage>451</fpage><lpage>478</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-biochem-062917-011942</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9176271</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29570352</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Paternoga</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Structural conservation of antibiotic interaction with ribosomes</article-title><source>Nat Struct Mol Biol</source><year>2023</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>1380</fpage><lpage>1392</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41594-023-01047-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10497419</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37550453</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ribosome-targeting antibiotics and mechanisms of bacterial resistance</article-title><source>Nat Rev Microbiol</source><year>2014</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>35</fpage><lpage>48</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24336183</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Aminoglycoside antibiotics in the 21st century</article-title><source>ACS Chem Biol</source><year>2013</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>105</fpage><lpage>115</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23110460</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zaher</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fidelity at the molecular level: lessons from protein synthesis</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2009</year><volume>136</volume><fpage>746</fpage><lpage>762</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2009.01.036</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3691815</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19239893</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Recht</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name><name><surname>Douthwaite</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Puglisi</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Basis for prokaryotic specificity of action of aminoglycoside antibiotics</article-title><source>EMBO J</source><year>1999</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>3133</fpage><lpage>3138</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/emboj/18.11.3133</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1171394</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10357824</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moazed</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Noller</surname><given-names>HF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Interaction of antibiotics with functional sites in 16S ribosomal RNA</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1987</year><volume>327</volume><fpage>389</fpage><lpage>394</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2953976</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Prezant</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Mitochondrial ribosomal RNA mutation associated with both antibiotic-induced and non-syndromic deafness</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><year>1993</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>289</fpage><lpage>294</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7689389</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Böttger</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name><name><surname>Springer</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Prammananan</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kidan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Sander</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structural basis for selectivity and toxicity of ribosomal antibiotics</article-title><source>EMBO Rep</source><year>2001</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>318</fpage><lpage>323</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/embo-reports/kve062</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1083859</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11306553</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hobbie</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genetic analysis of interactions with eukaryotic rRNA identify the mitoribosome as target in aminoglycoside ototoxicity</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2008</year><volume>105</volume><fpage>20888</fpage><lpage>20893</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0811258106</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2634874</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19104050</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>M-X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mitochondrial 12S rRNA mutations associated with aminoglycoside ototoxicity</article-title><source>Mitochondrion</source><year>2011</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>237</fpage><lpage>245</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21047563</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Matt</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Dissociation of antibacterial activity and aminoglycoside ototoxicity in the 4-monosubstituted 2-deoxystreptamine apramycin</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2012</year><volume>109</volume><fpage>10984</fpage><lpage>10989</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1204073109</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3390888</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22699498</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Amunts</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Toots</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Scheres</surname><given-names>SHW</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramakrishnan</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ribosome. The structure of the human mitochondrial ribosome</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2015</year><volume>348</volume><fpage>95</fpage><lpage>98</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.aaa1193</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4501431</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25838379</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Mitoribosome structure with cofactors and modifications reveals mechanism of ligand binding and interactions with L1 stalk</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2024</year><volume>15</volume><elocation-id>4272</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-024-48163-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11106087</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38769321</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fosso</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Garneau-Tsodikova</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>New trends in aminoglycosides use</article-title><source>Medchemcomm</source><year>2014</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>1075</fpage><lpage>1091</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/C4MD00163J</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4111210</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25071928</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Prokhorova</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Aminoglycoside interactions and impacts on the eukaryotic ribosome</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2017</year><volume>114</volume><fpage>E10899</fpage><lpage>E10908</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1715501114</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5754804</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29208708</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilhelm</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Sherman</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phenotypic suppression of nonsense mutants in yeast by aminoglycoside antibiotics</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1979</year><volume>277</volume><fpage>148</fpage><lpage>150</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">366439</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Manuvakhova</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Keeling</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Bedwell</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Aminoglycoside antibiotics mediate context-dependent suppression of termination codons in a mammalian translation system</article-title><source>RNA</source><year>2000</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>1044</fpage><lpage>1055</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/s1355838200000716</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1369979</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10917599</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Keeling</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Gunn</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Bedwell</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Therapeutics based on stop codon readthrough</article-title><source>Annu Rev Genomics Hum Genet</source><year>2014</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>371</fpage><lpage>394</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-genom-091212-153527</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5304456</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24773318</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shalev</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Structural basis for selective targeting of leishmanial ribosomes: aminoglycoside derivatives as promising therapeutics</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2015</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>8601</fpage><lpage>8613</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkv821</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4787808</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26264664</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sabbavarapu</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Design of novel aminoglycoside derivatives with enhanced suppression of diseases-causing nonsense mutations</article-title><source>ACS Med Chem Lett</source><year>2016</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>418</fpage><lpage>423</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acsmedchemlett.6b00006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4834649</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27096052</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Benveniste</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structure-activity relationships among the aminoglycoside antibiotics: role of hydroxyl and amino groups</article-title><source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source><year>1973</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>402</fpage><lpage>409</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/aac.4.4.402</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC444567</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4598613</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Allosteric control of the ribosome by small-molecule antibiotics</article-title><source>Nat Struct Mol Biol</source><year>2012</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>957</fpage><lpage>963</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nsmb.2360</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3645490</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22902368</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wallis</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>von Ahsen</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Schroeder</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Famulok</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A novel RNA motif for neomycin recognition</article-title><source>Chem Biol</source><year>1995</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>543</fpage><lpage>552</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9383458</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Borovinskaya</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Structural basis for aminoglycoside inhibition of bacterial ribosome recycling</article-title><source>Nat Struct Mol Biol</source><year>2007</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>727</fpage><lpage>732</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17660832</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wasserman</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Chemically related 4,5-linked aminoglycoside antibiotics drive subunit rotation in opposite directions</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2015</year><volume>6</volume><elocation-id>7896</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncomms8896</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4522699</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26224058</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fourmy</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Recht</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name><name><surname>Blanchard</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Puglisi</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structure of the A site of Escherichia coli 16S ribosomal RNA complexed with an aminoglycoside antibiotic</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1996</year><volume>274</volume><fpage>1367</fpage><lpage>1371</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8910275</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smolkin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Towards catalytic antibiotics: Redesign of aminoglycosides to catalytically disable bacterial ribosomes</article-title><source>Chembiochem</source><year>2019</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>247</fpage><lpage>259</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30474295</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>PGC-1α-mediated imbalance of mitochondria-lipid droplet homeostasis in neomycin-induced ototoxicity and nephrotoxicity</article-title><source>Acta Pharm Sin B</source><year>2024</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>4413</fpage><lpage>4430</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.apsb.2024.05.024</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11544387</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39525588</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Itoh</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Structure of the mitoribosomal small subunit with streptomycin reveals Fe-S clusters and physiological molecules</article-title><source>Elife</source><year>2022</year><volume>11</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.77460</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9731571</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36480258</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sighel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Inhibition of mitochondrial translation suppresses glioblastoma stem cell growth</article-title><source>Cell Rep</source><year>2021</year><volume>35</volume><elocation-id>109024</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.celrep.2021.109024</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8097689</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33910005</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aibara</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Andréll</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Amunts</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rapid isolation of the mitoribosome from HEK cells</article-title><source>J Vis Exp</source><year>2018</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3791/57877</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6235407</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30346389</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Functional insights from the structure of the 30S ribosomal subunit and its interactions with antibiotics</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2000</year><volume>407</volume><fpage>340</fpage><lpage>348</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11014183</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Holm</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>mRNA decoding in human is kinetically and structurally distinct from bacteria</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2023</year><volume>617</volume><fpage>200</fpage><lpage>207</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41586-023-05908-w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10156603</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37020024</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ogle</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Recognition of cognate transfer RNA by the 30S ribosomal subunit</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2001</year><volume>292</volume><fpage>897</fpage><lpage>902</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11340196</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>An</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ordureau</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Körner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Paulo</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Harper</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Systematic quantitative analysis of ribosome inventory during nutrient stress</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2020</year><volume>583</volume><fpage>303</fpage><lpage>309</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41586-020-2446-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7351614</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32612236</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yousefi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Monitoring mitochondrial translation in living cells</article-title><source>EMBO Rep</source><year>2021</year><volume>22</volume><elocation-id>e51635</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15252/embr.202051635</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8024989</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33586863</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Structural basis for differential inhibition of eukaryotic ribosomes by tigecycline</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2024</year><volume>15</volume><elocation-id>5481</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-024-49797-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11213857</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38942792</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rosenberg</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Allison</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Potentiating aminoglycoside antibiotics to reduce their toxic side effects</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2020</year><volume>15</volume><elocation-id>e0237948</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0237948</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7467299</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32877437</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R41"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Le</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Aminoglycoside-related nephrotoxicity and ototoxicity in clinical practice: A review of pathophysiological mechanism and treatment options</article-title><source>Adv Ther</source><year>2023</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>1357</fpage><lpage>1365</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36738370</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R42"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aibara</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Modelska</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Amunts</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structural basis of mitochondrial translation</article-title><source>Elife</source><year>2020</year><volume>9</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.58362</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7438116</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32812867</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R43"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Itoh</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Mechanism of membrane-tethered mitochondrial protein synthesis</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2021</year><volume>371</volume><fpage>846</fpage><lpage>849</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.abe0763</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7610362</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33602856</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R44"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bock</surname><given-names>LV</given-names></name><name><surname>Grubmüller</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of cryo-EM cooling on structural ensembles</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2022</year><volume>13</volume><elocation-id>1709</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-022-29332-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8971465</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35361752</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R45"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hammill</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Protection for medication-induced hearing loss: the state of the science</article-title><source>Int J Audiol</source><year>2018</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>S67</fpage><lpage>S75</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29688112</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R46"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Garetz</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Altschuler</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Schacht</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Attenuation of gentamicin ototoxicity by glutathione in the guinea pig in vivo</article-title><source>Hear Res</source><year>1994</year><volume>77</volume><fpage>81</fpage><lpage>87</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7928740</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R47"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>ST-L</given-names></name><name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>FR</given-names></name><name><surname>Cate</surname><given-names>JHD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Selective inhibition of human translation termination by a drug-like compound</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2020</year><volume>11</volume><elocation-id>4941</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-020-18765-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7532171</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33009412</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R48"><label>48</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Structural basis for selective stalling of human ribosome nascent chain complexes by a drug-like molecule</article-title><source>Nat Struct Mol Biol</source><year>2019</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>501</fpage><lpage>509</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41594-019-0236-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6919564</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31160784</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R49"><label>49</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lintner</surname><given-names>NG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Selective stalling of human translation through small-molecule engagement of the ribosome nascent chain</article-title><source>PLoS Biol</source><year>2017</year><volume>15</volume><elocation-id>e2001882</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.2001882</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5360235</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28323820</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R50"><label>50</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><name><surname>Iadanza</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Hesketh</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name><name><surname>Rawson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ranson</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Collection, pre-processing and on-the-fly analysis of data for high-resolution, single-particle cryo-electron microscopy</article-title><source>Nat Protoc</source><year>2019</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>100</fpage><lpage>118</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30487656</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R51"><label>51</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Punjani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rubinstein</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Fleet</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Brubaker</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>cryoSPARC: algorithms for rapid unsupervised cryo-EM structure determination</article-title><source>Nat Methods</source><year>2017</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>290</fpage><lpage>296</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28165473</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R52"><label>52</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kimanius</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharov</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakane</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Scheres</surname><given-names>SHW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>New tools for automated cryo-EM single-particle analysis in RELION-4.0</article-title><source>Biochem J</source><year>2021</year><volume>478</volume><fpage>4169</fpage><lpage>4185</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1042/BCJ20210708</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8786306</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34783343</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R53"><label>53</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Holvec</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The structure of the human 80S ribosome at 1.9 Å resolution reveals the molecular role of chemical modifications and ions in RNA</article-title><source>Nat Struct Mol Biol</source><year>2024</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>1251</fpage><lpage>1264</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38844527</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R54"><label>54</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goddard</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>UCSF ChimeraX: Meeting modern challenges in visualization and analysis</article-title><source>Protein Sci</source><year>2018</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>14</fpage><lpage>25</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/pro.3235</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5734306</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28710774</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R55"><label>55</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Emsley</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Lohkamp</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>WG</given-names></name><name><surname>Cowtan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Features and development of coot</article-title><source>Acta Crystallogr D Biol Crystallogr</source><year>2010</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>486</fpage><lpage>501</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1107/S0907444910007493</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2852313</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20383002</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R56"><label>56</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Amunts</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Improved automated model building for cryo-EM maps using CryFold</article-title><source>bioRxiv</source><year>2024</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2024.11.13.623164</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R57"><label>57</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Afonine</surname><given-names>PV</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Real-space refinement in PHENIX for cryo-EM and crystallography</article-title><source>Acta Crystallogr D Struct Biol</source><year>2018</year><volume>74</volume><fpage>531</fpage><lpage>544</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1107/S2059798318006551</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6096492</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29872004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R58"><label>58</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liebschner</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Macromolecular structure determination using X-rays, neutrons and electrons: recent developments in Phenix</article-title><source>Acta Crystallogr D Struct Biol</source><year>2019</year><volume>75</volume><fpage>861</fpage><lpage>877</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1107/S2059798319011471</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6778852</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31588918</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><title>Structural analysis of neomycin binding to mitoribosome <italic>in vitro</italic>.</title><p><bold>a</bold> Chemical structure of neomycin. <bold>b</bold> Overall structure of the neomycin-bound mitoribosome in non-rotated state comprising the mtSSU (yellow), mtLSU (blue), mRNA (red), A-site tRNA (magenta) and P-site tRNA (green). rRNA helices h44 and H69 are shown as cartoon in gold and blue, respectively. <bold>c</bold> Close-up view of Neo1 occupying the conserved pocket formed by h44. <bold>d</bold> Close-up view of Neo2 binding pocket formed by residues from h1 and h44. <bold>e</bold> Close-up view of Neo3 binding pocket in h28. <bold>f</bold> Close-up view of Neo4 binding pocket formed by H69 and stabilized by both H69 and nucleotides from the mtSSU. Key interacting nucleotides are represented as sticks (oxygen in red, nitrogen in blue).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS207556-f001"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><title>Structural analysis of neomycin binding to cytosolic ribosomes <italic>in vitro</italic>.</title><p><bold>a</bold> Luciferase reporter assays of cytosolic ribosomes in response to neomycin at different concentrations of 1, 5, 10, 15, 20, 25, 30, 40, 50 and 100 μM (data present mean ± s.d., n = 3 independent experiments). <bold>b</bold> Overall structure of neomycin-bound cytosolic ribosomes in rotated state comprising the SSU (yellow), LSU (blue), mRNA (red), A/P-site tRNA (magenta) and P/E-site tRNA (green). rRNA helices h44 and H69 are shown as cartoon in gold and blue respectively. <bold>c</bold> Close-up view of Neo1 bound to h44. <bold>d</bold> Close-up view of Neo11 bound to a novel pocket within h44 in the rotated state. <bold>e</bold> A different conformation of Neo11 bound to in the partially rotated state. <bold>f</bold> A novel pocket accommodating three neomycin molecules (Neo13, Neo14, and Neo18), with G1940 adopting a unique conformation upon neomycin binding (orange represents the conformation before binding, blue represents the conformation after binding). <bold>g</bold> Close-up view of Neo19 bound to a pocket formed by H53 and H54 from the LSU. <bold>h</bold> Comparison showing that in the mitoribosome, the Neo19 site is preoccupied by mitochondrial protein mL30 (PDB: 7QI5<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref></sup>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS207556-f002"/></fig><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><title><italic>In vivo</italic> effects and structural dynamics of neomycin on human mitoribosomes.</title><p><bold>a</bold> Cell viability of HEK293T cells measured by the CCK-8 assay after treatment with increasing concentrations of neomycin for 3 h, 24 h, and 72 h respectively (data present mean ± s.d., n = 3 independent experiments). <bold>b</bold> <italic>De novo</italic> mitochondrial nascent protein synthesis measured via L-AHA labeling. <bold>c</bold> Overall cryo-EM structure of native mitoribosome with different tRNAs and cofactors. Coloring is consistent with previous figures. <bold>d</bold> MD simulations depicting the temperature-dependent binding stability of neomycin molecules (Neo1, Neo2, and Neo3) within the mtSSU, illustrating the relative movement of the neomycin molecules within their binding pocket. The changes in distance between the ligand mass center and the binding pocket mass center (defined as the centroid of residues within 3 Å of the ligand in initial cryo-EM structure) during molecular dynamics simulations at temperatures ranging from 90 K to 310 K. <bold>e</bold> Calculated linear interaction energy for neomycin within the mtSSU.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS207556-f003"/></fig><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><title><italic>In vivo</italic> effects and structural analysis of neomycin with human cytosolic ribosomes.</title><p><bold>a</bold> <italic>In vivo</italic> translation assays using the NLuc cell line at various time points following treatment with different concentrations of neomycin (data present mean ± s.d., n = 3 independent experiments). <bold>b</bold> <italic>De novo</italic> nascent protein synthesis measured via L-AHA labeling. <bold>c</bold> Quantification of CFTR nonsense allele readthrough in cultured HEK293T cells treated with increasing concentrations of neomycin for 24 h and 48 h (data present mean ± s.d., n = 3 independent experiments). <bold>d</bold> Overall cryo-EM structure of native cytosolic ribosomes with different tRNAs and cofactors. Coloring is consistent with previous figures. <bold>e</bold> MD simulations depicting the temperature-dependent binding stability of neomycin molecules (Neo1, Neo10, and Neo11) within the SSU, illustrating the relative movement of the neomycin molecules within their binding pocket. The changes in distance between the ligand mass center and the binding pocket mass center (defined as the centroid of residues within 3 Å of the ligand in initial cryo-EM structure) during molecular dynamics simulations at temperatures ranging from 90 K to 310 K. <bold>f</bold> Calculated linear interaction energy for neomycin within the SSU. <bold>g</bold> <italic>In vitro</italic> translation assays with luciferase reporters in the presence of 0.02 mM neomycin under varying redox conditions (data present mean ± s.d., n = 3 independent experiments). The grey bar indicates an increasingly reducing environment, established by increasing concentrations of TCEP (lane 1: 0.1 mM H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>; lane 2: 0 mM TCEP; lane 3: 0.1 mM TCEP; lane 4: 1 mM TCEP; lane 5: 5 mM TCEP). <bold>h</bold> Cell viability of HEK293T cells measured by the CCK-8 assay after treatment with increasing concentrations of neomycin in the presence or absence of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> (data present mean ± s.d., n = 3 independent experiments). <bold>i</bold> <italic>In vivo</italic> translation assays with luciferase reporters in response to different concentrations of neomycin in a 0.3 mM H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> environment (data present mean ± s.d., n = 3 independent experiments).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS207556-f004"/></fig></floats-group></article>