<!DOCTYPE article
 PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" article-type="preprint"><?all-math-mml yes?><?use-mml?><?origin ukpmcpa?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">bioRxiv</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>bioRxiv : the preprint server for biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2692-8205</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">EMS207548</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2025.07.21.665833</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="archive">PPR1055015</article-id><article-version-alternatives><article-version article-version-type="status">preprint</article-version><article-version article-version-type="number">1</article-version></article-version-alternatives><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Thermal acclimation fails to confer a carbon budget advantage to invasive species over natives</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Juillard</surname><given-names>Thibaut</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CR1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bachofen</surname><given-names>Christoph</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Conedera</surname><given-names>Marco</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Dumont</surname><given-names>Mattéo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Limousin</surname><given-names>Jean-Marc</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Milano</surname><given-names>Arianna</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pezzatti</surname><given-names>Gianni Boris</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>ViIagrosa</surname><given-names>Alberto</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">5</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A6">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Grossiord</surname><given-names>Charlotte</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Plant Ecology Research Laboratory PERL, School of Architecture, Civil and Environmental Engineering ENAC, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/02s376052</institution-id><institution>EPFL</institution></institution-wrap>, <postal-code>CH-1015</postal-code><city>Lausanne</city>, <country country="CH">Switzerland</country></aff><aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Community Ecology Unit, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/04bs5yc70</institution-id><institution>Swiss Federal Institute for Forest, Snow and Landscape Research WSL</institution></institution-wrap>, <postal-code>CH-8903</postal-code>, <city>Birmensdorf</city>, <country country="CH">Switzerland</country></aff><aff id="A3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/050jn9y42</institution-id><institution>Institut National des Sciences Appliquées de Lyon, INSA</institution></institution-wrap>, <postal-code>69100</postal-code><city>Villeurbanne</city>, <country country="FR">France</country></aff><aff id="A4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/008rywf59</institution-id><institution>CEFE</institution></institution-wrap>, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/051escj72</institution-id><institution>Univ Montpellier</institution></institution-wrap>, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/02feahw73</institution-id><institution>CNRS</institution></institution-wrap>, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/046b3cj80</institution-id><institution>EPHE</institution></institution-wrap>, IRD, <city>Montpellier</city>, <country country="FR">France</country></aff><aff id="A5"><label>5</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/01jpkw634</institution-id><institution>Mediterranean Center for Environmental Studies</institution></institution-wrap> (CEAM Foundation). Joint Research Unit University of Alicante-CEAM, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/05t8bcz72</institution-id><institution>University of Alicante</institution></institution-wrap>, <postal-code>03690</postal-code>, <city>Sant Vicent del Raspeig</city>, <state>Alicante</state>, <country country="ES">Spain</country></aff><aff id="A6"><label>6</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/01jpkw634</institution-id><institution>CEAM</institution></institution-wrap>-Department de Ecologia, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/05t8bcz72</institution-id><institution>Universitat d’Alacant</institution></institution-wrap>, <addr-line>POB 99</addr-line>, <postal-code>E-03080</postal-code><city>Alacant</city>, <country country="ES">Spain</country></aff><author-notes><corresp id="CR1"><label>*</label>Corresponding author: Thibaut Juillard (<email>thibaut.juillard@epfl.ch</email>)</corresp><fn id="FN1"><p id="P1">The author responsible for distribution of materials integral to the findings presented in this article in accordance with the policy described in the Instructions for Authors (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://academic.oup.com/plphys/pages/General-Instructions">https://academic.oup.com/plphys/pages/General-Instructions</ext-link>) is Thibaut Juillard (<email>thibaut.juillard@epfl.ch</email>)</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted"><day>27</day><month>07</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="preprint"><day>24</day><month>07</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><permissions><ali:free_to_read/><license><ali:license_ref>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is licensed under a <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/4.0/">CC BY-ND 4.0 International license</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p id="P2">Both native and invasive plants can adjust photosynthesis and respiration when exposed to warmer temperatures. However, it is uncertain if invasive plants are more plastic and exhibit higher acclimation to rising temperatures than native ones, a trait that could contribute to their invasive behavior in novel environments. We compared the capacity of a highly invasive palm in central Europe (<italic>Trachycarpus fortunei</italic>) and two native co-occurring species (<italic>Ilex aquifolium</italic> and <italic>Tilia cordata</italic>) to acclimate photosynthesis and respiration to air temperature changes using a two-year-long transplant experiment across Europe (mean temperatures ranging from 8.4 to 21.8°C). We measured the optimal temperature of photosynthesis (T<sub>opt</sub>), the assimilation at optimal temperature (A<sub>opt</sub>), the thermal breath of photosynthesis (T<sub>80</sub>), the respiration at 25°C (R<sub>25</sub>), the temperature sensitivity of respiration (Q<sub>10</sub>), and simulated the whole-plant carbon budget. For all species, T<sub>opt</sub>, A<sub>opt,</sub> and T<sub>80</sub> increased with warming, while R<sub>25</sub> decreased in the native species and Q<sub>10</sub> decreased in the invasive species only. Consequently, acclimation enhanced the carbon budget of the invasive and native plants in the warm and hot sites. The invasive palm had a similar or lower acclimation capacity than other species and a lower but constant carbon budget across the European temperature gradient. Our work reveals that not all invasive plants exhibit greater photosynthetic plasticity than native ones, suggesting that temperature-driven enhancement of their carbon budget may play a limited role in future invasion processes.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec id="S1" sec-type="intro"><label>1</label><title>Introduction</title><p id="P3">Global warming promotes the spread of invasive plant species worldwide, representing one of the most significant threats to plant biodiversity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R70">Walther <italic>et al</italic>., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R44">Liu <italic>et al</italic>., 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R52">Pyšek <italic>et al</italic>., 2020</xref>). Among possible factors, long-lived invasive plants can outperform native species under a warmer climate as they tend to be adapted to broader air temperature (T<sub>air</sub>) ranges (<italic>e.g</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34">Higgins and Richardson, 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">Finch <italic>et al</italic>., 2021</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R66">Turbelin and Catford, 2021</xref>), can extend their growing seasons more significantly (<italic>e.g</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">Fridley, 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36">Juillard <italic>et al</italic>., 2024</xref>), and acclimate various functional traits more extensively (<italic>e.g</italic>. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">Davidson, Jennions and Nicotra, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">Gioria <italic>et al</italic>., 2023</xref>). Higher carbon (C) uptake and plant productivity following a better thermal acclimation of photosynthesis and respiration may, in turn, enhance species competitiveness (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">Duan <italic>et al</italic>., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R77">Yu <italic>et al</italic>., 2019</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31">Grossiord <italic>et al</italic>., 2022</xref>). Still, few studies investigated photosynthetic and respiratory thermal acclimation in the context of species invasiveness (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R67">Verlinden and Nijs, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">Godoy, Valladares and Castro-Díez, 2011</xref>; Ripley <italic>et al</italic>., 2020), with none addressing if invasive plants are more plastic than native ones with increasing temperature. Yet, understanding and predicting these processes would help reduce uncertainties in climate-vegetation models, where acclimation is often simplified or fully neglected (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">Crous, Uddling and De Kauwe, 2022</xref>) and would allow finding appropriate conservation strategies for forests highly susceptible to invasion as a consequence of global warming.</p><p id="P4">Plants generally acclimate rapidly to higher T<sub>air</sub> (within one month; <italic>e.g</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37">Kattge and Knorr, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40">Kumarathunge <italic>et al</italic>., 2019</xref>) by increasing their optimal temperature (T<sub>opt</sub>, <italic>i.e</italic>., the temperature at which the net assimilation (A<sub>net</sub>) reaches its maximum), its corresponding optimal net assimilation value (A<sub>opt</sub>), and their thermal breath (T<sub>80</sub>), which represents the temperature range where photosynthesis reaches &gt;80 % of its maximum (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R76">Yamori, Hikosaka and Way, 2014</xref>), thereby maintaining C gain despite warmer air (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38">Kruse <italic>et al</italic>., 2019</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R68">Vico <italic>et al</italic>., 2019</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">Choury <italic>et al</italic>., 2022</xref>). Thermal acclimation of photosynthesis also depends on stomatal conductance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38">Kruse <italic>et al</italic>., 2019</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39">Kullberg, Slot and Feeley, 2023</xref>) and phenology (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31">Grossiord <italic>et al</italic>., 2022</xref>), which vary interannually (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R51">Petrik <italic>et al</italic>., 2022</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">Didion-Gency <italic>et al</italic>., 2024</xref>), leading to significant uncertainties in plant’s thermal acclimation capacity. Shifts in A<sub>opt</sub>, T<sub>opt</sub>, and T<sub>80</sub> are mainly driven by an increase in the maximum catalytic activity of Rubisco (V<sub>Cmax</sub>) and the maximum ratio of electron transport (J<sub>max</sub>). Further, V<sub>Cmax</sub> and J<sub>max</sub> are both limited by nitrogen availability, therefore, thermal acclimation of photosynthesis also depends on nitrogen allocation, for which invasive plants tend to be more plastic than native ones (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">Feng and Fu, 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">Funk, Glenwinkel and Sack, 2013</xref>).</p><p id="P5">In parallel, acclimation to higher T<sub>air</sub> can also involve lowering the rate of respiration at 25°C (R<sub>25</sub>) and the respiration yield every 10°C (Q<sub>10</sub>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">Atkin and Tjoelker, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">Atkin, Bruhn and Tjoelker, 2005</xref>), thereby limiting C loss at high temperatures as respiration increases exponentially (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">Atkin and Tjoelker, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R73">Way and Yamori, 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">Crous, Uddling and De Kauwe, 2022</xref>). Plants with higher photosynthesis acclimation can show higher respiration acclimation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">Dusenge, Duarte and Way, 2019</xref>), although respiration can also acclimate more extensively to T<sub>air</sub> than assimilation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">Campbell <italic>et al</italic>., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R72">Way and Oren, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">Crous, Uddling and De Kauwe, 2022</xref>). Just as for photosynthesis, the duration of exposure to changed temperatures can influence respiration acclimation. Typically, acclimation of R<sub>25</sub> to a particular T<sub>air</sub> occurs during tissue development, while Q<sub>10</sub> varies more rapidly with seasonal changes in ambient T<sub>air</sub> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">Atkin, Bruhn and Tjoelker, 2005</xref>). Some studies found that respiration tends to acclimate universally among plant species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">Crous, Uddling and De Kauwe, 2022</xref>), and others reported acclimation to be species-specific independently of biomes or functional groups (<italic>e.g</italic>., evergreen <italic>vs</italic>. deciduous) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R60">Slot and Kitajima (2015)</xref>). However, respiratory rates are inversely proportional to the leaf nitrogen content and the specific leaf area (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41">Lee, Reich and Bolstad, 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R75">Xu, Schuster and Griffin, 2007</xref>), frequently found to be higher in invasive species than in native ones (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">Baruch and Goldstein, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42">Leishman <italic>et al</italic>., 2007</xref>). Therefore, temperature-induced reduction of respiratory rates could favor invasive species at high temperatures, but this remains largely unknown.</p><p id="P6">In this study, we compared the acclimation of leaf photosynthesis and respiration of the invasive <italic>Trachycarpus fortunei</italic>, a palm native from Southeastern China, with two co-occurring natives growing in the southern Alps in a sub-mediterranean climate (<italic>i.e</italic>., the evergreen <italic>Ilex aquifolium</italic> and deciduous <italic>Tilia cordata</italic>). Since the 2000s, <italic>T. fortunei</italic> has been colonizing natural forests worldwide, impacting the regeneration of native species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">Fehr <italic>et al</italic>., 2023</xref>). In the southern Alps, the spread of <italic>T. fortunei</italic> has been correlated with the rise in T<sub>air</sub> since the 1970s (ΔMAT: +1.7°C) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R69">Walther <italic>et al</italic>., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">Fehr <italic>et al</italic>., 2023</xref>). As such, <italic>T. fortunei</italic> is suspected to benefit from warmer temperatures to outcompete its native competitors, but whether this includes enhanced photosynthetic and respiratory thermal acclimation is unknown. Using a transplant experiment in five sites covering a large range of mean T<sub>air</sub> across Europe, we measured the responses of photosynthesis and respiration to temperature over two years. A soil-plant-atmosphere continuum (SPAC) model was used to estimate the impact of temperature acclimation on the leaf and whole-plant C budget over an entire growing season. We hypothesized that (1) the invasive <italic>T. fortunei</italic> acclimates more extensively than the native species to increased T<sub>air</sub>, leading to higher A<sub>opt</sub>, T<sub>opt</sub>, and T<sub>80</sub>. Similarly, (2) the invasive <italic>T. fortunei</italic> displays lower R<sub>25</sub> and Q<sub>10</sub> than native species with higher T<sub>air</sub> and that, as such, (3) <italic>T. fortunei</italic> assimilates more C than native species in warmer sites.</p></sec><sec id="S2" sec-type="materials | methods"><label>2</label><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="S3"><label>2.1</label><title>Experimental design</title><p id="P7">We selected five sites across a temperature gradient in Europe for a transplant experiment: one reference site located in the sub-Mediterranean climate where <italic>T. fortunei</italic> is the most invasive in Europe (<italic>i.e</italic>., the lowlands of the southern slope of the Swiss Alps), and four sites with differences of respectively -6°, -3°, +3°, and +6°C mean summer T<sub>air</sub> (from April to October) compared to the reference site in the last ten years (2010-2020). This allowed us to assess the acclimation of the photosynthetic and respiration properties along a large T<sub>air</sub> gradient, thereby covering regions where <italic>T. fortunei</italic> already has or could become invasive in future years (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">Fehr <italic>et al</italic>., 2023</xref>). In addition to the reference site in southern Switzerland (sub-Mediterranean climate), sites spanned from south-eastern Spain (thermic semi-arid), southern France (Mediterranean) to the Swiss Plateau (temperate), and the Swiss Alps (cold) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). The elevation of the sites ranged between 1 and 965 m a.s.l. (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref> for more details). During the measurement period (2022 and 2023), mean annual T<sub>air</sub> were 8.4, 13.3, 15.2, 17.7, and 21.8°C from the coldest to the warmest site, respectively, with slightly warmer conditions in 2022 than in 2023 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S1</xref>).</p><p id="P8"><italic>T. fortunei</italic> typically co-occurs with other species in the forest understory (<italic>e.g</italic>., the native evergreen <italic>Ilex aquifolium</italic> and deciduous <italic>Tilia cordata</italic>), which it occasionally excludes when dominating the canopy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">Fehr <italic>et al</italic>., 2023</xref>). To simulate the natural half-shady understory environment, we constructed a wooden shading infrastructure (6 × 4 × 1.8 m) in an unobstructed area on all sites. The top and sides were covered with a permeable shading tissue obstructing 70% of sunlight. Mean yearly incoming solar radiation for 2022-2023 was similar among sites (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S1</xref>).</p><p id="P9">In November 2021, we dug out 200 saplings of <italic>T. fortunei</italic> of 50-70 cm in height in a freshly invaded sub-Mediterranean forest (Cugnasco, Switzerland; 46°10’15” N, 8°55’49” E, 205 m a.s.l., MAT 12.2 ºC, MAP: 1757 mm; 1.1 km from our reference site). We further bought 200 saplings of <italic>T. cordata</italic> (Morbio Superiore, Switzerland) and 150 saplings of <italic>I. aquifolium</italic> (Wiler bei Utzenstorf, Switzerland) from commercial producers. All individuals were immediately potted in 7 L pots with generic sandy forest soil made of 20% peat and mineral substrate (Ph = 6.3; Ökohum; DE) and overwintered at the reference site.</p><p id="P10">In March 2022, 100 healthy individuals of each species (<italic>i.e</italic>., 300 saplings) were randomly separated into five groups of 20 individuals per species and transported to the five sites (n = 60 saplings per site). The plants for the coldest site were kept at the second coldest one (temperate climate) until April 2022 and from December 2022 to March 2023 to avoid exposure to temperatures below -15°C as it could have killed <italic>T. fortunei</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">Fehr and Burga, 2016</xref>). Despite this, 75% of the individuals of <italic>T. fortunei</italic> at the two coldest sites suffered frost damage during the winter of 2022-2023, limiting the number of replicates to four in 2023. At each site, pots were placed inside the shading infrastructure in four rows of 15 individuals each, alternating species to randomize potential differences in light and wind conditions. Each pot was individually connected to a drip irrigation system equipped with individual pressure resistances (Allenspach GreenTech AG, CH) to guarantee the same irrigation for each pot. Plants were watered automatically every two days at dawn to field capacity to ensure water availability throughout the experiment. We recorded T<sub>air</sub>, RH, and solar radiation (data logger: EM-100; air temperature and humidity: Atmos-14, Meter Group Inc.; USA; light quantum sensor: SQ-100X-SS, Apogee Instruments; USA) inside each shading infrastructure every 30 minutes at 1,5 m above the ground. We also monitored the soil moisture of each plant’s pot at 10 cm depth monthly with a soil moisture meter (TDR-100, Spectrum Technologies; USA).</p><p id="P11">For two years (2022-2023), the measurement campaigns were conducted in May, July, and September (six in total) during two consecutive growing seasons (<italic>i.e</italic>., 2022 and 2023). We tracked leaf flush and senescence at each site with phenocams (IPX5, VisorTech; DE). To guarantee that we measured fully expanded leaves, the first campaign of each year in May was conducted one month after all individuals of <italic>T. cordata</italic> had flushed.</p></sec><sec id="S4"><label>2.2</label><title>CO<sub>2</sub> assimilation and respiration responses to air temperature</title><p id="P12">We measured the optimal temperature (T<sub>opt</sub>), net assimilation at the optimal temperature (A<sub>opt</sub>), thermal breath (T<sub>80</sub>), dark respiration at 25°C (R<sub>25</sub>), and respiration yield (Q<sub>10</sub>) of one-year-old (or fully developed of the current year in deciduous <italic>T. cordata</italic>), undamaged leaves of 10 individuals per species (4 individuals of <italic>T. fortunei</italic> in 2023). Hence, every year in May, one leaf per individual was selected for T<sub>opt</sub>, A<sub>opt</sub>, and T<sub>80</sub> measurements, while an adjacent leaf was chosen for R<sub>25,</sub> and Q<sub>10</sub>.</p><p id="P13">T<sub>opt</sub>, A<sub>opt</sub>, and T<sub>80</sub> were obtained through CO<sub>2</sub> assimilation response to T<sub>air</sub> curves using portable photosynthesis systems (Li-6800, Licor Biosciences; USA) similar to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27">Gauthey <italic>et al</italic>., (2023)</xref> and Deluigi <italic>et al</italic>., (2025). Measurements were conducted approx. every 1-2 hours at five or six time points during the day, reflecting different ambient T<sub>air</sub> from the sunrise (<italic>i.e</italic>., the coldest T<sub>air</sub> of the day) to the middle of the afternoon (<italic>i.e</italic>., the warmest T<sub>air</sub> of the day) to obtain the possible largest T<sub>air</sub> range (from 12 to 35°C on average across sites and campaigns). Air temperature within the Li-6800 chamber was set according to the ambient T<sub>air</sub>, which was measured continuously (RS-91, RS Instruments; DE). By doing so, we ensured to track the temperature response curve of the ambient T<sub>air</sub> and to avoid possible artifacts associated with differences between the ambient temperature experienced by the plants and the conditions in the cuvette, as well as bias associated with the calculations of T<sub>L</sub> within gas exchange systems (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R65">Still <italic>et al</italic>., 2019</xref>). To extend the temperature range, we additionally decreased and increased the temperature of the cuvette by 5°C during the coldest and warmest time of the day, respectively. Relative humidity within the cuvette was increased at high temperatures to avoid stomatal closure due to high VPD. Hence, VPD ranged between 1 (fixed minimum) and maximum 3,5 kPa (when T<sub>air</sub> reached &gt; 38°C). T<sub>opt</sub>, A<sub>opt</sub>, and T<sub>80</sub> were measured at saturating light (PPFD of 1500 μmol m<sup>−2</sup> s<sup>−1</sup>) and ambient CO<sub>2</sub> (400 ppm). Measurements of R<sub>25</sub> and Q<sub>10</sub> were conducted as described above, except that the leaf of each individual was wrapped in aluminum foil for at least 30 minutes before each measurement to dark-acclimate the leaves and that light was reduced to 0 μmol m<sup>−2</sup> s<sup>−1</sup> inside the cuvette during the measurements. All measurements were taken after the gas exchange rates had stabilized for at least 5 min.</p><p id="P14">We extracted T<sub>opt</sub>, A<sub>opt</sub>, and T<sub>80</sub> of each individual by fitting our measurements of assimilation at different T<sub>air</sub> with a parabolic curve in R (4.1.1, R Core Team, 2021), using the following equation as in Choury <italic>et al</italic>., (2022): <disp-formula id="FD1"><label>(1)</label><mml:math id="M1"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula> where A<sub>i</sub> is the net assimilation at temperature T<sub>i</sub> and b is the width of the curve. T<sub>80</sub> was then calculated after resolving <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD1">equation (1)</xref> for A<sub>i</sub> = 0.8 A<sub>opt</sub> and isolating T<sub>i</sub>. Similarly, R<sub>25</sub> and Q<sub>10</sub> were obtained after fitting the respiration measurements at different T<sub>air</sub> with an exponential curve in R, using the following equation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">Choury <italic>et al</italic>., 2022</xref>): <disp-formula id="FD2"><label>(2)</label><mml:math id="M2"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>25</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>25</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p></sec><sec id="S5"><label>2.3</label><title>SPAC modeling of leaf-level photosynthesis and respiration</title><p id="P15">To assess the temperature effect on the annual leaf-level C uptake (C<sub>leaf</sub>), we modeled the instantaneous leaf-level net photosynthesis at 30-minute intervals from leaf flushing to senescence with a mechanistic soil-plant-atmosphere continuum (SPAC) model proposed by Garcia-Tejera <italic>et al</italic>. (2017). The model was modified to account for the acclimation of temperature responses of photosynthesis and respiration (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>). The original model calculates iteratively net assimilation (A<sub>net</sub>) and stomatal conductance (g<sub>s</sub>) based on environmental drivers and physiological parameters. A<sub>net</sub> is calculated as: <disp-formula id="FD3"><label>(3)</label><mml:math id="M3"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula> where C<sub>a</sub> is the ambient CO<sub>2</sub> concentration, C<sub>i</sub> is the intracellular CO<sub>2</sub> concentration, and R<sub>d</sub> is the dark respiration rate. g<sub>s</sub> is derived from its theoretical value at unlimited water availability (g<sub>s,max</sub>): <disp-formula id="FD4"><label>(4)</label><mml:math id="M4"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mtext>max</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>Γ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula> where B is the CO<sub>2</sub> uptake limiting rate of either J<sub>max</sub> or V<sub>Cmax</sub>, G is the CO<sub>2</sub> compensation point of photosynthesis, E is a metric of carboxylation and oxygenation rates, and D and F are constants. g<sub>s</sub> is then derived from g<sub>s,max</sub> based on hydraulic parameters, water transport from the soil to the leaf, and transpiration (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S2</xref>, equations in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Tables S1 &amp; S2</xref>).</p><p id="P16">To model leaf temperature (T<sub>L</sub>), we used a leaf energy balance model by Kevin Tu (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://landflux.org/Tools.php">http://landflux.org/Tools.php</ext-link>) as in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R45">Marias, Meinzer and Still (2017)</xref>. As such, T<sub>L</sub> varied with T<sub>air</sub>, light, RH, and g<sub>s</sub> following the equations from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35">Jones (1992)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R64">Sridhar and Elliott (2002)</xref>, and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R46">Monteith and Reifsnyder (2007)</xref> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table S1</xref>). As T<sub>L</sub> impacts g<sub>s</sub>, and vice versa, we nested the SPAC optimization process for g<sub>s</sub> calculations into a second optimization process to calculate T<sub>L</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>). R<sub>d</sub> was calculated with T<sub>L</sub> following <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD2">equation (2)</xref>. V<sub>Cmax</sub> and J<sub>max</sub> were adjusted for T<sub>L</sub> following the peaked Arrhenius function equation as in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40">Kumarathunge <italic>et al</italic>. (2019)</xref>. To incorporate T<sub>L</sub> acclimation in our model, we adjusted the entropy factor (ΔS, J mol<sup>-1</sup> K<sup>-1</sup>) and the activation energy (Ha, kJ mol<sup>-1</sup>) in the peaked Arrhenius function with the general coefficients proposed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40">Kumarathunge <italic>et al</italic>. (2019)</xref> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Tables S2 &amp; S3</xref>). For respiration, we adjusted R<sub>25</sub> with T<sub>air</sub> with linear species-specific equations that we derived from our results (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Tables S1</xref>): <disp-formula id="FD5"><label>(5)</label><mml:math id="M5"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable columnalign="left"><mml:mtr columnalign="left"><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>25</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.50</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.0037</mml:mn><mml:msub><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula> <disp-formula id="FD6"><label>(6)</label><mml:math id="M6"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable columnalign="left"><mml:mtr columnalign="left"><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>25</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.42</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.0293</mml:mn><mml:msub><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mn>1.</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula> <disp-formula id="FD7"><label>(7)</label><mml:math id="M7"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable columnalign="left"><mml:mtr columnalign="left"><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>25</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.36</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.0317</mml:mn><mml:msub><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="P17">To parametrize the model, we measured J<sub>max,25</sub> and V<sub>c,max,25</sub> on five individuals of the three species in July 2023 at our reference site with the Li-6800 following the methodology used in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">Didion-Gency <italic>et al</italic>., (2022)</xref>. In May 2022, we measured the minimum stomatal conductance (g<sub>min</sub>) on 4-5 saplings per species at EPFL (46°31’15.3”N, 6°34’04.0”E, Lausanne, CH). In September each year (2022 and 2023), we measured the leaf area of 4-10 individuals of each species at every site. For this, we photographed ten representative leaves of <italic>I. aquifolium</italic> and <italic>T. cordata</italic>, and all the leaves of <italic>T. fortunei</italic>. We extracted the leaf area using the software Fiji (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R57">Schindelin <italic>et al</italic>., 2012</xref>). The mean leaf area of <italic>I. aquifolium</italic> and <italic>T. cordata</italic> was multiplied by the total number of leaves of each individual to compute the total leaf area. Finally, the leaf area index (LAI) was obtained by dividing the total leaf area by the pot’s upper surface.</p><p id="P18">We calibrated and validated the model with A<sub>net</sub> measurements that we took diurnally at the five experimental sites during every campaign. A<sub>net</sub> was measured approximately every hour with the Li-6800 under ambient light, T<sub>air</sub>, and RH. We randomly selected 70 % of the measurements to calibrate influential model parameters that we could not measure similarly as in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31">Grossiord <italic>et al</italic>. (2022)</xref> and Deluigi <italic>et al</italic>., (2025). The model was calibrated using a differential evolution (DEzs) Markov chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) sampler (Ter <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">Braak and Vrugt, 2008</xref>) using the R package BayesianTools (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33">Hartig <italic>et al</italic>., 2023</xref>). For each species, we run 10,000 iterations of three independent chains. We confirmed the convergence of the calibration with the Gelman–Rubin diagnostic and a threshold of 1.1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">Gelman and Rubin, 1992</xref>). We used the 30 % remaining measurements to assess the goodness-of-fit (RMSE, percent bias, and Nash-Sutcliff efficiency) between the measured and modeled A<sub>net</sub> at each site. To estimate the effect of photosynthetic temperature acclimation on the plant C budget, we ran the model without acclimation by keeping V<sub>C,max</sub>, J<sub>max</sub>, R<sub>25</sub>, and Q<sub>10</sub> constant (mean of the reference site).</p></sec><sec id="S6"><label>2.4</label><title>Statistical analyses</title><p id="P19">Species and site differences in T<sub>opt</sub>, T<sub>80</sub>, A<sub>opt</sub>, R<sub>25</sub>, and Q<sub>10</sub> were tested through analysis of variance by using species (<italic>i.e</italic>., <italic>T. fortunei, I. aquifolium</italic>, and <italic>T. cordata</italic>) and climate (semi-arid, Mediterranean, sub-Mediterranean, temperate, and cold) and their interaction as fixed effects. No variable transformation was required to ensure homoscedasticity. Tukey’s HSD post hoc tests were used to separately estimate differences between species or climates. Linear regressions were used to test the relationships between T<sub>opt</sub>, A<sub>opt</sub>, R<sub>25</sub>, Q<sub>10,</sub> and T<sub>air</sub> (mean of the two weeks preceding the measurements) and between A<sub>opt</sub> and T<sub>opt</sub>. All statistical tests were done using the software R (4.1.1, R Core Team, 2021).</p></sec></sec><sec id="S7" sec-type="results"><label>3</label><title>Results</title><sec id="S8"><label>3.1</label><title>Photosynthetic and respiration responses to air temperature</title><p id="P20">In both years, A<sub>opt</sub>, T<sub>opt</sub>, and T<sub>80</sub> differed between species and climates (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001 for A<sub>opt</sub> and T<sub>opt</sub> and <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05 for T<sub>80</sub>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref> &amp; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table S4</xref>), with generally higher values in the warmest site and lower values in the coldest one (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S3</xref> &amp; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table S5</xref>). In all sites, A<sub>opt</sub> and T<sub>opt</sub> were lower in <italic>T. fortunei</italic> (2.86 µmol m<sup>2</sup> s<sup>-1</sup> and 21.3°C on average, respectively) than in <italic>I. aquifolium</italic> (5.5 µmol m<sup>2</sup> s<sup>-1</sup> and 22.7°C on average, respectively) and <italic>T. cordata</italic> (6.96 µmol m<sup>2</sup> s<sup>-1</sup> and 23.9°C on average, respectively), even in the reference sub-Mediterranean climate where <italic>T. fortunei</italic> is highly invasive (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig 2</xref>). Similarly, <italic>T. fortunei</italic> had a lower T<sub>80</sub> (11.1°C on average) than <italic>I. aquifolium</italic> (13.9°C on average) and <italic>T. cordata</italic> (15.2°C on average) in all sites (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>).</p><p id="P21">A<sub>opt</sub> and T<sub>opt</sub> were strongly correlated with the mean T<sub>air</sub> of the two preceding weeks, suggesting rapid photosynthetic acclimation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>). The relationship between mean T<sub>air</sub> and T<sub>opt</sub> was significant for all species (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01), but steeper for the two evergreen species than for the deciduous one (+0.60, +0.55, and + 0.33°C T<sub>opt</sub> per °C mean T<sub>air</sub> for <italic>T. fortunei, I. aquifolium</italic>, and <italic>T. cordata</italic>, respectively). The same relationship with A<sub>opt</sub> was significant in <italic>T. fortunei</italic> (+0.16 µmol m<sup>2</sup> s<sup>-1</sup> per °C; p &lt; 0.001) and <italic>I. aquifolium</italic> (+0.19 µmol m<sup>2</sup> s<sup>-1</sup> per °C; <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001), but not for <italic>T. cordata</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>). Air temperature and T<sub>80</sub> were only correlated in <italic>T. fortunei</italic> (+ 0.19°C per °C air temperature, R<sup>2</sup> = 0.25, <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S4</xref>). A<sub>opt</sub>, T<sub>opt</sub>, and T<sub>80</sub> were positively correlated in all species (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref> &amp; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S5</xref>), except for T<sub>opt</sub> and T<sub>80</sub> in <italic>T. fortunei</italic>. In <italic>T. fortunei</italic>, A<sub>opt</sub> increased by 0.12 µmol m<sup>2</sup> s<sup>-1</sup> per °C positive shift in T<sub>opt</sub>. The same correlation was steeper in <italic>I. aquifolium</italic> and <italic>T. cordata</italic> (+0.23 and +0.27 µmol m<sup>2</sup> s<sup>-1</sup> per °C shift in T<sub>opt</sub>, respectively; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>).</p><p id="P22">R<sub>25</sub> varied across sites and species (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref> &amp; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table S4</xref>) with higher values in the colder sites, except in <italic>T. fortunei</italic>. On average, R<sub>25</sub> was almost half as high in <italic>T. fortunei</italic> (0.40 µmol m<sup>2</sup> s<sup>-1</sup>) than in <italic>I. aquifolium</italic> and <italic>T. cordata</italic> (0.85 and 0.75 µmol m<sup>2</sup> s<sup>-1</sup>, respectively) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref>). R<sub>25</sub> decreased with increasing mean T<sub>air</sub> of the two preceding weeks in <italic>I. aquifolium</italic> and <italic>T. cordata</italic> (-0.03 µmol m<sup>2</sup> s<sup>-1</sup> / °C in both species, P &lt; 0.01; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref>) but not in <italic>T. fortunei</italic>, suggesting limited temperature acclimation in that species. On the other hand, while Q<sub>10</sub> was different between species and sites (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref> &amp; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table S4</xref>), Q<sub>10</sub> decreased with increasing mean T<sub>air</sub> only in <italic>T. fortunei</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S9"><label>3.2</label><title>Modelled carbon uptake</title><p id="P23">The SPAC model produced more precise predictions for <italic>I. aquifolium</italic> and <italic>T. cordata</italic> than for <italic>T. fortunei</italic> (R<sup>2</sup> = 0.61, 0.66, and 0.17; NSE = 0.47, 0.62, and 0.11, respectively). Still, bias was low in all species (-0.61, 1.41, and 1.72%, respectively, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table S6</xref>), indicating a high accuracy of the model.</p><p id="P24">Overall, the model revealed significant differences in the annual leaf-level C uptake (C<sub>leaf</sub>) between species (<italic>i.e</italic>., 360, 345, and 587 gC m<sup>-2</sup> on average for <italic>T. fortunei, I. aquifolium</italic>, and <italic>T. cordata</italic>, respectively; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7</xref>) and climates (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001), as well as an interaction between species and climate (<italic>P</italic> = 0.016, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table S7</xref>). At the reference site, <italic>T. fortunei</italic> had the lowest C<sub>leaf</sub> (321 gC m<sup>-2</sup>) compared to <italic>I. aquifolium</italic> and <italic>T. cordata</italic> (418 and 615 gC m<sup>-2</sup>, respectively; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7</xref>). However, <italic>T. fortunei</italic> maintained a relatively constant C<sub>leaf</sub> between the sites except at the warmest site, where a high R resulted in a lower C<sub>leaf</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7</xref> &amp; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table S8</xref>). In contrast, both native species show the lowest C<sub>leaf</sub> at the coldest site, a progressively higher C<sub>leaf</sub> until a peak at the Mediterranean site, and a subsequent decrease at the warmest site (<italic>i.e</italic>., semi-arid) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7</xref>). Notably, <italic>T. cordata</italic> was the only species that kept a similarly high C<sub>leaf</sub> at the warmest site as at the reference sites despite higher R (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7</xref>).</p><p id="P25">Total leaf area did not vary largely between sites, apart for <italic>T. fortunei</italic>, which had a larger leaf area in the three warmest sites compared to the two colder ones (<italic>i.e</italic>., because of frost damage in winter 2022-2023; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S6</xref>). As a consequence, total C uptake (C<sub>tot</sub>) showed similar patterns as C<sub>leaf</sub> across sites for all species (<italic>i.e</italic>., peaking at the Mediterranean site; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S7</xref>) with higher C<sub>tot</sub> in <italic>T. cordata</italic> (<italic>i.e</italic>., because of its higher leaf area; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S6</xref>) compared to the other species.</p><p id="P26">In contrast to C<sub>leaf</sub>, <italic>T. fortunei</italic> had lower C<sub>tot</sub> in the two coldest sites because of reduced leaf area.</p><p id="P27">Acclimation of photosynthesis and respiration contributed strongly to the variation in C<sub>leaf</sub>. Without considering acclimation, C<sub>leaf</sub> of <italic>T. fortunei</italic> would have decreased at the temperate and Mediterranean sites (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table S9</xref>) and remained similar than the C<sub>leaf</sub> with acclimation at more extreme climates (cold and semi-arid conditions). Similarly, <italic>T. cordata</italic> would have had a significantly lower C<sub>leaf</sub> at the Mediterranean and semi-arid sites. Contrastingly, acclimation did not modify the C<sub>leaf</sub> in <italic>I. aquifolium</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="S10" sec-type="discussion"><label>4</label><title>Discussion</title><sec id="S11"><label>4.1</label><title>Photosynthetic and respiratory acclimation is not higher in invasive palms than in native species</title><p id="P28">Against our initial hypothesis, the invasive <italic>T. fortunei</italic> did not show a higher photosynthetic acclimation than the native species, especially compared to the evergreen <italic>I. aquifolium</italic> that showed a similar thermal plasticity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs 3</xref> &amp; 4). All species had higher T<sub>opt</sub> in the warmer sites than the colder ones (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>), but the two evergreen species showed similar T<sub>opt</sub> acclimation rates at almost double that of the deciduous one (about +0.6°C <italic>vs</italic>. +0.3°C per degree T<sub>air</sub>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig 4</xref>.). Such differences between functional groups can be explained by the higher need for species with long-lasting tissues to tolerate a broader range of thermal conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R76">Yamori, Hikosaka and Way, 2014</xref>). Despite those differences between functional groups, all our shifts in T<sub>opt</sub> were within the range of +0.3 to 0.8 °C per degree T<sub>air</sub>, as found in most studies on leaf thermal acclimation (<italic>e.g</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40">Kumarathunge <italic>et al</italic>., 2019</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">Choury <italic>et al</italic>., 2022</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">Crous, Uddling and De Kauwe, 2022</xref>). The T<sub>opt</sub> shifts were probably driven by changes in the ratio between V<sub>C,max</sub> and J<sub>max</sub>, as commonly found in other C3 species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37">Kattge and Knorr, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R63">Smith and Dukes, 2017</xref>), even if more work would be needed to confirm this.</p><p id="P29">In contrast to previous studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32">Gunderson <italic>et al</italic>., 2010</xref>; Sendall, Lusk and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R55">Reich, 2016</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38">Kruse <italic>et al</italic>., 2019</xref>), we also observed an increase of A<sub>opt</sub> with rising T<sub>air</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>) and generally higher values at warmer sites (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>). Several studies have underpinned the important role of stomatal aperture on A<sub>opt</sub> shifts with temperature, especially compared to T<sub>opt,</sub> which is generally less impacted by stomatal closure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38">Kruse <italic>et al</italic>., 2019</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">Akaji, Torimaru and Akada, 2024</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R59">Slot <italic>et al</italic>., 2024</xref>). In our study, plants were well-watered, and VPD was as low as technically possible during the measurements, allowing us to measure the thermal acclimation of A<sub>opt</sub> mostly without the bias of increasing stomatal closure. These results are far-reaching as they suggest that VPD effects on stomata may hide the actual temperature acclimation potential of A<sub>opt</sub> driven by higher enzymatic activity in warmer environments (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">Berry and Bjorkman, 1980</xref>). Still, similarly to T<sub>opt</sub>, <italic>T. fortunei</italic> did not show larger A<sub>opt</sub> shifts than the other species (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>). Higher T<sub>opt</sub> also led to higher A<sub>opt</sub>, and for every °C change in T<sub>opt</sub>, A<sub>opt</sub> only increased by 0.11 µmol m<sup>2</sup> s<sup>-1</sup> in the invasive species, while it increased up to three times more for <italic>T. cordata</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>). However, <italic>T. fortunei</italic> was the only species increasing its T<sub>80</sub> with T<sub>air</sub> (+ 0.19°C per °C air temperature; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S3</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R61">Slot and Winter (2017)</xref> found an increase in T<sub>80</sub> that was accompanied by the rise in the J<sub>max</sub>:V<sub>C,max</sub> ratio. Hence, a higher T<sub>80</sub> could be either related to a higher J<sub>max</sub>, or a lower V<sub>C,max</sub>. The higher T<sub>80</sub> in the invasive palm could thus indicate a decrease in V<sub>C,max</sub> or increase in J<sub>max</sub> with higher T<sub>air</sub>.</p><p id="P30">Contrary to our initial hypothesis, R<sub>25</sub> in <italic>T. fortunei</italic> did not decrease with higher T<sub>air</sub>, showing no evidence of acclimation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figs 5</xref> &amp; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>). Wang <italic>et al</italic>. (2020) observed that V<sub>C,max</sub> and R<sub>25</sub> were decreasing with increasing T<sub>air</sub> as less active Rubisco is needed for a given value of V<sub>c,max</sub> at higher temperatures, decreasing the respiratory costs for Rubisco turnover and therefore R<sub>25</sub>. As R<sub>25</sub> of <italic>T. fortunei</italic> remained relatively constant across temperatures, it supports the notion that V<sub>C,max</sub> remained stable as well in that species. The constant R<sub>25</sub> may also indicate a lack of acclimation pressure, as at temperatures below 30°C, respiratory rates were low in this species (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref>). This corroborates that palms can display lower foliar respiration rates than dicot species below 35 °C (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">Cavaleri, Oberbauer and Ryan, 2008</xref>). In contrast to <italic>T. fortunei</italic>, in the two native species, R<sub>25</sub> decreased with higher T<sub>air</sub> (−0.03 μmol CO<sub>2</sub> m<sup>−2</sup> s<sup>−1</sup> per degree T<sub>air</sub> on average; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref>), with similar rates as in other studies (<italic>e.g</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R55">Reich <italic>et al</italic>., 2016</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R78">Zhu <italic>et al</italic>., 2020</xref>) following the consistent shifts of R<sub>25</sub> with T<sub>air</sub> found in a wide range of species and diverse experimental designs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R60">Slot and Kitajima, 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">Crous, Uddling and De Kauwe, 2022</xref>). Contrastingly, <italic>T. fortunei</italic> shifted Q<sub>10</sub> while the native species did not (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figs 5</xref> &amp; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>). Similar acclimation of Q<sub>10</sub> was found in other works focusing on evergreen species (<italic>e.g</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R53">Quan, Wang and Wang, 2020</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">Crous, Uddling and De Kauwe, 2022</xref>) and typically occurs when respiration is limited by low substrate availability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">Atkin and Tjoelker, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R74">van de Weg, Fetcher and Shaver, 2013</xref>). The decrease in Q<sub>10</sub> at high temperatures allowed the invasive palm to increase its A<sub>net</sub> at warmer sites and could partially explain the broader T<sub>80</sub> we observed at high temperatures (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S3</xref>). Q<sub>10</sub> shifts have been associated with short-term changes of respiration with T<sub>air</sub> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">Atkin and Tjoelker, 2003</xref>) and our findings contrast with studies measuring evergreen species in climatic chambers that observed no acclimation with temperature (<italic>e.g</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">Dusenge, Madhavji and Way, 2020</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">Choury <italic>et al</italic>., 2022</xref>), potentially because Q<sub>10</sub> also varies seasonally and its acclimation depends on the warming duration and intensity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">Atkin, Bruhn and Tjoelker, 2005</xref>; O’Sullivan <italic>et al</italic>., 2013). In fact, all our measured parameters (A<sub>opt</sub>, T<sub>opt</sub>, T<sub>80</sub>, R<sub>25</sub>, and Q<sub>10</sub>) shifted systematically with T<sub>air</sub> within two weeks in the three species. These results align with other studies (<italic>e.g</italic>., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37">Kattge and Knorr, 2007</xref>; Kumarathunge <italic>et al</italic>., 2019) stating that the commonly used 30-day acclimation period may be generally overestimated and that future works should consider using shorter acclimation periods (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R62">Smith and Dukes, 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R55">Reich <italic>et al</italic>., 2016</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R68">Vico <italic>et al</italic>., 2019</xref>). Second, all species (<italic>i.e</italic>., invasive and native ones) demonstrated a short acclimation duration and the invasive palm did not benefit from a more extensive photosynthetic and respiratory acclimation than native tree species.</p></sec><sec id="S12"><label>4.2</label><title>Impact of photosynthetic and respiratory acclimation on the leaf-level and plant C budget</title><p id="P31">Contrary to our expectations, the invasive palm generally showed lower C<sub>leaf</sub> and C<sub>tot</sub> than native species across all sites, even at the reference site where the palm invades the natural ecosystem (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figs. 7</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S6</xref>). While higher C gains increase the competitivity of plant species (Pearcy <italic>et al</italic>., 1987), lower C costs in invasive plants also play a significant role in invasion processes, and <italic>T. fortunei</italic> may have benefitted from other characteristics (<italic>e.g</italic>., longer photosynthetic period in autumn, lower whole-plant respiration, herbivory, and tissue turnover (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">Fridley <italic>et al</italic>., 2022</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36">Juillard <italic>et al</italic>., 2024</xref>)) to be invasive under current climatic conditions. At the reference site, <italic>T. fortunei</italic> also shares these characteristics with several other natives (<italic>e.g</italic>., <italic>Ilex aquifolium, Hedera helix</italic>) and non-native evergreen species (<italic>e.g</italic>., <italic>Prunus laurocerasus</italic>) currently spreading in the understory of sub-Mediterranean deciduous forests, which could confirm the important role of these characteristics in the forest composition changes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">Conedera <italic>et al</italic>., 2018</xref>).</p><p id="P32">The similar C<sub>leaf</sub> of <italic>T. fortunei</italic> between the sites (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7</xref>) can be explained by the relatively low increase in A<sub>opt</sub> per °C T<sub>opt</sub> (+0.11 µmol m<sup>2</sup> s<sup>-1</sup> per °C T<sub>opt</sub>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>), while T<sub>opt</sub> showed the highest increase with T<sub>air</sub> among the compared species (+0.60°C per °C T<sub>air</sub>). Hence, accurate A<sub>opt</sub> measurements not biased by stomatal closure at high VPD are crucial to predict whole tree carbon exchange acclimation realistically. At the leaf level, the invasive palm performed similarly well at the reference site than in the two colder sites, while the native species had a lower C<sub>leaf</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7</xref>), which shows that if <italic>T. fortunei</italic> is not damaged by frost in colder climates (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figs S6 &amp; S7</xref>), its photosynthetic capacity allows to perform equally well as the native species. In contrast, native species acclimated more to the higher T<sub>air</sub> at the Mediterranean site than the invasive palm (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig 7</xref> &amp; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S1</xref>), potentially limiting the capacity of the invasive palm to invade those environments. At the warmest site, C<sub>leaf</sub> was lower in all species. Still, high temperatures especially limited the performance of <italic>I. aquifolium</italic> due to high respiratory rates (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figs 7</xref> &amp; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8</xref>), highlighting the critical role of respiration on the C budget at temperatures above 30°C.</p><p id="P33">Acclimation of photosynthesis and respiration allowed the invasive palm to increase C uptake and reduce C losses (leading to a higher C budget) in intermediate sites with milder conditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8</xref>). Nevertheless, the importance of acclimation was limited in extreme climates (both cold and hot ones), suggesting that shifts in photosynthetic and respiratory patterns are insufficient to compensate for the harsher climatic conditions. In contrast, acclimation allowed the native <italic>T. cordata</italic> to increase the C budget in the hottest environments (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8</xref>). Still, the highest C budget was observed in the Mediterranean climate (+2.5°C), suggesting a limited enhancement of the C budget under global warming. Previous work also reported increased C gains in some temperate trees with a rise between +2 and +5 °C T<sub>air</sub>, especially because warming also leads to a certain extent to a longer growing season in deciduous trees (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">Duan <italic>et al</italic>., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31">Grossiord <italic>et al</italic>., 2022</xref>). On the other hand, the absence of photosynthetic and respiratory acclimation benefits for <italic>I. aquifolium</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8</xref>) could be explained by the high respiratory rates that drastically reduced the C<sub>leaf</sub> in all sites, even the cold ones (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig 7</xref>). As a shade-tolerant species, <italic>I. aquifolium</italic> tends to have high leaf N content, which has been associated with high respiration (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R54">Reich <italic>et al</italic>., 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R48">Niinemets, Valladares and Ceulemans, 2003</xref>), potentially constraining the positive effect of T<sub>air</sub> on its C budget.</p><p id="P34">Overall, our results suggest that photosynthetic and respiration thermal acclimation may not be the primary underlying mechanisms driving the fast propagation of the invasive palm in recent decades. Those findings are consistent with reports of invasive species conserving their initial niche (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R67">Verlinden and Nijs, 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43">Liu <italic>et al</italic>., 2020</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R56">Ripley <italic>et al</italic>., 2020</xref>). In addition, our results confirm that some long-lived invasive species have not reached their potential range yet, as observed in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">Bradley, Early and Sorte (2015)</xref>. Their range expansion could, therefore, be predicted from physiological measurements directly but not from the extrapolation of their native or current range (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R70">Walther <italic>et al</italic>., 2009</xref>). Invasive plants often depend on many traits to colonize a new environment, and future invasion patterns in a warmer environment are difficult to predict. Our results suggest that low foliar respiratory rates may provide an advantage to the invasive palm over the native plants. Given that respiration plays a vital role at high temperatures, high respiratory rates often observed in fast-growing invasive species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R47">Montesinos, 2022</xref>), could, therefore, reduce the C budget of fast-growing invasive species under higher temperatures.</p></sec></sec><sec id="S13" sec-type="conclusions"><label>5</label><title>Conclusion</title><p id="P35">Using a natural temperature gradient across European study sites, we showed that acclimation of photosynthesis and respiration rapidly occurs in young plants exposed to understory conditions and can play a significant role in the C budget of both invasive and native plant species. Contrary to our expectations, the invasive palm <italic>T. fortunei</italic> did not demonstrate higher acclimation capacity than its native competitors and had a lower (but more constant) C budget overall. In central and southern Europe, T<sub>air</sub> during summer could increase by 5–7°C by the end of the century compared to 1995–2014 (SSP5-8.5) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">Carvalho, Cardoso Pereira and Rocha, 2021</xref>), which would decrease the C budget of all species measured in this study. It is, therefore, likely that native sub-Mediterranean species will be outcompeted by more thermophilic invasive species in the future (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R70">Walther <italic>et al</italic>., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R44">Liu <italic>et al</italic>., 2017</xref>), which will likely lead to species composition changes in these forests.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="SM"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1"><label>Supplementary material</label><media xlink:href="EMS207548-supplement-Supplementary_material.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" id="d8aAcFbB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack id="S14"><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>This study was supported by the Sandoz Family Foundation. CG and CB were supported by the Swiss National Science Foundation (310030_204697). AV was supported by EVER project (CIPROM/2022/37-Prometeu program, GVA). CEAM is funded by Generalitat Valenciana. We thank Janisse Deluigi, Stéphane Jenni, Samuel Reyes, Alex Tunas Corzon, Gabor Reiss, Luis Pizarro Pietro, Eugénie Mas, Kevin Knecht, Elias Ackermann, Omar Basquet, Alice Gauthey, Krzysztof Wroński, Jolan Wicht, Margaux Didion-Gency, Valentin Meister, Patrick Favre, and Maxwell Bergström for their precious help during the management of the experimental sites and the fieldwork. We also thank Mercedes Carmona and Diana Fernández in the Forestry nursery of Guardamar del Segura (Conselleria de Medio Ambiente, Infraestructuras y Territorio, Generalitat Valenciana, ES;), <italic>Schutz Filisur Alpin Gartencenter</italic> at Filisur (CH), and the CEFE CNRS at Montpellier (FR) for hosting the experimental sites and providing water access all along the experiment.</p></ack><sec id="S15" sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability statement</title><p id="P36">Data will be made available on the Dryad Digital Repository.</p></sec><fn-group><fn fn-type="con" id="FN2"><p id="P37"><bold>Author Contributions</bold></p><p id="P38">TJ, CG, and CB planned and designed the research. All authors carried out the fieldwork. TJ, CB, and MD performed data analyses. TJ wrote the manuscript draft. All authors contributed to the review and editing of the manuscript.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><ref id="R1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Akaji</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Torimaru</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Akada</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Intraspecific variation in photosynthetic thermal acclimation in Fagus crenata seedlings from two populations growing at different elevations in northern Japan</article-title><source>Tree Physiology</source><year>2024</year><volume>44</volume><issue>8</issue><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39046278</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Atkin</surname><given-names>OK</given-names></name><name><surname>Bruhn</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Tjoelker</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Response of Plant Respiration to Changes in Temperature: Mechanisms and Consequences of Variations in Q10 Values and Acclimation</article-title><source>Advances in Photosynthesis and Respiration</source><year>2005</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.ph.37.030175.001511</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Atkin</surname><given-names>OK</given-names></name><name><surname>Tjoelker</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Thermal acclimation and the dynamic response of plant respiration to temperature</article-title><source>Trends in Plant Science</source><year>2003</year><volume>8</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>343</fpage><lpage>351</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12878019</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baruch</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldstein</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Leaf construction cost, nutrient concentration, and net CO2 assimilation of native and invasive species in Hawaii</article-title><source>Oecologia</source><year>1999</year><volume>121</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>183</fpage><lpage>192</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28308558</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Berry</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bjorkman</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Photosynthetic Response and Adaptation to Temperature in Higher Plants</article-title><source>Annual Review of Plant Physiology</source><year>1980</year><volume>31</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>491</fpage><lpage>543</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.pp.31.060180.002423</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Braak</surname><given-names>Ter</given-names></name><name><surname>Vrugt</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Differential Evolution Markov Chain with snooker updater and fewer chains</article-title><source>Statistics and Computing</source><year>2008</year><volume>18</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>435</fpage><lpage>446</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11222-008-9104-9</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bradley</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Early</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Sorte</surname><given-names>CJB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Space to invade? Comparative range infilling and potential range of invasive and native plants</article-title><source>Global Ecology and Biogeography</source><year>2015</year><volume>24</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>348</fpage><lpage>359</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/geb.12275</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Acclimation of photosynthesis and respiration is asynchronous in response to changes in temperature regardless of plant functional group</article-title><source>New Phytologist</source><year>2007</year><volume>176</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>375</fpage><lpage>389</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17692077</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carvalho</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Cardoso Pereira</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rocha</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Future surface temperatures over Europe according to CMIP6 climate projections: an analysis with original and bias-corrected data</article-title><source>Climatic Change</source><year>2021</year><volume>167</volume><issue>1–2</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>17</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10584-021-03159-0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cavaleri</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Oberbauer</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><name><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Foliar and ecosystem respiration in an old-growth tropical rain forest</article-title><source>Plant, Cell and Environment</source><year>2008</year><volume>31</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>473</fpage><lpage>483</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18182017</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Choury</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Tropical rainforest species have larger increases in temperature optima with warming than warm-temperate rainforest trees</article-title><source>New Phytologist</source><year>2022</year><volume>234</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1220</fpage><lpage>1236</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/nph.18077</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9311211</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35263440</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Conedera</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Drivers of broadleaved evergreen species spread into deciduous forests in the southern Swiss Alps</article-title><source>Regional Environmental Change</source><year>2018</year><volume>18</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>425</fpage><lpage>436</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10113-017-1212-7</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crous</surname><given-names>KY</given-names></name><name><surname>Uddling</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>De Kauwe</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Temperature responses of photosynthesis and respiration in evergreen trees from boreal to tropical latitudes</article-title><source>New Phytologist</source><year>2022</year><volume>234</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>353</fpage><lpage>374</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/nph.17951</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9994441</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35007351</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Davidson</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Jennions</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nicotra</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Do invasive species show higher phenotypic plasticity than native species and, if so, is it adaptive? A meta-analysis</article-title><source>Ecology Letters</source><year>2011</year><volume>14</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>419</fpage><lpage>431</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21314880</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Didion-Gency</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Impact of warmer and drier conditions on tree photosynthetic properties and the role of species interactions</article-title><source>New Phytologist</source><year>2022</year><volume>236</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>547</fpage><lpage>560</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/nph.18384</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9804646</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35842790</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Didion-Gency</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Chronic warming and dry soils limit carbon uptake and growth despite a longer growing season in beech and oak</article-title><source>Plant Physiology</source><year>2024</year><volume>194</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>741</fpage><lpage>757</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/plphys/kiad565</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10828195</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37874743</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Plastic responses of Populus yunnanensis and Abies faxoniana to elevated atmospheric CO2 and warming</article-title><source>Forest Ecology and Management</source><year>2013</year><volume>296</volume><fpage>33</fpage><lpage>40</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foreco.2013.01.032</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dusenge</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Duarte</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Way</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plant carbon metabolism and climate change: elevated CO2 and temperature impacts on photosynthesis, photorespiration and respiration</article-title><source>New Phytologist</source><year>2019</year><volume>221</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>32</fpage><lpage>49</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29983005</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dusenge</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Madhavji</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Way</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Contrasting acclimation responses to elevated CO2 and warming between an evergreen and a deciduous boreal conifer</article-title><source>Global Change Biology</source><year>2020</year><volume>26</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>3639</fpage><lpage>3657</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32181545</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fehr</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The invasive Chinese windmill palm (Trachycarpus fortunei) impacts forest vegetation and regeneration on the southern slope of the European Alps</article-title><source>Applied Vegetation Science</source><year>2023</year><issue>May 2023</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>31</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/avsc.12765</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fehr</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Burga</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Aspects and Causes of Earlier and Current Spread of Trachycarpus fortunei in the Forests of Southern Ticino and</article-title><source>Palms</source><year>2016</year><volume>60</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>125</fpage><lpage>136</lpage><comment>Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.zora.uzh.ch/id/eprint/127489/">http://www.zora.uzh.ch/id/eprint/127489/</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name><name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nitrogen allocation, partitioning and use efficiency in three invasive plant species in comparison with their native congeners</article-title><source>Biological Invasions</source><year>2008</year><volume>10</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>891</fpage><lpage>902</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10530-008-9240-3</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Finch</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>Effects of Climate Change on Invasive Species, Invasive Species in Forests and Rangelands of the United States</source><year>2021</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-3-030-45367-1_17</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fridley</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Extended leaf phenology and the autumn niche in deciduous forest invasions</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2012</year><volume>485</volume><issue>7398</issue><fpage>359</fpage><lpage>362</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22535249</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fridley</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A general hypothesis of forest invasions by woody plants based on whole-plant carbon economics</article-title><source>Journal of Ecology</source><year>2022</year><issue>April 2022</issue><fpage>4</fpage><lpage>22</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1365-2745.14001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Funk</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Glenwinkel</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Sack</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Differential Allocation to Photosynthetic and Non-Photosynthetic Nitrogen Fractions among Native and Invasive Species</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2013</year><volume>8</volume><issue>5</issue><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0064502</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3659119</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23700483</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gauthey</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Absence of canopy temperature variation despite stomatal adjustment in Pinus sylvestris under multidecadal soil moisture manipulation</article-title><source>New Phytologist</source><year>2023</year><volume>240</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>127</fpage><lpage>137</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37483100</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gelman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rubin</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inference from Iterative Simulation Using Multiple Sequences</article-title><source>Statistical Science</source><year>1992</year><volume>7</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>457</fpage><lpage>511</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/2246134</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gioria</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Why Are Invasive Plants Successful?</article-title><source>Annual Review of Plant Biology</source><year>2023</year><volume>74</volume><fpage>635</fpage><lpage>670</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36750415</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Godoy</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Valladares</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Castro-Díez</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multispecies comparison reveals that invasive and native plants differ in their traits but not in their plasticity</article-title><source>Functional Ecology</source><year>2011</year><volume>25</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1248</fpage><lpage>1259</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2435.2011.01886.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grossiord</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Warming may extend tree growing seasons and compensate for reduced carbon uptake during dry periods</article-title><source>Journal of Ecology</source><year>2022</year><month>April</month><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>15</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1365-2745.13892</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gunderson</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Thermal plasticity of photosynthesis: The role of acclimation in forest responses to a warming climate</article-title><source>Global Change Biology</source><year>2010</year><volume>16</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>2272</fpage><lpage>2286</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2486.2009.02090.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><element-citation publication-type="web"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hartig</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>General-Purpose MCMC and SMC Samplers and Tools for Bayesian Statistics</source><year>2023</year><comment>Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/florianhartig/BayesianTools">https://github.com/florianhartig/BayesianTools</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Higgins</surname><given-names>SI</given-names></name><name><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Invasive plants have broader physiological niches</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source><year>2014</year><volume>111</volume><issue>29</issue><fpage>10610</fpage><lpage>10614</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1406075111</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4115511</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24989502</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name></person-group><source>Plants and Microclimate: A Quantitative Approach to Environmental Plant Physiology</source><publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name><year>1992</year><edition>Third</edition></element-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Juillard</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Invasive palms have more efficient and prolonged CO2 assimilation compared to native sub-Mediterranean vegetation</article-title><source>Forest Ecology and Management</source><year>2024</year><volume>556</volume><issue>January</issue><elocation-id>121743</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foreco.2024.121743</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R37"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kattge</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Knorr</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Temperature acclimation in a biochemical model of photosynthesis: A reanalysis of data from 36 species</article-title><source>Plant, Cell and Environment</source><year>2007</year><volume>30</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>1176</fpage><lpage>1190</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17661754</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R38"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kruse</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Optimization of photosynthesis and stomatal conductance in the date palm Phoenix dactylifera during acclimation to heat and drought</article-title><source>New Phytologist</source><year>2019</year><volume>223</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1973</fpage><lpage>1988</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31093986</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R39"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kullberg</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name><surname>Slot</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Feeley</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Thermal optimum of photosynthesis is controlled by stomatal conductance and does not acclimate across an urban thermal gradient in six subtropical tree species</article-title><source>Plant Cell and Environment</source><year>2023</year><volume>46</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>831</fpage><lpage>849</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36597283</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R40"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kumarathunge</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Acclimation and adaptation components of the temperature dependence of plant photosynthesis at the global scale</article-title><source>New Phytologist</source><year>2019</year><volume>222</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>768</fpage><lpage>784</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30597597</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R41"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><name><surname>Reich</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name><name><surname>Bolstad</surname><given-names>PV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Acclimation of leaf respiration to temperature is rapid and related to specific leaf area, soluble sugars and leaf nitrogen across three temperate deciduous tree species</article-title><source>Functional Ecology</source><year>2005</year><volume>19</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>640</fpage><lpage>647</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2435.2005.01023.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R42"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leishman</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Leaf trait relationships of native and invasive plants: Community- and global-scale comparisons</article-title><source>New Phytologist</source><year>2007</year><volume>176</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>635</fpage><lpage>643</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17822409</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R43"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Most invasive species largely conserve their climatic niche</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source><year>2020</year><volume>117</volume><issue>38</issue><fpage>23643</fpage><lpage>23651</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.2004289117</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7519298</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32883880</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R44"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Do invasive alien plants benefit more from global environmental change than native plants?</article-title><source>Global Change Biology</source><year>2017</year><volume>23</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>3363</fpage><lpage>3370</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27888560</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R45"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marias</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Meinzer</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name><name><surname>Still</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Impacts of leaf age and heat stress duration on photosynthetic gas exchange and foliar nonstructural carbohydrates in Coffea arabica</article-title><source>Ecology and Evolution</source><year>2017</year><volume>7</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1297</fpage><lpage>1310</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ece3.2681</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5306013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28303198</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R46"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Monteith</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Reifsnyder</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Principles of Environmental Physics: 3rd Edition</chapter-title><source>Physics Today</source><publisher-name>ELSEVIER</publisher-name><year>2007</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1063/1.3128494</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R47"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Montesinos</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fast invasives fastly become faster: Invasive plants align largely with the fast side of the plant economics spectrum</article-title><source>Journal of Ecology</source><year>2022</year><volume>110</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>1010</fpage><lpage>1014</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1365-2745.13616</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R48"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Niinemets</surname><given-names>Ü</given-names></name><name><surname>Valladares</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Ceulemans</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Leaf-level phenotypic variability and plasticity of invasive Rhododendron ponticum and non-invasive Ilex aquifolium co-occurring at two contrasting European sites</article-title><source>Plant, Cell and Environment</source><year>2003</year><volume>26</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>941</fpage><lpage>956</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12803621</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R49"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>O’Sullivan</surname><given-names>OS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>High-resolution temperature responses of leaf respiration in snow gum (Eucalyptus pauciflora) reveal high-temperature limits to respiratory function</article-title><source>Plant, Cell and Environment</source><year>2013</year><volume>36</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>1268</fpage><lpage>1284</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23278101</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R50"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pearcy</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Carbon Gain by Plants in Natural Environments</article-title><source>BioScience</source><year>1987</year><volume>37</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>21</fpage><lpage>29</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/1310174</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R51"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Petrik</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Interannual adjustments in stomatal and leaf morphological traits of European beech (Fagus sylvatica L.) demonstrate its climate change acclimation potential</article-title><source>Plant Biology</source><year>2022</year><volume>24</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>1287</fpage><lpage>1296</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35238138</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R52"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pyšek</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Scientists’ warning on invasive alien species</article-title><source>Biological Reviews</source><year>2020</year><volume>95</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1511</fpage><lpage>1534</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/brv.12627</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7687187</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32588508</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R53"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Quan</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Thermal acclimation of leaf dark respiration of Larix gmelinii: A latitudinal transplant experiment</article-title><source>Science of the Total Environment</source><year>2020</year><volume>743</volume><elocation-id>140634</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32653708</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R54"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reich</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Relationships of leaf dark respiration to leaf nitrogen, specific leaf area and leaf life-span: a test across biomes and functional groups</article-title><source>Oecologia</source><year>1998</year><fpage>471</fpage><lpage>482</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28307896</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R55"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reich</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Boreal and temperate trees show strong acclimation of respiration to warming</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2016</year><volume>531</volume><issue>7596</issue><fpage>633</fpage><lpage>636</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26982730</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R56"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ripley</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Invasive grasses of sub-Antarctic Marion Island respond to increasing temperatures at the expense of chilling tolerance</article-title><year>2020</year><fpage>765</fpage><lpage>773</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/aob/mcz156</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7182586</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31583397</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R57"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schindelin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Fiji: An open-source platform for biological-image analysis</article-title><source>Nature Methods</source><year>2012</year><volume>9</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>676</fpage><lpage>682</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.2019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3855844</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22743772</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R58"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sendall</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lusk</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Reich</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Trade-offs in juvenile growth potential vs. shade tolerance among subtropical rain forest trees on soils of contrasting fertility</article-title><source>Functional Ecology</source><year>2016</year><volume>30</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>845</fpage><lpage>855</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1365-2435.12573</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R59"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Slot</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The stomatal response to vapor pressure deficit drives the apparent temperature response of photosynthesis in tropical forests</article-title><source>New Phytologist</source><year>2024</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38736030</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R60"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Slot</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kitajima</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>General patterns of acclimation of leaf respiration to elevated temperatures across biomes and plant types</article-title><source>Oecologia</source><year>2015</year><volume>177</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>885</fpage><lpage>900</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25481817</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R61"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Slot</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Winter</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Photosynthetic acclimation to warming in tropical forest tree Seedlings</article-title><source>Journal of Experimental Botany</source><year>2017</year><volume>68</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>2275</fpage><lpage>2284</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/erx071</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5447879</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28453647</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R62"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>NG</given-names></name><name><surname>Dukes</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plant respiration and photosynthesis in global-scale models: Incorporating acclimation to temperature and CO2</article-title><source>Global Change Biology</source><year>2013</year><volume>19</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>45</fpage><lpage>63</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23504720</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R63"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>NG</given-names></name><name><surname>Dukes</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Short-term acclimation to warmer temperatures accelerates leaf carbon exchange processes across plant types</article-title><source>Global Change Biology</source><year>2017</year><volume>23</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>4840</fpage><lpage>4853</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28560841</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R64"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sridhar</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Elliott</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>On the development of a simple downwelling longwave radiation scheme</article-title><source>Agricultural and Forest Meteorology</source><year>2002</year><volume>112</volume><issue>3–4</issue><fpage>237</fpage><lpage>243</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0168-1923(02)00129-6</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R65"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Still</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>When a cuvette is not a canopy: A caution about measuring leaf temperature during gas exchange measurements</article-title><source>Agricultural and Forest Meteorology</source><year>2019</year><volume>279</volume><issue>November 2018</issue><elocation-id>107737</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.agrformet.2019.107737</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R66"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Turbelin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Catford</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><source>Invasive plants and climate change, Climate Change: Observed Impacts on Planet Earth</source><publisher-name>Elsevier B.V</publisher-name><year>2021</year><edition>Third</edition><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/B978-0-12-821575-3.00025-6</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R67"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Verlinden</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nijs</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Alien plant species favoured over congeneric natives under experimental climate warming in temperate Belgian climate</article-title><year>2010</year><fpage>2777</fpage><lpage>2787</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10530-009-9683-1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R68"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vico</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Can leaf net photosynthesis acclimate to rising and more variable temperatures?</article-title><source>Plant Cell and Environment</source><year>2019</year><volume>42</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1913</fpage><lpage>1928</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30706948</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R69"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Walther</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Palms tracking climate change</article-title><source>Global Ecology and Biogeography</source><year>2007</year><volume>16</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>801</fpage><lpage>809</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1466-8238.2007.00328.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R70"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Walther</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Alien species in a warmer world: risks and opportunities</article-title><source>Trends in Ecology and Evolution</source><year>2009</year><volume>24</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>686</fpage><lpage>693</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19712994</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R71"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Acclimation of leaf respiration consistent with optimal photosynthetic capacity</article-title><source>Global Change Biology</source><year>2020</year><volume>26</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>2573</fpage><lpage>2583</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32091184</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R72"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Way</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Oren</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Differential responses to changes in growth temperature between trees from different functional groups and biomes: a review and synthesis of data</article-title><source>Tree Physiology</source><year>2010</year><volume>30</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>669</fpage><lpage>688</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20368338</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R73"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Way</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamori</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Thermal acclimation of photosynthesis : on the importance of adjusting our definitions and accounting for thermal acclimation of respiration</article-title><year>2014</year><fpage>89</fpage><lpage>100</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23812760</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R74"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van de Weg</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Fetcher</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Shaver</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Response of dark respiration to temperature in Eriophorum vaginatum from a 30-year-old transplant experiment in Alaska</article-title><source>Plant Ecology and Diversity</source><year>2013</year><volume>6</volume><issue>3–4</issue><fpage>377</fpage><lpage>381</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/17550874.2012.729618</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R75"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name><name><surname>Schuster</surname><given-names>WSF</given-names></name><name><surname>Griffin</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Seasonal variation of temperature response of respiration in invasive Berberis thunbergii (Japanese barberry) and two co-occurring native understory shrubs in a northeastern US deciduous forest</article-title><source>Oecologia</source><year>2007</year><volume>153</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>809</fpage><lpage>819</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17609983</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R76"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamori</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Hikosaka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Way</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Temperature response of photosynthesis in C3, C4, and CAM plants: Temperature acclimation and temperature adaptation</article-title><source>Photosynthesis Research</source><year>2014</year><volume>119</volume><issue>1–2</issue><fpage>101</fpage><lpage>117</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23801171</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R77"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Elevated temperature differently affects growth, photosynthetic capacity, nutrient absorption and leaf ultrastructure of Abies faxoniana and Picea purpurea under intra- And interspecific competition</article-title><source>Tree Physiology</source><year>2019</year><volume>39</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>1342</fpage><lpage>1357</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30977829</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R78"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Acclimation of leaf respiration temperature responses across thermally contrasting biomes</article-title><source>New Phytologist</source><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32931621</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><title>Map of the five experimental sites in Europe (from the coldest to the warmest: Filisur (cold, dark blue), Birmensdorf (temperate, light blue), Cadenazzo (sub-Mediterranean, yellow), Montpellier (Mediterranean, orange), and Guardamar del Segura (semi-arid, red).</title><p>On the left are pictures of the three focal species included in the study. The right panels show the mean air temperature and VPD within each shading infrastructure from April to October 2022 and 2023. At the bottom right is a picture showing the shading infrastructure.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS207548-f001"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><title>Assimilation-temperature response curves for the summer months (mean of May-October) of both years (2022-2023) for <italic>T. fortunei, I. aquifolium</italic>, and <italic>T. cordata</italic> at the five experimental sites (indicated with colors from blue to red going from the coldest to the warmest).</title><p>On the right panels, the mean and standard errors of A<sub>opt</sub>, T<sub>opt</sub>, and T<sub>80</sub> at each site are shown (n = 4-10 individuals per species). Different letters indicate significative differences (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05) between sites for each species.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS207548-f002"/></fig><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><title>A<sub>opt</sub> and T<sub>opt</sub> (n = 4-10 individuals per species) averaged by campaigns in relation to air temperature of the two weeks preceding the measurements for <italic>T. fortunei, I. aquifolium</italic>, and <italic>T. cordata</italic>.</title><p>Colors represent climates from blue to red, from the coldest to the warmest. Linear regression lines were added when significant.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS207548-f003"/></fig><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><title>Assimilation at the optimal temperature (A<sub>opt</sub>) in function of the optimal temperature of photosynthesis (T<sub>opt</sub>) (n = 4-10 individuals per species) in <italic>T. fortunei, I. aquifolium</italic>, and <italic>T. cordata</italic> during all campaigns in 2022 and 2023.</title><p>Colors represent sites from blue to red, from the coldest to the warmest. Linear regression lines were added when significant.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS207548-f004"/></fig><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><title>Respiration-temperature response curves for the summer months (mean of May-October) of both years (2022-2023) for <italic>T. fortunei, I. aquifolium</italic>, and <italic>T. cordata</italic> at the five experimental sites (indicated with colors from blue to red, from the coldest to the warmest).</title><p>The right panels show the mean and standard errors of R<sub>25</sub> and Q<sub>10</sub> at each site (n = 4-10 individuals per species). Different letters indicate significant differences (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05) between the sites.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS207548-f005"/></fig><fig id="F6" position="float"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><title>R<sub>25</sub> and Q<sub>10</sub> (n = 4-10 individuals per species) averaged by campaigns in relation to the air temperature of the two weeks preceding the measurements for <italic>T. fortunei, I. aquifolium</italic>, and <italic>T. cordata</italic>.</title><p>Colors represent sites from blue to red, from the coldest to the warmest. Linear regression lines were added when significant.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS207548-f006"/></fig><fig id="F7" position="float"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><title>Daily mean leaf-level C budget in <italic>T. fortunei, I. aquifolium</italic>, and <italic>T. cordata</italic> at the five experimental sites from 15<sup>th</sup> October 2022 to 15<sup>th</sup> October 2023.</title><p>The right panels show the annual leaf-level C uptake for each site over the same period. Net assimilation corresponds to the plain bar, whereas respiration is dashed. Error bars indicate the uncertainty of J<sub>max,25</sub>, V<sub>Cmax,25</sub>, R<sub>25</sub>, and Q<sub>10</sub> (n = 37–57). Different letters indicate significant differences (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05) between the sites.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS207548-f007"/></fig><fig id="F8" position="float"><label>Fig. 8</label><caption><title>Differences between the modeled annual leaf-level C uptake (ΔA<sub>net</sub>) at every site and the reference site (sub-Mediterranean).</title><p>Positive values indicate higher annual leaf-level C uptake in the respective sites compared to the reference one. For each site, the lighter bars show results obtained with non-acclimated physiological traits (<italic>i.e</italic>., the traits from the reference site), while the darker bars correspond to the outputs of the model with acclimated physiology. Error bars indicate the uncertainty of modeled J<sub>max,25</sub> and V<sub>Cmax,25</sub>, R<sub>25</sub>, and Q<sub>10</sub> (n = 37–57). Significant differences between acclimated and non-acclimated simulations are represented with stars (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05 = *; <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01 = **; <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001 = ***).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS207548-f008"/></fig><table-wrap id="T1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Location of the experimental sites and associated climatic conditions.</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="middle" align="left" style="border-top:solid 1px #ffffff">Experimental site</th><th valign="middle" align="center" style="border-top:solid 1px #ffffff;border-left: 1px solid #000000">Filisur<break/>(CH)</th><th valign="middle" align="center" style="border-top:solid 1px #ffffff;border-left: 1px solid #000000">Birmensdorf<break/>(CH)</th><th valign="middle" align="center" style="border-top:solid 1px #ffffff;border-left: 1px solid #000000">Cadenazzo<break/>(CH)</th><th valign="middle" align="center" style="border-top:solid 1px #ffffff;border-left: 1px solid #000000">Montpellier<break/>(FR)</th><th valign="middle" align="center" style="border-top:solid 1px #ffffff;border-left: 1px solid #000000">Guardamar del<break/>Segura (ES)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="middle" align="left" style="border-top:double 2px #000000">Climate</td><td valign="middle" align="center" style="border-top:double 2px #000000;border-left:solid 1px #000000">Cold</td><td valign="middle" align="center" style="border-top:double 2px #000000;border-left:solid 1px #000000">Temperate</td><td valign="middle" align="center" style="border-top:double 2px #000000;border-left:solid 1px #000000">Sub-<break/>Mediterranean</td><td valign="middle" align="center" style="border-top:double 2px #000000;border-left:solid 1px #000000">Mediterranean</td><td valign="middle" align="center" style="border-top:double 2px #000000;border-left:solid 1px #000000">Semi-arid</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left">Location</td><td valign="middle" align="center" style="border-left:solid 1px #000000">46°40’13.0“N<break/>9°40’06.6”E</td><td valign="middle" align="center" style="border-left:solid 1px #000000">47°21 ’41.6“N<break/>8°27’21.5”E</td><td valign="middle" align="center" style="border-left:solid 1px #000000">46°09’38.2“N<break/>8°56’00.9”E</td><td valign="middle" align="center" style="border-left:solid 1px #000000">43°38’19.2“N<break/>3°51’41.1”E</td><td valign="middle" align="center" style="border-left:solid 1px #000000">38°05’46.2“N<break/>0°38’51.7”W</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left">Altitude [m a.s.l.]</td><td valign="middle" align="center" style="border-left:solid 1px #000000">965</td><td valign="middle" align="center" style="border-left:solid 1px #000000">540</td><td valign="middle" align="center" style="border-left:solid 1px #000000">203</td><td valign="middle" align="center" style="border-left:solid 1px #000000">57</td><td valign="middle" align="center" style="border-left:solid 1px #000000">1</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left">MAT<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFN1">*</xref> 2010-2020 [°C]</td><td valign="middle" align="center" style="border-left:solid 1px #000000">8.4</td><td valign="middle" align="center" style="border-left:solid 1px #000000">12.0</td><td valign="middle" align="center" style="border-left:solid 1px #000000">12.3</td><td valign="middle" align="center" style="border-left:solid 1px #000000">15.8</td><td valign="middle" align="center" style="border-left:solid 1px #000000">18.7</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left" style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000">T<sub>air</sub><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFN1">*</xref> April-October 2010-2020 [°C]</td><td valign="middle" align="center" style="border-left:solid 1px #000000;border-bottom:solid 1px #000000">12.6</td><td valign="middle" align="center" style="border-left:solid 1px #000000;border-bottom:solid 1px #000000">16.5</td><td valign="middle" align="center" style="border-left:solid 1px #000000;border-bottom:solid 1px #000000">17.7</td><td valign="middle" align="center" style="border-left:solid 1px #000000;border-bottom:solid 1px #000000">20.1</td><td valign="middle" align="center" style="border-left:solid 1px #000000;border-bottom:solid 1px #000000">22.5</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TFN1"><label>*</label><p id="P39">MAT = mean annual temperature; T<sub>air</sub> = air temperature</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></floats-group></article>