<!DOCTYPE article
 PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" article-type="preprint"><?all-math-mml yes?><?use-mml?><?origin ukpmcpa?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">bioRxiv</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>bioRxiv : the preprint server for biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2692-8205</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">EMS205888</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2025.05.20.655023</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="archive">PPR1026015</article-id><article-version-alternatives><article-version article-version-type="status">preprint</article-version><article-version article-version-type="number">1</article-version></article-version-alternatives><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Diverse behavioural responses of vampire bats to human disturbance revealed by state-space modelling of sparse GPS data</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Ribeiro</surname><given-names>Rita</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zariquiey</surname><given-names>Carlos M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chavez</surname><given-names>Wendi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>Kristhie Pillaca</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Manuttupa</surname><given-names>Joaquin Clavijo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Huiman</surname><given-names>Marco Antonio Risco</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Villafuerte</surname><given-names>Roselvira Zuniga</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A6">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Quintanilla</surname><given-names>Walter Campana</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Medrano-Uchuya</surname><given-names>Noelia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>French</surname><given-names>Hollie</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Czyzewski</surname><given-names>Jakub</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A7">7</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shiva</surname><given-names>Carlos</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A8">8</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Falcon</surname><given-names>Nestor</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A8">8</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Valderrama</surname><given-names>William</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A8">8</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>Daniel P.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A9">9</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rocke</surname><given-names>Tonie E.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A10">10</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Matthiopoulos</surname><given-names>Jason</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN1">#</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Streicker</surname><given-names>Daniel G.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN1">#</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1"><label>1</label>School of Biodiversity, One Health and Veterinary Medicine, College of Medical, Veterinary and Life Sciences, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/00vtgdb53</institution-id><institution>University of Glasgow</institution></institution-wrap>, <city>Glasgow</city>, <country country="GB">UK</country></aff><aff id="A2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/03x94j517</institution-id><institution>Medical Research Council</institution></institution-wrap>, Centre for Virus Research, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/00vtgdb53</institution-id><institution>University of Glasgow</institution></institution-wrap>, <city>Glasgow</city>, <country country="GB">UK</country></aff><aff id="A3"><label>3</label>Facultad de Salud Pública y Administración, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/03yczjf25</institution-id><institution>Universidad Peruana Cayetano Heredia</institution></institution-wrap>, <city>Lima</city>, <country country="PE">Perú</country></aff><aff id="A4"><label>4</label>ILLARIY (Asociación para el Desarrollo y Conservación de los Recursos Naturales), Lima, Perú</aff><aff id="A5"><label>5</label>Escuela Profesional de Ciencias Biológicas. Facultad de Ciencias, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/031vfrf75</institution-id><institution>Universidad Nacional de Piura</institution></institution-wrap>, <city>Piura</city>, <country country="PE">Perú</country></aff><aff id="A6"><label>6</label>Centro de Investigación Vertebrate, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/03gsd6w61</institution-id><institution>Universidad Nacional San Antonio Abad del Cusco</institution></institution-wrap>, <city>Cusco</city>, <country country="PE">Perú</country></aff><aff id="A7"><label>7</label>School of Biodiversity, One Health and Veterinary Medicine, BioElectronics Unit, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/00vtgdb53</institution-id><institution>University of Glasgow</institution></institution-wrap>, <city>Glasgow</city>, <country country="GB">UK</country></aff><aff id="A8"><label>8</label>Facultad de Medicina Veterinaria y Zootecnia, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/03yczjf25</institution-id><institution>Universidad Peruana Cayetano Heredia</institution></institution-wrap>, <city>Lima</city>, <country country="PE">Perú</country></aff><aff id="A9"><label>9</label>U.S. Geological Survey, Montana Cooperative Wildlife Research Unit, Wildlife Biology Program, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/0078xmk34</institution-id><institution>University of Montana</institution></institution-wrap>, <city>Missoula</city>, <state>Montana</state>, <country country="US">USA</country></aff><aff id="A10"><label>10</label>U.S. Geological Survey, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/038d10y34</institution-id><institution>National Wildlife Health Center</institution></institution-wrap>, <city>Madison</city>, <state>Wisconsin</state>, <country country="US">USA</country></aff><author-notes><corresp id="CR1"><bold>Correspondence:</bold> Rita Ribeiro, SBOHVM, College of Medical, Veterinary &amp; Life Sciences, Graham Kerr Building, University of Glasgow, Glasgow G12 8QQ, <email>ritaclaudia.cardosoribeiro@glasgow.ac.uk</email></corresp><fn id="FN1"><label>#</label><p id="P1">Joint Senior Authors</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted"><day>27</day><month>05</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="preprint"><day>25</day><month>05</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><permissions><ali:free_to_read/><license><ali:license_ref>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is licensed under a <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0 International license</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p id="P2"><list list-type="order" id="L1"><list-item><p id="P3">Human activities can alter animal movement, having unexpected consequences for disease transmission. In Latin America, culls of common vampire bats (<italic>Desmodus rotundus</italic>) for rabies control have been indicated to raise viral spatial spread by increasing long-range movement and inter-colony mixing among surviving bats, but behavioural responses to disturbance have not been quantified.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P4">We used Global Positioning System (GPS) tags to track the movements of 93 vampire bats from 5 roosts in the Peruvian Andes over 9 nights after human disturbance (capture, handling and tag attachment). Responses to disturbance were modelled under a Bayesian state-space framework that estimated bat departure time, activity duration, and travel distances while accounting for the sparse GPS data obtainable in a topographically complex landscape where vampire bats occur.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P5">A large fraction of bats (43%, 39/90) abandoned the study area on the night of disturbance, with more abandonment observed in groups expected to have greater dispersal capacity (males and bats with longer forearms). Among the remaining bats, we observed high individual heterogeneity on the night of disturbance, with some bats staying atypically close to the roost and others travelling unusually long distances. With increasing time post-disturbance, bats tended to remain closer to the roost.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P6">Analysis of inferred flight histories showed that bats travelled &gt;5 km on most nights, with high variability both within individuals across nights and between individuals in the same roost.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P7">By inferring movement from irregular and error-prone data, our model extends the utility of animal-borne GPS tracking to landscapes with poor satellite visibility, revealing greater complexity in vampire bat movement than previously recognised. Vampire bat disturbance was associated with three distinct behavioural responses: roost abandonment, increased flight distances and extreme individual heterogeneity on the night of disturbance. In the context of vampire bat management, such perturbations would be expected to exacerbate the spatial spread of rabies and potentially undermine the efficacy of culling activities which are currently practiced by most Latin American governments.</p></list-item></list></p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Bayesian integrated model</kwd><kwd>disease control measures</kwd><kwd>JAGS</kwd><kwd>perturbation effect</kwd><kwd>travel distance</kwd><kwd>wildlife management</kwd><kwd>wildlife telemetry</kwd><kwd>zoonoses</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="S1" sec-type="intro"><label>1</label><title>Introduction</title><p id="P8">Human-induced changes in animal movement can influence disease dynamics and increase spillover risk to humans or domestic animals by forcing the mixing of infected and uninfected populations, potentially increasing the incidence and spatial extent of pathogens (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">Blackwood et al., 2013</xref>). For example, in Brazil, urbanization and habitat loss forced non-human primates into cities potentially increasing human exposure to yellow fever virus (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">Couto-Lima et al., 2017</xref>). In Europe, badger culling for managing bovine tuberculosis increased survivors’ ranging and dispersal behaviours, likely explaining increased tuberculosis risk in cattle outside of culled areas (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">Ham et al., 2019</xref>). Independently, disturbance may induce chronic stressors that diminish immunity and increase infection rate and intensity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">Becker et al., 2018</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42">Seltmann et al., 2017</xref>).</p><p id="P9">Bats are important reservoirs of zoonotic viruses including Nipah virus (Paramyxoviridae, <italic>Henipavirus nipahense</italic>), Hendra virus (Paramyxoviridae, <italic>Henipavirus hendraense</italic>), Marburg virus (Filoviridae, Orthomarburgvirus), and various Lyssaviruses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">Calisher et al., 2006</xref>). The high mobility of bats arising from their capacity for flight, together with their high sensitivity to human disturbance - including occasional, deliberate human persecution - may inadvertently increase human disease risk (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32">O’Shea et al., 2016</xref>). Indeed, bat disturbance has been linked to increases in the spread or incidence of both rabies virus and Marburg virus (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">Amman et al., 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R46">Streicker et al., 2012</xref>). Despite the potential links between zoonotic risk and bat movement, few studies have quantified how human disturbance affects bat movement, likely due to challenges posed by bats’ cryptic lifestyles and small size, which restricts available tracking technologies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31">O’Mara et al., 2014</xref>). One study using radiotelemetry revealed that disturbance from removal of big brown bats (<italic>Eptesicus fuscus</italic>) from houses induced roost switching, potentially exacerbating rabies virus transmission (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R45">Streicker et al., 2013</xref>). Another study using Global Positioning System (GPS) tags in straw-coloured fruit bats (<italic>Eidolon helvum</italic>) showed that disturbance from human capture led to increased daytime movements (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">Costa et al., 2020</xref>). While these studies suggest that human disturbance can affect bat behaviour, reactions and intensity of responses may vary across species and types of disturbance.</p><p id="P10">In Latin America, <italic>Desmodus rotundus</italic> (the common vampire bat) is the main reservoir of rabies virus (Rhabdoviridae, Lyssavirus), which causes sporadic lethal outbreaks in humans and a sustained agricultural burden through livestock mortality (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41">Schneider et al., 2009</xref>). This species is routinely disturbed during campaigns aimed at controlling vampire bat-transmitted rabies (VBR). Sanctioned population control (culling) uses anticoagulant poisons (‘vampiricides’) that can be topically applied to bats or injected into livestock for later consumption by bats during blood feeding (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R53">World Health Organization, 2018</xref>). However, unsanctioned efforts to reduce vampire bat populations are common and include direct killing of captured bats and destruction, sealing or burning of roosts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32">O’Shea et al., 2016</xref>). Despite decades of culling, high VBR burdens persist in enzootic areas and spatiotemporal analyses show viral expansions into historically rabies-free regions of Latin America (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">Benavides et al., 2016</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40">Rojas-Sereno et al., 2022</xref>). Epidemiological models explaining the limited efficacy of culls indicated that increased bat mixing after disturbance could raise VBR incidence and local spillovers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">Blackwood et al., 2013</xref>). Consistent with this idea, evaluation of a large culling campaign in Peru showed that culling did not limit rabies spillover to livestock, and culling in response to livestock rabies cases (reactive culling) increased viral spatial spread, an effect that was hypothesized to arise from increased movement of rabies-incubating bats (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R51">Viana et al., 2023</xref>). While these observational studies suggest that culling affects bat movement with downstream repercussions for rabies transmission, the behavioural responses of vampire bats to disturbance remains unexplored.</p><p id="P11">Directly measuring the fine-scale behavioural response of vampire bats to human disturbances is hampered by technical and ecological challenges. In mark-recapture studies, low between-roost recapture rates limit inference on movement (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">Britzke et al., 2014</xref>). Very High Frequency (VHF)-radio tracking has also been applied, but it is labour-intensive, error-prone and only detects animal presence in close proximity to antennas (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R49">Thomas et al., 2011</xref>). Use in vampire bats has thus been limited to coarse-scale studies at foraging sites and identification of unknown roosts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39">Rocha et al., 2020</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R46">Streicker et al., 2012</xref>). Recent advances in GPS allow for the monitoring of animal movements at high spatial and temporal resolutions with lightweight tags equipped for remote data recovery, making them suitable for small animals such as bats (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">Kays et al., 2015</xref>). However, the reliance of GPS on satellite visibility introduces challenges in complex landscapes, including highly mountainous or densely forested areas. Indeed, to our knowledge, no GPS study on vampire bats has been reported.</p><p id="P12">Here, we used lightweight GPS tags to assess fine-scale movement of vampire bats in the Peruvian Andes in response to human disturbance, developing a new method to reconstruct movement despite the sparse and error-prone data expected from the obstructive local topography. We jointly reconstructed and identified ecological correlates of two fundamental metrics of movement: nightly departure time and distance from the roost at different times of the night. We hypothesised that bats would leave the roost under conditions of darkness at night, and that disturbance from capture, handling, and tagging, would induce roost abandonment and longer flights.</p></sec><sec id="S2" sec-type="materials | methods"><label>2</label><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="S3"><label>2.1</label><title>Study area and design</title><p id="P13">The study was conducted between April 2022 and June 2023 in 5 vampire bat roosts, located &gt;51.6 km apart (range 51.6-186 km). Roosts are in a region in southern Peru (departments of Ayacucho, Apurimac, and Cusco, AAC), that is characterised by rugged topography, with altitudes ranging from 1200 to 6000 meters (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1a</xref>). AAC is a hotspot of rabies in Peru, accounting for 60.2% of all reported livestock cases between 2003 and 2019, and this region is subjected to regular bat culls (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R51">Viana et al., 2023</xref>). Vampire bats live below 3600 meters, roosting predominantly in natural caves, abandoned houses, mines, and irrigation canals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">Benavides et al., 2016</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">2020</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S4"><label>2.2</label><title>Data collection</title><p id="P14">Vampire bats were captured and handled under approved ethics protocols (University of Glasgow, EA28a/21) and permits from local authorities, including SERFOR (Servicio Nacional Forestal y de Fauna Silvestre, Nos. D000024-2022, D000107-2022, D000103-2024 and D000188-2024-MIDAGRI-SERFOR-DGGSPFFS-DGSPFS) and SERNANP (Servicio Nacional de Áreas Naturales Protegidas por el Estado, N° 021-2023-SERNANP-SHM/J).</p><p id="P15">Two capture and tagging sessions per roost were carried out from April to October (the Peruvian dry season), with at least three months between sessions. Roost 2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1c</xref>) had only one tagging session due to data recovery challenges. Each session aimed to tag 10 adult vampire bats (5 males, 5 females). All capture sessions began after dusk, except the first capture in April 2022, when due to logistical constraints, captures began in the morning. Vampire bats were captured using mist and butterfly nets. Captured bats were fit with a 3.5 mm wing ring (Porzana, UK), and weight (g), sex, reproductive status (non-reproductive, scrotal male, pregnant, or lactating female), age (adult, subadult, or juvenile), and forearm length (mm) were recorded. We applied lightweight GPS tags (2.8 g, 8 cm length [including a 5 cm antenna]; nanoFix®, PathTrack, UK) to bats that met specific inclusion criteria (see below). After light sedation using intramuscular (pectoral) injection (29-gauge needle, 1.0 mL syringe) of Ketamine (20–25 mg/kg) diluted in saline (NaCl) at a 50/50 volume ratio or Midazolam (0.25 mg/kg, used in 2023 to allow faster recovery times), GPS tags were attached to the skin of the dorsal side of each bat using an absorbable suture (Monosyn®, B Braun), threaded through custom tag loops (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">Castle et al., 2015</xref>). According to the manufacturer, the absorbable sutures lose 50% of their strength after 14 days, allowing natural tag detachment. Prior to suturing, hair was trimmed, and a small amount of cyanoacrylate-based glue was used to secure the tags. Sedation and tag suturing were carried out by a veterinarian, ensuring it didn’t impair flight or walking. GPS tags were painted with UV fluorescent paint to aid in recovery for reuse (Starglow®, Glowtec, UK).</p><p id="P16">GPS tagging was limited to healthy adult bats, excluding pregnant and lactating females. The average weight of tagged bats was 43.4 g (± 3.4 g, N=93), so the tags represented a maximum of 7% of the bat’s weight (mean = 6.5 ± 0.48%, N=93). Recommendations for bat tracking studies indicate that attached devices should not exceed 10% of body mass, with a best practice of limiting to 5%. However, heavier tags are acceptable for short-term use in some species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">Aldridge &amp; Brigham, 1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31">O’Mara et al., 2014</xref>). From our prior fieldwork, adult vampire bats (N=3,429) weigh, on average 41.9 g (± 8.44, N=2,751) and 51.5 g (± 9.1, N=678) after feeding, indicating nightly weight gains of over 9 g. Additionally, during pregnancy and after birth, females can weigh over 85 g and continue foraging. These observations indicate that the tags would be tolerable for short-term use.</p><p id="P17">During the initial deployment in April 2022, GPS tags were programmed to record locations every 5 minutes (10 tags) or 10 minutes (5 tags) for 3 and 6 nights, respectively. To extend tracking duration, later deployments used a 15-minute interval for 9 nights. Our model (see below) considered this difference between deployments and reconstructed distances from the roost every 15 minutes. Tags operated nightly from 6 PM to 6 AM, with data stored onboard and downloaded remotely via one or two solar-powered UHF base stations (PathTrack, UK) placed near the roost.</p></sec><sec id="S5"><label>2.3</label><title>Data cleaning</title><p id="P18">Data cleaning was performed in R version 4.4.0 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36">R Core Team, 2024</xref>). The nanoFix GPS tags require at least 4 visible satellites to record a position (‘fix’). The number of visible satellites, along with an accuracy indicator for high satellite counts, determines the positional accuracy. Due to the complex topography of the Peruvian Andes, most GPS points were missing since &lt;4 satellites were in range at the attempted connection time, resulting in a sparse and irregular dataset that required the model framework outlined below to reconstruct movement.</p><p id="P19">GPS fixes recorded before tag application and 1 hour after capture were removed to account for the tag attachment process. Data from the first night were otherwise included because quantifying the disturbance immediately after capture was one of our objectives. Cleaning of the remained data excluded: one inaccurate fix (6 satellites connected, but accuracy indicator &gt;30, considered unreliable), all fixes from one bat with a malfunctioning tag (distances up to 6 km recorded before attachment), all data from 3 bats with &lt;3 fixes across the study period, and all data from an unrealistically sessile bat (suggesting tag loss or death). As detailed in the supplementary information, we also removed GPS fix jumps, and outliers of estimated flight speed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">Gupte et al., 2022</xref>). The speed (km/hour) of each segment between subsequent fixes was calculated, along with the Euclidean distance from the roost for each fix, using base R and the sf package (v1.0-19) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33">Pebesma, 2018</xref>). Our state-space model was designed to be robust to GPS errors, so we could have omitted data filtering based on speed entirely. However, we anticipated that simultaneously inferring and filtering speed within the model could hinder convergence.</p><sec id="S6"><label>2.3.1</label><title>Variable definition and processing</title><p id="P20">We investigated predictors of bats’ nightly departure time and distance travelled from the roost. Vampire bats are thought to be lunar phobic, departing before moonrise or after moonset (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">Crespo et al., 1972</xref>). We therefore modelled departure time as a function of the number of hours until complete darkness, which depended on the interplay of moonrise, moonset, astronomical night start (occurs after sunset and dusk) and end (occurs before dawn). For each roost and night, we calculated the hours from sunset until darkness using the <italic>suncalc</italic> package (v0.5.1) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R48">Thieurmel &amp; Elmarhraoui, 2022</xref>). We predicted that longer periods until darkness delay departure times. We also hypothesised that sex influences departure time, as female vampire bats, which maintain cooperative relationships that include behaviours such as visiting other roosts, might leave earlier in the night (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38">Ripperger &amp; Carter, 2021</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R52">Wilkinson, 1985</xref>).</p><p id="P21">Distance from the roost was modelled with variables related to roost location, individual bat characteristics, and human disturbance (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table S1</xref>). Roost-related variables within 5 km radii of roosts included proportion of permanent water, predicted vampire bat roost density (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37">Ribeiro et al., 2023</xref>) and cattle density (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">Greenhall et al., 1983</xref>), calculated using the packages <italic>sf</italic> (v1.0-19) and <italic>terra</italic> (v1.7-71) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">Hijmans, 2024</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33">Pebesma, 2018</xref>). We predicted that the availability of alternative roosts and preferred food sources (cattle) near the roost would reduce the distance bats travel. Since cattle graze near water and vampire bats can use rivers as corridors, we hypothesized that permanent water sources near roosts could aid prey searching, decreasing distances from the roost (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">Mialhe, 2013</xref>). Individual characteristics included bat sex and forearm length. We hypothesised that males would fly further distances due to reduced offspring care (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">Delpietro et al., 2017</xref>). As flight speed is correlated with forearm length, we expected a positive effect of bat forearm length on distance from the roost (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">Hopkins et al., 2003</xref>).</p><p id="P22">Human disturbance was defined as the effects of capture, handling, and tagging, with key variables being the night of capture (‘night 0’) versus subsequent nights, and the time (in hours) post-disturbance, calculated as the difference between the start of the tracking session and each GPS fix. We averaged time post-disturbance per bat and night to summarise nightly patterns, while reducing the effect of the irregular GPS fix intervals and potential autocorrelation. This also aligns with our model structure, which accounts for individual, roost and night effects. We anticipated that disturbance would increase flight distance following capture, with distances decreasing over time as behaviour normalised. Finally, because vampire bats in our study area are deliberately or accidentally disturbed by humans (e.g., capture, culling, roost destruction or shifts in agricultural practices), we also included a variable describing the number of rural human settlements within 5 km of each roost as a proxy for historical disturbance levels.</p></sec><sec id="S7"><label>2.3.2</label><title>Modelling framework</title><p id="P23">We developed a Bayesian state-space model with two latent variables: the bats’ departure time (<italic>t</italic>, in minutes since the daily activation of the GPS at 6 PM) and its distance from the roost (<italic>ψ</italic>, in km). The model reconstructed distances from the roost every 15 minutes and estimated the duration of activity and return time to the roost, accounting for both process error (i.e., the natural stochasticity in the biological processes) and observation error (i.e., GPS measurement error). The model assumed nightly returns to the roost.</p><p id="P24">Although our data indicated that returns occurred on at least 56.6% of bats and nights, this is likely a conservative estimate due to data limitations – including missed fixes during 15-minute intervals when bats departed or returned quickly, and signal loss at the roost – potentially leading to underestimation of return rates. We also assumed that most bats would depart before 1 AM, as our experiments were conducted on nights when the moon set before 1 AM in 95% of cases.</p><p id="P25">For each individual bat <italic>i</italic> and night <italic>j, t<sub>i,j</sub></italic> is the departure time in minutes after 6 PM, with a maximum value of 420 minutes (1 AM). The expected and realised departure instances, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M1"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mtext>τ</mml:mtext><mml:mo>¯</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <italic>τ<sub>i,j</sub></italic>, are expressed as a proportion of the interval between 6 PM and 1 AM, <disp-formula id="FD1"><label>(1)</label><mml:math id="M2"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>τ</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>420</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula> <disp-formula id="FD2"><label>(2)</label><mml:math id="M3"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>420</mml:mn><mml:msub><mml:mtext>τ</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="P26">The expected departure instance <inline-formula><mml:math id="M4"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mtext>τ</mml:mtext><mml:mo>¯</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> was modelled as a logit function of the number of hours until darkness and bat sex, <disp-formula id="FD3"><label>(3)</label><mml:math id="M5"><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mtext>τ</mml:mtext><mml:mo>¯</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>_</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mtext>+</mml:mtext><mml:msub><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mtext>2</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="P27"><italic>τ<sub>i,j</sub></italic> was modelled by a Beta distribution, with mean <inline-formula><mml:math id="M6"><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mtext>τ</mml:mtext><mml:mo>¯</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> and a process error, quantified by the standard deviation of departure instance, <italic>σ</italic> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table S2</xref>), capturing pooled inter-trip and inter-individual variation, <disp-formula id="FD4"><label>(4)</label><mml:math id="M7"><mml:msub><mml:mtext>τ</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>~</mml:mo><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:math></disp-formula> <disp-formula id="FD5"><label>(5)</label><mml:math id="M8"><mml:msub><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mtext>τ</mml:mtext><mml:mo>¯</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mtext>τ</mml:mtext><mml:mo>¯</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mtext>τ</mml:mtext><mml:mo>¯</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:math></disp-formula> <disp-formula id="FD6"><label>(6)</label><mml:math id="M9"><mml:msub><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mtext>τ</mml:mtext><mml:mo>¯</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mtext>τ</mml:mtext><mml:mo>¯</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mtext>τ</mml:mtext><mml:mo>¯</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="P28">The duration of nightly activity after departure was modelled with a uniform distribution, assuming that once a bat departed, it remained away for at least 20 minutes. The maximum duration of a trip was the time left after departing and the end of GPS activation (720 minutes), <disp-formula id="FD7"><label>(7)</label><mml:math id="M10"><mml:mtext>Δ</mml:mtext><mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>~</mml:mo><mml:mi>U</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>20</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>720</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="P29">To estimate distances travelled from the roost, we defined a parametric model of distance against time, for each individual bat <italic>i</italic>, night <italic>j</italic>, and each block <italic>k</italic> of 15 minutes after 6 PM, <disp-formula id="FD8"><label>(8)</label><mml:math id="M11"><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>ψ</mml:mi><mml:mo>¯</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>exp</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mn>15</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mtext>Δ</mml:mtext><mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mtext>τ</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Δ</mml:mtext><mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>∑</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle><mml:msub><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>ζ</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="P30">This equation assumes that only one trip is made per night and is flexible regarding the point of start, end, and maximum distance. It also assumes that the net velocity is away from the roost until the maximum distance is reached, and then toward the roost thereafter, for 15-minute intervals. The exponential of the intercept <italic>β</italic><sub>0</sub>, corresponds to the maximum distance from the roost. <italic>β<sub>i</sub></italic> corresponds to the terms for the effect of night of disturbance (<italic>night<sub>j</sub></italic>) for each bat, and <italic>B<sub>n</sub></italic> is the parameter for the n<sup>th</sup> covariate effect (forearm length, sex, roost density, number of human rural settlements, cattle density, permanent water and time post-disturbance). We added an individual-level random effect <italic>ζ<sub>i</sub></italic> with mean 0 and standard deviation <inline-formula><mml:math id="M12"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>ζ</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">N</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, to capture the influence of individual variation (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table S2</xref>). In both departure time and distance models, we considered random effects of individual, roost, calendar night, and session of capture. Only the random effect of individual on the distance model was relevant, hence it was kept.</p><p id="P31">The mid-point of the trip, <italic>τ<sub>mid,i,j</sub></italic>, was defined as the proportion of time between departure and return until reaching maximum distance, with a parameter <italic>σ<sub>mid,i,j</sub></italic>, which made sure that the distance from the roost climbed smoothly from the start of the trip to the midpoint and then declined to the trip’s endpoint, preventing unrealistic jumps in movement. <italic>τ<sub>mid,i,j</sub></italic> was given a beta prior distribution and was set to be close to the middle of the trip duration (mean 0.5 and variance 0.001). <italic>σ<sub>mid,i,j</sub></italic> was fixed to a sufficiently large value to ensure that the bats did not immediately reach their maximum distance after departure or instantaneously returned to the roost, <disp-formula id="FD9"><label>(9)</label><mml:math id="M13"><mml:msub><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>mid</mml:mtext><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>max</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>τ</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>mid</mml:mtext><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mtext>τ</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>mid</mml:mtext><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>2.</mml:mn></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="P32">The realisation of distance giving rise to observations, <italic>ψ<sub>i,j,k</sub></italic>, was modelled using a normal distribution, with mean <inline-formula><mml:math id="M14"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>ψ</mml:mi><mml:mo>¯</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and variance <italic>O<sub>i,j,k</sub></italic>, <disp-formula id="FD10"><label>(10)</label><mml:math id="M15"><mml:msub><mml:mi>ψ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>~</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="script">N</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>ψ</mml:mi><mml:mo>¯</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mtext>with</mml:mtext><mml:msub><mml:mi>ψ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>≥</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mtext>km</mml:mtext><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="P33"><italic>O<sub>i,j,k</sub></italic> is a combined error, that incorporates observation error <italic>ξ<sub>i,j,k</sub></italic>, the standard deviation of GPS error, and process error, in the form of an overdispersion parameter <italic>φ</italic>, to account for further uncertainty that cannot be explained by the observation model (i.e., 0.6 km is the GPS error for 4 satellites), <disp-formula id="FD11"><label>(11)</label><mml:math id="M16"><mml:msub><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>ξ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.6</mml:mn><mml:msup><mml:mi>φ</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="P34">The overdispersion parameter <italic>φ</italic> was estimated by the model, but we encouraged it to be close to 0 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table S2</xref>) to prioritize the identification of biological effects. Using data from a GPS tag placed at a single location in our study area, we fitted a regression of the standard deviation of distances against the number of satellites and estimated the standard deviation of GPS error for each satellite count (standard deviation of 0.3 km when 4 satellites were visible; deviance explained = 0.986). This regression produced the two parameters <italic>γ</italic><sub>0</sub> and <italic>γ</italic><sub>1</sub> which, in combination with the number of visible satellites that generated each positional fix, <italic>N<sub>i,J,k</sub></italic>, informed <italic>ξ<sub>i,J,k</sub></italic>, <disp-formula id="FD12"><label>(12)</label><mml:math id="M17"><mml:msub><mml:mi>ξ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>exp</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="P35">We used Bayesian Stochastic Search Variable Selection (SSVS) with spike and slab priors to estimate model coefficients conditional to a variable being retained in the model (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">O’Hara &amp; Sillanpää, 2009</xref>). If a variable was participating in the model, the coefficient value was given a normal distribution, with mean 0 and standard deviation <italic>τ</italic><sub>1</sub>, with <italic>τ</italic><sub>1</sub> being estimated by the model, except for the coefficient for hours until darkness, which was given a gamma prior distribution to preserve its positivity (mean 0.01 and variance 0.0001). The posterior for the probability of retention <italic>ρ</italic> was modelled with a Bernoulli distribution (variable included or excluded), with the parameter <italic>ρ</italic> being estimated by the model with a constrained Beta prior (i.e., a variable has a 25% probability of being included), meaning that variables need strong evidence to be included.</p><p id="P36">To assess goodness of fit, we calculated the R<sup>2</sup> by comparing the observed and predicted distances from the roost. The models were fitted in JAGS 4.3.2 using rjags (v4-15) and runjags (v2.2.2-4) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">Denwood &amp; Plummer, 2024</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34">Plummer, 2023</xref>). The model ran with four independent chains, for 10,000 samples per chain after discarding the first 500,000 interactions as burn-in, with thinning of 200 (retaining every 200<sup>th</sup> iteration). Convergence across chains was assessed through visual inspections of the posterior and the Gelman-Rubin diagnostic test (using coda (v0.19-4.1) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35">Plummer et al., 2006</xref>)). <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table S2</xref> lists the final model parameter priors and posteriors.</p><sec id="S8"><label>2.3.2.1</label><title>Drivers of roost abandonment</title><p id="P37">We fitted binomial generalised linear models (GLM) to examine whether roost abandonment was associated with bat individual traits (sex, forearm length, and weight), hypothesising that stronger bats (i.e., males, heavier, and bats with longer forearms) would be less likely to return. Model performance was compared across six models using the Akaike information criterion (AIC) and pseudo-R<sup>2</sup>.</p></sec></sec></sec></sec><sec id="S9" sec-type="results"><label>3</label><title>Results</title><p id="P38">Between April 2022 and June 2023, 93 adult vampire bats were GPS tagged across 5 roosts in southern Peru (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table S3</xref>). Twenty-four percent of tags (20/83) were recovered after use, most of them found inside roosts, allowing partial redeployment. Among the 60 bats with recovered GPS data, 89% of possible observations (14,142 out of 15,842) were not recorded due to having &lt;4 visible satellites, leaving a total of 1700 GPS fixes. The night of capture (‘night 0’) had the most fixes (24.7%), followed by ‘night 1’ after capture (18.2%), ‘night 2’ (17.9%), ‘night 3’ (14.1%), ‘night 4’ (11.1%), ‘night 5’ (7.7%), ‘night 6’ (4.5%), ‘night 7’ (1.2%) and ‘night 8’ (0.6%). Data cleaning excluded a further 22.3% of the fixes, leaving 1321 fixes from 55 bats (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S1</xref>). Visualization of the GPS data showed that vampire bats occasionally flew to distances &gt;5km from the roost but spent most time near roosts (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1b-f</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig.S2</xref>). Individual bats from the same roost foraged in different areas, did not visit the same locations every night, and used a variety of flight paths, highlighting great behavioural variation among and within individuals (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1b, d, e, f</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S3d, e</xref>).</p><p id="P39">Filtering out 3 bats which were confirmed dead, we recovered no GPS data from 30 bats and 9 additional bats were not detected after night 0, indicating the possibility that 43% (39/90) of bats abandoned our study areas following our capture and tagging effort. While we cannot rule out tag loss or death of these missing animals in unobservable locations within our study area, recapture data point to long- or medium-term roost abandonment. Of the 51 bats which returned to the roost according to GPS records, 15.7% were recaptured during capture sessions immediately following the tracking period. In contrast, of the 39 missing bats, we recaptured only 1 bat (2.6%) from roost 2 (where we faced challenges in recovering data), while none from other roosts were recaptured. As missing bats would be expected to have similar recapture rates if their apparent disappearance from the study area was an artefact of GPS tag loss or failure, we would have expected at least 6 recaptures. Moreover, during surveys conducted between 4-32 months after GPS tagging, 5 of the missing bats (12.8%) were recaptured. Comparable long-term recapture rates between bats that disappeared from the study area and those that remained argue against disappearance being due to mortality.</p><p id="P40">A binomial GLM revealed that roost abandonment was non-random and consistent with expectations of vampire bat dispersal biology. Bats with longer forearms (-0.96 [SE = 0.35], P&lt;0.01) and male bats (-1.11 [SE = 0.66], P=0.09) were less likely to return to the roost, although there was only weak evidence for the latter effect (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table S4; Fig. S4</xref>). These findings strongly support considerable short-term roost abandonment by vampire bats following disturbance. Complementing this, the GPS data also revealed high variation in movement on the night of disturbance across all roosts except roost 2, which had data from only one bat (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S5</xref>).</p><p id="P41">By fitting a Bayesian state-space model to the GPS data, we explored correlates of departure time and maximum nightly distance from the roost. The model gave a good fit to the data with an R<sup>2</sup> of 0.80 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S6</xref>), estimating that bats typically departed ~2 hours after the GPS started at 6 PM (posterior mean of 124 minutes, 95% credible interval (CI) [58.3; 220.5]) and were out of the roost for &lt;6 hours (345 minutes, 95% CI [190.0; 497.4]) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S7</xref>). The number of hours until darkness had a small but significant effect on departure time, with bats leaving the roost as soon as there was no sunlight or moonlight (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3a</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table S5</xref>). Our model, which reconstructs the movement curve for each bat, filling gaps due to missing observations, predicted larger distances from the roost compared to observed data (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig 3c-d</xref>). Within the distance component of the model, time post-disturbance had a negative effect on maximum nightly distance travelled from the roost (retention probability [P]=0.95) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3a, d</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table S5; Figs. S8-S9</xref>). This result indicates that bats tended to fly further away after disturbance but then returned to their baseline distances, with a decrease in maximum nightly distance of 0.17 km per night (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S8</xref>). The interaction between bat and night highlighted high heterogeneity among individuals, particularly on the night of the disturbance, when some bats stayed unusually close to the roost and others undertook the longest movements recorded in the study period (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs. 3b</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table S6; Figs. S10-S11</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S10" sec-type="discussion"><label>4</label><title>Discussion</title><p id="P42">Behavioural responses of wildlife to human disturbances can undermine efforts to prevent disease spillover but fine-scale studies are currently restricted to relatively large-bodied species and in simple habitats. By developing a Bayesian state-space model to reconstruct movement histories from sparse and error-prone GPS data from 93 vampire bats in the Peruvian Andes, we identified three behavioural responses to human disturbance which could exacerbate rabies transmission and dilute the effectiveness of bat population control efforts seeking to prevent bat bites and rabies spillover.</p><p id="P43">First, we found that 43% of the GPS-tagged bats appeared to abandon the roost, an effect that was unlikely to be explained by bat mortality or GPS failure. Since return to the vicinity of the roost at any point in the study would have triggered data upload to our receivers, we believe this indicates that bats left the study area, at least for the 9-day duration of the study, though their destination is unknown. Given that vampire bat dispersal is generally male-biased and that forearm length is linked to flight ability, the finding of putatively stronger flyers more frequently disappearing after tagging further supports transient roost abandonment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">Delpietro et al., 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R47">Streicker et al., 2016</xref>). Although we cannot rule out the possibility that tags detached in areas with poor satellite coverage, the small number of stationary tags detected, and the absence of GPS fixes prior to this putative detachment makes this explanation unlikely. We observed two other behavioural responses among bats that remained detectable: a general tendency for longer distance movements after disturbance and elevated individual heterogeneity on the night of capture.</p><p id="P44">Collectively, these three perturbations could have unintended consequences for both the transmission and management of VBR. Roost switching following the application of vampiricide poison would dilute local population reduction and may potentially disperse bats to lower density roosts or roosts where bats have fewer social connections, reducing the efficiency of poison transfer. Similarly, increased dispersal of rabies-positive vampire bats following disturbance is predicted to raise rabies incidence in bats from nearby roosts, potentially explaining findings why reactive culls increased livestock rabies risk in adjacent areas (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">Blackwood et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R51">Viana et al., 2023</xref>). Since viral spatial spread is believed to be strongly influenced by male bat movement, the tendency for male bats to abandon roosts after capture would be particularly problematic (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R47">Streicker et al., 2016</xref>). For future research, the effects of disturbance that we report are consistent with those from other mammals, indicating that studies seeking to understand the natural, post-disturbance behaviour of vampire bats using GPS tags should delay data recording for 4 nights (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43">Stiegler et al., 2024</xref>).</p><p id="P45">A caveat when drawing conclusions about culling is that our study measured the effects of a relatively mild disturbance. While our disturbance shares similarities with culling - capture, handling, the application of a foreign object, and release - there are key differences. Vampire bats have strong cooperative networks, characterised by blood meal sharing and intense allogrooming, which could be disrupted by the sickness behaviours and mortality associated with poisoning (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">Carter &amp; Leffer, 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38">Ripperger &amp; Carter, 2021</xref>). As such, culls may lead to stronger effects on movement than the relatively mild disturbance we induced. Capture locations may also vary between our study and real-world management. While we carried out captures in roosts for greater tractability, this form of capture accounts for only 26% of culling events, with captures at properties where bats attack livestock being more common (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R51">Viana et al., 2023</xref>). Additional field experiments that separate effects of human presence at roost sites, capture, handling and poisoning, could clarify vampire bat population management.</p><p id="P46">High resolution GPS tracking also revealed that constraints on bat movement and VBR spread may be less restrictive than implied by previous observational or radiotelemetry data. For example, rather than consistently foraging downstream of their roosts, following valleys or rivers we observed vampire bats travelling over mountains and foraging in both directions along rivers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">Ávila-Flores et al., 2019</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R50">Trajano, 1996</xref>). Furthermore, similar to other colonial species such as seabirds, vampire bats exhibited high movement behavioural heterogeneity within the colony (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">Cleasby et al., 2023</xref>). Our data also challenge the notion that vampire bats return to the same foraging location and even individual animals for blood feeding every night (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">Greenhall, 1988</xref>). Overall, heterogeneity across individual bats and within bats over short time periods helps explain the sometimes-sporadic evidence of vampire bat bites on livestock and humans (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R44">Streicker &amp; Allgeier, 2016</xref>) and implies that pathogen-infected bats are likely to expose multiple animals at different locations. Incorporating these behavioural ecological insights on vampire bats into models of rabies spread could enhance our understanding of its dynamics.</p><p id="P47">Our study fills an analytical gap that has arisen between the declining size and increasing battery life of GPS tags - which have expanded their applicability in wildlife research - and the problematic data generated when such studies are conducted in challenging habitats (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">D’Eon et al., 2002</xref>). The Bayesian framework, which jointly estimated departure times and distances from a fixed starting point (the roost), enabled inferences from sparse and irregular GPS data. While our objective was not intended to infer exact animal locations throughout the night, it did allow us to estimate how individual, landscape, disturbance and temporal factors affected key characteristics of bat movement while accounting for uncertainty. Furthermore, this approach enabled us to estimate the true distances bats can travel - that are critical for disease management − but that are often missed in sparse datasets, which tend to underrepresent maximum distances (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">Hooten et al., 2017</xref>). By enabling inference from such a challenging dataset, our approach extends the use of GPS tracking to other species and environmental conditions where conventional analyses may fail or be strongly biased by satellite visibility constraints.</p><p id="P48">A potential limitation of our approach are the assumptions that vampire bats do a single trip and return to the roost every night. If some long-distance movements instead reflect roost switching, our results may overestimate true foraging distances; however, we note that eventual return to the roost was required for data recovery so either behaviour reflects short term movements after disturbance. The assumption of a single trip per night was broadly supported by overall model fit and parameter convergence. However, a subset of bat-nights (13%) showed non-convergence, resulting in a bimodal distribution more consistent with multiple trips within a night (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S10</xref>). However, our model can identify such misspecifications and highlight that vampire bats may undertake multiple trips per night. The significance of multiple trips from a rabies perspective will depend on whether trips represent scouting activities that inform foraging activities (e.g. evaluating lunar brightness) or multiple bouts of foraging which would increase rabies exposures in prey. Empirical data on vampire bat activity, roost-switching and abandonment rates through automated radio frequency identification (RFID) systems would be useful to validate our interpretation.</p><p id="P49">Understanding animal movement in response to disturbance is important to design effective strategies for disease management but conventionally has been frustrated in some species and environments due to sparse data and error in movement data. This study provides evidence to support a change in the management of VBR. By enabling simultaneous inference and predictors of nightly movement curves for individual vampire bats, we show three responses to disturbance (increase in maximum distance travelled, individual heterogeneity in movement, and roost abandonment) which are compatible with the hypothesis that disturbing vampire bats by culling may trigger them to abandon the roost or to fly further, potentially promoting viral spread. Increased movement and roost abandonment immediately following disturbance from culling would also be expected to dilute the distribution of poison across roosts, potentially reducing efficacy. In contrast, disturbance induced movement could benefit the recently proposed application of vaccines with the capacity for self-dissemination since roost switching would ‘seed’ vaccine transmission to a larger number of roosts than previously appreciated (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">Griffiths et al., 2022</xref>). Most generally, our study highlights the value and analytical challenges of incorporating new data streams provided by increasingly accessible field-deployable technologies into wildlife ecology and management.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="SM"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1"><label>Supplementary information</label><media xlink:href="EMS205888-supplement-Supplementary_information.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" id="d5aAcEbB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack id="S11"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We are grateful to Elsa Cardenas Canales, Haris Malik and Carlos Tello for field assistance; Lynda Dunbar and Marieke Pingen for help with the suturing technique; Fred Touzalin and Pathtrack for insights and assistance with the GPS. We thank Holly Niven for helpful discussions about the analysis, and Nardus Mollentze, Travis Mcdevitt-Galles, and our colleagues from the Streicker group for peer review and feedback on earlier versions of the manuscript. We thank SENASA (National and Regional offices) for feedback and support. The project was funded by the NSF/BBSRC Ecology and Evolution of Infectious Diseases Program (DEB 2011069, BB/V003798/1). D.G.S. was funded by a Wellcome Trust Senior Research Fellowship (217221/Z/19/Z). This research received support from the UK Medical Research Council through core funding of the MRC-University of Glasgow Centre for Virus Research (Virus Cross Species Transmission Programme: MC_UU_00034/3).</p><p>Any use of trade, firm, or product names is for descriptive purposes only and does not imply endorsement by the U.S. Government.</p></ack><sec id="S12" sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p id="P50">Data and code for this study are deposited in the Dryad Digital Repository and will be made publicly available upon publication, at which point the corresponding DOI will be shared.</p></sec><fn-group><fn id="FN2" fn-type="conflict"><p id="P51"><bold>Conflict of interest:</bold> The authors have no conflict of interest to declare.</p></fn><fn id="FN3" fn-type="con"><p id="P52"><bold>Author Contributions:</bold></p><p id="P53">Conceptualization: R.R., J.M., D.G.S. Methodology: R.R., J.C., J.M., D.G.S. Analysis and visualisation: R.R., J.M. Investigation: R.R., C.M.Z., W.C., K.P.R., J.C.M., M.A.R.H., R.Z.V., W.C.Q., N.M-U., H.F., D.G.S. Resources and management: C.M.Z., C.S., N.F., W.V. Data Curation: R.R. Project administration: D.G.S., Funding acquisition: D.P.W., T.E.R., J.M., D.G.S. Supervision: R.R., J.M., D.G.S. Writing (original draft): R.R., J.M., D.G.S. All authors contributed critically to the drafts and gave final approval for publication.</p></fn><fn id="FN4"><p id="P54"><bold>Statement on inclusion:</bold> Our study involved scientists from multiple countries, including those based in the study location, fostering diversity and inclusion from the project’s outset. Co-authors were actively involved in project design, infrastructure, management, investigation, and manuscript preparation.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><ref id="R1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aldridge</surname><given-names>HDJN</given-names></name><name><surname>Brigham</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Load Carrying and Maneuverability in an Insectivorous Bat: a Test of the 5% “Rule” of Radio-Telemetry</article-title><source>Journal of Mammalogy</source><year>1988</year><volume>69</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>379</fpage><lpage>382</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/1381393</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Amman</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name><name><surname>Nyakarahuka</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>McElroy</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Dodd</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Sealy</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name><name><surname>Schuh</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Shoemaker</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><name><surname>Balinandi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Atimnedi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaboyo</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Nichol</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Marburgvirus resurgence in Kitaka mine bat population after extermination attempts, Uganda</article-title><source>Emerging Infectious Diseases</source><year>2014</year><volume>20</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>1761</fpage><lpage>1764</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4193183</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25272104</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3201/eid2010.140696</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ávila-Flores</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Bolaina-Badal</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Gallegos-Ruiz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sánchez-Gómez</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Use of linear features by the common vampire bat (Desmodus rotundus) in a tropical cattle-ranching landscape</article-title><source>Therya</source><year>2019</year><volume>10</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>229</fpage><lpage>234</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.12933/therya-19-890</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Forbes</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Plowright</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Altizer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anthropogenic resource subsidies and host -parasite dynamics in wildlife</article-title><source>Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society B: Biological Sciences</source><year>2018</year><volume>373</volume><issue>1745</issue><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5882992</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29531141</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rstb.2017.0086</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Benavides</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Valderrama</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Recuenco</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Uieda</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzán</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Avila-Flores</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Velasco-Villa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Almeida</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>de Andrade</surname><given-names>FAG</given-names></name><name><surname>Molina-Flores</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Vigilato</surname><given-names>MAN</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Defining New Pathways to Manage the Ongoing Emergence of Bat Rabies in Latin America</article-title><source>Viruses</source><year>2020</year><volume>12</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>13</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7551776</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32911766</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/v12091002</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Benavides</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Valderrama</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Streicker</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Spatial expansions and travelling waves of rabies in vampire bats</article-title><source>Proceedings of the Royal Society B: Biological Sciences</source><year>2016</year><volume>283</volume><issue>1832</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rspb.2016.0328</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blackwood</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Streicker</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Altizer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rohani</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Resolving the roles of immunity, pathogenesis, and immigration for rabies persistence in vampire bats</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source><year>2013</year><volume>110</volume><issue>51</issue><fpage>20837</fpage><lpage>20842</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3870737</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24297874</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1308817110</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Britzke</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name><name><surname>Gumbert</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Hohmann</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Behavioral response of bats to passive integrated transponder tag reader arrays placed at cave entrances</article-title><source>Journal of Fish and Wildlife Management</source><year>2014</year><volume>5</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>146</fpage><lpage>150</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3996/082012-JFWM-065</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Calisher</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Childs</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Field</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name><name><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>KV</given-names></name><name><surname>Schountz</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bats: Important reservoir hosts of emerging viruses</article-title><source>Clinical Microbiology Reviews</source><year>2006</year><volume>19</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>531</fpage><lpage>545</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1539106</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16847084</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/CMR.00017-06</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Leffer</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Social grooming in bats: Are vampire bats exceptional?</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2015</year><volume>10</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>11</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4596566</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26445502</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0138430</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Castle</surname><given-names>KT</given-names></name><name><surname>Weller</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Cryan</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hein</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Schirmacher</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Using sutures to attach miniature tracking tags to small bats for multimonth movement and behavioral studies</article-title><source>Ecology and Evolution</source><year>2015</year><volume>5</volume><issue>14</issue><fpage>2980</fpage><lpage>2989</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4542000</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26306181</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ece3.1584</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cleasby</surname><given-names>IR</given-names></name><name><surname>Owen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Butler</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Baer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Blackburn</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bogdanova</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name><name><surname>Coledale</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Daunt</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Dodd</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Assessing the importance of individual- and colony-level variation when using seabird foraging ranges as impact assessment and conservation tools</article-title><source>Ibis</source><year>2023</year><volume>166</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>871</fpage><lpage>895</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/ibi.13284</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><name><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Rainho</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Abedi-Lartey</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fahr</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wikelski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dechmann</surname><given-names>DKN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assessing roost disturbance of strawcoloured fruit bats (Eidolon helvum) through tri-axial acceleration</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2020</year><volume>15</volume><issue>11 November</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7682868</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33226991</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0242662</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Couto-Lima</surname><given-names>Di</given-names></name><name><surname>Madec</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Bersot</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name><name><surname>Campos</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Motta</surname><given-names>MDA</given-names></name><name><surname>Dos Santos</surname><given-names>FB</given-names></name><name><surname>Vazeille</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Da Costa Vasconcelos</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name><name><surname>Lourenço-De-Oliveira</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Failloux</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Potential risk of re-emergence of urban transmission of Yellow Fever virus in Brazil facilitated by competent Aedes populations</article-title><source>Scientific Reports</source><year>2017</year><volume>7</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5501812</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28687779</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-017-05186-3</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crespo</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><name><surname>Linhart</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Burns</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Foraging Behavior of the Common Vampire Bat Related to Moonlight</article-title><source>Journal of Mammalogy</source><year>1972</year><volume>53</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>366</fpage><lpage>368</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/1379175</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>D’Eon</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name><surname>Serrouya</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Kochanny</surname><given-names>CO</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>GPS radiotelemetry error and bias in mountainous terrain</article-title><source>Wildlife Society Bulletin</source><year>2002</year><volume>30</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>430</fpage><lpage>439</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Delpietro</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>Russo</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>GG</given-names></name><name><surname>Lord</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Delpietro</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reproductive seasonality, sex ratio and philopatry in Argentina’s common vampire bats</article-title><source>Royal Society Open Science</source><year>2017</year><volume>4</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>14</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5414252</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28484615</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rsos.160959</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Denwood</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Plummer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>runjags: Interface Utilities, Model Templates, Parallel Computing Methods and Additional Distributions for MCMC Models in JAGS</article-title><year>2024</year><comment>(R package version 2.2.2-4; p. 61). R package version 2.2.2-4. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/ku-awdc/runjags">https://github.com/ku-awdc/runjags</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Greenhall</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Greenhall</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Feeding behavior</chapter-title><source>Natural History of Vampire Bats</source><publisher-loc>Boca Raton</publisher-loc><publisher-name>CRC Press Inc</publisher-name><edition>1st Editio</edition><year>1988</year><fpage>7</fpage><lpage>17</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Greenhall</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Joermann</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Desmodus rotundus</article-title><source>Mammalian Species</source><year>1983</year><volume>202</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/3503895</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Griffiths</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Broos</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bergner</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Meza</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name><name><surname>Suarez</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><name><surname>Da Silva Filipe</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Tello</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Streicker</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Longitudinal deep sequencing informs vector selection and future deployment strategies for transmissible vaccines</article-title><source>PLoS Biology</source><year>2022</year><volume>20</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>19</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9017877</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35439242</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.3001580</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gupte</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name><name><surname>Beardsworth</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Spiegel</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Lourie</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Toledo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nathan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Bijleveld</surname><given-names>AI</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A guide to pre-processing high-throughput animal tracking data</article-title><source>Journal of Animal Ecology</source><year>2022</year><volume>91</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>287</fpage><lpage>307</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9299236</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34657296</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1365-2656.13610</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ham</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Donnelly</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Astley</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>SYB</given-names></name><name><surname>Woodroffe</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of culling on individual badger Meles meles behaviour: Potential implications for bovine tuberculosis transmission</article-title><source>Journal of Applied Ecology</source><year>2019</year><volume>56</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>2390</fpage><lpage>2399</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8447922</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34565831</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1365-2664.13512</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><element-citation publication-type="web"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hijmans</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><source>terra: Spatial Data Analysis</source><year>2024</year><comment>(R package version 1.7-71). <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://cran.r-project.org/package=terra">https://cran.r-project.org/package=terra</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hooten</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>McClintock</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></name><name><surname>Morales</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><source>Animal Movement: Statistical Models For Telemetry Data</source><publisher-loc>Boca Raton</publisher-loc><publisher-name>CRS Press</publisher-name><edition>1st Editio</edition><year>2017</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1201/9781315117744</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hopkins</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name><name><surname>Sánchez-Hernández</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Romero-Almaraz</surname><given-names>MDL</given-names></name><name><surname>Gilley</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Schnell</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name><name><surname>Kennedy</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Flight speeds of four species of Neotropical bats</article-title><source>Southwestern Naturalist</source><year>2003</year><volume>48</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>711</fpage><lpage>714</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1894/0038-4909(2003)048&lt;0711:FSOFSO&gt;2.0.CO;2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kahle</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Wickham</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>ggmap: Spatial visualization with ggplot2</article-title><source>The R Journal</source><year>2013</year><volume>5</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>144</fpage><lpage>161</lpage><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://journal.r-project.org/archive/2013-1/kahle-wickham.pdf">http://journal.r-project.org/archive/2013-1/kahle-wickham.pdf</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kays</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Crofoot</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Jetz</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Wikelski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Terrestrial animal tracking as an eye on life and planet</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2015</year><volume>348</volume><issue>6240</issue><elocation-id>aaa2478</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26068858</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mialhe</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of Desmodus rotundus (E. Geoffroy, 1810) (Chiroptera, Phyllostomidae) shelters in the Municipality of São Pedro - SP</article-title><source>Brazilian Journal of Biology</source><year>2013</year><volume>73</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>521</fpage><lpage>526</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24212692</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>O’Hara</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>Sillanpää</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A review of bayesian variable selection methods: What, how and which</article-title><source>Bayesian Analysis</source><year>2009</year><volume>4</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>85</fpage><lpage>118</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1214/09-BA403</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>O’Mara</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Wikelski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dechmann</surname><given-names>DKN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>50 years of bat tracking: Device attachment and future directions</article-title><source>Methods in Ecology and Evolution</source><year>2014</year><volume>5</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>311</fpage><lpage>319</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/2041-210X.12172</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>O’Shea</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Cryan</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayman</surname><given-names>DTS</given-names></name><name><surname>Plowright</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Streicker</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multiple mortality events in bats: A global review</article-title><source>Mammal Review</source><year>2016</year><volume>46</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>175</fpage><lpage>190</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5942905</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29755179</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/mam.12064</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pebesma</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Simple Features for R: Standardized Support for Spatial Vector Data</article-title><source>The R Journal</source><year>2018</year><volume>10</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>439</fpage><lpage>446</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.32614/RJ-2018-009</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Plummer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><source>rjags: Bayesian graphical models using MCMC</source><year>2023</year><comment>(R package version 4-15). <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://cran.r-project.org/package=rjags">https://cran.r-project.org/package=rjags</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Plummer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Best</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Cowles</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Vines</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>CODA: Convergence Diagnosis and Output Analysis for MCMC</article-title><source>R News</source><year>2006</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>7</fpage><lpage>11</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><element-citation publication-type="book"><collab>R Core Team</collab><source>R: A Language and Environment for Statistical Computing</source><publisher-loc>Vienna, Austria</publisher-loc><publisher-name>R Foundation for Statistical Computing</publisher-name><year>2024</year><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.r-project.org/">https://www.r-project.org/</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="R37"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ribeiro</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Matthiopoulos</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindgren</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Tello</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Zariquiey</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Valderrama</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Rocke</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name><name><surname>Streicker</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Incorporating environmental heterogeneity and observation effort to predict host distribution and viral spillover from a bat reservoir</article-title><source>Proceedings of the Royal Society B: Biological Sciences</source><year>2023</year><volume>290</volume><issue>20231739</issue><fpage>11</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10688441</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37989240</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rspb.2023.1739</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R38"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ripperger</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>GG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Social foraging in vampire bats is predicted by long-term cooperative relationships</article-title><source>PLoS Biology</source><year>2021</year><volume>19</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>17</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8460024</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34555014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.3001366</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R39"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rocha</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Ulloa-Stanojlovic</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name><name><surname>Rabaquim</surname><given-names>VCV</given-names></name><name><surname>Fadil</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Pompei</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Brandão</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name><name><surname>Dias</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ortega</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Relations between topography, feeding sites, and foraging behavior of the vampire bat, Desmodus rotundus</article-title><source>Journal of Mammalogy</source><year>2020</year><volume>101</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>164</fpage><lpage>171</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jmammal/gyz177</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R40"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rojas-Sereno</surname><given-names>ZE</given-names></name><name><surname>Streicker</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Medina-Rodríguez</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name><surname>Benavides</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Drivers of spatial expansions of vampire bat rabies in Colombia</article-title><source>Viruses</source><year>2022</year><volume>14</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9697077</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36366416</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/v14112318</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R41"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Romijn</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name><surname>Uieda</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Tamayo</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>da Silva</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name><name><surname>Belotto</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>da Silva</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Leanes</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rabies transmitted by vampire bats to humans: An emerging zoonotic disease in Latin America?</article-title><source>Revista Panamericana de Salud Publica = Pan American Journal of Public Health</source><year>2009</year><volume>25</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>260</fpage><lpage>269</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19454154</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R42"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seltmann</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Czirják</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Courtiol</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bernard</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Struebig</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Voigt</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Habitat disturbance results in chronic stress and impaired health status in forest-dwelling paleotropical bats</article-title><source>Conservation Physiology</source><year>2017</year><volume>5</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>14</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5388297</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28421138</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/conphys/cox020</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R43"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stiegler</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gallagher</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hering</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Müller</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Tucker</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Apollonio</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Arnold</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Barker</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name><surname>Barthel</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Bassano</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>van Beest</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Mammals show faster recovery from capture and tagging in human-disturbed landscapes</article-title><source>Nature Communications</source><year>2024</year><volume>15</volume><issue>1</issue><elocation-id>8079</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11402999</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39278967</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-024-52381-8</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R44"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Streicker</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Allgeier</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Foraging choices of vampire bats in diverse landscapes: potential implications for land-use change and disease transmission</article-title><source>Journal of Applied Ecology</source><year>2016</year><volume>53</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1280</fpage><lpage>1288</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4950014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27499553</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1365-2664.12690</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R45"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Streicker</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Franka</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>FR</given-names></name><name><surname>Rupprecht</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anthropogenic roost switching and rabies virus dynamics in house-roosting big brown bats</article-title><source>Vector-Borne and Zoonotic Diseases</source><year>2013</year><volume>13</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>498</fpage><lpage>504</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23590325</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R46"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Streicker</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Recuenco</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Valderrama</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Benavides</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Vargas</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Pacheco</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Condori Condori</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Montgomery</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Rupprecht</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Rohani</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Altizer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ecological and anthropogenic drivers of rabies exposure in vampire bats: Implications for transmission and control</article-title><source>Proceedings of the Royal Society B: Biological Sciences</source><year>2012</year><volume>279</volume><issue>1742</issue><fpage>3384</fpage><lpage>3392</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3396893</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22696521</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rspb.2012.0538</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R47"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Streicker</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Winternitz</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Satterfield</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Condori-Condori</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Broos</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Tello</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Recuenco</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Velasco-Villa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Altizer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Valderrama</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Host-pathogen evolutionary signatures reveal dynamics and future invasions of vampire bat rabies</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source><year>2016</year><volume>113</volume><issue>39</issue><fpage>10926</fpage><lpage>10931</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5047211</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27621441</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1606587113</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R48"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thieurmel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Elmarhraoui</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Package “suncalc” Title Compute Sun Position, Sunlight Phases, Moon Position and Lunar Phase</article-title><year>2022</year><comment>(R package version 0.5.1). <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://cran.r-project.org/package=suncalc">https://cran.r-project.org/package=suncalc</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="R49"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Holland</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Minot</surname><given-names>EO</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Wildlife tracking technology options and cost considerations</article-title><source>Wildlife Research</source><year>2011</year><volume>38</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>653</fpage><lpage>663</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1071/WR10211</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R50"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Trajano</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Movements of cave bats in southeastern Brazil, with emphasis on the population ecology of the common vampire bat, Desmodus rotundus (Chiroptera)</article-title><source>Biotropica</source><year>1996</year><volume>28</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>121</fpage><lpage>129</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/2388777</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R51"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Viana</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Benavides</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Broos</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Loayza</surname><given-names>DI</given-names></name><name><surname>Niño</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Bone</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>da Silva Filipe</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Orton</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Bazan</surname><given-names>WV</given-names></name><name><surname>Matthiopoulos</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Streicker</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of culling vampire bats on the spatial spread and spillover of rabies virus</article-title><source>Science Advances</source><year>2023</year><volume>9</volume><issue>10</issue><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10005164</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36897949</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/sciadv.add7437</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R52"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wilkinson</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The social organization of the common vampire bat</article-title><source>Behav Ecol Sociobiol</source><year>1985</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>111</fpage><lpage>121</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R53"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>World Health Organization</collab><article-title>WHO Expert Consultation on rabies, third report</article-title><source>WHO technical report series</source><year>2018</year><volume>1012</volume><comment>Licence: CC BY-NC-SA 3.0 IGO</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16485446</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Study area and GPS data from 55 bats (1 colour, 1 bat) captured from 5 roosts (numbered triangles) and tracked for up to 9 nights.</title><p>(a) Elevation map with the 5 study roosts in AAC, with an inset map of Peru highlighting the study region. (b) roost 1, (c) roost 2, (d) roost 3, (e) roost 4 and (f) roost 5. Due to the varying scales of movement across the roosts, this figure does not use a standardised scale, and only 95% of the fixes closest to the roost were plotted to avoid outliers. Maps used ggmap (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27">Kahle &amp; Wickham, 2013</xref>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS205888-f001"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Predicted probabilities of vampire bats returning to the roost following disturbance, from a binomial GLM.</title><p>(a) Shows sex-specific estimates with 95% confidence intervals; (b) shows the relationship of probability of return with forearm length (mm), with the 95% confidence interval shaded.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS205888-f002"/></fig><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Predictors of vampire bat departure time and distance from the roost.</title><p>(a) Standardised effect sizes on the log-odds scale (departure time, logit model) or log scale (distance, exponential model), coloured by SSVS retention probability. (b) Individual variation in the distance from the roost on the disturbance night (bat-night interaction). (c) Observed maximum distances (km) from the roost per bat and night. (d) Predicted maximum distances (km) per bat and night. In (c) and (d), night 0 is the disturbance night; squares indicate means, and black dots are outliers.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS205888-f003"/></fig><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Reconstructed movement curves for 9 bats across 9 nights. First row: bats that travelled longer distances on night 0; middle row: bats that travelled similar distances across different nights; bottom row: bats that left the roost after night 0 and did not return. The shaded area indicates the credible intervals. Purple lines indicate night zero, with progressively lighter colours indicating later nights. Due to the varying scales of movement, the y-axis is not standardised.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS205888-f004"/></fig></floats-group></article>