<!DOCTYPE article
 PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" article-type="preprint"><?all-math-mml yes?><?use-mml?><?origin ukpmcpa?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">bioRxiv</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>bioRxiv : the preprint server for biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2692-8205</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">EMS207331</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2025.07.18.665620</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="archive">PPR1051925</article-id><article-version-alternatives><article-version article-version-type="status">preprint</article-version><article-version article-version-type="number">1</article-version></article-version-alternatives><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>A pangenomics-enabled platform for the high-throughput discovery of antifungal resistance factors in crop pathogens</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Puccetti</surname><given-names>Guido</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Flückiger</surname><given-names>Daniel</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Edel</surname><given-names>Dominique</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Delude</surname><given-names>Camille</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tralamazza</surname><given-names>Sabina Moser</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Badet</surname><given-names>Thomas</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Scalliet</surname><given-names>Gabriel</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN1">§</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Croll</surname><given-names>Daniel</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN1">§</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Laboratory of Evolutionary Genetics, Institute of Biology, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/00vasag41</institution-id><institution>University of Neuchâtel</institution></institution-wrap>, <postal-code>CH-2000</postal-code>, <city>Neuchâtel</city>, <country country="CH">Switzerland</country></aff><aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Syngenta Crop Protection AG, Stein, Switzerland</aff><author-notes><corresp id="CR1">Correspondence: <email>gabriel.scalliet@syngenta.com</email>; <email>daniel.croll@unine.ch</email></corresp><fn id="FN1"><label>§</label><p id="P1">Jointly supervised the work</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted"><day>21</day><month>07</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="preprint"><day>19</day><month>07</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><permissions><ali:free_to_read/><license><ali:license_ref>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is licensed under a <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0 International license</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p id="P2">The rise of antifungal resistance is a global challenge for both human health and food security, because resistance emergence easily outpaces the antifungal development pipeline. Furthermore, resistance arises often in parallel and through alternative mechanisms. In agriculture, where vast areas are sprayed by diverse cocktails of antifungal resistance gains are particularly complex. Despite broad efforts, knowledge of resistance mechanisms is often limited to model genotypes and empirical evidence from the field is lacking. Here, we define and validate a high-throughput pipeline for antifungal resistance discovery informed by emerging resistance gains at continental scale. We analyzed a thousand-genome European diversity panel of the major wheat pathogen <italic>Zymoseptoria tritici</italic> and assessed resistance levels against over 40 fungicides covering all major classes. We optimized high-throughput phenotyping assays to comprehensively capture emerging resistance phenotypes. Pangenome-informed genotyping techniques revealed a total of 2280 genes associated with antifungal resistance. This expands by an order of magnitude the current knowledge and establishes a refined atlas of resistance mutations. We generated mutants to recapitulate several of the discovered resistance factors. Hence, our approach captures in-field resistance gains across Europe for all major fungicide classes and can define exact molecular targets. Broad knowlegde of resistance gains will guide more sustainable fungicide development pipelines.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec id="S1" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p id="P3">Fungicide resistance is a global concern for medicine and agriculture <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref></sup>. Critical challenges arise as the development of new fungicides is slower than the rate at of resistance emergence <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref></sup>. Understanding the molecular mechanisms of fungicide resistance is crucial to inform drug design and to mitigate resistance breakdowns and improve the lifespan of fungicides. Resistance mechanisms are typically identified through molecular genetics approaches such as random mutagenesis or reverse genetics <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref></sup>. However, such analyses focused on single genetic backgrounds often only poorly represent the potential for resistance mechanisms and selection in the field can produce a wider range of outcomes <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref></sup>. Variations within pathogen species in the molecular target or detoxification genes are important factors for resistance heterogeneity <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref></sup>. Genetic monitoring of pathogen populations and assessing changes in fungicide resistance can identify the rise of new resistance in the field <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref></sup>. However, targeted genetic monitoring alone is unable to pinpoint the emergence of new resistance mechanisms <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref></sup>.</p><p id="P4">Genomic surveys of pathogen species enable the unbiased discovery of genetic factors contributing to trait variation including fungicide resistance <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref></sup>. Genome-wide association studies (GWAS) are powerful applications to natural populations capturing a wide spectrum of genetic factors contributing to complex traits <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref></sup>. GWAS identified standing variation in fungicide resistance in diverse crop pathogens <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">20</xref></sup>. Applications to the sugarbeet pathogen <italic>Cercospora beticola</italic> mapped contributions of mutations in the ergosterol biosynthesis gene <italic>Cyp51</italic> to azole fungicide resistance <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">20</xref></sup>. In the wheat pathogen <italic>Zymoseptoria tritici</italic> both the known target of azole resistance and additional not previously identified factors were mapped. GWAS discovery was facilitated by the high diversity and spatially explicit sampling <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">22</xref></sup>. However, the molecular basis of fungicide resistance in agricultural contexts remains largely unknown. A major factor are complex genetic contributions to resistance including <italic>e.g</italic>. variation generated by transposable elements (TEs) or structural variation. Such complexity was found in a regulatory region for a drug exporter gene and convergently in multiple pathogens <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">23</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">25</xref></sup>. Molecular targets can also evolve copy-number variation in response to fungicide selection such as the paralog emergence in <italic>Z. tritici</italic> and <italic>Candida albicans</italic> <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27">27</xref></sup>. Complex genetic variation can be mapped using reference-free genotyping approaches such as k-mers integrated into GWAS <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">28</xref></sup>. Azole resistance in <italic>Z. tritici</italic> is at least in part governed by complex genetic variation, which was only recovered using such reference-free genotyping approaches <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">28</xref></sup>.</p><p id="P5">The power of large pathogen panels to uncover variation in important traits was recently shown by the establishment of thousand-genome panels for the major wheat pathogen <italic>Z. tritici</italic> <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">29</xref></sup>. The panels revealed global patterns in pathogen emergence, adaptation to the climatic factors as well as a complex set of resistance mutations for demethylation inhibitors (DMI) such as azoles. The GWAS panel constructed from European samples identified a total 158 genes associated with resistance to six DMIs. Notably, the panel mapped resistance to a paralog of <italic>SdhC1</italic>, termed <italic>SdhC3</italic>, which was recently discovered as a contributor to succinate dehydrogenase inhibitors (SDHI). The contribution of paralogs to fungicide resistance highlights the need to assess genetic diversity comprehensively beyond single genotypes <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">30</xref></sup>. The full spectrum of resistance mutations remains largely unknown as highlighted by recent work <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31">31</xref></sup>.</p><p id="P6">In this study, we develop and validate a high-throughput pipeline integrating the collection of a diverse pathogen panel for GWAS, a robust discovery of fungicide resistance associated genetic variants and functional validation of GWAS candidates. We determined the sensitivity of comprehensive European diversity panel of the wheat pathogen <italic>Z. tritici</italic> for over 40 fungicides and established a comprehensive fungicide resistance atlas cataloguing an exhaustive set of genetic factors underpinning resistance breakdowns in a geographic context.</p></sec><sec id="S2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="S3"><title>Establishment of a European diversity panel</title><p id="P7">To establish a high-throughput pipeline linking natural variation to the genetic basis of fungicide resistance, we established a five steps process depicted in (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1A</xref>). The pipeline includes the establishment of a diverse strain collection capturing relevant geographic and temporal scales of fungicide resistance gains across the European continent. Second, we optimized a high-throughput phenotyping assay to profile differential fungicide susceptibility across the panel. Third, we implemented GWAS to comprehensively map genetic factors contributing to resistance across the genome and, finally, used molecular genetics assays to validate predicted resistance phenotypes. The European diversity panel captures a timespan of 15 years and originates from extensive field monitoring efforts<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref></sup>. The European continent has long experienced fungicide applications, covers a wide range of climates and fungicide regimes (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table S1</xref>). Sampling for the European diversity panel was augmented in areas of intense fungicide application and wheat production (Eurostat, 2024) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table S2</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1B</xref>). A key factor for GWAS mapping power is the diversity and size of the population <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">21</xref></sup>. To estimate the impact of collection size has on the number of genetic variants, we randomly subsampled the European diversity panel to 100-1000 strains. We found an average increase of 0.4% (1905 SNPs) per each 100 strains added, with an overall gain between 100 and 1000 of 3.7% (17141 SNPs) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1C</xref>). These results show that even a collection of 100 strains across Europe can effectively represent genetic variability. The diversity panel showed an average of 1.2% synonymous point mutations and 0.4% missense point mutations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1D</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S4"><title>Maximize fungicide resistance discovery</title><p id="P8">The composition of the GWAS panel affects mapping power <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32">32</xref></sup>. To maximize locus discovery, we systematically examined the effects of temporal, spatial, and panel size variation. We first subset the panel into two timeframes (sampled 2005-2015 or 2016-2019 with the latter period including the first applications of mefentrifluconazole. The earlier panel subset (2005-2015) consisted of 370 strains and the post-2016 collection was composed of 529 strains. The post-2016 collection showed significantly higher relative growth in mefentrifluconazole compared to the earlier collection (p &lt; 0.01; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2 A-C</xref>). GWAS analyses identified five SNPs on chromosome 3 in the 2005-2015 panel, intersecting with the gene 3_01019 (a Zinc-finger C2H2-type transcription factor). In contrast, the later collection set revealed 152 SNPs associated with mefentrifluconazole resistance within ~41 kb of <italic>Cyp51</italic> and addition to three SNPs located upstream of <italic>Mfs1</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2 D</xref>).</p><p id="P9">Besides the introduction of new fungicides, fungicide application practices vary significantly across Europe, leading to region-specific selection pressure. Hence, local adaptation could produce heterogenous outcomes in adaptation <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33">33</xref></sup>. In Europe, west-to-east represents a gradient in increased DMI resistance consistent with fungicide application practices <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref></sup>. We compared 294 strains collected after 2015 and from either Western Europe and the British Isles or from 176 strains collected in Eastern Europe (East) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2E, F, G</xref>). The relative growth of prothioconazole of strains from the two panels showed no significant difference (<italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.2; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2E</xref>). The Western European panel revealed an amino acid substitution in the <italic>Cyp51</italic> gene (Ser524Thr) compared to the Eastern mapping panel (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2H</xref>).</p><p id="P10">Finally, we examined the influence of panel size on the statistical power of GWAS to detect fungicide associations. We subset the European diversity panel into panels ranging from 100 to 800 samples, with each panel size being randomized 100 times. The number of significant SNPs reached a plateau in detected associations, starting at about 700 strains (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3A-B</xref>). The SNPs linked to mefentrifluconazole resistance converged in four different regions, including <italic>Cyp51</italic>, a region ~35 kb from <italic>Cyp51</italic>, the <italic>Mfs1</italic> gene (for mefentrifluconazole), and 12_00117 (gene of unknown function). Subsampling revealed that 200 strains were sufficient to map <italic>Cyp51</italic> resistance mutations (mean of 6.6 SNPs) and <italic>Mfs1</italic> (mean 4 SNPs). For prothioconazole, 200 samples were sufficient to identify <italic>Cyp51</italic> (mean of 1.03 SNPs), and 12_00177 (mean of 8.6 SNPs). For sample sizes up to 800 strains, the association mapping consistently reveals a region ~35 kb from <italic>Cyp51, Cyp51</italic> and <italic>Mfs1</italic>-associated mutations for mefentrifluconazole (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3B</xref>). Similarly, for prothioconazole, the proportion of genes associated with resistance reached a plateau from 600 strains with a stable number of mutations mapped in 12_00117 (3-4%) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3C</xref>). These findings show that the composition of the GWAS panel significantly affects the power to map loci even under less controlled environmental conditions.</p></sec><sec id="S5"><title>Fungicide concentration and assay runtime impact resistance gene discovery</title><p id="P11">We assessed whether fungicide concentration affects the expression of resistance mechanisms. For this, we assessed growth responses to a range of epoxiconazole concentrations (10 mg.L<sup>-1</sup> to 0.01 mg.L<sup>-1</sup>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4A</xref>). At the lowest dose, growth of 0.2% strains was suppressed and GWAS analyses revealed no significant associations for this response. Higher concentrations of epoxiconazole led to a higher proportion of susceptible strains with most strains exhibiting intermediate growth levels (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4B</xref>). At concentrations of 0.1 and 1 mg.L<sup>-1</sup> epoxiconazole, GWAS mapped missense substitutions in the target gene <italic>Cyp51</italic> including Ser524Arg and two SNPs upstream of 7_00448 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4D</xref>). At 1 mg.L<sup>-1</sup>, GWAS identified three synonymous SNPs in the drug exporter gene <italic>Mfs1</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4E</xref>). At the highest dose (10 mg.L<sup>-1</sup>), most strains showed no growth without any GWAS associations for the observed growth variation. Overall, we identified a total of 266 SNPs significantly associated with epoxiconazole resistance over the concentration range. Beyond concentration, colony growth kinetics in response to fungicides can potentially affect GWAS performance. Thus, we assessed GWAS outcomes for relative growth 7- and 14-days post inoculation (dpi) for four different fungicides. GWAS discovery of resistance mutations to the QoI azoxystrobin were unaffected by the assay runtime consistently identified the Gly143Ala resistance mutation in the cytochrome b (<italic>cob</italic>) gene (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig 5A</xref>). For fenpropimorph (SBI class II), GWAS identified a single synonymous SNP (Pro660Pro) in the gene 7_00011 upstream of <italic>Mfs1</italic> with a 7-dpi runtime and three additional SNPs with the 14-dpi runtime. Two SNPs were synonymous variants in <italic>Mfs1</italic> (Asn114Asn and Ile116Ile). No significant associations were observed with fenhexamid (SBI class III) regardless of runtime (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig 5BC</xref>). Finally, resistance to the SDHI carboxin at the short runtime was governed by a missense mutation in a gene encoding an epoxide hydrolase (1_00671; Glu115Lys) and three mutations in a gene encoding a methyltransferase (8_00208). At the longer runtime, only a downstream mutation near an ABC transporter gene (4_00005) was found to significantly impact resistance (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig 5D</xref>). These findings highlight that the effects of resistance mutations are expressed at least in part contingent on the degree of fungicide exposure and the colony growth stage.</p></sec><sec id="S6"><title>Contributions of complex genetic variants</title><p id="P12">Structural variation including transposable elements (TEs) and indels contribute to fungicide resistance variation in <italic>Z. tritici</italic> <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">28</xref></sup>. Consequently, we genotyped the European diversity panel using a diverse set of genetic markers including SNPs, short indels, k-mers, TEs, and copy number variants (CNVs). We identified 8,536,499 SNPs and 6,606,877 indels segregating in the panel. For GWAS discovery, we focused on the best genotyped variants and remove rare variants (minor allele frequency &lt;5%) retaining 472,041 biallelic SNPs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6A</xref><bold>)</bold>. The 23,959 retained biallelic indels showed a long tail for larger deletions (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table S3</xref>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6B</xref>). We identified 186 significant indels and 901 significant SNPs. To reduce the reference genome bias, we assessed k-mer frequencies among strains (Voichek and Weigel, 2020). We identified 66,877 significant k-mers associated to variation in fungicide resistance (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table S4</xref>). We were able to localize 65.58% of the k-mers to the reference genome and a total of 98.28% to the pangenome of the species (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6C</xref>) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table S5</xref>). We screen for polymorphic TE insertions in the European diversity panel and identified 2,542 loci with a minor allele frequency of &gt;1%. A total 792 loci showed presence of the TE in the reference genome and 1,750 were absent (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6D</xref><bold>)</bold>. Nearly 9% of all TE polymorphisms showed a significant association with fungicide resistance (<italic>n</italic> = 218 loci) with the <italic>Copia</italic> (RLC) and DNA transposons (DTX) being the most abundant TE superfamilies (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table S6</xref>). Variation in copy numbers (<italic>i.e</italic>. CNVs) was significantly associated with fungicide resistance at 68 loci. Of these, CNV loci overlapped with two genes (7_00456 and 5_00703; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table S7</xref>). Hence, reference genome free genotyping and accounting for complex genetic variation improves substantially GWAS discovery for resistance mutations.</p></sec><sec id="S7"><title>Establishment of a fungicide resistance atlas</title><p id="P13">We performed and integrated GWAS findings for 15 fungicide classes relevant for agriculture. The compounds including fungicides specifically recommended to combat <italic>Z. tritici</italic> in wheat fields, additional crop protection fungicides as well as clinical compound classes such as echinocandins (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6A</xref>) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table S8</xref>). We first focused on SNP-based GWAS and included 43 assessments of fungicide resistance covering 30 distinct compounds, distinct assay runtimes and compound concentrations. We discovered a total 901 significantly associated loci with 61.1% (<italic>n</italic> = 557) SNPs in coding regions of 146 different genes. Of these, 41.8% (<italic>n</italic> = 377) SNPs were synonymous variants, 19.1% (<italic>n =</italic> 174) were missense variants and 3 were altered stop codons. The DMI class of compounds (<italic>n</italic> = 5 tested) accounted for 71.5% of the total (645 SNPs) with 327 SNPs localized to a 40 kb region near the <italic>Cyp</italic>51 gene encoding the molecular target of azoles. The large region with significant associations is consistent with a selective sweep generating long-range linkage disequilibrium. The drug exporter coding sequence of <italic>Mfs</italic>1 showed associations with three DMIs including cyproconazole, epoxiconazole, and mefentrifluconazole. Additionally, <italic>Mfs1</italic> variants were associated with two additional fungicide classes targeting the sterol biosynthesis pathway (<italic>i.e</italic>., SBI II and SBI IV). SDHIs (<italic>n</italic> = 4 tested) showed the second highest proportion of SNPs associated with resistance, accounting for 18.4 % (<italic>n</italic> = 166) of the significant SNPs and covered 18 genes. Isofetamid showed 143 (100%) SNPs within ~10 kb of <italic>SdhC3</italic> gene, which encodes resistance associated paralog of the <italic>SdhC1</italic> subunit <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref></sup>. GWAS of QoI fungicides resistance identified four SNPs with azoxystrobin revealing the Gly143Ala substitution in the <italic>cytochrome b</italic> (cob) gene encoding the molecular target of QoIs <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34">34</xref></sup>. Pyribencarb resistance was unexpectedly associated with substitutions in the <italic>Cyp51</italic> gene. GWAS for QiI fungicide resistance revealed associations with a broad range of genes with florylpicoxamid resistance being associated with four genes (1_01890, 3_01116, 9_00415, 11_00307) suggesting non-target site resistance mechanisms. Carbamate and N-phenyl carbamate fungicide resistance were both associated to the Glu198Ala substitution in the beta-tubulin gene. The substitution showed a strong negative cross-resistance between the two alleles (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figure 9 A-D</xref>). In addition, the anilinopyrimidine fungicides pyrimethanil and mepanipyrim also showed associations with the same Glu198Ala substitution in the beta-tubulin gene. Anilinopyrimidine fungicides are thought to act on a different target, at least in <italic>B. cinerea</italic> <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35">35</xref></sup>. The clinically relevant echinocandin and the anilinopyrimidine fungicides not applied to control <italic>Z. tritici</italic> revealed also significant loci in the genome (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table S8</xref>). The allele swap Glu198Ala in the <italic>beta-tubulin</italic> gene was associated to a shift of sensitivity of the anilinopyrimidine besides to carbendazim (MBC) and diethofencarb (N-phenyl carbamates). The reference free k-mer GWAS approach expanded the discovery of resistance factors beyond simple variants mapped to a reference genome. Assessing k-mers not mapping to the reference genome, we identified an average of 2699 k-mers associated with SDHI fungicide resistance and an average of 403 k-mers for DMI resistance (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig 7B</xref>). Isofetamid resistance showed the highest proportion (89.9 %) of k-mers not aligning to the reference genome. The proportion of aligning k-mers increases to 76-91% when considering the pangenome of the species (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table S9</xref>). For two genomes included in the species pangenome (<italic>i.e</italic>. 3D7 and 3D1) all significant k-mers mapped to the <italic>SdhC3</italic> paralog associated with SDHI resistance (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7D</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S8"><title>Reference-free mapping and validation of resistance factors</title><p id="P14">We further investigated resistance loci for which SNP-based GWAS alone was not successful. We focused on the gene <italic>SdhC1</italic> and carboxin resistance (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figure 8A</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table S4</xref>). The top 20 most significantly associated k-mers with resistance, showed overlaps with the coding sequence of <italic>SdhC1</italic>. Of these k-mers, 16 to a precise location pinpointing a Thr79Asn amino acid substitution (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figure 8B</xref>). The substitution was missed in the SNP-based GWAS due to the very low frequency (3%) typically excluded in SNP filtering (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figure 8A</xref>). The Thr79Asn was first detected in 2016 in Germany followed by a more widespread occurrence across Europe with a notable frequency increase in Ireland <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref></sup>. We functionally validated the impact of the Thr79Asn substitution by generating isogenic mutants in the reference genome strain IPO323 lacking Ku70 (Δku70). Two independent mutants showed significantly increased growth on carboxin-amended media compared to the susceptible IPO323 reference. Hence, this mutation affecting the inhibitor binding site of the SDH enzyme is indeed associated with gains of carboxin resistance in Europe (Scalliet et al., 2012; Steinhauer et al., 2019) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figure 8D</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure S1 A-C</xref>).</p><p id="P15">The fungicide resistance atlas revealed a negative cross-resistance associated with the Glu198Ala substitution in the beta-tubulin gene. Encoding Glu at position 198 is associated with higher resistance against diethofencarb (a methyl benzimidazole carbamate class member). Encoding Ala at the same position confers resistance to carbendazim (N-phenyl carbamate class) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figure 9C</xref>) <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36">36</xref></sup>. The negative cross-resistance was previously characterized by showing that the Glu198Ala substitution confers resistance to carbendazim and sensitivity to diethofencarb <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37">37</xref></sup>. We found that Glu198Ala also mediates resistance to the anilinopyrimidine fungicide class (such as pyrimethanil and mepanipyrim fungicides). The anilinopyrimidine fungicides have not been used for <italic>Z. tritici</italic> control or for the control of wheat pathogens in general. We observed a strong antagonistic growth response for strains growing either well on carbendazim (10 mg.L<sup>-1</sup>) or diethofencarb (10 mg.L<sup>-1</sup>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figure 9A</xref>), as well as between carbendazim (10 mg.L<sup>-1</sup>) and pyrimethanil (50 mg.L<sup>-1</sup>). Strains more susceptible to pyrimethanil tended also to be more susceptible to diethofencarb (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figure 9BC</xref>), however the correlation in growth responses was not significant (<italic>p</italic> = 0.49; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figure 9C</xref>). We used molecular genetics to assess the impact of the point mutation associated with pyrimethanil resistance. For this, we generated isogenic lines of the IPO323 Δku70 background swapping the beta-tubulin Glu198 for Ala (GAG to GCG) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figure 9D</xref>). The resulting mutant (with the Glu198Ala mutation) exhibited resistance to carbendazim, and susceptibility to both diethofencarb and pyrimethanil. Hence, the negative cross-resistance predicted by the fungicide resistance atlas indeed replicates in functional assays.</p><p id="P16">We analyzed evidence for two additional resistance mechanisms associated with fungicide classes not specifically applied against <italic>Z. tritici</italic>. Terbinafine, a class III sterol biosynthesis inhibitor (SBI), is commonly used to treat human fungal infections and was investigated for multidrug resistance (MDR) in filamentous fungi <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38">38</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39">39</xref></sup>. In <italic>Z. tritici</italic>, terbinafine has been used to screen for genotypes with <italic>MFS1</italic> overexpression <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">25</xref></sup>. A recent study indicated that MDR mediated by <italic>MFS1</italic> promoter variation is more variable than previous thought <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31">31</xref></sup>. Both SNP and k-mer based GWAS identified <italic>MFS1</italic> as the top gene associated with terbinafine resistance, with six synonymous SNPs and the most significant association at position 36,492 bp on chromosome 7 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Figure 10A</xref>). Interestingly, a second <italic>MFS</italic> gene (10_00421) was associated with terbinafine resistance through a synonymous SNP (Val531Val) and 86 mapped k-mers (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure S2 A</xref>). To test for contributions of the additional <italic>MFS</italic> gene to resistance, we inserted a tetracyclin-repressible promoter upstream of the gene. The promoter is tunable by doxycycline. A promoter swap was also performed at the <italic>MFS1</italic> locus as a control. In addition, we produced a knock-out mutant of 10_00421 to assess whether deletion of the gene would confer oversensitivity to terbinafine (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Figure 10B</xref>). As expected, overexpression of <italic>MFS1</italic> (<italic>OE_MFS1</italic>) conferred resistance in media supplemented with terbinafine and epoxiconazole, while doxycycline-induced repression restored sensitivity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Figure 10C</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure S2 B</xref>). However, neither overexpression nor the knock-out of 10_00421 altered terbinafine resistance (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure S3 A, B</xref>). Hence, we found no support to recapitulate the GWAS association in the IPO323 background. Genomic retracing of resistance alleles in the European diversity panel suggested that the two resistance-associated alleles were gained independently (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure S4 A</xref>).</p><p id="P17">Finally, we focused on structural variants associated with pyrimethanil resistance. K-mer GWAS identified 396 significant k-mers with 228 aligning exclusively to a genome from a strain originally collection in the US (<italic>i.e</italic>. I93). K-mers mapped to a structural variant of 1,668 bp spanning positions 5,571,841-5,573,509 bp on chromosome 1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Figure 10D</xref>). This region encodes the candidate gene mediating resistance (jg.10233) and segregates both a functional and a loss-of-function haplotype in the European diversity panel (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Figure S5</xref>). K-mer mapping comparisons suggested additional structural variation among genomes associated with resistance (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table S10</xref>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Figure 10E</xref>). We hypothesized that the truncated jg.10233 haplotype confers pyrimethanil resistance ()Figure. Introducing the alternative haplotypes of jg.10233 into the IPO323 genetic background lacking the locus yielded revealed no detectable variation in resistance. Hence, additional factors may play a role in this newly discovered locus for pyrimethanil sensitivity.</p></sec></sec><sec id="S9" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p id="P18">A comprehensive understanding of genetic factors contributing to emerging fungicide resistance is crucial for effectively managing fungicide deployment and development of new compounds. This study introduces a high-throughput pipeline capturing continent-wide genetic diversity of a major crop pathogen. The genomic survey revealed a complex landscape of resistance against dozens of compounds. Complex genetic variation makes important contributions to overall resistance. We refined association mapping studies with analyses of structural variation. We confirmed some key predicted resistance mutations using functional assays.</p><p id="P19">Sample size, genetic and phenotypic variability affect the power of GWAS analyses <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">21</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40">40</xref></sup>. The established European diversity panel comprises 1420 strains sampled in a hierarchical manner. We showed that even a fraction of the panel would represent a large proportion of the discovered genetic diversity. However, smaller sample sizes would have prevented a robust mapping of most discovered loci. Earlier population genetic analyses and monitoring programs have highlighted the heterogeneous distribution of resistance across Europe <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41">41</xref></sup>. We found direct evidence for this heterogeneity by contrasting GWAS subpanels split along a East-West axis or segmenting the panel by collection years. We also found that the discovery threshold to robustly discover variants was heterogenous among fungicides. This is most likely explained by the population frequencies of resistance and single locus contributions to resistance. The GWAS power analyses also revealed that prothioconazole resistance mapped to the <italic>cytochrome b</italic> locus beyond the expected molecular target gene <italic>Cyp51</italic> and the multidrug resistance factor <italic>MFS1</italic>. A possible explanation for the association of <italic>cytochrome b</italic> are the geographic congruence of DMI and QoI exposure. This combination may lead to populations being co-selected for dual resistance and genetic correlations. Alternatively, the multigenic basis of prothiconazole resistance may either be related to yet unknown variation in DMI resistance <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42">42</xref></sup> or, more likely, to the necessary conversion of prothioconazole towards prothioconazole-desthio by oxidation in fungal cells, an essential conversion for Cyp51 inhibition and antifungal activity <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43">43</xref></sup>. Finally, we identified significant impacts of the fungicide concentration in the assay on GWAS discovery. In particular, loci associated with strong resistance mechanism (<italic>e.g. Cyp51</italic> substitutions) were detected at lower doses (sufficient to control x% of the isolates) compared to complementary resistance mechanism (such as <italic>MFS1</italic> mediated multidrug resistance). This finding suggests that in our settings, complementary resistance mechanisms (<italic>i.e</italic>. detoxification by MFS1) display a more distinguishable phenotypic effect in backgrounds already carrying primary target resistance (<italic>i.e</italic>. resistant <italic>Cyp51</italic> haplotype). The substantial improvements in GWAS discovery highlights how standard fungicide resistance assay platforms can be optimized.</p><p id="P20">We show that a comprehensive approach to genotype genetic variation is crucial for the mapping of fungicide resistance loci. The resulting fungicide resistance atlas comprises 901 significant SNPs, 66,877 unique K-mers, with 40,040 aligning to unique location in the reference genome, 186 significant indels, 218 TE insertion polymorphisms and 68 CNV loci. The resistance atlas confirmed previously discovered substitutions in <italic>CYP51</italic> including Ser524Thr, Ile381Val, Ser188Asn,Val136Phe and Asp134Gly <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R44">44</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R45">45</xref></sup>, Gly143Ala in <italic>cytochrome b</italic> <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref></sup>, Glu198Ala in beta tubulin and genetic variation in or nearby the multidrug resistance factor <italic>Mfs1</italic> <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref></sup>. Non-SNP based are known to contribute to phenotypic variation including melanin production, asexual reproduction and fungicide resistance in the pathogen <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R46">46</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R47">47</xref></sup>. Here, we showed that nearly a tenth of all polymorphic TE insertion loci are associated with fungicide resistance. A hotspot for resistance gains mediated by TEs is in the promoter region of <italic>Mfs1</italic> <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R48">48</xref></sup>. We identified previously unknown contributions by TEs (<italic>i.e</italic>. fluxapyroxad resistance) as well as confirming the involvement of TEs for <italic>MFS1</italic> mediated resistance (Omrane et al., 2017). Expanding genotyping approaches beyond single reference genomes was particularly important. Only ~65% of the k-mers aligned to the reference genome while expanding the mapping to a pangenome resolved nearly all k-mer locations <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">28</xref></sup>. K-mer based GWAS identified the dispensable <italic>SdhC3</italic> paralog associated with increased isofetamid-resistance <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref></sup>. Hence, reference-free GWAS is an essential and powerful tool for identifying standing resistance in pathogen species.</p><p id="P21">Functional validation through targeted manipulation of candidate genes is necessary for confirming causal relationships between genetic variations and phenotypic traits. We prioritized loci identified through different GWAS approaches. We confirmed the GWAS mapping of the Thr79Asn substitution in the <italic>SdhC1</italic> gene <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R49">49</xref></sup>. The substitution was detected through k-mer association for carboxin resistance. Furthermore, we shed light on the negative cross-resistance between mutations for anilopyrimidine fungicide resistance. We found that the Glu198Ala substitution in the beta-tubulin gene confers resistance to the anilopyrimidine pyrimethanil revealing a potentially species-specific effect of the mutation. In <italic>B. cinerea</italic>, the activity of anilinopyrimidines fungicides is reversed by the addition of methionine and field resistance is driven by mutations in at least two genes involved in mitochondrial processes. Therefore, anilopyrimidines in <italic>B. cinerea</italic> are thought to primarily target a mitochondrial function connected to methionine biosynthesis <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35">35</xref></sup>, whereas high doses affect tubulin function in <italic>Z. tritici</italic>. We failed to replicate though the GWAS discovery of 10_00421, an MFS associated with terbinafine resistance. One plausible explanation for this observation is epistasis, where the effect of one gene is contingent upon the presence of specific alleles in other genes <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R50">50</xref></sup>. Terbinafine resistance maybe mediated by 10_00421 interacting with other variants including <italic>MFS1</italic> overexpression. Similarly, the IPO323 reference genome background may not be adequate to replicate the mapped resistance effect. Contributions by a structural variant associated with pyrimethanil resistance could also not be replicated. Designing molecular genetic assays replicating GWAS findings are notoriously challenging as associations are contingent to some degree on the genomic background and some relevant genetic variation may not be accounted for. However, more efficient assay designs and the systematic screening of multiple genomic backgrounds for hypothesis testing should reduce this challenge.</p><p id="P22">Overall, our work establishes a comprehensive fungicide resistance atlas recapitulating the emergence of resistance to a multitude of fungicide classes, including most frequently used ones such as DMIs, SDHIs and QoIs. The atlas provides blueprint for functionally validating contributions of individual variants and maps systematically fungicide cross-resistance. We provide concrete insights how pathogen diversity panels should be constructed, how to evaluate and mitigate mapping power limitations, and to what extent geographic and temporal sampling is relevant. Systematic reference-free genotyping accounting for complex variants turned out to be crucial to capture the full spectrum of resistance gains. Building a pangenome-informed atlas of emerging resistance benefits both the discovery of resistance mechanisms and guides towards more sustainable applications of compound mixtures.</p></sec><sec id="S10" sec-type="materials | methods"><title>Material and methods</title><sec id="S11"><title>European diversity panel</title><p id="P23">For resistance monitoring purposes, Syngenta sampled pathogens from commercial and trial sites across Europe. The fungicide resistance monitoring efforts for <italic>Z. tritici</italic> led to a collection of 8607 strains. Strains were selected from the collection based on a hierarchical clustering approach grouping sampling locations into 100-km radius areas. Within each area, we balanced the collection over the 2005-2019 sampling years based on availability. The European diversity panel included 1420 strains from 27 different countries previously sequenced <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">29</xref></sup> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table S1</xref>). Estimation of fungicides application were based on the yearly sale in kg across the continent. The information was obtained based on the average fungicide application within the time range 2011-2021 (DOI:10.2908/aei_fm_salpest09). Wheat production per country was obtained by FAO and was average in tons between 2017-2019. Maps were plotted in ggplot using the package (‘rnaturalearth’) <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R51">51</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R52">52</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="S12"><title>Purification of the European diversity panel</title><p id="P24">All strains included in the European diversity panel were collected from infected leaves across Europe, preferably with visible pycnidia, wrapped in dry paper towels, and packed into a paper envelope for shipment. Upon arrival in the laboratory, samples were labeled with a unique code, and the arrival date was recorded. The leaves were dried, wrapped in fresh paper towels if necessary, and stored at 4°C until further processing. Leaves with symptoms were cut into 2 cm pieces, surface-sterilized in 2% bleach for 2 minutes, and rinsed with sterile distilled water. Leaf cuts were placed on wet filter paper in Petri dishes (1.3 mL water for 9 cm dishes) and incubated at 20°C for 24 hours. Single strains were picked from cirri under a binocular microscope and transferred to V8 agar plates with antibiotics. Plates were incubated for 4-7 days at 20°C. To ensure that only a single genotype was collected per sample, a single spore isolation step was performed for every sample. Single colonies were subcultured on fresh V8 plates and incubated under the same conditions for an additional 7 days. Each isolate was stored independently in a cryovial preserved in liquid nitrogen. Fresh cells harvested from V8 plates incubated at 18°C for a period of five days were used as inoculum for all experiments. Media recipes used in this study have been summarized (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table S11</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S13"><title>Solid culture assays for fungicide sensitivity determination</title><p id="P25">We assessed fungicide sensitivity using relative colony size estimates on solid medium (fixed fungicide concentration). The European diversity panel strains stored at -80C° were arrayed in 96-well cryo-stock plates in skim milk with 20% glycerol (used as mother array plates). From the mother array plates, the strains to be tested were transferred using a 96-floating pin replicator tool (408FS2AS, V&amp;P Scientific Inc.) to 96-well flat bottom plates (model 3370, Corning) pre-filled with 100μl YPD liquid medium and left to grow at 18°C for 7 days to reach a growth plateau. Spore suspensions were not further standardized and directly spotted using a Rotor HDA (Rotor+) (Singer Inc., Watchet, UK) with sterile pins (RePads) (Singer Inc., Watchet, UK) onto AE agar media plates (PlusPlates) amended or not with fungicides. The fungicides were dissolved in DMSO and then mixed with AE-agar to achieve a final concentration of 1% DMSO. Five different fungicide concentrations were applied to achieve final concentrations of 50, 10, 1, 0.1, and 0.01 mg.L<sup>-1</sup> per plate. Single concentrations were then selected for further GWAS studies. Control plates only contained AE-agar with 1% DMSO. Spotted AE-agar plates were incubated at 20°C for 7 days in the dark before imaging. Image capture was performed using a Phenobooth (Singer, Watchet, UK), and image analysis performed with the Phenosuite (version 2.21) software package (Singer Inc., Watchet,) by comparing paired growth areas of colonies grown on control plates without fungicide (DMSO controls) with fungicide-amended plates. The relative growth area on amended media (<italic>area</italic><sub>e</sub>) relative to controls (<italic>area</italic><sub>c</sub>) was estimated using the following formula: <disp-formula id="FD1"><mml:math id="M1"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Relative</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mtext>growth</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mtext>area</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/></mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mtext>area</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/></mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mtext>area</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/></mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>∗</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="P26">Plates with signs of contamination were excluded. Plates with &gt;2x more growth on fungicide-amended plates <italic>vs</italic>. controls were excluded as well. Relative growth estimates and assayed fungicides are reported in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table S1</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table S2</xref>. Fungicide sensitivity of the transformants was determined on solid medium (fixed fungicide concentration). For the spotting assay the suspended spores were spotted on AE media amended with 1% of a 100× DMSO solution of the active ingredients to pre-melted AE-agar. AE media was supplemented with 20,5,2.5 mg.L<sup>-1</sup> of terbinafine and epoxiconazole and each experiment was performed with and without doxycycline (30 mg.L<sup>-1</sup>). We supplemented AE media as well with 10 and 50 mg.L<sup>-1</sup> of carbendazim, 1 and 10 mg.L<sup>-1</sup> of diethofencarb, 20, 50 mg.L<sup>-1</sup> of pyrimethanil and 5,10 and 20 mg.L<sup>-1</sup> of carboxin. Pre-culture of the inoculum and fungicide sensitivity tests were performed as following previously described procedures <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="S14"><title>DNA extraction, Illumina sequencing, and SNP calling</title><p id="P27">Whole-genome sequencing data was previously described <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">29</xref></sup>. For 1134 strains high-quality genomic DNA was extracted using the DNeasy Plant Mini Kits (Qiagen Inc.) following the manufacturer’s instructions. Paired-end sequencing of 250 cycles with an ~500 bp insert size was performed by Novogene Inc. using the Illumina NovaSeq 6000 platform. We used Trimmomatic v.0.39 to trim low-quality sequencing reads and remove adapter contamination in each isolate <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R53">53</xref></sup>. Filtered sequences were aligned to the <italic>Z. tritici</italic> reference genome IPO323 <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R54">54</xref></sup> using Bowtie2 v.2.3.3 <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R55">55</xref></sup>. The Genome Analysis Toolkit (GATK) v.4.0.1.2 <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R56">56</xref></sup> was used for single nucleotide polymorphism (SNP) calling and variant filtration. The GATK HaplotypeCaller was run with the command -emitRefConfidence GVCF and - sample_ploidy 1. Joint variant calling was performed using the tool GenotypeGVCFs merging HaplotypeCaller gvcfs produced for an additional 283 from a previous study <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">29</xref></sup> with the option -maxAlt 2 <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R57">57</xref></sup>. To investigate the impact of sample size on the number of detected alleles, we randomly subsampled the European collection 100 times. The number of strains included in each subsample varied from 100 to 1000. Vcftools v0.1.15 <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R58">58</xref></sup> was used to perform the random subsetting. To estimate the total number of SNPs based on the annotation of the <italic>Z. tritici</italic> 2015 genome <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R59">59</xref></sup>, we used SnpEFF <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R60">60</xref></sup> with the “-csvStats”. Finally, the total number of synonymous and missense point mutations was normalized based on the corresponding gene length (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table S12</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S15"><title>SNP-based genome-wide association mapping and bootstrapping</title><p id="P28">For SNP-based GWAS on the Europe diversity panel, we retained SNPs with a genotyping call rate of ≥90% and a MAF ≥5% resulting in a final set of 472,103 biallelic SNPs (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table S1</xref>). Traits for GWAS included the relative growth estimates for 43 traits (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table S2</xref>). We tested 15 fungicide classes with an over representation of DMI, SDHI, QOI, QII, classes applied in <italic>Z. tritici</italic>. We accounted for relatedness by constructing a genetic relatedness matrix (GRM) among strains using all genome-wide SNPs with the option “-gk 2” in Gemma <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R61">61</xref></sup>. Thus, all the associations were performed using a univariate linear mixed model (MLM+K) where K is the GRM as a random effect: <disp-formula id="FD2"><mml:math id="M2"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>W</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>ε</mml:mi><mml:mo>;</mml:mo><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mo>~</mml:mo><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>ε</mml:mi><mml:mo>~</mml:mo><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula> <italic>y</italic> represents a vector of phenotypic values for <italic>n</italic> individuals; <italic>W</italic> is a matrix of covariates (fixed effects with a column vector of 1), <italic>α</italic> is a vector of the corresponding coefficients, including the intercept; <italic>x</italic> is a vector of the genotypes of the SNP marker, <italic>β</italic> is the effect size of the marker; <italic>u</italic> is a vector of random individual effects; <italic>ε</italic> is a vector of random error; <italic>τ</italic>-1 is the variance of the residual errors; <italic>λ</italic> is the ratio between the two variance components; <italic>K</italic> is the <italic>n</italic> × <italic>n</italic> GRM and <italic>I</italic><sub><italic>n</italic></sub> is an <italic>n</italic> × <italic>n</italic> identity matrix and <italic>MVN</italic><sub><italic>n</italic></sub> represents the multivariate normal distribution. We applied a stringent Bonferroni threshold (<italic>α</italic> = 0.05; <italic>p</italic> = <italic>α</italic> / total number of SNPs) to identify most robust SNP associations. Significant SNPs were annotated using snpEff v5.0e <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R60">60</xref></sup>. We provide links to all association mapping outcomes in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table S13</xref>. To investigate the impact of geographic and temporal distribution on the number of detected resistant alleles, the European diversity panel was split in strains collected from the West and East of Europe after 2016. For the temporal distribution, we split the strains before and after 2016. T-test between relative growth values of West and East and before-after 2016 strains were performed using the command t.test built-in function in R. Subsequently, the results were visualized through figures generated in R ggplot2 and adjusted in Illustrator <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R52">52</xref></sup>. In the Manhattan plot for <italic>p</italic>-value within 0.1 and 0.01 we retained only 1 out of every 30 rows, for <italic>p</italic>-value within than 0.2 and 0.1 we retained only 1 out of every 300 rows and for <italic>p</italic>-value greater than 0.2 we retained only 1 out of every 400 rows for visualization purposes. To investigate the impact of sample size on the number of detected resistant alleles, the number of strains included in each subsample varied from 100 to 800 strains. Vcftools v0.1.15 <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R58">58</xref></sup> and gemma were used to perform the random subsetting and the GWAS. SNPEFF <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R60">60</xref></sup> was utilized to annotate the SNPs and genes based on the <italic>Z. tritici</italic> 2015 genome annotation <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R59">59</xref></sup> (See <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table S14</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table S15</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S16"><title>K-mer based genome-wide association mapping</title><p id="P29">We performed k-mer based GWAS on the same 43 traits used for SNP-based GWAS following a previously described approach <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R62">62</xref></sup>. We used k-mers of 25-bp length as suggested for small genomes such as <italic>Z. tritici</italic> following previous studies <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">28</xref></sup>. Quality-filtered sequencing reads (see above) of 1406 strains from the European diversity panel were used for k-mer screening. K-mers were counted using a two-step process: The canonization involved treating each k-mer and its reverse complement as equivalent. In contrast, non-canonization treats the k-mer and its reverse complement as distinct entities. A k-mer and the reverse complement are supposed to have the same chance to appear in fastq files. However, bias can favor the presence of one of the two forms for some k-mer. Therefore, k-mers were then filtered based on two criteria: (1) a k-mer must appear in both its canonized and non-canonized forms in at least 5% of the strains, and (2) it must appear in both forms in at least 20% of the strains in which it was found. A GRM was estimated with EMMA (Efficient Mixed-Model Association) as an identity-by-state (IBS) matrix under the assumption that each k-mer has a small, random effect on the phenotype. GWAS was performed by using an LMM+K model in Gemma with a likelihood ratio test to determine p-values. Beta estimation and significance testing were performed using the patched version of kmers_gwas.py, incorporating the recommendations outlined (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/voichek/kmersGWAS/issues/53">https://github.com/voichek/kmersGWAS/issues/53</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/voichek/kmersGWAS/issues/91">https://github.com/voichek/kmersGWAS/issues/91</ext-link>). A k-mer was significant when the p-value passed the permutation-based threshold as described by Voichek and Weigel (2020). For all k-mer association mapping see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table S16</xref>. We attempted to map all significant k-mers for each trait to the reference genome using the short-read aligner bowtie v1.2.2 <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R55">55</xref></sup> with the command “-a --best --strata” and retained the k-mers with a unique alignment (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table S4</xref>). We used the center position of the mapped k-mer to the reference genome as a coordinate to inspect nearby features using BEDtools v2.31.0 <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R63">63</xref></sup>. Finally, the proportion of significant k-mers aligning and not aligning across the 19 pangenomes <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">30</xref></sup>, per each fungicide, was obtained with bowtie v1.2.2, with the command “-a –best –strata” (Langmead and Salzberg, 568 2012) (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table S9</xref>). The proportion of significant k-mers aligning and not aligning to I93, UA005, I93 jg.10233 and SV_UA005.jg.10233 regions were obtained with bowtie v1.2.2, with the command “-a –best –strata”. We provided each k-mer association mapping file (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table S13</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S17"><title>TEs detection and association study</title><p id="P30">We performed TE based GWAS on the same 43 traits used for SNP-based GWAS. TE annotation was performed with ngs-te-mapper2 <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R64">64</xref></sup>. This is a three-stage pipeline. In the first stage the sequencing reads are queried against a library of TE sequences, for which we used the TE consensus sequences obtained from 20 fully assembled genomes of 19 global strains <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">30</xref></sup>. The “junction reads” that align both on a TE consensus sequence and on the flanking, genome are used to determine the site of insertion of reference and non-reference TEs. Non reference TEs were categorized as reference TEs when located within proximity (up to 100 bp) to a reference TE of the same family. This adjustment aimed to mitigate potential inaccuracies in detection while enhancing the overall frequency of detected TEs. Consequently, insertions of the identical element within a narrow window were treated as a singular insertion for subsequent analyses. For the association analysis, we set the maf to 1% and we used the relatedness matrix (GRM) estimated from european vcf the genome-wide SNPs using the option “-gk 2” in GEMMA <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R61">61</xref></sup>. A summary of the significant TEs is in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table S6</xref>. We provided each TE association mapping file (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table S13</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S18"><title>CNV genotyping</title><p id="P31">We performed CNV-based GWAS on the same 43 traits used for SNP-based GWAS. We trimmed the Illumina raw reads with Trimmomatic v.0.32 <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R53">53</xref></sup> and mapped to the <italic>Z. tritici</italic> (IPO323) reference genome with Bowtie2 v.2.4.0 very-sensitive-local option. To define copy number variation (CNV) to the dataset (n=1420 samples) we used GATK germline copy number caller v.4.1.9.0<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R56">56</xref></sup> in case mode against a previously constructed GATK CNV cohort model built from 1109 <italic>Z. tritici</italic> genomes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R65">65</xref></sup>. CNV interval was set to 1000 bp windows with no overlap. We filtered for GC content in windows (min=0.1 and max=0.9), as well as extremely low and high read counts (--low-count-filter-count-threshold = 5, -- extreme-count-filter-minimum-percentile = 1, --extreme-count-filter-maximum-percentile=99). We used a prior table for chromosomal ploidy to assign prior probabilities for each ploidystate. Finally, we called CNV genotypes using the Determine Germline Contig Ploidy, Germline CNV Caller and Post process Germline CNV Calls functions in case mode. CNV GWAS analysis involved preprocessing the data by removing duplicated chromosomes, converting CNV events into four categories (more than one copy, one copy, no copy, or missing), and identifying and removing the least frequent allele at each position, retaining only the most frequent allele. The association analysis was conducted using GEMMA <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R61">61</xref></sup> with a minor allele frequency threshold of 5% and with GRM constructed from genome-wide SNPs using the “-gk 2” option. A summary of the significant CNVs is in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table S7</xref>. We provided each CNV association mapping file (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table S13</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S19"><title>Indels-based genome-wide association mapping</title><p id="P32">For Indels-based GWAS on the Europe diversity panel, we retained Indels with a genotyping call rate of ≥90% and a MAF ≥5% resulting in a final set of 23,959 indels. Traits for GWAS included the relative growth estimates for 43 traits (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table S2</xref>). We tested 15 fungicide classes with an over-representation of DMI, SDHI, QOI, QII, classes applied in <italic>Z. tritici</italic>. We accounted for relatedness by constructing a genetic relatedness matrix (GRM) among strains using all genome-wide SNPs with the option “-gk 2” in GEMMA <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R61">61</xref></sup>. Thus, all the associations were performed using a univariate linear mixed model (MLM+K), where K is the GRM as a random effect. A summary of the significant Indels is in (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table S17</xref>). We provided each Indels association mapping file (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table S13</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S20"><title>Mutant selection criteria</title><p id="P33">Locus refinement was conducted employing stringent selection criteria encompassing <italic>p</italic>-value significance, effect size, gene functionality, and mutation type (intragenic vs. intergenic). The significance threshold for the <italic>p</italic>-value was determined by adhering to Bonferroni’s correction. Additionally, we focused on selecting mutations with a beta (&gt;=2), indicative of a twofold effect. Missense point mutations were accorded higher priority over synonymous mutations. Moreover, emphasis was placed on previously characterized functions, such as MFS, and SDH subunits, while structural variants were given preferential consideration. The list of the mutants is in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table S18</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="S21"><title>Molecular methods for transformations</title><p id="P34">All the genes were synthesized by GENEWIZ (Suzhou, China) and were inserted in the multisite pNOV2114 Hyg_gateway. To generate the KO of 10_00421 (KO_ Zt09_10_00421), we designed the final plasmid Hygr_pNOV2114_KO_G10877_MFS. The pNOV2114 backbone was supplemented with a region 799bps upstream the 5’ of 10_00421 gene and 2274 downstream 3’ of the 10_00421 gene. We substitute the 10_00421 gene with a short terminator, followed by the constitutive promoter TrpC <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R66">66</xref></sup>, and with the hygromycin resistance cassette (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Figure 10B</xref> for a graphical overview and supplemental file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table S18</xref> with plasmids sequences). For the structural variants SV_I93.jg.10233 and SV_UA005.jg.10233 we inserted in the IPO323 background with a region of 1560 bps at position 5571672 on chromosome 1. The flanking region included 977 bps upstream and 1000 bps downstream, the position 5571672 on chromosome 1. The Hygr_pNOV2114_jg10233_I93 and Hygr_pNOV2114_jg10233_UA005 included a short terminator, followed by the constitutive promoter TrpC <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R66">66</xref></sup>, followed by the hygromycin resistance cassette and, respectively the structural variants of I93 (1556 bps) and of UA005 (1560 bps). For generating the expression constructs under the control of a tetracycline-repressing promoter we designed a fragment containing the full Tet repressor expression cassette followed by operator sequences fused to mfaI minimal promoter upstream the starting codon of <italic>Mfs1</italic> (Hygr_pNOV2114_OE_G07914.1_MFS1) and 09_00421 (Hygr_pNOV2114_OE_G10877_newMfs). For the Single swap (SW) point mutation we selected a region of 1888 bps encompassing the <italic>beta-tubulin</italic> (pNOV2114_SW_G02218_BetaTUB) gene and a region of 2017 bps encompassing the <italic>SdhC1</italic> gene (pNOV2114_SW_G09103_SDHC). All entry and subsequent binary plasmids were transfer to <italic>A. tumefaciens. Z. tritici</italic> transformation was performed as described previously <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R67">67</xref></sup>. <italic>Z. tritici</italic> transformants were selected on Hygromycine, Carbendazim (AE + 10 mg.L<sup>-1</sup>) or Carboxin (AE + 10 mg.L<sup>-1</sup>) depending by the selection cassette. All clones were then validated by PCR and three combination of primers were tested (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table S19</xref>). For the single-point mutation, a Sanger sequencing step was included to confirm the cloned fragment.</p></sec><sec id="S22"><title>AlphaFold2</title><p id="P35">We further investigated the 3D structure of SDHC1 using AlphaFold2 <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R68">68</xref></sup>. We imputed the sequences SDHC1 (08_00228) to predict the 3D structure. Local Distance Difference Test (lDDT) scores were employed to assess the confidence in amino acid positioning within their local structural environments. While the first few amino acids generally exhibit lower lDDT scores, the score at position 79 was high (approximately 100), indicating a high degree of confidence in its predicted location. However, it’s important to acknowledge that the lDDT score at this position could be influenced by the low coverage of SDHC1 sequences, particularly at the beginning of the protein, within the AlphaFold2 database.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="SM"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1"><label>Supplementary Figure</label><media xlink:href="EMS207331-supplement-Supplementary_Figure.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" id="d71aAcEbB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD2"><label>Supplementary Table</label><media xlink:href="EMS207331-supplement-Supplementary_Table.zip" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="zip" id="d71aAcEcB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack id="S23"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank Nadja Lindenberger, Regula Frey, Salvatore Accardo and Syngenta’s monitoring team for collecting the strains analyzed in this work. Ursula O provided insightful feedback on the manuscript.</p><sec id="S24"><title>Funding</title><p>This work was supported by an Innosuisse grant (32532.1 IP-LS) to GS and DC. DC was supported by Swiss National Science Foundation grants 173265 and 201149.</p></sec></ack><sec id="S25" sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p id="P36">Genome sequencing data is available on the NCBI Sequence Read Archive (accession numbers are provided in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table S1</xref>). Additional datasets are made available in supplementary materials.</p></sec><fn-group><title>Declarations</title><fn fn-type="con" id="FN2"><p id="P37">Author contributions: GP, GS and DC conceived the study, GP performed the research and analyzed the data. GP, DF, DE and CD performed analyses. SFFT provided materials. TB and SMT provided datasets. GS and DC supervised the work and acquired funding. GP, DC and GS wrote the manuscript.</p></fn><fn fn-type="conflict" id="FN3"><p id="P38"><bold>Competing interests</bold>:</p><p id="P39">CD, DE, DF, SFFT and GS were employed by Syngenta at the time of the study. The other authors declare no conflict of interest exists.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><ref id="R1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hellin</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Spatio-temporal distribution of DMI and SDHI fungicide resistance of <italic>ZYMOSEPTORIA TRITICI</italic> throughout EUROPE based on frequencies of key target-site alterations</article-title><source>Pest Manag Sci</source><year>2021</year><volume>77</volume><fpage>5576</fpage><lpage>5588</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34392616</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lockhart</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Chowdhary</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gold</surname><given-names>JAW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The rapid emergence of antifungal-resistant human-pathogenic fungi</article-title><source>Nat Rev Microbiol</source><year>2023</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>818</fpage><lpage>832</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41579-023-00960-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10859884</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37648790</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schürch</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Occurrence of <italic>Aspergillus fumigatus</italic> azole resistance in soils from Switzerland</article-title><source>Med Mycol</source><year>2023</year><volume>61</volume><elocation-id>myad110</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/mmy/myad110</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10653585</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37930839</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y-Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genetic diversity of field Fusarium asiaticum and Fusarium graminearum isolates increases the risk of fungicide resistance</article-title><source>Phytopathol Res</source><year>2023</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>51</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Puccetti</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A large European diversity panel reveals complex azole fungicide resistance gains of a major wheat pathogen</article-title><year>2025</year><comment>Preprint at</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2025.03.19.644200</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Hawkins</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanglard</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Gurr</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Worldwide emergence of resistance to antifungal drugs challenges human health and food security</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2018</year><volume>360</volume><fpage>739</fpage><lpage>742</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29773744</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fouché</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Directed evolution predicts cytochrome <italic>b</italic> G37V target site modification as probable adaptive mechanism towards the QII fungicide fenpicoxamid in <italic>Zymoseptoria tritici</italic></article-title><source>Environ Microbiol</source><year>2022</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>1117</fpage><lpage>1132</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34490974</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rubin</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>EMS and UV irradiation induce unstable resistance against CAA fungicides in Bremia lactucae</article-title><source>Eur J Plant Pathol</source><year>2011</year><volume>129</volume><fpage>339</fpage><lpage>351</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scalliet</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Mutagenesis and Functional Studies with Succinate Dehydrogenase Inhibitors in the Wheat Pathogen Mycosphaerella graminicola</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2012</year><volume>7</volume><elocation-id>e35429</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0035429</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3334918</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22536383</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kretschmer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Fungicide-Driven Evolution and Molecular Basis of Multidrug Resistance in Field Populations of the Grey Mould Fungus Botrytis cinerea</article-title><source>PLoS Pathog</source><year>2009</year><volume>5</volume><elocation-id>e1000696</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1000696</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2785876</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20019793</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Steinhauer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A dispensable paralog of succinate dehydrogenase subunit C mediates standing resistance towards a subclass of SDHI fungicides in Zymoseptoria tritici</article-title><source>PLOS Pathog</source><year>2019</year><volume>15</volume><elocation-id>e1007780</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1007780</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6941823</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31860693</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bellah</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A highly multiplexed assay to monitor pathogenicity, fungicide resistance and gene flow in the fungal wheat pathogen Zymoseptoria tritici</article-title><source>PLOS ONE</source><year>2023</year><volume>18</volume><elocation-id>e0281181</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0281181</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9901794</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36745583</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Torriani</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><name><surname>Brunner</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name><surname>McDonald</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Sierotzki</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>QoI resistance emerged independently at least 4 times in European populations of <italic>Mycosphaerella graminicola</italic>: Qol resistance in <italic>Mycosphaerella graminicola</italic></article-title><source>Pest Manag Sci</source><year>2009</year><volume>65</volume><fpage>155</fpage><lpage>162</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18833571</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Torriani</surname><given-names>SFF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Zymoseptoria tritici: A major threat to wheat production, integrated approaches to control</article-title><source>Fungal Genet Biol</source><year>2015</year><volume>79</volume><fpage>8</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26092783</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cools</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hammond-Kosack</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Exploitation of genomics in fungicide research: current status and future perspectives: Genomics and fungicide research</article-title><source>Mol Plant Pathol</source><year>2013</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>197</fpage><lpage>210</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/mpp.12001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6638899</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23157348</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genomic diversity of the pathogenic fungus Aspergillus fumigatus in Japan reveals the complex genomic basis of azole resistance</article-title><source>Commun Biol</source><year>2024</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>274</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s42003-024-05902-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10940670</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38486002</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>McDonald</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Croll</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Genetic Architecture of Emerging Fungicide Resistance in Populations of a Global Wheat Pathogen</article-title><source>Genome Biol Evol</source><year>2020</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>2231</fpage><lpage>2244</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/gbe/evaa203</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7846115</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32986802</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bartoli</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Roux</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genome-Wide Association Studies In Plant Pathosystems: Toward an Ecological Genomics Approach</article-title><source>Front Plant Sci</source><year>2017</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>763</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2017.00763</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5441063</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28588588</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hartmann</surname><given-names>FE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The complex genomic basis of rapid convergent adaptation to pesticides across continents in a fungal plant pathogen</article-title><source>Mol Ecol</source><year>2021</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>5390</fpage><lpage>5405</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33211369</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Spanner</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genome-Wide Association and Selective Sweep Studies Reveal the Complex Genetic Architecture of DMI Fungicide Resistance in <italic>Cercospora beticola</italic></article-title><source>Genome Biol Evol</source><year>2021</year><volume>13</volume><elocation-id>evab209</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/gbe/evab209</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8459168</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34499119</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hayes</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Overview of Statistical Methods for Genome-Wide Association Studies (GWAS)</chapter-title><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Gondro</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Der Werf</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayes</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><source>Genome-Wide Association Studies and Genomic Prediction</source><publisher-name>Humana Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Totowa, NJ</publisher-loc><year>2013</year><volume>1019</volume><fpage>149</fpage><lpage>169</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23756890</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sánchez-Vallet</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hartmann</surname><given-names>FE</given-names></name><name><surname>Marcel</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name><name><surname>Croll</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nature’s genetic screens: using genome-wide association studies for effector discovery: Nature’s genetic screens</article-title><source>Mol Plant Pathol</source><year>2018</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>3</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/mpp.12592</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6638067</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29226559</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Fungicide-induced transposon movement in Monilinia fructicola</article-title><source>Fungal Genet Biol</source><year>2015</year><volume>85</volume><fpage>38</fpage><lpage>44</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26537535</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Omrane</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Fungicide efflux and the MgMFS1 transporter contribute to the multidrug resistance phenotype in <italic>Z ymoseptoria tritici</italic> field isolates: Fungicide efflux &amp; <italic>MgMFS 1</italic> contribute to MDR in <italic>Z. tritici</italic></article-title><source>Environ Microbiol</source><year>2015</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>2805</fpage><lpage>2823</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25627815</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Omrane</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Plasticity of the <italic>MFS1</italic> Promoter Leads to Multidrug Resistance in the Wheat Pathogen <italic>Zymoseptoria tritici</italic></article-title><source>mSphere</source><year>2017</year><volume>2</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/mSphere.00393-17</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5656749</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29085913</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hawkins</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Paralog Re-Emergence: A Novel, Historically Contingent Mechanism in the Evolution of Antimicrobial Resistance</article-title><source>Mol Biol Evol</source><year>2014</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>1793</fpage><lpage>1802</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/molbev/msu134</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4069618</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24732957</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sanglard</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Finding the needle in a haystack: Mapping antifungal drug resistance in fungal pathogen by genomic approaches</article-title><source>PLOS Pathog</source><year>2019</year><volume>15</volume><elocation-id>e1007478</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1007478</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6355021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30703166</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dutta</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>McDonald</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Croll</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Combined Reference-Free and Multi-Reference Approaches Uncover Cryptic Variation Underlying Rapid Adaptation in Microbial Pathogens</article-title><year>2022</year><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://biorxiv.org/lookup/doi/10.1101/2022.05.16.492091">http://biorxiv.org/lookup/doi/10.1101/2022.05.16.492091</ext-link></comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1011801</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10688896</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37972199</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Feurtey</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A thousand-genome panel retraces the global spread and adaptation of a major fungal crop pathogen</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2023</year><volume>14</volume><elocation-id>1059</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-023-36674-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9958100</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36828814</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Badet</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Oggenfuss</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Abraham</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>McDonald</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Croll</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A 19-isolate reference-quality global pangenome for the fungal wheat pathogen Zymoseptoria tritici</article-title><source>BMC Biol</source><year>2020</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>12</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12915-020-0744-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7014611</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32046716</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="confproc"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Neau</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Patry-Leclaire</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Duplaix</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>A-S</given-names></name><name><surname>Fillinger</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><source>Screen of potential multi-drug resistant Zymoseptoria tritici field isolates reveals genotypic and phenotypic diversity suggesting multiple mechanisms involved in MDR</source><conf-name>16 th european conference on fungal genetics</conf-name><conf-sponsor>Susanne Zeilinger-Migsich and Hubertus Haas</conf-sponsor><conf-loc>Innsbruck, Austria</conf-loc><year>2023</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genome-wide Association Studies in Ancestrally Diverse Populations: Opportunities, Methods, Pitfalls, and Recommendations</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2019</year><volume>179</volume><fpage>589</fpage><lpage>603</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2019.08.051</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6939869</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31607513</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pimentão</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Cuco</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Pascoal</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Cássio</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Castro</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Current trends and mismatches on fungicide use and assessment of the ecological effects in freshwater ecosystems</article-title><source>Environ Pollut</source><year>2024</year><volume>347</volume><elocation-id>123678</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38447649</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fraaije</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Role of Ascospores in Further Spread of QoI-Resistant Cytochrome <italic>b</italic> Alleles (G143A) in Field Populations of <italic>Mycosphaerella graminicola</italic></article-title><source>Phytopathology®</source><year>2005</year><volume>95</volume><fpage>933</fpage><lpage>941</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18944416</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mosbach</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Anilinopyrimidine Resistance in Botrytis cinerea Is Linked to Mitochondrial Function</article-title><source>Front Microbiol</source><year>2017</year><volume>8</volume><elocation-id>2361</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2017.02361</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5714876</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29250050</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hawkins</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Fraaije</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fitness Penalties in the Evolution of Fungicide Resistance</article-title><source>Annu Rev Phytopathol</source><year>2018</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>339</fpage><lpage>360</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29958074</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Che</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multiple-fungicide resistance to carbendazim, diethofencarb, procymidone, and pyrimethanil in field isolates of Botrytis cinerea from tomato in Henan Province, China</article-title><source>Crop Prot</source><year>2016</year><volume>84</volume><fpage>56</fpage><lpage>61</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leroux</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Chapeland</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Desbrosses</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Gredt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Patterns of cross-resistance to fungicides in Botryotinia fuckeliana (Botrytis cinerea) isolates from French vineyards</article-title><source>Crop Prot</source><year>1999</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>687</fpage><lpage>697</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moreno-Sabater</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Terbinafine Resistance in Dermatophytes: A French Multicenter Prospective Study</article-title><source>J Fungi</source><year>2022</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>220</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/jof8030220</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8948947</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35330222</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Drenth</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>McTaggart</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Wingfield</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fungal clones win the battle, but recombination wins the war</article-title><source>IMA Fungus</source><year>2019</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>18</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s43008-019-0020-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7325676</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32647622</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R41"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Feurtey</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A Thousand-Genome Panel Retraces the Global Spread and Climatic Adaptation of a Major Crop Pathogen</article-title><year>2022</year><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://biorxiv.org/lookup/doi/10.1101/2022.08.26.505378">http://biorxiv.org/lookup/doi/10.1101/2022.08.26.505378</ext-link></comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2022.08.26.505378</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R42"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Mechanism of Binding of Prothioconazole to <italic>Mycosphaerella graminicola</italic> CYP51 Differs from That of Other Azole Antifungals</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>2011</year><volume>77</volume><fpage>1460</fpage><lpage>1465</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.01332-10</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3067226</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21169436</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R43"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Prothioconazole and Prothioconazole-Desthio Activities against Candida albicans Sterol 14-α-Demethylase</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>2013</year><volume>79</volume><fpage>1639</fpage><lpage>1645</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.03246-12</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3591943</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23275516</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R44"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cools</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Impact of Recently Emerged Sterol 14α-Demethylase (CYP51) Variants of Mycosphaerella graminicola on Azole Fungicide Sensitivity</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>2011</year><volume>77</volume><fpage>3830</fpage><lpage>3837</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.00027-11</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3127603</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21478305</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R45"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leroux</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Albertini</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Gautier</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gredt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>A-S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mutations in theCYP51 gene correlated with changes in sensitivity to sterol 14α-demethylation inhibitors in field isolates ofMycosphaerella graminicola</article-title><source>Pest Manag Sci</source><year>2007</year><volume>63</volume><fpage>688</fpage><lpage>698</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17511023</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R46"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krishnan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Transposable element insertions shape gene regulation and melanin production in a fungal pathogen of wheat</article-title><source>BMC Biol</source><year>2018</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>78</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12915-018-0543-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6047131</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30012138</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R47"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Milgate</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><name><surname>Solomon</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name><surname>McDonald</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The identification of a transposon affecting the asexual reproduction of the wheat pathogen <italic>Zymoseptoria tritici</italic></article-title><source>Mol Plant Pathol</source><year>2021</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>800</fpage><lpage>816</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/mpp.13064</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8232023</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33949756</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R48"><label>48</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Patry-Leclaire</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Neau</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Pitarch</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>A-S</given-names></name><name><surname>Fillinger</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><source>Plasticity of the MFS1 promotor is not the only driver of Multidrug resistance in Zymoseptoria tritici</source><year>2023</year><comment>Preprint at</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2023.12.27.573052</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R49"><label>49</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rehfus</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Strobel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Bryson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Stammler</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mutations in <italic>sdh</italic> genes in field isolates of <italic>Zymoseptoria tritici</italic> and impact on the sensitivity to various succinate dehydrogenase inhibitors</article-title><source>Plant Pathol</source><year>2018</year><volume>67</volume><fpage>175</fpage><lpage>180</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R50"><label>50</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Campa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>García-Fernández</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferreira</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genome-Wide Association Study (GWAS) for Resistance to Sclerotinia sclerotiorum in Common Bean</article-title><source>Genes</source><year>2020</year><volume>11</volume><elocation-id>1496</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/genes11121496</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7764677</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33322730</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R51"><label>51</label><element-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Massicotte</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>South</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><source>rnaturalearth: World Map Data from Natural Earth. 1.0.1</source><year>2017</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.32614/CRAN.package.rnaturalearth</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R52"><label>52</label><element-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wickham</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>ggplot2: Create Elegant Data Visualisations Using the Grammar of Graphics. 3.5.1</source><year>2007</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.32614/CRAN.package.ggplot2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R53"><label>53</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bolger</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lohse</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Usadel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Trimmomatic: a flexible trimmer for Illumina sequence data</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2014</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>2114</fpage><lpage>2120</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btu170</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4103590</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24695404</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R54"><label>54</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goodwin</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Finished Genome of the Fungal Wheat Pathogen Mycosphaerella graminicola Reveals Dispensome Structure, Chromosome Plasticity, and Stealth Pathogenesis</article-title><source>PLoS Genet</source><year>2011</year><volume>7</volume><elocation-id>e1002070</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1002070</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3111534</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21695235</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R55"><label>55</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Langmead</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Salzberg</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fast gapped-read alignment with Bowtie 2</article-title><source>Nat Methods</source><year>2012</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>357</fpage><lpage>359</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.1923</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3322381</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22388286</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R56"><label>56</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McKenna</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The Genome Analysis Toolkit: A MapReduce framework for analyzing next-generation DNA sequencing data</article-title><source>Genome Res</source><year>2010</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>1297</fpage><lpage>1303</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gr.107524.110</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2928508</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20644199</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R57"><label>57</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van der Auwera</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>O’Connor</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name></person-group><source>Genomics in the Cloud: Using Docker, GATK, and WDL in Terra</source><publisher-name>O’Reilly Media</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Sebastopol, CA</publisher-loc><year>2020</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R58"><label>58</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Danecek</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The variant call format and VCFtools</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2011</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>2156</fpage><lpage>2158</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btr330</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3137218</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21653522</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R59"><label>59</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grandaubert</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhattacharyya</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Stukenbrock</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>RNA-seq-Based Gene Annotation and Comparative Genomics of Four Fungal Grass Pathogens in the Genus <italic>Zymoseptoria</italic> Identify Novel Orphan Genes and Species-Specific Invasions of Transposable Elements</article-title><source>G3 GenesGenomesGenetics</source><year>2015</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>1323</fpage><lpage>1333</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1534/g3.115.017731</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4502367</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25917918</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R60"><label>60</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cingolani</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A program for annotating and predicting the effects of single nucleotide polymorphisms, SnpEff: SNPs in the genome of Drosophila melanogaster strain w <sup>1118</sup> ; iso-2; iso-3</article-title><source>Fly (Austin)</source><year>2012</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>80</fpage><lpage>92</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4161/fly.19695</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3679285</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22728672</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R61"><label>61</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Stephens</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genome-wide efficient mixed-model analysis for association studies</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><year>2012</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>821</fpage><lpage>824</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng.2310</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3386377</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22706312</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R62"><label>62</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Voichek</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Weigel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identifying genetic variants underlying phenotypic variation in plants without complete genomes</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><year>2020</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>534</fpage><lpage>540</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41588-020-0612-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7610390</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32284578</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R63"><label>63</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Quinlan</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>BEDTools: a flexible suite of utilities for comparing genomic features</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2010</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>841</fpage><lpage>842</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btq033</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2832824</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20110278</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R64"><label>64</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Linheiro</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Bergman</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Whole Genome Resequencing Reveals Natural Target Site Preferences of Transposable Elements in Drosophila melanogaster</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2012</year><volume>7</volume><elocation-id>e30008</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0030008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3276498</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22347367</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R65"><label>65</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tralamazza</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Gluck-Thaler</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Feurtey</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Croll</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Copy number variation introduced by a massive mobile element facilitates global thermal adaptation in a fungal wheat pathogen</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2024</year><volume>15</volume><elocation-id>5728</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-024-49913-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11231334</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38977688</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R66"><label>66</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Derbyshire</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Phosphopantetheinyl transferase (Ppt)-mediated biosynthesis of lysine, but not siderophores or DHN melanin, is required for virulence of Zymoseptoria tritici on wheat</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2018</year><volume>8</volume><elocation-id>17069</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-018-35223-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6244202</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30459352</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R67"><label>67</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bowler</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>New capabilities for <italic>Mycosphaerella graminicola</italic> research</article-title><source>Mol Plant Pathol</source><year>2010</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>691</fpage><lpage>704</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1364-3703.2010.00629.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6640411</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20696006</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R68"><label>68</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mirdita</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>ColabFold: making protein folding accessible to all</article-title><source>Nat Methods</source><year>2022</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>679</fpage><lpage>682</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41592-022-01488-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9184281</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35637307</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Flowchart of the fungicide resistance discovery pipeline connecting natural variation to the genetic basis of resistance.</title><p>A: Establishing a comprehensive collection of strains across space and time, designing and optimizing a phenotypic assay to profile fungicide resistance, performing GWAS, and conducting functional validation. B-C: European maps representing European isolate distribution (black dots) and colored the average ton of fungicide applied between 2011 and 2020 and wheat production in between 2017 and 2019. C: Average number of SNP variants derived from a random subsampling of the European collection from 100 up to 1000 strains. D: Percentage of synonymous and missense variants, normalized by gene length across the core chromosomes in the European collection.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS207331-f001"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Sampling distribution and association studies of geographically and sampling epoch-constrained panels.</title><p>(A) Frequency of strains before and after 2015 per year. (B) Relative growth differences for mefentrifluconazole (7 dpi, 0.1 mg.L<sup>-1</sup>) * t-test p-value&lt;0.05. (C) Geographic distribution of strains before and after 2015. (D) Manhattan plot of mefentrifluconazole resistance based on relative growth. For visualization purposes, SNPs have been randomly subsampled. (E) Frequency of strains in the West and East of Europe. (F) Relative growth differences for prothioconazole (7 dpi, 1 mg.L<sup>-1</sup>). (G) Geographic distribution of strains in Western and Eastern Europe. (H) Manhattan plot of prothioconazole resistance based on relative growth values.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS207331-f002"/></fig><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Significant associations (Bonferroni) based on random subsets of strains assayed for mefentrifluconazole and prothiconazole resistance.</title><p>(A-B) The average number of associations above the Bonferroni threshold for various subsample sizes, bootstrapped 100 times. Summaries are based on relative growth values for mefentrifluconazole and prothiconazole. (C-D): Significant association counts for associations in proximity to genes with known functions. Color coding indicates the functional class of the closest gene: purple (<italic>Cyp51</italic>), green (others), pink (close to <italic>Cyp51</italic> – from 7_00451 to 7_00459), light blue (MFS1), red (<italic>Cytb</italic>), light green (others), light green (12_00177).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS207331-f003"/></fig><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Relative colony growth resistance phenotyping and association mapping</title><p>(A): Colony growth in presence of fungicides at 0.01, 0.1, 1, 10 mg.L<sup>-1</sup>. (B): Frequency distribution of relative colony sizes. 0 corresponds to no growth and 100 corresponds to equal growth on control and fungicide medium. C: Manhattan plots showing ignificant associations above the Bonferroni threshold (blue dotted line). D: Venn diagram of SNPs above the Bonferroni threshold. (E) Scatter plot <italic>p</italic>-values above the Bonferroni threshold overlapping with a gene detected for resistance assessments in concentrations 0.1, 1, 10 mg.L<sup>-1</sup> of epoxiconazole and based on relative growth.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS207331-f004"/></fig><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>Relative colony growth resistance phenotyping and impact of colony age (7 vs 14 dpi).</title><p>(A) Azoxystrobin (1 mg.L<sup>-1</sup>), (B) fenpropimorph (1 mg.L<sup>-1</sup>), (C) fenhexamid (50 mg.L<sup>-1</sup>), (D) carboxin (10 mg.L<sup>-1</sup>). The Manhattan plots show brown rectangles corresponding to regions with SNPs significantly associated with resistance. In the scatterplot, the blue color corresponds to SNPs overlapping with genes significantly associated for measurements at 7 dpi and red colors correspond to 14 dpi data.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS207331-f005"/></fig><fig id="F6" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title>SNP and indel variant distribution in the European diversity panel.</title><p>(A) Minor allele frequency distribution of coding and non-coding variants in the European diversity panel. (B) Indel length distribution. (C) Proportion of k-mers aligning (yellow) or lacking positioning (blue) on the reference genome (IPO323) and on the pangenome of the species. (D) Count of the most frequent TE superfamilies present in the European diversity panel split into reference and non-reference TEs.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS207331-f006"/></fig><fig id="F7" position="float"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><title>Construction of a SNP and k-mer based fungicide resistance atlas.</title><p>(A) Scatter plot of SNP <italic>p</italic>-values above the Bonferroni threshold overlapping with genes and for the 43 assays based on relative growth. Fungicides are grouped and colored based on classes: SBI class II, SBI class III, SBI class IV, SDHI, anilino-pyrimidines, DMI, MBC, N-phenyl carbamates, QII, QOI, and others (corresponding to PP-fungicides, dicarboximides, carbamothioic acid derivative, echinocandin, 2-aminonicotinate). (B) Proportion of k-mers aligning (yellow) and not aligning (blue) on the IPO323 genome. (C) Proportion of aligned and un aligned significant k-mers for isofetamid on the species pangenome. In blue, aligning; in yellow, proportion not aligning to the pangenome. (D) Manhattan plot for the chromosome 3 of positions 3.1-3.3 Mb and a synteny plot of the same region represented by the reference genomes Aus01 and 3D7 strains highlighting the rearrangement of the locus. In red, TEs; in yellow, annotated gene regions.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS207331-f007"/></fig><fig id="F8" position="float"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><title>Profiling and functional validation the Thr79Asn variant in <italic>SdhC1</italic> associated with carboxin resistance.</title><p>(A) Manhattan plot of carboxin resistance variants (10 mg.L<sup>-1</sup>) with k-mers (circles) and SNPs (triangles). (B) Zoom on the k-mers mapping to the <italic>SdhC</italic>1 gene region at 820.7-821.4 kb on chromosome 8. Multiple sequence alignment of k-mers matching either the Thr residue (in green) or Asn (in red) at the codon position 79. (C) Frequency of the Asn residue across the European diversity panel. (D) Violin plot comparing relative growth values in strains with Thr and Asn. (E) Functional validation of mutants shown on a spotting assay including IPO323 (wild type), dKU70 (green dots) and SDHC_Thr79Asn (red dots) on AE media amended with carboxin at 5, 10, 20 mg.L<sup>-1</sup>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS207331-f008"/></fig><fig id="F9" position="float"><label>Figure 9</label><caption><title>Profiling and functional validation of the Glu198Ala variant in <italic>beta-tubulin</italic> associated with pyrimethanil, diethofencarb, and carbendazim resistance.</title><p>(A) Correlation of relative growth values between carbendazim and diethofencarb. (B) Correlation of relative growth values between pyrimethanil and carbendazim. (C) Correlation of relative growth values between pyrimethanil and diethofencarb. (D) Fungal colonies in the presence of pyrimethanil (50 mg.L<sup>-1</sup>), diethofencarb (10 mg.L<sup>-1</sup>), and carbendazim (10 mg.L<sup>-1</sup>). (E) Zoomed Manhattan plot of significant SNPs for pyrimethanil, diethofencarb, and carbendazim, highlighting the <italic>beta-tubulin</italic> gene region (506.4–506.6 kb) on chromosome 1. Each significant SNP is labeled with the resistance-associated allele (Thr or Asn). (F) Functional validation of the mutants shown on the spotting assay with IPO323 (wild type), dKU70 (green dots), and SDHC_Thr79Asn (red dots) on AE medium amended with pyrimethanil (50 mg.L<sup>-1</sup>), diethofencarb (1 mg.L<sup>-1</sup>), and carbendazim (10 mg.L<sup>-1</sup>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS207331-f009"/></fig><fig id="F10" position="float"><label>Figure 10</label><caption><title>Profiling and functional validation of the role of the 10_00421 gene in terbinafine resistance.</title><p>(A) Manhattan plot of significant SNPs (triangle) and k-mers (dots) for terbinafine relative growth values (0.1 mg.L<sup>-1</sup>). Shapes identify variant types including SNPs (dots) and k-mers (triangle). (B) Construct design of OE_MFS1, OE_Zt09_10_00421, and KO_Zt09_10_00421 and (C) spotting assays on terbinafine (0.02 mg.L<sup>-1</sup>), with and without doxorubicin (dox) (at 30 mg.L<sup>-1</sup>). (D) Synteny plot of the chromosome 1 (5.568-5.577 Mb) of genomes IPO323 and I93. In light blue, gene regions; in dark blue is the gene jg.10233. (E) Proportion of k-mers aligning (yellow) or not (blue) to the genomes of IPO323, I93, and 19UA005; proportion k-mers aligning (yellow) or not (blue) to the structural variant (SV) affecting the gene jg.10233 in the strains I93 and 19UA005. (F) Spotting assay for pyrimethanil concentration (50 mg.L<sup>-1</sup>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS207331-f010"/></fig></floats-group></article>