<!DOCTYPE article
 PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" article-type="preprint"><?all-math-mml yes?><?use-mml?><?origin ukpmcpa?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">bioRxiv</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>bioRxiv : the preprint server for biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2692-8205</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">EMS205860</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2025.05.22.655486</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="archive">PPR1025295</article-id><article-version-alternatives><article-version article-version-type="status">preprint</article-version><article-version article-version-type="number">1</article-version></article-version-alternatives><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>MIK2-clade receptor function in perception of a <italic>Fusarium</italic>-derived elicitor is conserved among different plant families</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Maroschek</surname><given-names>Julian</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rösgen</surname><given-names>Yvonne</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rössner</surname><given-names>Clemens</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Snoeck</surname><given-names>Simon</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Schwechheimer</surname><given-names>Claus</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zipfel</surname><given-names>Cyril</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hückelhoven</surname><given-names>Ralph</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CR1">✉</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Phytopathology, TUM School of Life Sciences Weihenstephan, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/02kkvpp62</institution-id><institution>Technical University of Munich</institution></institution-wrap>, <postal-code>85354</postal-code><city>Freising</city>, <country country="DE">Germany</country></aff><aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Plant Systems Biology, TUM School of Life Sciences Weihenstephan, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/02kkvpp62</institution-id><institution>Technical University of Munich</institution></institution-wrap>, <postal-code>85354</postal-code><city>Freising</city>, <country country="DE">Germany</country></aff><aff id="A3"><label>3</label>Developmental Biology of Plants, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/033eqas34</institution-id><institution>Justus-Liebig-University</institution></institution-wrap>, <postal-code>35392</postal-code><city>Gießen</city>, <country country="DE">Germany</country></aff><aff id="A4"><label>4</label>Institute of Plant and Microbial Biology, Zurich-Basel Plant Science Center, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/02crff812</institution-id><institution>University of Zurich</institution></institution-wrap>, <postal-code>8008</postal-code><city>Zurich</city>, <country country="CH">Switzerland</country></aff><aff id="A5"><label>5</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/02tdtzx53</institution-id><institution>The Sainsbury Laboratory</institution></institution-wrap>, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/026k5mg93</institution-id><institution>University of East Anglia</institution></institution-wrap>, <addr-line>Norwich Research Park</addr-line>, <postal-code>NR4 7UH</postal-code><city>Norwich</city>, <country country="GB">United Kingdom</country></aff><author-notes><corresp id="CR1">
<label>✉</label><email>hueckelhoven@tum.de</email>
</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted"><day>25</day><month>05</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="preprint"><day>23</day><month>05</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><permissions><ali:free_to_read/><license><ali:license_ref>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is licensed under a <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">CC BY-NC 4.0 International license</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p id="P1">Plants constantly monitor their environment to adapt to potential threats to their health and fitness. This involves cell-surface receptors that can detect conserved microbe-associated molecular patterns (MAMPs) or endogenous immunogenic signals, initiating signaling pathways to induce broad-spectrum disease resistance, known as pattern-triggered immunity (PTI). In <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>, the leucine-rich repeat receptor kinase (LRR-RK) MIK2 is an exceptionally versatile receptor involved in the perception of the vast family of Brassicales-specific endogenous SCOOP peptides as well as potential MAMPs derived from <italic>Fusarium</italic> and related fungi. Although only plant species belonging to the order of Brassicales encode genes for SCOOP peptides and show SCOOP-responsiveness, the <italic>Fusarium</italic>-derived elicitor fraction also induces PTI responses in plants from other lineages. In this study, we demonstrate that <italic>Fusarium</italic> elicitor-responsiveness and proteins belonging to the MIK2-clade are widely conserved among seed plants. We identified a MIK2-clade protein from tomato, which shares properties of <italic>At</italic>MIK2 in the perception of the <italic>Fusarium</italic> elicitor but not of SCOOP peptides. Tomato mutants lacking the receptor show compromised PTI responses to the fungal elicitor and enhanced susceptibility to infection by <italic>Fusarium oxysporum</italic>. Our data provide insights into the evolutionary trajectory of MIK2 as a multifunctional receptor involved in plant immunity.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec id="S1" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p id="P2">To respond appropriately to changes in their environment and potential dangers, plants require the ability to sense and transmit signals coming from their surroundings. A major threat to plant fitness and survival is posed by pathogenic microbes or other pests. Therefore, plants constantly monitor their environment with membrane-localized pattern recognition receptors (PRRs). PRRs are receptor kinases (RKs) or receptor proteins (RPs) that evolved to recognize conserved molecules of microbial origin. Collectively, these molecular signatures are referred to as microbe-associated molecular patterns (MAMPs) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">Boller and Felix, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">Basu <italic>et al</italic>., 2018</xref>). In addition, specialized receptors detect plant-derived danger signals, known as damage-associated molecular patterns (DAMPs). Those primary endogenous danger signals are passively released by injury or destruction caused by invading pathogens or other pests. In addition, so-called secondary endogenous danger signals are actively processed and released after tissue damage or other stimuli. Due to similarities to metazoan cytokines, secondary danger molecules are also commonly referred to as phytocytokines (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">Gust <italic>et al</italic>., 2017</xref>).</p><p id="P3">After ligand-perception by PRRs, the signal feeds into a conserved signaling pathway to induce broad-spectrum disease-resistance, known as pattern-triggered immunity (PTI) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37">Jones and Dangl, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">Boller and He, 2009</xref>). In the case of proteinaceous ligands, PRRs belonging to the class of leucine-rich repeat receptor kinases (LRR-RKs) readily recruit co-receptors of the SOMATIC EMBRYOGENESIS RECEPTOR-LIKE KINASE (SERK) family, including BRI1-ASSOCIATED RECEPTOR KINASE 1 (BAK1) or BAK1-LIKE 1 (BKK1) in a ligand-dependent manner to form activated receptor-complexes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">DeFalco and Zipfel, 2021</xref>). In addition, receptor-like cytoplasmic kinases (RLCKs) such as BOTRYTIS-INDUCED KINASE 1 (BIK1) and PBS1-LIKE 1 (PBL1) constitutively associate with the cytoplasmic region of the PRR-complexes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27">Hailemariam <italic>et al</italic>., 2024</xref>). Upon ligand-perception and receptor-activation, the signal is transduced to the cytoplasm where an array of immune-signaling events is induced. Following the activation and release of RLCKs from the receptor-complex, plants initiate the rapid and transient elevation of cytoplasmic free-calcium concentration [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>cyt</sub>, the production of reactive oxygen species (ROS) in the apoplast and the phosphorylation-dependent activation of mitogen-activated protein kinase (MAPK)-cascades (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41">Köster <italic>et al</italic>., 2022</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R71">Sun and Zhang, 2022</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R81">Wu <italic>et al</italic>., 2023</xref>). Through the activation of transcriptional regulators, including transcription factors (TFs) and chromatin modifiers, extensive transcriptional reprogramming is initiated (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">Bigeard <italic>et al</italic>., 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R46">Li <italic>et al</italic>., 2016</xref>). Assisted by posttranscriptional, epigenetic and posttranslational regulators, the transcriptional reprogramming culminates in a broad array of defense responses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R46">Li <italic>et al</italic>., 2016</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R79">Withers and Dong, 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R72">Tao <italic>et al</italic>., 2023</xref>). Those include the synthesis and emission of phytohormones like ethylene, the biosynthesis and secretion of antimicrobial compounds like phytoalexins as well as the reinforcement of plant cell walls by the deposition of lignin and callose (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33">Hückelhoven, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">Ahuja <italic>et al</italic>., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">Bednarek, 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R91">Zipfel, 2013</xref>).</p><p id="P4">PTI signaling is tightly controlled by both negative and positive feedback mechanisms, to enhance weak or attenuate overshooting immune responses. One of those mechanisms is also mediated by membrane-localized receptors that perceive the aforementioned phytocytokines. These endogenous peptides can be actively released by enzymatic processing, regulate intercellular signaling and can function simultaneously in growth and development as well as in immunity, positioning them as key players in the growth-defense trade-off (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R64">Rzemieniewski and Stegmann, 2022</xref>).</p><p id="P5">In most cases, plant PRRs and receptors for phytocytokines are restricted to the perception of either exogenous or endogenous signals. However, there are very few exceptions, like the NEMATODE-INDUCED LRR-RLK 1 (NILR1) receptor from <italic>Solanum tuberosum</italic> (potato), which perceives both the exogenous nematode-associated molecular pattern (NAMP) ascaroside and the endogenous plant hormone brassinosteroid (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32">Huang <italic>et al</italic>., 2024</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31">Huang <italic>et al</italic>., 2023</xref>, 2023; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32">Huang <italic>et al</italic>., 2024</xref>). Another example for a receptor with dual ligands is MALE DISCOVERER 1-INTERACTING RECEPTOR-LIKE KINASE 2 (MIK2) from <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>. MIK2 is the receptor for the extensive family of SERINE-RICH ENDOGENOUS PEPTIDEs (SCOOPs), which are specific to the order of Brassicales, with 50 members in <italic>A. thaliana</italic> alone (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">Hou <italic>et al</italic>., 2021</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R59">Rhodes <italic>et al</italic>., 2021</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R69">Snoeck <italic>et al</italic>., 2024</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R86">Yang <italic>et al</italic>., 2023a</xref>). Aside a conserved SxS motif, which is found in the large majority of SCOOPs, the amino acid sequences of the individual peptides are highly variable (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">Gully <italic>et al</italic>., 2019</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R69">Snoeck <italic>et al</italic>., 2024</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R86">Yang <italic>et al</italic>., 2023a</xref>). Most recently, AI-assisted structural modeling coupled with phylogenomics revealed that the highly conserved SxS motif mediates binding to MIK2 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R69">Snoeck <italic>et al</italic>., 2024</xref>). This was then supported by crystallography and cryoEM structural studies, which also indicated that MIK2 <italic>N</italic>-glycosylation facilitates its interaction with the co-receptor BAK1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36">Jia <italic>et al</italic>., 2024</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R83">Wu <italic>et al</italic>., 2024</xref>).</p><p id="P6">In addition to the perception of the large and diverse set of SCOOPs, MIK2 is also indispensable for PTI responses triggered by a proteinaceous elicitor found in extracts of diverse <italic>Fusarium</italic> and related fungal species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">Coleman <italic>et al</italic>., 2021</xref>), consistent with MIK2’s role in basal resistance against <italic>Fusarium oxysporum</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R75">van der Does <italic>et al</italic>., 2017</xref>). Even though the true nature of the fungal elicitor is yet to be revealed, bioinformatics approaches have identified SCOOP-LIKE (SCOOPL) peptide sequences as epitopes within different <italic>Fusarium</italic> proteins. When synthesized based on the characteristics of major plant SCOOPs, those SCOOPL peptides also triggered PTI responses in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">Hou <italic>et al</italic>., 2021</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R59">Rhodes <italic>et al</italic>., 2021</xref>). However, most of the proposed SCOOPL peptide sequences are hardly conserved beyond the fungal genus <italic>Fusarium</italic>, while comparable MIK2-dependent elicitor activity could also be found in extracts from the related fungal genus <italic>Trichoderma</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">Coleman <italic>et al</italic>., 2021</xref>). Additionally, the <italic>Fusarium</italic> elicitor triggers PTI-like responses in various non-Brassicales plant species, including soybean, tomato and barley, while the perception of SCOOP and SCOOPL peptides is restricted to the order of Brassicales (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">Coleman <italic>et al</italic>., 2021</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R69">Snoeck <italic>et al</italic>., 2024</xref>).</p><p id="P7">Here we report about an LRR-RK from tomato with phylogenetic origin common to <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> MIK2 (<italic>At</italic>MIK2). This tomato protein belonging to the MIK2-clade shares functions of <italic>At</italic>MIK2 in response to the <italic>Fusarium</italic> elicitor and resistance to <italic>Fusarium</italic> infection, but not in perception of plant SCOOPs or synthetic <italic>Fusarium</italic> SCOOPL peptides, thus suggesting that the Brassicales-specific function of MIK2 as a SCOOP receptor has arisen from a more ancient function as a PRR for a <italic>Fusarium</italic>-derived MAMP.</p></sec><sec id="S2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="S3"><title><italic>Fusarium</italic> elicitor-responsiveness and proteins of the MIK2-clade are conserved among different plant families</title><p id="P8">Bioinformatics approaches already identified SCOOP-LIKE peptide sequences embedded in proteins of <italic>Fusarium oxysporum</italic> f.sp. <italic>conglutinans</italic> isolate <italic>Fo5176</italic> (<italic>Foc</italic>SCOOPL) that show <italic>At</italic>MIK2-dependent immunogenic activity in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>. We first wanted to test whether predicted fungal SCOOPL peptides share elicitor activity with the enriched elicitor fraction generated from mycelial extracts of the fungal pathogen <italic>Fusarium oxysporum</italic> (EnFOE), outside the order of Brassicales. Similar to <italic>At</italic>SCOOP12, the <italic>Foc</italic>SCOOPL<sup>FOXB_11846</sup> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R83">Wu <italic>et al</italic>., 2024</xref>) and <italic>Foc</italic>SCOOPL<sup>F9F6H0</sup> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R59">Rhodes <italic>et al</italic>., 2021</xref>) peptides only triggered the accumulation of reactive oxygen species (ROS) in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> and <italic>Brassica rapa</italic>, while species like soybean (<italic>Glycine max</italic>), tomato (<italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic>) and barley (<italic>Hordeum vulgare</italic>) did not respond to treatment with either of these peptides (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">fig. 1b-d</xref>). In contrast, treatment with EnFOE triggered a transient ROS burst also in most of the tested non-Brassicales plant species (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">fig. 1a</xref>). Interestingly, the solanaceous species <italic>Nicotiana benthamiana</italic> is unresponsive to <italic>At</italic>SCOOP12, <italic>Foc</italic>SCOOPLs as well as EnFOE, but, like all other plant species tested, responds to treatment with flg22 and chitin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">fig. 1a-d</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">fig. S1a-b</xref>). This raises the possibility that EnFOE-induced ROS production in some non-Brassicales plant species is triggered by immunogenic patterns of a different nature than the proposed SCOOPL <italic>Fusarium</italic> peptides.</p><p id="P9">Differences in the responsiveness to the <italic>Fusarium</italic> elicitor and SCOOP/SCOOPL peptides in different plants motivated us to look for putative orthologues of <italic>At</italic>MIK2 in diverse plant families, which might share its role in the perception of the <italic>Fusarium</italic> elicitor, but have not evolved to recognize SCOOPs. Hence, we searched for proteins with structural and phylogenetic relation to <italic>At</italic>MIK2 outside the order of Brassicales. A phylogenetic analysis including representatives of major angiosperm lineages and Ginkgo (a gymnosperm) revealed that genes of the MIK2-clade are evolutionarily conserved in seed plants (100% support), but could not be identified in bryophytes, lycophytes and monilophytes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">fig. 1e-f</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">fig. S1c</xref>). A duplication event in a common ancestor of monocots, dicots and water lilies gave rise to the MIK2-clade as sister to the MIK2-sister-clade (94% support), while only the latter contains two sequences of the basic angiosperm <italic>Amborella trichopoda</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">fig. 1e-f</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">fig. S1c</xref>). Both clades harbor representatives of the orders of Poales, Solanales, Brassicales and Fabales. Within the MIK2-clade, several duplication events occurred, e.g. between one and two at the root of dicots (81% and 41% support). However, most retained gene duplications appear at family- or even species-level (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">fig. 1e-f</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">fig. S1c</xref>). Lower gene copy numbers indicate that MIK2-sister-clade genes are largely purged after duplication events and are even completely lost in most species belonging to the Brassicales (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">fig. 1e-f</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">fig. S1c</xref>). In contrast, we observed that MIK2-clade genes are more often retained. We counted between four (chickpea) and twenty-three (peanut) copies in Fabales, between five (tomato) and eleven (potato) copies in Solanales and in grasses from one in rice up to seventeen copies in barley (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">fig. 1f</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">fig. S1c</xref>). Due to relatively low annotation certainty of the Solanales plants <italic>Nicotiana benthamiana, Nicotiana tabacum</italic> and wild tomato <italic>Solanum chilense</italic>, those species were only included in the phylogenetic tree, but we cannot make statements on actual copy numbers (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">fig. 1e-f</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">fig. S1c</xref>).</p><p id="P10">Interestingly, Brassicales members tend to retain fewer copies, ranging between one in <italic>Schrenkiella parvula</italic> and six in <italic>Capsella rubella</italic>, than other Rosids and Asterids like potato with eleven copies or sunflower with fourteen copies (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">fig. 1f</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">fig. S1c</xref>). We identified five MIK2-clade genes in tomato, while <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> exhibits two copies, <italic>MIK2</italic> (AT4G08850) and <italic>MIK2-LIKE</italic> (AT1G35710), as a result of a brassica-specific duplication (100% support). A duplication specific to Fabales (100% support) followed by several lineage specific duplications resulted in twenty maintained genes in <italic>Glycine max</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">fig. 1f</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">fig. S1c</xref>). In summary, genes of the MIK2-clade are evolutionarily conserved in seed plants and show a highly species-dependent pattern of gene duplication and retention.</p></sec><sec id="S4"><title>A MIK2-clade protein from <italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic> shows similar properties to <italic>At</italic>MIK2 in <italic>Fusarium</italic> elicitor perception</title><p id="P11">To continue our search for putative orthologues of <italic>At</italic>MIK2 in the perception of the <italic>Fusarium</italic> elicitor, we decided to further investigate the MIK2-clade proteins identified in <italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic>, a plant species that is commonly affected by <italic>Fusarium</italic> infections (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R50">McGovern, 2015</xref>). For this purpose, we cloned the five tomato MIK2-clade genes as well as the gene from the MIK2-sister-clade, which we have designated as <italic>SlMIK2-A to -E</italic> and <italic>SlMIK2-SISTER</italic>, respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">fig. 2a</xref>). Subsequently, we transiently expressed the proteins in <italic>Nicotiana benthamiana</italic>, which naturally does not respond to EnFOE- or SCOOP-treatment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">fig. 1a-d</xref>). Since this approach has proven successful for <italic>At</italic>MIK2 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">Coleman <italic>et al</italic>., 2021</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R59">Rhodes <italic>et al</italic>., 2021</xref>), we included the wildtype and a kinase-dead version (<italic>At</italic>MIK2^km, K802A) of the protein as positive and negative controls. All proteins tested expressed in <italic>Nicotiana benthamiana</italic>, even though <italic>Sl</italic>MIK2-E expressed to a lower degree when compared to the others (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">fig. S2c</xref>).</p><p id="P12">Similar to what was reported before, leaf discs from <italic>Nicotiana benthamiana</italic> transiently over-expressing <italic>At</italic>MIK2 showed a clear ROS-burst when treated with <italic>At</italic>SCOOP12. By contrast, this was not the case when leaves expressed <italic>At</italic>MIK2^km or either of the <italic>Sl</italic>MIK2 or <italic>Sl</italic>MIK2-SISTER proteins, where no <italic>At</italic>SCOOP12-induced ROS accumulation could be detected (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">fig. 2c</xref>). Similarly, treatment with the <italic>Foc</italic>SCOOPL peptides induced ROS production only if leaves were expressing the wildtype version of <italic>At</italic>MIK2 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">fig. S2a-b</xref>). In contrast, treatment with EnFOE did not only induce ROS accumulation in leaves transformed with wildtype <italic>At</italic>MIK2, but also transient expression of the <italic>Sl</italic>MIK2-A protein conferred EnFOE-sensitivity to <italic>Nicotiana benthamiana</italic>, whereas this could not be observed for any of the other tomato proteins tested (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">fig. 2b</xref>). These results suggest that <italic>Sl</italic>MIK2-A might serve a function comparable to that of <italic>At</italic>MIK2 in perception of EnFOE, but not of <italic>At</italic>SCOOP or <italic>Foc</italic>SCOOPL peptides.</p><p id="P13">Additional evidence for a probable common evolutionary origin of <italic>AtMIK2</italic> and genes belonging to the tomato MIK2-clade was gathered through a synteny analysis. This revealed that a conserved genomic region harbors <italic>AtMIK2</italic> and four of the tomato MIK2-clade genes in the respective plant species (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">fig. 2d</xref>). While <italic>SlMIK2-B</italic> to -<italic>D</italic> reside in tandem on the minus strand, <italic>SlMIK2-A</italic> is located on the plus strand and separated from the others by an unrelated gene (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">fig. 2d</xref>).</p><p id="P14">With a 1048-amino acid long protein sequence and a predicted LRR-RK structure containing 25 LRRs, the <italic>Sl</italic>MIK2-A protein shows 48% identity and 65% similarity to the sequence of <italic>At</italic>MIK2 (1045 amino acids, 24 LRRs). Interestingly, <italic>SlMIK2-A</italic> is predicted to be spliced into four different variants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">fig. 2e</xref>). This might be the reason for the characteristic double-band observed on the western blot, since the C-terminal Myc-tag would allow the detection of the three splice-variants that share the same C-terminus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">fig. 2e, 2g</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">fig. S2c</xref>). Even though the protein resulting from splice-variant 1 is the most similar to <italic>At</italic>MIK2, we have cloned all four splice-variants individually, either by removal of the additional introns in the region coding for the extracellular domain (splice-variants 2 &amp; 4), shortening and changing the C-terminal sequence coding for the cytoplasmic-domain (splice-variant 3), or mutation of splice-sites (splice-variant 1).</p><p id="P15">The individual splice-variants were transiently over-expressed in <italic>Nicotiana benthamiana</italic>, alongside the unmodified (genomic) and a kinase-dead version of <italic>Sl</italic>MIK2-A (^km, K791A), as well as <italic>At</italic>MIK2 and <italic>At</italic>MIK2^km (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">fig. 2g</xref>). Only splice-variant 1 conferred EnFOE-sensitivity to <italic>Nicotiana benthamiana</italic> comparable to <italic>At</italic>MIK2 and <italic>Sl</italic>MIK2-A when expressed through its genomic sequence (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">fig. 2f</xref>). None of the individually expressed splice-variants were able to confer <italic>At</italic>SCOOP12-sensitivity to <italic>Nicotiana benthamiana</italic> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">fig. S2d</xref>). As is the case for <italic>At</italic>MIK2, <italic>Sl</italic>MIK2-A requires a functional kinase domain to confer EnFOE-sensitivity to <italic>Nicotiana benthamiana</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">fig. 2f</xref>). Through RT-qPCR analysis with splice-variant-specific primers, we identified that transcripts of splice-variant 1 are the most abundant in tomato wildtype plants. While splice-variants 2 and 4 are on average 74% and 55% less abundant than splice-variants 1, expression of splice-variant 3 was barely detectable (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">fig. S2e</xref>). In summary, the most abundantly transcribed splice-variant of <italic>SlMIK2-A</italic> is also the only one translated into a protein that can confer EnFOE-sensitivity to <italic>Nicotiana benthamiana</italic>. The expression of this splice-variant was also induced 2 hours after treatment with EnFOE or chitin in whole plants and 21 days after infection with <italic>Fusarium oxysporum</italic> f.sp. <italic>lycopersici</italic> (strain <italic>Fol007</italic>) in shoot stems (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">fig. 2h</xref>).</p><p id="P16">Similar to what has been observed for <italic>At</italic>MIK2 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R75">van der Does <italic>et al</italic>. 2017</xref>), also <italic>Sl</italic>MIK2-A (splice-variant 1) seemingly localizes to the plasma membrane (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">fig. 2i-j</xref>). We transiently co-expressed <italic>At</italic>MIK2-GFP and <italic>Sl</italic>MIK2-A-mCherry in <italic>Nicotiana benthamiana</italic> and imaged with confocal microscopy 36 hours after infiltration (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">fig. 2i</xref>). Measurement of the fluorescence intensity along the indicated ROI line show an overlap of GFP- and mCherry-signals at the cell periphery (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">fig. 2j</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S5"><title><italic>Sl</italic>MIK2-A forms ligand-induced complexes with tomato BAK1 orthologues and depletes elicitor-activity from EnFOE</title><p id="P17">Since <italic>At</italic>MIK2 has previously been shown to form ligand-induced complexes with the common co-receptor <italic>At</italic>BAK1 after treatment with EnFOE, <italic>At</italic>SCOOPs and <italic>Fusarium</italic> SCOOPL peptides (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">Coleman <italic>et al</italic>., 2021</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">Hou <italic>et al</italic>., 2021</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R59">Rhodes <italic>et al</italic>., 2021</xref>), we tested whether similar complexes are induced between their tomato counterparts. Tomato has two proteins with a high sequence similarity to <italic>At</italic>BAK1, termed <italic>Sl</italic>SERK3a and <italic>Sl</italic>SERK3b, both of which have been implicated to function in plant innate immunity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R49">Mantelin <italic>et al</italic>., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R55">Peng and Kaloshian, 2014</xref>). We tested ligand-induced complex formation between <italic>Sl</italic>MIK2-A and both tomato BAK1 orthologues in co-immunoprecipitation (CoIP) experiments using transient expression in <italic>Nicotiana benthamiana</italic>. The receptor pair from <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> was used as positive control, while <italic>Sl</italic>MIK2-B, which does not seem to be involved in the perception of EnFOE (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">fig. 2 b</xref>), was included as negative control.</p><p id="P18">Reflecting previous results from the gain-of-function assay (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">fig. 2c</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">fig. S2a</xref>), treatment with <italic>At</italic>SCOOP12 and the <italic>Foc</italic>SCOOPL<sup>FOXB_11846</sup> peptide induced a ligand-induced complex between <italic>At</italic>MIK2 and <italic>At</italic>BAK1, while no clear interaction between any of the tomato proteins could be observed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">fig. 3b</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S3a</xref>). In contrast, EnFOE-treatment induced complex formation between <italic>At</italic>MIK2 and <italic>At</italic>BAK1 but also triggered the interaction of <italic>Sl</italic>MIK2-A with either <italic>Sl</italic>SERK3a or <italic>Sl</italic>SERK3b (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">fig. 3a</xref>). However, EnFOE did not induce association between <italic>Sl</italic>MIK2-B and either of the tomato BAK1 orthologues (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">fig. 3a</xref>). These results suggest a conserved perception mechanism of the <italic>Fusarium</italic> elicitor in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> and <italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic>.</p><p id="P19">Since the results from the CoIP experiments indicate interaction between an elicitor-active molecule in EnFOE and the ectodomain of <italic>At</italic>MIK2 as well as <italic>Sl</italic>MIK2-A, we sought for a way to further substantiate this supposition. For this purpose, we adopted a so-called ligand depletion assay (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R67">Shu <italic>et al</italic>., 2021</xref>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">fig. 3c</xref>). We expressed affinity-tagged ectodomains (N-terminal TwinStrep tag) of different LRR-RKs in <italic>Nicotiana benthamiana</italic> and collected them with apoplastic wash fluids (AWFs). We subsequently coupled the tagged ectodomains to affinity columns, while other apoplastic molecules were washed out. We then run preparations containing our elicitor activity through the ectodomain-lined columns and subsequently analyzed the flow-through for depletion of the ligands. Since all our ligands of interest induce a transient elevation of cytosolic-free calcium concentrations [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>cyt</sub>, we checked for remaining elicitor activity with a highly sensitive Ca<sup>2+</sup> bioassay using apoaequorin-expressing <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> Columbia-0 wildtype (Col-0<sup>AEQ</sup>) and <italic>mik2</italic><sup>AEQ</sup> mutants generated in the same genetic background <italic>via</italic> CRISPR/Cas9-mediated knock-out (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">fig. S3c</xref>).</p><p id="P20">The ectodomains of both <italic>At</italic>MIK2 (e<italic>At</italic>MIK2) and <italic>Sl</italic>MIK2-A (e<italic>Sl</italic>MIK2-A) expressed to a satisfying degree in <italic>Nicotiana benthamiana</italic>. As controls, we have additionally expressed the ectodomains of <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> CLAVATA1 (e<italic>At</italic>CLV1) and <italic>Sl</italic>MIK2-B (e<italic>Sl</italic>MIK2-B), both of which are not assumed to interact with any of our ligands of interest. As expected, preparations containing <italic>At</italic>SCOOP12 [25 nM], that were run through columns lined with the ectodomains of its <italic>bona fide</italic> receptor <italic>At</italic>MIK2, were depleted from elicitor activity and triggered no calcium transient distinguishable between Col-0<sup>AEQ</sup> wildtype and <italic>mik2</italic><sup>AEQ</sup> mutant seedlings (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">fig. 3e</xref>). In contrast, the same preparations that were run through columns lined with e<italic>At</italic>CLV1, induced a clear MIK2-dependent calcium-response in Col-0<sup>AEQ</sup> seedlings (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">fig. 3e</xref>). The same is true for both e<italic>Sl</italic>MIK2-A and e<italic>Sl</italic>MIK2-B, where neither of the ectodomains were able to deplete <italic>At</italic>SCOOP12 activity from the preparations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">fig. 3e</xref>). <italic>At</italic>SCOOP12 activity was hence specifically depleted by <italic>At</italic>MIK2 ectodomains but not by any other LRR ectodomain tested.</p><p id="P21">We then used the same set-up for the EnFOE preparations. Similar to <italic>At</italic>SCOOP12, columns lined with <italic>At</italic>MIK2 fully depleted the elicitor activity from EnFOE, while preparations filtered through e<italic>At</italic>CLV1-lined columns retained the ability to induce an <italic>At</italic>MIK2-dependent calcium transient in Col-0<sup>AEQ</sup> wildtype seedlings (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">fig. 3d</xref>). Columns lined with the ectodomain of <italic>Sl</italic>MIK2-A also depleted EnFOE preparations from elicitor activity, and the respective flow-through did not trigger a calcium response in wildtype seedlings that significantly exceeded that of the <italic>mik2</italic><sup>AEQ</sup> mutants. Preparations filtered through the columns lined with e<italic>Sl</italic>MIK2-B still harbored <italic>At</italic>MIK2-dependent elicitor activity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">fig. 3d</xref>). The ectodomain of tomato <italic>Sl</italic>MIK2-A could hence specifically deplete the elicitor activity from EnFOE that is perceived <italic>At</italic>MIK2-dependently in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>. This suggests that ectodomains of <italic>At</italic>MIK2 and <italic>Sl</italic>MIK2-A have affinity to the same elicitor activity in EnFOE. Neither of the ectodomains tested could deplete the control peptide flg22, where all unbound fractions still harbored comparable <italic>At</italic>FLS2-dependent elicitor activity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">fig. 3f</xref>). To confirm approximately equal amounts of purified ectodomains used in each assay, proteins were subsequently eluted from the columns and visualized by western blot analysis (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">fig. S3b</xref>).</p><p id="P22">Taken together, these results further substantiate the proposed dual role of <italic>At</italic>MIK2 both in the perception of endogenous SCOOP peptides and the exogenous <italic>Fusarium</italic> elicitor, while the phylogenetically related <italic>Sl</italic>MIK2-A protein exclusively interacts with EnFOE-contained elicitor activity and has not evolved to participate in the perception of SCOOPs.</p></sec><sec id="S6"><title><italic>Sl</italic>MIK2-A is important for EnFOE-induced PTI responses and resistance against <italic>Fusarium oxysporum</italic> infection in tomato</title><p id="P23">To confirm the role of <italic>Sl</italic>MIK2-A in EnFOE-induced PTI responses in the native system, we generated two independent CRISPR/Cas9-mediated knock-out mutants in tomato. Both <italic>Slmik2-A</italic><sup>CRISPR</sup> lines have homozygous frame-shift mutations within the first 500 base pairs (bp) of the coding sequence, introducing premature stopcodons and affecting all 4 possible splice-variants (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">fig. S3d</xref>). The corresponding wildtype control was transformed with a control construct (lacking the sequences of the guide RNAs) and has undergone tissue culture alongside the CRISPR mutants (azygous wildtype control). T-DNAs were segregated out in subsequent generations.</p><p id="P24">We first tested the tomato mutants for ROS production after elicitor treatment. When treated with EnFOE, both <italic>Slmik2-A</italic><sup>CRISPR</sup> mutants showed a significantly reduced EnFOE-induced accumulation of ROS when compared to the azygous wildtype control (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">fig. 4a</xref>). However, ROS production in response to the fungal elicitor chitin was not altered by mutation of <italic>SlMIK2-A</italic>, since the wildtype and both mutant lines responded to a comparable degree (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">fig. 4b</xref>). Similarly, the EnFOE-induced accumulation of the phytohormone ethylene was significantly lower in the CRISPR mutants when compared to the corresponding wildtype control (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">fig. 4c</xref>). Interestingly, both mutants also showed a reduced chitin-induced ethylene accumulation when compared to the wildtype, which was significantly lower in line #2. Notably, even wildtype plants required relatively high concentrations of chitin (500 μg/mL) for the induction of a measurable accumulation of ethylene (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">fig. 4d</xref>). However, ethylene production in response to flg22 was on similar levels between all three plant lines tested (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">fig. 4e</xref>), indicating that the mutants do not have a general impairment in MAMP-induced ethylene accumulation. Taken together, similar to <italic>At</italic>MIK2 in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>, loss of <italic>Sl</italic>MIK2-A in tomato leads to reduced sensitivity to treatment with EnFOE.</p><p id="P25">Finally, we wanted to see whether the loss of <italic>Sl</italic>MIK2-A has an influence on the susceptibility of tomato towards infection with <italic>Fusarium oxysporum</italic> f.sp. <italic>lycopersici</italic>. We inoculated 2-week-old seedlings with the spores of the fungal isolates <italic>Fol</italic>007 <italic>via</italic> root-dip infection (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R51">Mes <italic>et al</italic>., 1999</xref>). Growth parameters of infected plants (fresh-weight, plant height) were assessed 3 weeks post infection and calculated relative to those of mock-treated plants. On average, <italic>Fol007</italic>-infected azygous wildtype control plants showed around 8% reduction of fresh-weight compared to mock-treated plants, while the impact on both <italic>Slmik2-A</italic><sup>CRISPR</sup> mutants was significantly higher, with reductions of around 21% on average (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">fig. 4f</xref>, left panel). Similarly, also reductions of plant height in the mutants averaged around 21% and were significantly higher than those observed in the wildtype control plants, which on average showed a reduction of around 12% (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">fig. 4g</xref>, left panel). Nevertheless, general fresh-weight and plant height of mock-treated plants were not significantly different between wildtype control and either of the mutant lines (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">fig. 4f-g</xref>, right panels). In summary, loss of <italic>Sl</italic>MIK2-A does not generally impact growth parameters like fresh-weight and plant height in uninfected tomato plants. However, infection with <italic>Fusarium oxysporum</italic> f.sp. <italic>lycopersici</italic> strain <italic>Fol007</italic> has a significantly higher negative impact on <italic>Slmik2-A</italic><sup>CRISPR</sup> mutants than on the corresponding azygous wildtype control.</p></sec></sec><sec id="S7" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><sec id="S8"><title><italic>Fusarium</italic> elicitor-responsiveness and proteins of the MIK2-clade are conserved among different plant families</title><p id="P26">The <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana At</italic>MIK2 receptor is an interesting example of a PRR that is involved in the perception and integration of both endogenous and exogenous peptide signals. Most of the previously reported phenotypes of <italic>Atmik2</italic> mutants, including reduced salt-stress tolerance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38">Julkowska <italic>et al</italic>., 2016</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R75">van der Does <italic>et al</italic>., 2017</xref>), compromised responses to cell wall damage (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R75">van der Does <italic>et al</italic>., 2017</xref>) and enhanced susceptibility to herbivory (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R70">Stahl <italic>et al</italic>., 2022</xref>) could be directly or indirectly linked to its role as receptor for the large family of endogenous SCOOP peptides (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R86">Yang <italic>et al</italic>., 2023a</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R89">Zhai <italic>et al</italic>., 2024</xref>). In contrast, the elevated susceptibility to <italic>Fusarium oxysporum</italic> infection caused by loss of <italic>At</italic>MIK2 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R75">van der Does <italic>et al</italic>., 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">Coleman <italic>et al</italic>., 2021</xref>) could not necessarily be attributed to the SCOOP-MIK2 signaling module (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R86">Yang <italic>et al</italic>., 2023a</xref>). These findings further support a SCOOP-independent role of <italic>At</italic>MIK2 in the perception of an exogenous signal coming from <italic>Fusarium</italic> fungi. Peptide motifs with similarity to SCOOPs can be found embedded in various <italic>Fusarium</italic> proteins. When synthesized according to the predicted characteristics of plant SCOOPs, which are 13 amino acids in length and do not have posttranslational modifications, also the SCOOP-LIKE (SCOOPL) peptides from <italic>Fusarium</italic> induce PTI responses in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> reminiscent of those induced by the plant endogenous peptides (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">Hou <italic>et al</italic>., 2021</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R59">Rhodes <italic>et al</italic>., 2021</xref>). SCOOP peptides are, however, only encoded in genomes of plant species belonging to the order Brassicales, and only members of this plant order show responsiveness to SCOOPs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">Gully <italic>et al</italic>., 2019</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R69">Snoeck <italic>et al</italic>., 2024</xref>). Similarly, the synthetic SCOOPL peptides do not trigger any responses in non-Brassicales plant species (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">fig. 1b-d</xref>). In contrast, EnFOE does not only induce responses in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> and related species, but also in plants from other plant lineages like soybean, tomato and barley (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">Coleman <italic>et al</italic>., 2021</xref>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">fig. 1a</xref>). These findings could suggest that said other plant species might be responsive to additional elicitor active molecules in EnFOE, which are not perceived by <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>. However, it is also conceivable that the SCOOPL peptides identified so far are not responsible for MIK2-dependent elicitor activity observed in EnFOE, at least not in their bioinformatically predicted and synthetic form. Even the reported peptide sequences of plant SCOOPs are still mainly based on bioinformatic predictions and could deviate significantly in their natural appearance and function, as recently suggested for <italic>At</italic>SCOOP10 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">Guillou <italic>et al</italic>., 2022</xref>). Variations in the sequence of peptide elicitors can lead to loss of recognition by certain plant species, while others are able to tolerate shorter minimal motifs. This has for example been demonstrated for bacterial flagellin, where the flg22 epitope is perceived by <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> and tomato, while the shorter flg15 motif only triggers responses in tomato (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">Felix <italic>et al</italic>., 1999</xref>). Another example of divergent perception requirements on the same elicitor by different plant species has been shown for SCP (small cysteine-rich protein) from <italic>Sclerotinia sclerotiorum</italic>. While perception by <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> depends on the tertiary structure of the SCP, closely related <italic>Brassicaceae</italic> species also perceive the SCP fragments in their linear form (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R87">Yang <italic>et al</italic>., 2023b</xref>). To conclusively verify the true identity and characteristics of the elicitor active molecule in EnFOE, the current bioinformatic efforts should additionally be supported by biochemical approaches in the future.</p><p id="P27">Even though MIK2 in its role as SCOOP receptor has been demonstrated to be conserved only within the order Brassicales (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R69">Snoeck <italic>et al</italic>., 2024</xref>), our phylogenetic analysis revealed that genes of the MIK2-clade are evolutionarily conserved in seed plants and display a highly family- and even species-dependent pattern of duplication and retention (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">fig. 1e-f</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">fig. S1c</xref>). This might have been driven by different environmental conditions and pathogen pressures encountered by different plant species over the course of evolution. Neo-functionalization and retention of duplicated receptors, for example by obtaining new ligand-specificities to recognize additional microbial signatures, might have been advantageous in specific locations and during times of high pathogen pressure. Such receptors could have become obsolete and subsequently been lost once plants managed to avoid certain pathogens by different means, for example <italic>via</italic> the adaptation to new environmental conditions that are not favorable for these microbes. This could have for example been the case for the herbivore-associated molecular pattern (HAMP) receptor INR, which is specific to the clade of Phaseoloid legumes and has been independently lost in some of the species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R68">Snoeck <italic>et al</italic>., 2022</xref>). Even though it is common knowledge that classical MAMPs are usually highly conserved microbial structures that are not easily altered by the pathogens (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">Boller and Felix, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">Couto and Zipfel, 2016</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R56">Ranf, 2017</xref>), this must not necessarily be the case for every MAMP in a newly evolved ligand-receptor relation. It is conceivable that quite a few novel interactions are readily lost again due to insufficient conservation of the ligand and only good matches lead to the manifestation of a lasting ligand-receptor relation and subsequently the retention of the receptor. Even the prominent flg22 epitope, although considered highly conserved, has polymorphic sequences in certain bacteria that managed to evade immune-detection by most plant species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">Fürst <italic>et al</italic>., 2020</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R78">Wei <italic>et al</italic>., 2020</xref>). Interestingly, members of Brassicales seem to retain fewer MIK2-clade gene copies compared to species belonging to other plant orders (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">fig. 1e-f</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">fig. S1c</xref>). This could be related to their gained ability to perceive SCOOP peptides and hence their involvement in various biological processes. A duplication might lead to an imbalance in multiple, usually finely tuned signaling pathways and hence not be readily retained.</p><p id="P28">Surprisingly, in contrast to other plant species tested, <italic>Nicotiana benthamiana</italic> is unresponsive to treatment with EnFOE. Whether this exemption is due to the lack of a suitable MIK2-clade protein cannot be finally demonstrated, since the available genomic data is incompletely annotated. Even though two <italic>N. benthamiana</italic> proteins might share a common origin with <italic>At</italic>MIK2 according to our phylogenetic analysis, they form a deviating cluster away from other Solanales proteins and do neither come back to <italic>At</italic>MIK2 or tomato MIK2-clade proteins as top hit when reblasted against the respective proteomes. It is nevertheless possible that EnFOE actually triggers responses in wildtype <italic>Nicotiana benthamiana</italic>, which simply stay below our detection limit, since even elicitation with high concentrations of flg22 or chitin only induce comparably weak ROS responses in this plant species (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">fig. S1a-b</xref>).</p><p id="P29">Taken together, the demonstrated EnFOE-responsiveness in different plant species and our phylogenetic analysis raise the possibility of a conserved perception mechanism for the <italic>Fusarium</italic> elicitor involving proteins of the MIK2-clade across different plant orders.</p></sec><sec id="S9"><title>A MIK2-clade protein from <italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic> shows similar properties to <italic>At</italic>MIK2 in <italic>Fusarium</italic> elicitor perception</title><p id="P30">Since genes of the MIK2-clade show a highly species-dependent pattern of gene duplication and retention (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">fig. 1e-f</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">fig. S1c</xref>), identification of a clear functional orthologue of <italic>At</italic>MIK2 in terms of EnFOE perception was difficult merely based on the phylogenetic relation. Therefore, we tested all five proteins of the MIK2-clade as well as the protein from the MIK2-sister-clade from the Solanales species <italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic>. Indeed, transient over-expression of the <italic>Sl</italic>MIK2-A protein conferred EnFOE-sensitivity to <italic>Nicotiana benthamiana</italic> comparable to <italic>At</italic>MIK2, while this was not the case for the other tomato proteins of the MIK2- or MIK2-sister-clade (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">fig. 2b</xref>). In line with the lack of responsiveness of <italic>Solanum lycopsericum</italic> to treatment with <italic>At</italic>SCOOP12 and <italic>Foc</italic>SCOOPL peptides (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">fig. 1b-d</xref>), neither of the tested tomato proteins were able to confer sensitivity to respective elicitors to <italic>Nicotiana benthamiana</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">fig. 2c</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">fig. S2a-b</xref>). These results further support the hypothesis of a conserved EnFOE perception mechanism that requires proteins of the MIK2-clade in different plant orders, whereas the perception of SCOOPs has evolved only in members of Brassicales (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R69">Snoeck <italic>et al</italic>., 2024</xref>).</p><p id="P31">Additional support that <italic>At</italic>MIK2 and <italic>Sl</italic>MIK2-A might derive from a common ancestor and hence share a conserved function in the perception of EnFOE, is provided by our synteny analysis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">fig. 2d</xref>). Both receptor genes reside at a conserved genomic region in respective plant species. Interestingly, the syntenic locus in <italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic> additionally harbors the genes coding for <italic>Sl</italic>MIK2-B, -C and -D (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">fig. 2d</xref>), which are not able to confer EnFOE-sensitivity to <italic>N. benthamiana</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">fig. 2a</xref>). Intriguingly, the intracellular domain of <italic>Sl</italic>MIK2-C is almost identical to that of <italic>Sl</italic>MIK2-A, while its extracellular domain shows higher similarity to that of <italic>Sl</italic>MIK2-B, potentially representing a product of recombination (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R48">Man <italic>et al</italic>., 2020</xref>). This is not the case for <italic>Sl</italic>MIK2-D, which is overall more similar to <italic>Sl</italic>MIK2-B (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">table S1</xref>).</p><p id="P32">Interestingly, <italic>SlMIK2-A</italic> is predicted to be spliced into 4 different variants, leading to variations in both the resulting ecto- and the kinase-domain (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">fig. 2e</xref>). In contrast, no comparable splice-variants that lead to alterations in the ectodomain are formed from <italic>AtMIK2</italic>. However, there are similarities between <italic>SlMIK2-A</italic> splice variant #3 and <italic>MIK2.2</italic>, both of which have a prolonged intron, resulting in shorter intracellular domains and sequence deviating c-termini. In both plant species, splice-variant #1 is predominantly expressed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">fig. 2e</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">fig. S2e</xref>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R75">van der Does <italic>et al</italic>., 2017</xref>) and translated into functional proteins involved in the perception of EnFOE, as demonstrated by our gain-of-function assay in <italic>Nicotiana benthamiana</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">fig. 2f</xref>). It has already been demonstrated that alternative splicing plays an important role in the fine-tuning of plant immune responses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43">Kufel <italic>et al</italic>., 2022</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">Godinho <italic>et al</italic>., 2024</xref>). For example, in the absence of infection, the S-domain receptor-like kinase Nt-Sd-RLK from <italic>Nicotiana tabacum</italic> is spliced to produce a shorter variant, lacking a kinase domain. Upon stimulation of tobacco cells with lipopolysaccharides (LPS), the splicing pattern shifts to favor the expression of a longer, signaling-competent variant that includes an active kinase domain (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R65">Sanabria and Dubery, 2016</xref>).</p><p id="P33">The expression of PRRs like <italic>FLS2</italic> and <italic>AtMIK2</italic> has been shown to be transcriptionally upregulated after treatment with elicitors like flg22 or <italic>At</italic>SCOOP12 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">Hou <italic>et al</italic>., 2021</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R93">Zipfel <italic>et al</italic>., 2004</xref>). Similarly, the transcription of <italic>SlMIK2-A</italic> (splice-variant 1) is induced after treatment with EnFOE or chitin as well as by infection with <italic>Fusarium oxysporum</italic> f.sp. <italic>lycopersici</italic> strain <italic>Fol007</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">fig. 2h</xref>). This upregulation of PRRs upon perception of MAMPs is thought to serve as a positive feedback mechanism to enhance perception capabilities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">Boller and Felix, 2009</xref>). As expected for a signaling-competent LRR-RK, <italic>Sl</italic>MIK2-A requires an active kinase domain to confer EnFOE-sensitivity to <italic>N. benthamiana</italic> and localizes to the plasma membrane (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">fig. 2f; 2i-j</xref>).</p><p id="P34">We could not confirm the function of <italic>Sl</italic>MIK2-A observed <italic>in Nicotiana benthamiana</italic> by complementation assays in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana mik2</italic> mutants. Even though we tried to express the protein in different variations (genomic sequence, coding sequence, codon-optimized synthetic sequence, chimeric proteins with <italic>At</italic>MIK2), with different tags (C-terminal cMyc, C-terminal GFP, N-terminal TwinStrep, untagged) and under the control of different promotors (<italic>p35S, pUBQ5, pAtMIK2</italic>), we did not obtain lines that stably expressed the protein of interest to a level detectable by western blot analysis (data not shown). This is reminiscent of problems with heterologous expression of <italic>Sl</italic>FLS2 in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>, which was speculated to be caused by failed recognition of the signal peptide or misfolding followed by subsequent discarding <italic>via</italic> ER-associated protein degradation (ERAD) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R60">Robatzek <italic>et al</italic>., 2007</xref>). Taken together, with <italic>Sl</italic>MIK2-A we identified a prime candidate for a MIK2 orthologue, which shares phylogenetic relations, a syntenic locus, a similar subcellular localization and EnFOE-related functions with <italic>At</italic>MIK2.</p></sec><sec id="S10"><title><italic>Sl</italic>MIK2-A forms EnFOE-induced complexes with tomato BAK1 orthologues and depletes elicitor-activity from EnFOE</title><p id="P35">For the perception of proteinaceous MAMPs like flg22 and elf18, respective PRRs commonly form ligand-induced complexes with members of the SERK family in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">Chinchilla <italic>et al</italic>., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R62">Roux <italic>et al</italic>., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">Heese <italic>et al</italic>., 2007</xref>) and similar mechanisms are in place in plants of other lineages (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R55">Peng and Kaloshian, 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R78">Wei <italic>et al</italic>., 2020</xref>). Also treatment with SCOOP peptides and EnFOE induces the association between <italic>At</italic>MIK2 with the coreceptor <italic>At</italic>BAK1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">Coleman <italic>et al</italic>., 2021</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">Hou <italic>et al</italic>., 2021</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R59">Rhodes <italic>et al</italic>., 2021</xref>). Similar to <italic>At</italic>MIK2 and <italic>At</italic>BAK1, <italic>Sl</italic>MIK2-A forms EnFOE-induced complexes with tomato BAK1 orthologues <italic>Sl</italic>SERK3a or <italic>Sl</italic>SERK3b when co-expressed in <italic>Nicotiana benthamiana</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">fig. 3a</xref>). In contrast, treatment with <italic>At</italic>SCOOP12 or <italic>Foc</italic>SCOOPL<sup>FOXB_11846</sup> peptide does not trigger interactions between the tomato receptor pairs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">fig. 3b</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">fig S3a</xref>). These results support an interaction between <italic>Sl</italic>MIK2-A and EnFOE and further substantiate the existence of a conserved mechanism for the perception of the <italic>Fusarium</italic> elicitor in different plant orders.</p><p id="P36">An additional support for interaction between the elicitor-active molecule in EnFOE and the ectodomain of <italic>At</italic>MIK2 and <italic>Sl</italic>MIK2- A is provided by our specially adopted ligand-depletion assay (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R67">Shu <italic>et al</italic>., 2021</xref>). We filtered elicitor preparations through ectodomain-lined affinity columns and analyzed the flow-through for remaining <italic>At</italic>MIK2-dependent elicitor activity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">fig. 3c-e</xref>). Indeed, columns lined with e<italic>At</italic>MIK2 or e<italic>Sl</italic>MIK2-A fully depleted <italic>At</italic>MIK2-dependent elicitor-activity from EnFOE flow-through (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">fig. 3d</xref>). These results also indicate that both ectodomains interact with the same elicitor molecules, since e<italic>Sl</italic>MIK2-A depletes the activity that is subsequently triggering <italic>At</italic>MIK2-dependent calcium-responses in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> seedlings (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">fig. 3d</xref>). In line with all previous results, <italic>At</italic>SCOOP12 is only depleted by the ectodomain of <italic>At</italic>MIK2, while this is not the case for e<italic>Sl</italic>MIK2-A (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">fig. 3e</xref>). The depleting activity of the <italic>At</italic>MIK2 ectodomain in our assay also does not seem to be due to a high degree of unspecific binding capacity of the receptor, since flg22 preparations that passed the e<italic>At</italic>MIK2-lined columns still harbored comparable <italic>At</italic>FLS2-dependent elicitor activity to those run through columns lined with all other tested ectodomains (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">fig. 3f</xref>). Therefore, the depletion assay that we have adopted and customized specifically for our purpose seems to be a useful tool to gain first insights into receptor-ligand interactions. Even though there are quite a few elaborate <italic>in vitro</italic> analytical approaches available to study plant receptor-ligand interactions, those often require costly equipment as well as knowledge about identity and concentrations of both interaction partners (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R66">Sandoval and Santiago, 2020</xref>). In combination with a sensitive bio-assay for the reliable readout of ligand depletion, our assay provides a simple and relatively inexpensive method to study ligand-receptor interactions on a basic level, similar to a comparable method published before (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R67">Shu <italic>et al</italic>. 2021</xref>). Our assay might be especially useful if the molecular nature of the ligand is still unknown or is not available in a purified form, as is the case with EnFOE.</p></sec><sec id="S11"><title><italic>Sl</italic>MIK2-A is important for EnFOE-induced PTI responses and resistance against <italic>Fusarium oxysporum</italic> infection in tomato</title><p id="P37">Comparable to <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana mik2</italic> mutants, knock-out of <italic>SlMIK2-A</italic> led to reduced PTI responses to the enriched <italic>Fusarium oxysporum</italic> elicitor. However, in contrast to the basically full loss of responsiveness in <italic>Atmik2</italic> mutants, <italic>Slmik2-A</italic> mutants still showed residual responses to EnFOE (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">Coleman <italic>et al</italic>., 2021</xref>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">fig. 4a; 4c</xref>). A possible explanation could be that the enrichment of EnFOE was initially optimized for <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> with the goal to eliminate all non-<italic>At</italic>MIK2-dependent elicitor activity from the preparations. It therefore is possible that tomato is perceiving an additional elicitor molecule present in EnFOE that is not perceived by <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>, for example by a PRR that is not conserved between different plant families, as it is quite often the case (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R92">Zipfel <italic>et al</italic>., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R57">Ranf <italic>et al</italic>., 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R77">Wang <italic>et al</italic>., 2016</xref>). It is also possible that a different epitope of the same elicitor is perceived by an additional receptor that is not phylogenetically related to MIK2, as is the case with tomato <italic>Sl</italic>FLS2 and <italic>Sl</italic>FLS3, which perceive different motifs of bacterial flagellin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">Hind <italic>et al</italic>., 2016</xref>). Future efforts to identify the true nature and characteristics of the molecule in EnFOE that triggers MIK2-dependent PTI responses will help to answer this question. Even though none of the other tomato proteins of the MIK2-clade and MIK2-sister-clade were able to confer EnFOE-sensitivity to <italic>Nicotiana benthamiana</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">fig. 2b</xref>), we cannot finally exclude that they might also be involved in the perception of EnFOE in the native system.</p><p id="P38">Surprisingly, while we could not observe differences in chitin-triggered ROS production between <italic>Slmik2-A</italic><sup>CRISPR</sup> mutants and the wildtype control (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">fig. 4b</xref>), the chitin-induced accumulation of ethylene was reduced in the mutants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">fig. 4d</xref>). However, flg22-induced accumulation of ethylene was not compromised, showing that the mutants are not generally impaired in MAMP-induced ethylene responses (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">fig. 4e</xref>). Interestingly, also loss of <italic>At</italic>MIK2 leads to reduced responses to certain other MAMPs like flg22 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R59">Rhodes <italic>et al</italic>., 2021</xref>) and <italic>At</italic>MIK2 has been proposed to serve as a scaffolding component for the coordination of perception events in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">Delplace <italic>et al</italic>., 2024</xref>). Potentially loss of <italic>Sl</italic>MIK2-A has a similar effect on certain other PTI-signaling pathways and outputs in tomato. Nevertheless, these results demonstrate an important contribution of <italic>Sl</italic>MIK2-A mainly to EnFOE-induced PTI responses in tomato.</p><p id="P39">The reduced ability of <italic>Slmik2-A</italic><sup>CRISPR</sup> mutants to recognize and respond to a danger signal coming from <italic>Fusarium</italic> also translates into an enhanced susceptibility to infection with the pathogen (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">fig. 4f-g</xref>). We deliberately chose a strain of <italic>Fusarium oxysporum</italic> f.sp. <italic>lycopersici</italic> (<italic>Fol007</italic>), which only mildly affects our wildtype control plants. It is known that <italic>Fol</italic> strains can actively interfere with and dampen PTI-signaling <italic>via</italic> the secretion of specialized effector proteins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">Di <italic>et al</italic>., 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R73">Tintor <italic>et al</italic>., 2020</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R44">Lamo <italic>et al</italic>., 2021</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">Blekemolen <italic>et al</italic>., 2023</xref>) and it was shown that the Avr2 effector from <italic>Fol</italic> affects PTI responses triggered by EnFOE when expressed in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">Coleman <italic>et al</italic>., 2021</xref>). Hence, if EnFOE-induced PTI is already partially shut down by the pathogen, the contribution a single involved RK has on overall resistance would most likely become small. Already without interference by pathogens, loss of a single PRR is sometimes not sufficient to cause alterations in resistance phenotypes, most likely due to the extensive arsenal of additional PRRs that perceive different MAMPs and act as an efficient backup system in the case of failure of one (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R93">Zipfel <italic>et al</italic>., 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">Boller and Felix, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">Fan <italic>et al</italic>., 2022</xref>). Even in a natural setting plants can survive the loss of a single PRR, as demonstrated by the <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> ecotypes Ws-0 and Cvi-0, which carry natural loss-of-function mutations in the FLS2 receptor (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">Gómez-Gómez <italic>et al</italic>., 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">Dunning <italic>et al</italic>., 2007</xref>). Interestingly, contributions of individual PRRs to overall resistance can also be diminished when the pathogens are supported to overcome the first layers of pre-invasive resistance, which was shown when bacteria are infiltrated in leaves rather than being sprayed on them (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R93">Zipfel <italic>et al</italic>., 2004</xref>). Nevertheless, even though we also assisted the <italic>Fol007</italic> strain by damaging the root tissue of our tomato plants prior inoculation with the spores, we could observe a stronger negative impact of infection on plant growth in our <italic>Slmik2-A</italic><sup>CRISPR</sup> mutants, with significantly enhanced reduction in plant height and fresh-weight when compared to the wildtype control (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">fig. 4f-g</xref>). This positive contribution of <italic>Sl</italic>MIK2-A to tomato resistance towards <italic>Fusarium</italic> infection might potentially be even more pronounced in a natural setting with a largely undamaged root system. In the laboratory setting, however, we had to damage the roots prior to inoculation to obtain reproducible results.</p><p id="P40">We here present insights into the evolutionary trajectory of a multifunctional plant PRR. <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> MIK2 is perceiving the exceptionally large and diverse family of endogenous SCOOP peptides while simultaneously being involved in the recognition of a yet to be identified danger signal deriving from <italic>Fusarium</italic> and related fungi (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">Coleman <italic>et al</italic>., 2021</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">Hou <italic>et al</italic>., 2021</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R59">Rhodes <italic>et al</italic>., 2021</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R69">Snoeck <italic>et al</italic>., 2024</xref>).</p><p id="P41">There are a few examples of cell-surface receptors with dual ligands, including <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> CARD1/HPCA1 involved in the perception of quinone and H<sub>2</sub>0<sub>2</sub> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R45">Laohavisit <italic>et al</italic>., 2020</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R82">Wu <italic>et al</italic>., 2020</xref>), potato NILR1 perceiving the NAMP ascaroside and the endogenous plant hormone brassinosteroid (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32">Huang <italic>et al</italic>., 2024</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31">Huang <italic>et al</italic>., 2023</xref>, 2023; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32">Huang <italic>et al</italic>., 2024</xref>) or the <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> RLP30 detecting SCP peptides from oomycetes and fungi as well as SCP-nonhomologous signals from bacteria (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R87">Yang <italic>et al</italic>., 2023b</xref>). Similar flexibility can also be observed for certain intracellular receptors which can perceive different microbial effector molecules (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">Brabham <italic>et al</italic>., 2024</xref>). On the other hand there are examples of single ligands that are perceived by multiple related receptors, like is the case for IDA and the LRR-RKs HAE and HSL2 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">Butenko <italic>et al</italic>., 2014</xref>), for the PEP1 and PEP2 peptides and the LRR-RKs PEPR1 and PEPR2 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34">Huffaker <italic>et al</italic>., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R85">Yamaguchi <italic>et al</italic>., 2010</xref>), or with CEP4, which functions through the three LRR-RKs CEPR1, CEPR2 and RLK7, all of which show distinct patterns of tissue- and cell-specific expression (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R63">Rzemieniewski <italic>et al</italic>., 2024</xref>). It remains an interesting question, why <italic>At</italic>MIK2 evolved the exclusive ability to function in the perception of the extraordinary large family of SCOOP peptides and the <italic>Fusarium</italic> elicitor, and why potential gene duplications that could facilitate the distribution of the work-load were not retained in most Brassicales. The fact that SCOOPs and their perception are restricted to members of Brassicales, while genes of the MIK2-clade and <italic>Fusarium</italic> elicitor-responsiveness are commonly found in angiosperms (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">fig. 1a-f</xref>) could suggest a more ancient role in the perception of the microbial signature while the function as receptor for the endogenous peptides has been gained later, either simultaneously or after the appearance of SCOOPs themselves. Situations where the perception of phytocytokines might have evolved through the molecular mimicry of microbial signatures has been proposed before (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R54">Ngou <italic>et al</italic>., 2024</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">Hou <italic>et al</italic>., 2021</xref>). Finally, it is also conceivable that SCOOPs initially evolved to serve different functions, for example as antimicrobial peptides. Such activities have been demonstrated for multiple SCOOPs, even before they were designated as such (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R84">Yadeta <italic>et al</italic>., 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R88">Yu <italic>et al</italic>., 2020</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R90">Zhang <italic>et al</italic>., 2022</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R53">Neukermans <italic>et al</italic>., 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R90">Zhang <italic>et al</italic>., 2022</xref>). One or multiple Brassicales-specific mutations on the ectodomain of MIK2 might then have given rise to the interaction with SCOOPs, while still retaining the initial function in perception of the <italic>Fusarium</italic> elicitor.</p></sec></sec><sec id="S12" sec-type="materials | methods"><title>Material and Methods</title><sec id="S13"><title>Plant lines and growth conditions</title><p id="P42">For ROS measurements in different plant species, <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> Col-0, <italic>Brassica rapa</italic> subsp. <italic>chinensis</italic> (Pak-Choi), <italic>Glycine max</italic> cv. Williams 82, <italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic> cv. M82 and <italic>Hordeum vulgare</italic> cv. Golden Promise were planted in soil:vermiculite substrate (ratio 8:1), stratified for 2 days (dark; 4°C) and grown under long-day conditions (16 hours light : 8 hours dark photoperiod; 20 – 22°C [16°C for <italic>Hordeum vulgare</italic>]; 55% rel. hum.) for 6 – 8 weeks. <italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic> CRISPR mutants and corresponding azygous wildtype control plants for ROS and ethylene measurements were grown for 8 – 12 weeks under the same conditions. <italic>Nicotiana benthamiana</italic> plants for ROS measurements and transient transformation were grown under long-day conditions as described above, but without stratification.</p><p id="P43">CRISPR-Cas9 mediated knock-out of <italic>AtMIK2</italic> and <italic>SlMIK2-A</italic> was performed using apoaequorin-expressing <italic>A. thaliana</italic> Col-0<sup>AEQ</sup> (pMAQ2, Marc Knight, University of Durham, UK) or <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic> cv. M82 as starting material, respectively.</p><p id="P44">For measurement of aequorin luminescence, seeds of <italic>A. thaliana</italic> Col-0<sup>AEQ</sup> wildtype, <italic>mik2</italic><sup>AEQ</sup> CRISPR and <italic>fls2</italic>-26<sup>AEQ</sup> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R58">Ranf <italic>et al</italic>., 2012</xref>) mutants were surface-sterilized, stratified for 2 days (dark; 4°C) and grown under long-day conditions (16 hours light : 8 hours dark photoperiod; 22°C) in liquid medium (½ Murashige &amp; Skoog medium plus vitamins [Duchefa, Haarlem, Netherlands], 2.5 g/L sucrose, 1 mM MES, pH 5.7) for 7 days.</p><p id="P45">For growth in a hydroponics system (Araponics, Liege, Belgium), seeds of <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic> cv. M82 wildtype were surface sterilized with chlorine gas, placed in seed-holders with solid medium (Murashige &amp; Skoog medium plus vitamins [Duchefa, Haarlem, Netherlands], 1 g/L phytagel) and stratified for 2 days (dark, 4°C). Subsequently, seed-holders were placed in hydroponic boxes containing liquid ‘standard’ medium (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R74">Tocquin <italic>et al</italic>., 2003</xref>), covered with plastic lids and grown under long-day conditions as described above. Medium was replaced weekly and lids were removed two weeks after germination.</p></sec><sec id="S14"><title>Molecular cloning</title><p id="P46">All genomic and coding sequences for transient over-expression in <italic>N. benthamiana</italic> were cloned into GoldenGate modules using appropriate primers and assembled to be expressed under the control of CaMV 35S promotor and terminator sequences. Gene cassettes were then ligated into a GoldenGate-modified pCB302 binary vector for plant expression. Cloned sequences and primers can be found in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">table S1</xref>. Proteins for gain-of-function assays, co-immunoprecipitation and confocal imaging experiments were fused to a C-terminal Myc, an enhanced monomeric GFP or a mCherry tag.</p><p id="P47">For the apoplastic expression of LRR ectodomains, sequences coding for the non-cytoplasmic domains were predicted (PHOBIUS; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39">Käll <italic>et al</italic>., 2004</xref>); <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://phobius.sbc.su.se/index.html">https://phobius.sbc.su.se/index.html</ext-link>) and amplified using appropriate primers (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">table S1</xref>). All constructs were N-terminally fused to a TwinStrep affinity tag, c-terminally tagged with HA and placed behind the signal peptide of <italic>At</italic>LORE (AT1G61380, AA 1-21) for reliable secretion.</p><p id="P48">For the generation of <italic>A. thaliana mik2</italic> CRISPR/Cas9 mutants, two different target sites were chosen using the chopchop software tool (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://chopchop.cbu.uib.no/">https://chopchop.cbu.uib.no/</ext-link>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">table S1</xref>). Designed guide RNA constructs were synthesized (Twist Bioscience, San Francisco, USA) and stacked into a GoldenGate-adapted pUC18-based vector. Guide RNA stacks and FastRed-pRPS5::Cas9 were subsequently ligated into a pICSL4723 vector for plant expression.</p><p id="P49">For the cloning of constructs for CRISPR/Cas9 mediated knock-out of <italic>SlMIK2-A</italic>, two different target sites were chosen using the chopchop software tool (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://chopchop.cbu.uib.no/">https://chopchop.cbu.uib.no/</ext-link>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">table S1</xref>). Chosen guide RNA (gRNA) sequences were synthesized (Twist Bioscience, San Francisco, USA) and stacked with respective gRNA scaffolds in a GoldenGate-adapted entry vector. Guide RNA stacks were subsequently ligated into a CRISPR-optimized vector containing pSlUBQ10::Cas9 and kanamycin resistance marker for plant expression.</p></sec><sec id="S15"><title>Elicitors</title><p id="P50">Enriched <italic>Fusarium oxysporum</italic> elicitor (EnFOE) fractions were prepared as described before (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">Coleman <italic>et al</italic>., 2021</xref>). Concentrations refer to μg total protein per mL. Shrimp shell-derived chitin (Cat no : C9752, Sigma-Aldrich, Taufkirchen, Germany) was ground to fine powder and extracted with ddH<sub>2</sub>O overnight at 4°C on a rotator. Concentrations refer to μg chitin powder that was resolved per mL of water before extraction. The flg22 peptide (QRLSTGSRINSAKDDAAGLQIA) was synthesized on an Abimed EPS221 system (Abimed, Langenfeld, Germany). <italic>At</italic>SCOOP12 (PVRSSQSSQAGGR), <italic>Foc</italic>SCOOPL<sup>FOXB_11846</sup> (ESSSSHSERAGGR) and <italic>Foc</italic>SCOOPL<sup>F9F6H0</sup> (YVQGSHSSHTGGR) from <italic>F. oxysporum</italic> f.sp. <italic>conglutinans</italic> (strain Fo5176) were ordered from Pepmic Corp. Ltd (Suzhou, China).</p></sec><sec id="S16"><title>Detection of ROS accumulation</title><p id="P51">Leaf discs (ø 4 mm) from 6-8-week-old soil grown plants were floated on 200 μL ddH<sub>2</sub>O for 6 hours (transiently transformed <italic>N. benthamiana</italic>) or overnight (all other plant species) in white 96-well plates (RT, dark). Water was replaced by 75 μL substrate consisting of 2 μg/mL type II horseradish peroxidase (Roche, Grenzach-Wyhlen, Germany) and 5 μM L-012 (WAKO Chemicals, Neuss, Germany). Emitted luminescence was recorded as relative light units (rlu) at 1 min intervals with a Tecan F200 (Tecan, Männersdorf, Switzerland) or a HRPCS5 Camera system (Photek, St. Leonards, UK). Measurements consisted of 10 mins background reading followed by 60-120 mins after elicitor treatment. Values were normalized to average background luminescence followed by subtraction of values for mock-treated samples (included for each genotype on each plate). Normalized values of individual leaf discs were summarized over the whole measurement after elicitor treatment and are presented as cumulative (cum.) ROS.</p></sec><sec id="S17"><title>Phylogenetic analysis</title><p id="P52">Sequences of full length proteins with similarity to <italic>At</italic>MIK2 of <italic>Amborella trichopoda, Aquilegia coerulea, Arabidopsis lyrate, Arabidopsis thaliana, Arachis hypogea, Boechera strictum, Brachipodium distachyon, Brassica oleracea, Brassica rapa, Capsella grandiflora, Capsella rubella, Cicer arietinum, Cleome violacea, Curcumis sativum, Eschscholzia californica, Euclidium syriacum, Ginkgo biloba, Glycine max, Helianthus annuus, Hordeum vulgare, Lens culinaris, Lepidum sativum, Lupinus albus, Manihot esculenta, Medicago truncatula, Nymphaea colorata, Olea europaea, Oryza sativa, Phaseolus vulgaris, Salix purpurea, Schrenkinella parvula, Solanum lycopersicum, Solanum tuberosum, Sorghum bicolor, Theobroma cacao, Thlapsi arvense, Trifolium pretense, Vitis vinifera</italic> and <italic>Zea mays</italic> were acquired using BLAST (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">Altschul <italic>et al</italic>., 1990</xref>) from Phytozome (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://phytozome-next.jgi.doe.gov/">https://phytozome-next.jgi.doe.gov/</ext-link>; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">Goodstein <italic>et al</italic>., 2012</xref>)or NCBI (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://blast.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/">https://blast.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/</ext-link>) for <italic>Nicotiana benthamiana, Nicotiana tabacum</italic> and <italic>Solanum chilense</italic>. A search for <italic>MIK2-clade</italic> genes in bryophytes, lycophytes and monilophytes using the ICIPS-garden BLAST server (http://134.176.27.173/blast/; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R61">Roessner <italic>et al</italic>., 2024</xref>) remained without results. The sequences were aligned using MAFFT (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40">Katoh <italic>et al</italic>., 2002</xref>). A Maximum-likelihood phylogeny was generated using IQ-TREE2 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R52">Minh <italic>et al</italic>., 2020</xref>) with 100 bootstraps. All computing was carried out using de.NBI VM large (28 VCPUs, 64 GB RAM). Sequences used for the analysis and gene copy numbers can be found in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">table S1</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="S18"><title>Synteny analysis</title><p id="P53">A locus analysis was performed for the MIK2-clade locus of <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic> v3.2 and <italic>A. thaliana</italic> ARAPORT11 as described before (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R69">Snoeck <italic>et al</italic>., 2024</xref>). In short, BLASTP (BLAST 2.9.0+, e-value 10) was used to identify the syntenic loci by mining the genomes initially for homologues of the strongly conserved neighbor genes of <italic>Arabidopsis MIK2</italic> (AT4G08850); AT4G08840 and AT4G08920. Subsequently, putative MIK2-clade proteins were identified using BLASTP, resulting in a list of four <italic>Sl</italic>MIK2-clade genes named A, B, C and D. Locus comparison was performed using R (v4.0.3) and the R-package genoPlotR (v0.8.11) using the extracted contiguous MIK2-clade loci and their corresponding annotation. The resulting figure was edited in Corel-DRAW Home &amp; Student x7.</p></sec><sec id="S19"><title>Aequorin luminescence measurements</title><p id="P54">7-day-old liquid-grown apoaequorin-expressing <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> seedlings were individually incubated in 96-well plates containing 100 μL of 5 μM coelenterazine-h solution (PJK, Kleinblittersdorf, Germany) overnight (RT, dark). Luminescence was recorded as relative light units (rlu) with a Luminokan Ascent 2.1 luminometer (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Dreieich, Germany). Each well was scanned 12 times at 10 sec intervals to determine background luminescence intensities, followed by 180 measurements in 10 sec intervals after treatment with elicitor solutions. Remaining aequorin was discharged by addition of 150 μL discharge solution (2 M CaCl<sub>2</sub>, 20 % ethanol) per well. Cytosolic calcium ion concentrations ([Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>cyt</sub>) were calculated as luminescence counts per second relative to total luminescence counts remaining (<italic>L/L</italic><sub><italic>max</italic></sub>) as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R58">Ranf <italic>et al</italic>., 2012</xref>). Normalized values of individual seedlings were summarized over the whole measurements after elicitor treatment and are presented as cumulative (cum.) [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>cyt</sub>.</p></sec><sec id="S20"><title>Ethylene measurements</title><p id="P55">For the measurement of ethylene accumulation after elicitor treatment, leaf discs (ø 4 mm) from youngest fully developed leaves of 8 – 12-week-old <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic> plants were floated on ddH<sub>2</sub>O overnight (RT, dark). The next day, for each sample 3 leaf discs were transferred to 5 mL glass vials containing 100 μL ddH<sub>2</sub>O and 50 μL elicitor or mock solution were added to indicated final concentrations. Vials were sealed airtight with rubber lids and incubated under gentle agitation for 4.5 hours. After incubation, 1 mL of air was sampled from the headspace with a 1 mL syringe and injected into a Varian 3300 gas chromatograph (Waters Corporation, Milford, USA) equipped with a 1 m long AlO<sub>3</sub> column. Detector was set to 225°C, injector and column to 80°C and ethylene was separated from the sample using O<sub>2</sub>, H<sub>2</sub> and N<sub>2</sub> at 0.5 MPa. Amount of ethylene was calculated using a method based on the area under the curve as described before (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42">Kruedener <italic>et al</italic>., 1995</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S21"><title>Gene-expression analysis</title><p id="P56">For the analysis of elicitor-induced changes in gene-expression, 4-week-old hydroponically grown <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic> plants (azygous wildtype control) were submerged in mock or elicitor solutions in the indicated concentrations for 2 hours. Subsequently, whole plants were frozen in liquid nitrogen and ground to fine powder using mortar and pestle. For the analysis of <italic>Fol</italic>007-induced changes in gene-expression, 3 randomly chosen mock and <italic>Fol</italic>007-infected azygous wildtype control plants from 5 infection experiment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">fig. 4f-f</xref>) were frozen in liquid nitrogen and ground to fine powder with mortar and pestle. For the analysis of <italic>SlMIK2-A</italic> splice-variant abundance, 10 leaf discs (ø4 mm) from youngest fully developed leaves of 8 – 12-week-old <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic> plants (azygous wildtype control) were frozen in liquid nitrogen and ground to fine powder using a tissue lyzer. RNA was isolated from 3 g powder or 10 ground leaf discs using TRIzol reagent (Roche, Switzerland) and the Direct-zol<sup>™</sup> RNA Miniprep Plus kit (Zymo Research, Germany). Synthesis of cDNA including DNaseI treatment was performed for 2 μg total RNA using the ReverseAid kit with random hexamer primers according to manufacturer (Cat No : K1621, Thermo Fisher Scientific, Germany). Real-time qPCR was performed using Takyon Low ROX SYBR (Eurogentec, Belgium) with a AriaMx Real-Time PCR system (Agilent Technologies, USA). Expression levels of target genes were calculated using the 2<sup>–ΔΔCT</sup> method (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R47">Livak and Schmittgen, 2001</xref>) and normalized to the tomato house-keeping gene <italic>SlEF1α</italic> (Solyc06g009970). For analysis, mean values from two technical replicates for each primer-sample combination were calculated. Data represent expression of target genes in elicitor- or <italic>Fol</italic>007-treated samples compared to respective mock-treated controls. Expression of individual <italic>SlMIK2-A</italic> splice-variants represents expression relative to the predominant splice-variant 1. Transcript-specific primer sequences used in the analysis can be found in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">table S1</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="S22"><title>Stable transformation of <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> and <italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic></title><p id="P57">For the generation of the <italic>A. thaliana mik2</italic> CRISPR mutant, wildtype apoaequorin-expression Col-0 plants (pMAQ2) were transformed with Agrobacteria (strain GV3101) carrying plasmids with respective constructs (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="S14">‘Molecular cloning’</xref>) by the floral-dip method. Homozygous knock-out mutation was confirmed in the T<sub>2</sub> generation by PCR and sequencing and T-DNA was segregated out using the FastRed marker as visual aid. Schematics of induced mutations are shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">fig. S3</xref>.</p><p id="P58">Generation of tomato (cv. M82) <italic>Slmik2-A</italic><sup>CRISPR</sup> mutants and the azygous wildtype control (construct lacking guide RNAs) was performed under sterile conditions using Agrobacteria (strain GV3101) carrying respective constructs (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="S14">‘Molecular cloning’</xref>). Transformation of cotyledons, followed by callus formation and regeneration of transgenic plants was performed as described before (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R80">Wittmann <italic>et al</italic>., 2016</xref>). Homozygous mutations were confirmed in the T<sub>2</sub> generation by PCR and sequencing. Removal of T-DNA though segregation in subsequent generations was confirmed by PCR. A potential off-target (with 3 mismatches) of one of the guide RNAs (Target 2, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">table S1</xref>) in the sequence of the receptor-like protein Cf-9 (LOC101255572) was confirmed as non-mutated by PCR and sequencing in all the lines. Schematics of induced mutations in <italic>SlMIK2-A</italic> are shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">fig. S4</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="S23"><title>Agrobacteria-mediated transient transformation of <italic>Nicotiana benthamiana</italic></title><p id="P59">Chemically competent Agrobacteria (strain GV3101) were transformed with desired constructs and selected on YEB plates (5 g/L beef extract, 1 g/L yeast extract, 5 g/L peptone, 5 g/L sucrose, 0.3 g/L MgSO<sub>4</sub>, 20 g/L agar-agar) containing appropriate antibiotics (10 μg/mL rifampicin, 30 μg/mL gentamicin, 50 μg/mL kanamycin) for 3 days at 28°C. For the preculture, selected colonies were inoculated in 3 mL low-salt LB medium (10 g/L peptone, 5 g/L yeast extract, 5 g/L NaCl) supplemented with 30 μg/mL gentamicin and 50 μg/mL kanamycin for 24 hours at 28°C with 180 rpm on a shaker. The next day, desired amounts of bacterial growth medium (10 g/L peptone, 10 g/L yeast extract, 5 g/L NaCl) supplemented with 30 μg/mL gentamicin, 50 μg/mL kanamycin and 20 μM acetosyringone (Cat no : D134406, Sigma-Aldrich, Taufkirchen, Germany) were inoculated with 10 μL/mL of fully grown subculture and incubated for 24 hours at 28°C with 180 rpm on a shaker. Agrobacteria were harvested by centrifugation (2,500xg, 5 min, RT) and washed with infiltration buffer (10 mM MES pH 5.8, 10 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 20 μM acetosyringone). Finally, bacteria were resolved to OD<sub>600</sub> of 1.0 in infiltration buffer and mixed in a 1:1 ratio with bacteria carrying plasmids for transformation with the p19 silencing suppressor (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R76">Voinnet <italic>et al</italic>., 2003</xref>). Bacterial suspensions were infiltrated into youngest fully-expanded leaves of 6 – 8-week-old <italic>N. benthamiana</italic> plants with a needleless syringe. After infiltration, plants were placed back to the growth chamber for 36 hours.</p></sec><sec id="S24"><title>Immunoblotting</title><p id="P60">Proteins were separated by SDS-PAGE using a 8% resolving gel and blotted onto PVDF membranes (supplier) using a wet-transfer system (Cat no : 1703930, Bio-Rad Laboratories, Feldkirchen, Germany). Membranes were blocked with 5 % milk in Phosphate-Buffered Saline (PBS) buffer for 2 hours, washed with PBS-T buffer (0.05% Tween20) and incubated with primary antibodies in 10% milk in PBS-T overnight at 4°C. Membranes were washed with PBS-T (3 x 10 min) and incubated with secondary antibodies in 5% milk in PBS-T for 2 hours at RT. Subsequently, membranes were washed with PBS-T (3 x 10 min), placed in SuperSignal West Dura substrate (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Dreieich, Germany) and visualized using a Fusion SL Imager (Vilber Lourmat, Eberhardzell, Germany) with the accompanying software. Coomassie brilliant blue or Ponceau S staining was performed to confirm equal protein loading and blotting.</p></sec><sec id="S25"><title>Ligand-depletion assay</title><p id="P61">Apoplastic expression of LRR ectodomains and ligand depletion assay were adopted from (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R45">Laohavisit <italic>et al</italic>., 2020</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R67">Shu <italic>et al</italic>., 2021</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35">Ishihama <italic>et al</italic>., 2022</xref>) <italic>N. benthamiana</italic> leaves were transformed with constructs designed to transiently overexpress apoplast-targeted, TwinStrep-tagged ectodomains of different LRR-RLKs (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="S14">‘Molecular cloning’</xref>) <italic>via</italic> infiltration with Agrobacteria as described above. 3 days after transformation, leaves were vacuum-infiltrated with cold buffer (20 mM Tris-HCl, pH 7.8), carefully dried with paper towels and rolled around 1 mL pipette tips. Tips were positioned in empty 20 mL plastic syringes, which in turn were placed in 50 mL centrifugation tubes. Apolastic wash fluids (AWFs) were then collected via centrifugation (5,000xg, 10 mins, 4°C) and frozen at -20°C until further processing.</p><p id="P62">For the ligand depletion assay, ectodomain-containing AWFs were thawed on ice, centrifuged (13,000xg, 10 mins, 4°C) and 6 mL of supernatant was run through Strep-Tactin® 4Flow® high capacity columns (Cat no : 2-1251-005, IBA Life Sciences, Göttingen, Germany). Residual AWFs were washed out with 2 mL 1x Buffer W (Cat no : 2-1003-100, IBA Life Sciences) and columns were equilibrated with 1 mL BSA solution (1 mg/mL). Elicitor preparations were diluted in BSA solution (1 mg/mL) to desired concentrations and run through the ectodomain-lined columns in 200 μL portions in 3 subsequent steps. The last 200 μL portion was eluted with 200 μL BSA solution (1 mg/mL). All three eluted portions were collected individually and frozen until further processing. To account for initial unspecific binding, only the 3<sup>rd</sup> portion was used for analysis of remaining elicitor activity in the subsequent Ca<sup>2+</sup>-bioassays (see ‘Aequorin luminescence measurements’) and is referred to as ‘unbound fraction’. Finally, ectodomains were eluted with 500 μL 1 x Buffer E (Cat no : 2-1000-025, IBA Life Sciences), boiled in SDS-sample buffer (50 mM Tris-HCl pH 6.8, 1% β-Mercaptoethanol, 2% SDS, 0.1% bromophenol blue, 10% glycerol) and ectodomain abundance was visualized by immunoblotting using TwinStrep-tag specific antibodies (Cat no : 2-1507-001, IBA Life Sciences).</p></sec><sec id="S26"><title>Co-Immunoprecipitation</title><p id="P63">Interactors of interest (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="S14">‘Molecular cloning’</xref>) were transiently co-expressed in <italic>N. benthamiana</italic> as described above. Agrobacteria suspensions were prepared to an overall OD<sub>600</sub> of 1.0 in a 1:1:1 ratio (interactor 1 : interactor 2 : p19 silencing suppressor). 36 hours after Agro-infiltration, elicitor solutions were diluted to desired concentrations in ddH<sub>2</sub>O and infiltrated into one half of transformed leaves using a needleless syringe, the second half of each leaf was infiltrated with ddH<sub>2</sub>O as mock treatment. 20 mins after infiltration of elicitor solutions, 70 leaf discs (ø 4 mm) per combination were harvested in 2 mL tubes containing glass pearls, snap-frozen in liquid nitrogen and ground to fine powder using a tissue lyzer. Powder was resolved in 700 μL protein extraction buffer (50 mM Tris-HCl pH 7.5, 150 mM NaCl, 10% glycerol, 0.5% NP-40, 1 mM EDTA, 1% PVPP, 1% protease inhibitor cocktail, 1 mM PMSF, 10 mM DTT) and tubes were rotated at 4°C for 30 mins. After extraction, samples were diluted with 700 μL wash buffer (like extraction buffer, but with only 0.1% NP-40 and without PVPP), centrifuged (13,000xg, 15 min, 4°C) and supernatants were transferred to fresh tubes. 100 μL input aliquots were boiled in SDS-sample buffer and remaining supernatant was added to 1.5 mL tubes containing 15 μL of GFP-trap slurry (GFP-Trap® Agarose, Cat no : gta, ChromoTek GmbH, Planegg-Martinsried, Germany) that was washed and equilibrated with wash buffer beforehand. Subsequently, samples were rotated for 3 hours at 4°C, supernatant was removed, GFP-trap washed 4 times with 400 μL wash buffer and boiled in SDS-sample buffer. GFP- and Myc-tagged fusion proteins were visualized by immunoblotting using anti-GFP and anti-Myc antibodies (Cat no : 3h9 and 9E1, ChromoTek GmbH, Planegg-Martinsried, Germany).</p></sec><sec id="S27"><title>Gain-of-function assay in <italic>Nicotiana benthamiana</italic></title><p id="P64">Proteins of interest (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="S14">‘Molecular cloning’</xref>) were transiently over-expressed in <italic>N. benthamiana</italic> as described above. 36 hours post infiltration, leaf discs (ø 4 mm) were taken for ROS measurements and protein extraction. Accumulation of reactive oxygen species was measured 6 hours after leaf disc excision as described above. Samples for protein extraction were placed in 2 mL tubes with glass pearls, snap-frozen in liquid nitrogen and ground to fine powder with a tissue lyzer. Powder was resolved in protein extraction buffer (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="S26">‘Co-Immunoprecipitation’</xref>, 20 μL /leaf disc) and rotated at 4°C for 30 mins. Samples were centrifuged (13,000xg, 15 min, 4°C) and supernatant boiled in SDS-sample buffer. Myc-tagged fusion proteins were visualized by immunoblotting using anti-Myc antibodies (as above).</p></sec><sec id="S28"><title>Confocal microscopy</title><p id="P65">To visualize subcellular localization of receptors of interest, fluorescently labelled <italic>At</italic>MIK2-GFP and <italic>Sl</italic>MIK2-A-mCherry (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="S14">‘Molecular Cloning’</xref>) were transiently over-expressed in <italic>N. benthamiana</italic> as described above in a 1:1:1 ratio with silencing suppressor p19. Laser-scanning microscopy pictures were obtained using a Leica TCS SP5 system (Leica, Wetzlar, Germany). Imaging was performed with a 20 x water immersion objective. For the detection of GFP fluorescence, an argon laser with emission wavelength of 488 nm was used and the signal was detected from 500 – 550 nm with a HyD detector. The fluorescence of mCherry was excited with a DPSS 561 laser emitting at 561 nm and detected at 570 – 620 nm.</p></sec><sec id="S29"><title><italic>Fusarium oxysporum</italic> infection assays</title><p id="P66">Root-dip method was adapted from (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R51">Mes <italic>et al</italic>., 1999</xref>). <italic>F. oxysporum</italic> f.sp. <italic>lycopersici</italic> strain <italic>Fol</italic>007 was kindly provided by Frank L. W. Takken, University of Amsterdam. Tomato seeds were planted in sieved soil, stratified for 7 days (dark, 4°C) and grown under long-day conditions (8 h : 16 h, light : dark photoperiod, 20 – 22°C, 55% RH) for 14 days before infection. Fungal strain Fol007 was grown on potato extract glucose agar (PDA) plates for 14 days (RT, 16h light). Agar-plugs of fully gown fungal plates were placed in sporulation medium (30 g/L sucrose, 1.7 g/L yeast nitrogen base, 10 g/L KNO<sub>3</sub>, autoclaved) and incubated for 4 days (dark, 28°C, 180 rpm). Fungal spores were harvested by filtration and centrifugation, washed 3 times and resuspended to a concentration of 25 mio spores/mL in sterile water. 2-week-old tomato seedlings were uprooted from the soil, roots were equalized to 1 cm length with a scalpel and dipped into spore or mock (sterile water) solution for 10 mins. Infected seedlings were repotted individually in sieved soil and grown for 3 additional weeks under the same conditions. For subsequent evaluation, above ground tissues of tomato plants were cut with a scalpel at soil level, fresh-weight was taken with a scale and plant height was measured with a ruler from the bottom to the meristem of the main stem. Individual values of <italic>Fusarium</italic> infected plants were normalized to mean values of mock-treated plants for each genotype and calculated as % fresh-weight and % plant height relative to mock.</p></sec><sec id="S30"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="P67">Statistical analyses (ordinary one-way ANOVA with Tukey’s multiple comparisons test) were performed using PRISM 8.0.1 (GraphPad Software, San Diego, USA). Different lowercase letters indicate statistical differences (adjusted P Value &lt; 0.05).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="SM"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1"><label>Supplementary Figures</label><media xlink:href="EMS205860-supplement-Supplementary_Figures.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" id="d5aAcEbB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD2"><label>Supplementary Tables</label><media xlink:href="EMS205860-supplement-Supplementary_Tables.xlsx" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.spreadsheetml.sheet" id="d5aAcEcB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack id="S31"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank Frank L. W. Takken for providing the <italic>Fusarium oxysporum</italic> f.sp. <italic>lycopersici</italic> strain <italic>Fol</italic>007 and Stefanie Ranf-Zipproth for providing the GoldenGate-based cloning system. In addition we especially thank Jonas Schweigel, Julia Hagn, Samuel Sadorf and Kristina Freymark, who set the basis for certain experiments with preliminary results from their student theses.</p><sec id="S32"><title>Funding</title><p>This work was supported by a grant (HU886/15-1 ”Fusarium elicitor-triggered immunity in model and crop plants”) from the German Research Foundation (R.H.), the Gatsby Charitable Foundation (C.Z.), the European Research Council under the European Union’s Horizon 2020 research and innovation program no. 773153 (project ‘IMMUNO-PEPTALK’) (C.Z.), the Swiss National Science Foundation grant no. 320030_228294 (C.Z.), the University of Zurich (C.Z. and S.S.), the de.NBI Cloud within the German Network for Bioinformatics Infrastructure (de.NBI) and ELIXIR-DE (Forschungszentrum Jülich and W-de.NBI-001, W-de.NBI-004, W-de.NBI-008, W-de.NBI-010, W-de.NBI-013, W-de.NBI-014, W-de.NBI-016, W-de.NBI-022) (C.R.), and the German Research Foundation in frame of the collaborative research center SFB924 (C.S. and Y.R.).</p></sec></ack><sec id="S33" sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p id="P68">All data will be deposited into a public repository upon acceptance of the manuscript.</p></sec><fn-group><fn fn-type="con" id="FN1"><p id="P69"><bold>Author contributions</bold></p><p id="P70">J.M. and R.H. designed the study. J.M. performed experiments, analysed and visualised data. Y.R. generated tomato CRISPR mutants. C.R. analysed and visualised the phylogeny and representation of gene copy numbers. S.S. analysed and visualised the synteny. C.S., C.Z. and R.H. supervised the study and acquired funding. C.R., J.M., R.H. and S.S. wrote the manuscript. All authors reviewed, edited and approved the final manuscript.</p></fn><fn id="FN2" fn-type="conflict"><p id="P71"><bold>Author notes</bold></p><p id="P72">Conflict of interest statement. None declared.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><ref id="R1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ahuja</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Kissen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Bones</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phytoalexins in defense against pathogens</article-title><source>Trends in plant science</source><year>2012</year><volume>17</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>73</fpage><lpage>90</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22209038</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Altschul</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><name><surname>Gish</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Myers</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></name><name><surname>Lipman</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Basic local alignment search tool</article-title><source>Journal of molecular biology</source><year>1990</year><volume>215</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>403</fpage><lpage>410</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2231712</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Basu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Varsani</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Louis</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Altering Plant Defenses: Herbivore-Associated Molecular Patterns and Effector Arsenal of Chewing Herbivores</article-title><source>Molecular plant-microbe interactions MPMI</source><year>2018</year><volume>31</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>13</fpage><lpage>21</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28840787</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bednarek</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chemical warfare or modulators of defence responses - the function of secondary metabolites in plant immunity</article-title><source>Current opinion in plant biology</source><year>2012</year><volume>15</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>407</fpage><lpage>414</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22445190</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bigeard</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Colcombet</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirt</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Signaling mechanisms in pattern-triggered immunity (PTI)</article-title><source>Molecular plant</source><year>2015</year><volume>8</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>521</fpage><lpage>539</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25744358</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blekemolen</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Stegman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Zipfel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Shan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Takken</surname><given-names>FLW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The PTI-suppressing Avr2 effector from Fusarium oxysporum suppresses mono-ubiquitination and plasma membrane dissociation of BIK1</article-title><source>Molecular plant pathology</source><year>2023</year><volume>24</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>1273</fpage><lpage>1286</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10502843</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37391937</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/mpp.13369</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boller</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Felix</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A renaissance of elicitors: perception of microbe-associated molecular patterns and danger signals by pattern-recognition receptors</article-title><source>Annual review of plant biology</source><year>2009</year><volume>60</volume><fpage>379</fpage><lpage>406</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19400727</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boller</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Innate immunity in plants: an arms race between pattern recognition receptors in plants and effectors in microbial pathogens</article-title><source>Science (New York, NY)</source><year>2009</year><volume>324</volume><issue>5928</issue><fpage>742</fpage><lpage>744</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2729760</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19423812</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1171647</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brabham</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>La Gómez De Cruz</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Were</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Shimizu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Saitoh</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hernández-Pinzón</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Lorang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujisaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Molnár</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Barley MLA3 recognizes the host-specificity effector Pwl2 from Magnaporthe oryzae</article-title><source>The Plant cell</source><year>2024</year><volume>36</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>447</fpage><lpage>470</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10827324</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37820736</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/plcell/koad266</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Butenko</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Wildhagen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Albert</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Jehle</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalbacher</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Aalen</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>Felix</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tools and Strategies to Match Peptide-Ligand Receptor Pairs</article-title><source>The Plant cell</source><year>2014</year><volume>26</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>1838</fpage><lpage>1847</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4079353</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24808051</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.113.120071</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chinchilla</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Zipfel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Robatzek</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kemmerling</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Nürnberger</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>JDG</given-names></name><name><surname>Felix</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Boller</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A flagellin-induced complex of the receptor FLS2 and BAK1 initiates plant defence</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2007</year><volume>448</volume><issue>7152</issue><fpage>497</fpage><lpage>500</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17625569</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coleman</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Maroschek</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Raasch</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Takken</surname><given-names>FLW</given-names></name><name><surname>Ranf</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hückelhoven</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Arabidopsis leucine-rich repeat receptor-like kinase MIK2 is a crucial component of early immune responses to a fungal-derived elicitor</article-title><source>The New phytologist</source><year>2021</year><volume>229</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>3453</fpage><lpage>3466</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33253435</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Couto</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Zipfel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regulation of pattern recognition receptor signalling in plants</article-title><source>Nature reviews Immunology</source><year>2016</year><volume>16</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>537</fpage><lpage>552</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27477127</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>DeFalco</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Zipfel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular mechanisms of early plant pattern-triggered immune signaling</article-title><source>Molecular cell</source><year>2021</year><volume>81</volume><issue>17</issue><fpage>3449</fpage><lpage>3467</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34686317</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Delplace</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Huard-Chauveau</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Roux</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Roby</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The receptor MIK2 interacts with the kinase RKS1 to control quantitative disease resistance to Xanthomonas campestris</article-title><source>Plant physiology</source><year>2024</year><volume>197</volume><issue>1</issue><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11663714</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39577458</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/plphys/kiae626</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Di</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Tintor</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Banfield</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Takken</surname><given-names>FLW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structure-function analysis of the Fusarium oxysporum Avr2 effector allows uncoupling of its immune-suppressing activity from recognition</article-title><source>The New phytologist</source><year>2017</year><volume>216</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>897</fpage><lpage>914</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5659127</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28857169</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/nph.14733</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dunning</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Jansen</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Helft</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Bent</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification and mutational analysis of Arabidopsis FLS2 leucine-rich repeat domain residues that contribute to flagellin perception</article-title><source>The Plant cell</source><year>2007</year><volume>19</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>3297</fpage><lpage>3313</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2174712</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17933906</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.106.048801</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Fröhlich</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Melzer</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Pruitt</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name><name><surname>Albert</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Joe</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hua</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Albert</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S-T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genotyping-by-sequencing-based identification of Arabidopsis pattern recognition receptor RLP32 recognizing proteobacterial translation initiation factor IF1</article-title><source>Nature communications</source><year>2022</year><volume>13</volume><issue>1</issue><elocation-id>1294</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8917236</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35277499</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-022-28887-4</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Felix</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Duran</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Volko</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Boller</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plants have a sensitive perception system for the most conserved domain of bacterial flagellin</article-title><source>The Plant journal for cell and molecular biology</source><year>1999</year><volume>18</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>265</fpage><lpage>276</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10377992</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fürst</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Albert</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Witte</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Fliegmann</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Felix</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Perception of Agrobacterium tumefaciens flagellin by FLS2XL confers resistance to crown gall disease</article-title><source>Nature plants</source><year>2020</year><volume>6</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>22</fpage><lpage>27</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31949311</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Godinho</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name><surname>Yanez</surname><given-names>RJR</given-names></name><name><surname>Duque</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pathogen-responsive alternative splicing in plant immunity</article-title><source>Trends in plant science</source><year>2024</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39701905</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gómez-Gómez</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Felix</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Boller</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A single locus determines sensitivity to bacterial flagellin in Arabidopsis thaliana</article-title><source>The Plant journal for cell and molecular biology</source><year>1999</year><volume>18</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>277</fpage><lpage>284</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10377993</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goodstein</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Shu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Howson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Neupane</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayes</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Fazo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitros</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Dirks</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Hellsten</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Putnam</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Rokhsar</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phytozome: a comparative platform for green plant genomics</article-title><source>Nucleic acids research</source><year>2012</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>D1178</fpage><lpage>86</lpage><comment>Database issue</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3245001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22110026</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkr944</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guillou</surname><given-names>M-C</given-names></name><name><surname>Balliau</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Vergne</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Canut</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Chourré</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Herrera-León</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramos-Martín</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmadi-Afzadi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>D’Amelio</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruelland</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Zivy</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The PROSCOOP10 Gene Encodes Two Extracellular Hydroxylated Peptides and Impacts Flowering Time in Arabidopsis</article-title><source>Plants (Basel, Switzerland)</source><year>2022</year><volume>11</volume><issue>24</issue><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9784617</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36559666</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/plants11243554</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gully</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Pelletier</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Guillou</surname><given-names>M-C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferrand</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Aligon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Pokotylo</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Perrin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Vergne</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Fagard</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruelland</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Grappin</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The SCOOP12 peptide regulates defense response and root elongation in Arabidopsis thaliana</article-title><source>Journal of experimental botany</source><year>2019</year><volume>70</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1349</fpage><lpage>1365</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6382344</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30715439</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/ery454</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gust</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Pruitt</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Nürnberger</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sensing Danger: Key to Activating Plant Immunity</article-title><source>Trends in plant science</source><year>2017</year><volume>22</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>779</fpage><lpage>791</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28779900</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hailemariam</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>C-J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mengiste</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Receptor-like cytoplasmic kinases: orchestrating plant cellular communication</article-title><source>Trends in plant science</source><year>2024</year><volume>29</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>1113</fpage><lpage>1130</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38816318</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heese</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hann</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Gimenez-Ibanez</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>AME</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Schroeder</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name><name><surname>Peck</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Rathjen</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The receptor-like kinase SERK3/BAK1 is a central regulator of innate immunity in plants</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source><year>2007</year><volume>104</volume><issue>29</issue><fpage>12217</fpage><lpage>12222</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1924592</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17626179</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0705306104</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hind</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Strickler</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Boyle</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name><surname>Dunham</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bao</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>O’Doherty</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name><name><surname>Baccile</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoki</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Viox</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></name><name><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Vinatzer</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Tomato receptor FLAGELLIN-SENSING 3 binds flgII-28 and activates the plant immune system</article-title><source>Nature plants</source><year>2016</year><volume>2</volume><elocation-id>16128</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27548463</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Mu</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Chai</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The Arabidopsis MIK2 receptor elicits immunity by sensing a conserved signature from phytocytokines and microbes</article-title><source>Nature communications</source><year>2021</year><volume>12</volume><issue>1</issue><elocation-id>5494</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8448819</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34535661</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-021-25580-w</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kud</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuhl</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Caplan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Dandurand</surname><given-names>L-M</given-names></name><name><surname>Zasada</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>NILR1 perceives a nematode ascaroside triggering immune signaling and resistance</article-title><source>Current biology CB</source><year>2023</year><volume>33</volume><issue>18</issue><fpage>3992</fpage><lpage>3997</lpage><elocation-id>e3</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37643618</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramirez</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Griebel</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kud</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuhl</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Caplan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Dandurand</surname><given-names>L-M</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A receptor for dual ligands governs plant immunity and hormone response and is targeted by a nematode effector</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source><year>2024</year><volume>121</volume><issue>42</issue><elocation-id>e2412016121</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11494329</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39388275</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.2412016121</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hückelhoven</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cell wall-associated mechanisms of disease resistance and susceptibility</article-title><source>Annual review of phytopathology</source><year>2007</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>101</fpage><lpage>127</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17352660</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huffaker</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pearce</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An endogenous peptide signal in Arabidopsis activates components of the innate immune response</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source><year>2006</year><volume>103</volume><issue>26</issue><fpage>10098</fpage><lpage>10103</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1502512</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16785434</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0603727103</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ishihama</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Laohavisit</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Takizawa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Shirasu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Apoplastic Expression of CARD1-ecto Domain in Nicotiana benthamiana and Purification from the Apoplastic Fluids</article-title><source>Bio-protocol</source><year>2022</year><volume>12</volume><issue>8</issue><elocation-id>e4387</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9081474</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35800094</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21769/BioProtoc.4387</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>N-glycosylation facilitates the activation of a plant cell-surface receptor</article-title><source>Nature plants</source><year>2024</year><volume>10</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>2014</fpage><lpage>2026</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39511417</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R37"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>JDG</given-names></name><name><surname>Dangl</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The plant immune system</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2006</year><volume>444</volume><issue>7117</issue><fpage>323</fpage><lpage>329</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17108957</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R38"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Julkowska</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Klei</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Fokkens</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Haring</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Schranz</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Testerink</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Natural variation in rosette size under salt stress conditions corresponds to developmental differences between Arabidopsis accessions and allelic variation in the LRR-KISS gene</article-title><source>Journal of experimental botany</source><year>2016</year><volume>67</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>2127</fpage><lpage>2138</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4809279</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26873976</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/erw015</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R39"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Käll</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Krogh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sonnhammer</surname><given-names>ELL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A combined transmembrane topology and signal peptide prediction method</article-title><source>Journal of molecular biology</source><year>2004</year><volume>338</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>1027</fpage><lpage>1036</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15111065</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R40"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Katoh</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Misawa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuma</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Miyata</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MAFFT: a novel method for rapid multiple sequence alignment based on fast Fourier transform</article-title><source>Nucleic acids research</source><year>2002</year><volume>30</volume><issue>14</issue><fpage>3059</fpage><lpage>3066</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC135756</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12136088</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkf436</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R41"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Köster</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>DeFalco</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Zipfel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ca2+ signals in plant immunity</article-title><source>The EMBO journal</source><year>2022</year><volume>41</volume><issue>12</issue><elocation-id>e110741</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9194748</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35560235</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15252/embj.2022110741</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R42"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>von Kruedener</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Schempp</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Elstner</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gas chromatographic differentiation between myeloperoxidase activity and Fenton-type oxidants</article-title><source>Free radical biology &amp; medicine</source><year>1995</year><volume>19</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>141</fpage><lpage>146</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7649486</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R43"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kufel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Diachenko</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Golisz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Alternative splicing as a key player in the fine-tuning of the immunity response in Arabidopsis</article-title><source>Molecular plant pathology</source><year>2022</year><volume>23</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>1226</fpage><lpage>1238</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9276941</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35567423</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/mpp.13228</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R44"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de Lamo</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Šimkovicová</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fresno</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>de Groot</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Tintor</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Rep</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Takken</surname><given-names>FLW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pattern-triggered immunity restricts host colonization by endophytic fusaria, but does not affect endophyte-mediated resistance</article-title><source>Molecular plant pathology</source><year>2021</year><volume>22</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>204</fpage><lpage>215</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7814963</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33205901</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/mpp.13018</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R45"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Laohavisit</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wakatake</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ishihama</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Mulvey</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Takizawa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Shirasu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quinone perception in plants via leucine-rich-repeat receptor-like kinases</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2020</year><volume>587</volume><issue>7832</issue><fpage>92</fpage><lpage>97</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32879491</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R46"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Shan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transcriptional Regulation of Pattern-Triggered Immunity in Plants</article-title><source>Cell host &amp; microbe</source><year>2016</year><volume>19</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>641</fpage><lpage>650</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5049704</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27173932</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chom.2016.04.011</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R47"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Livak</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmittgen</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analysis of relative gene expression data using real-time quantitative PCR and the 2(-Delta Delta C(T)) Method</article-title><source>Methods (San Diego, Calif)</source><year>2001</year><volume>25</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>402</fpage><lpage>408</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11846609</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R48"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Man</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gallagher</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Bartlett</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structural evolution drives diversification of the large LRR-RLK gene family</article-title><source>The New phytologist</source><year>2020</year><volume>226</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>1492</fpage><lpage>1505</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7318236</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31990988</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/nph.16455</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R49"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mantelin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>H-C</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Atamian</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name><surname>Takken</surname><given-names>FLW</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaloshian</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The receptor-like kinase SlSERK1 is required for Mi-1-mediated resistance to potato aphids in tomato</article-title><source>The Plant journal for cell and molecular biology</source><year>2011</year><volume>67</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>459</fpage><lpage>471</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21481032</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R50"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McGovern</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Management of tomato diseases caused by Fusarium oxysporum</article-title><source>Crop Protection</source><year>2015</year><volume>73</volume><fpage>78</fpage><lpage>92</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R51"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mes</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Weststeijn</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Herlaar</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Lambalk</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wijbrandi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Haring</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Cornelissen</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biological and Molecular Characterization of Fusarium oxysporum f. sp lycopersici Divides Race 1 Isolates into Separate Virulence Groups</article-title><source>Phytopathology</source><year>1999</year><volume>89</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>156</fpage><lpage>160</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18944790</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R52"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Minh</surname><given-names>BQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>Chernomor</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Schrempf</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Woodhams</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>von Haeseler</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lanfear</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>IQ-TREE 2: New Models and Efficient Methods for Phylogenetic Inference in the Genomic Era</article-title><source>Molecular biology and evolution</source><year>2020</year><volume>37</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>1530</fpage><lpage>1534</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7182206</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32011700</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/molbev/msaa015</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R53"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Neukermans</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Inzé</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mathys</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>de Coninck</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>van de Cotte</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Cammue</surname><given-names>BPA</given-names></name><name><surname>van Breusegem</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>ARACINs, Brassicaceae-specific peptides exhibiting antifungal activities against necrotrophic pathogens in Arabidopsis</article-title><source>Plant physiology</source><year>2015</year><volume>167</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>1017</fpage><lpage>1029</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4348783</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25593351</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.114.255505</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R54"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ngou</surname><given-names>BPM</given-names></name><name><surname>Wyler</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmid</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Kadota</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Shirasu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evolutionary trajectory of pattern recognition receptors in plants</article-title><source>Nature communications</source><year>2024</year><volume>15</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>308</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10834447</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38302456</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-023-44408-3</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R55"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>H-C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaloshian</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The tomato leucine-rich repeat receptor-like kinases SlSERK3A and SlSERK3B have overlapping functions in bacterial and nematode innate immunity</article-title><source>PloS one</source><year>2014</year><volume>9</volume><issue>3</issue><elocation-id>e93302</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3968124</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24675749</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0093302</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R56"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ranf</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sensing of molecular patterns through cell surface immune receptors</article-title><source>Current opinion in plant biology</source><year>2017</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>68</fpage><lpage>77</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28501024</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R57"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ranf</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gisch</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Schäffer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Illig</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Westphal</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Knirel</surname><given-names>YA</given-names></name><name><surname>Sánchez-Carballo</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Zähringer</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Hückelhoven</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Scheel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A lectin S-domain receptor kinase mediates lipopolysaccharide sensing in Arabidopsis thaliana</article-title><source>Nature immunology</source><year>2015</year><volume>16</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>426</fpage><lpage>433</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25729922</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R58"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ranf</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Grimmer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Pöschl</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Pecher</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Chinchilla</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Scheel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Defense-related calcium signaling mutants uncovered via a quantitative high-throughput screen in Arabidopsis thaliana</article-title><source>Molecular plant</source><year>2012</year><volume>5</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>115</fpage><lpage>130</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21859959</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R59"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rhodes</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Moussu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Boutrot</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Santiago</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zipfel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Perception of a divergent family of phytocytokines by the Arabidopsis receptor kinase MIK2</article-title><source>Nature communications</source><year>2021</year><volume>12</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>705</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7846792</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33514716</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-021-20932-y</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R60"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Robatzek</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bittel</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Chinchilla</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Köchner</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Felix</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Shiu</surname><given-names>S-H</given-names></name><name><surname>Boller</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular identification and characterization of the tomato flagellin receptor LeFLS2, an orthologue of Arabidopsis FLS2 exhibiting characteristically different perception specificities</article-title><source>Plant molecular biology</source><year>2007</year><volume>64</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>539</fpage><lpage>547</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17530419</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R61"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roessner</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Griep</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A land plant phylogenetic framework for GLABROUS INFLORESCENCE STEMS (GIS), SUPERMAN, JAGGED and allies plus their TOPLESS co-repressor</article-title><source>Molecular phylogenetics and evolution</source><year>2024</year><volume>201</volume><elocation-id>108195</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39260627</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R62"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roux</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwessinger</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Albrecht</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Chinchilla</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Holton</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Malinovsky</surname><given-names>FG</given-names></name><name><surname>Tör</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>de Vries</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zipfel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Arabidopsis leucine-rich repeat receptor-like kinases BAK1/SERK3 and BKK1/SERK4 are required for innate immunity to hemibiotrophic and biotrophic pathogens</article-title><source>The Plant cell</source><year>2011</year><volume>23</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>2440</fpage><lpage>2455</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3160018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21693696</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.111.084301</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R63"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rzemieniewski</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Leicher</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name><name><surname>Broyart</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Nayem</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wiese</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Maroschek</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Camgöz</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Olsson Lalun</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Djordjevic</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Vlot</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>CEP signaling coordinates plant immunity with nitrogen status</article-title><source>Nature communications</source><year>2024</year><volume>15</volume><issue>1</issue><elocation-id>10686</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11649690</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39681561</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-024-55194-x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R64"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rzemieniewski</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Stegmann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regulation of pattern-triggered immunity and growth by phytocytokines</article-title><source>Current opinion in plant biology</source><year>2022</year><volume>68</volume><elocation-id>102230</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35588597</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R65"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sanabria</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><name><surname>Dubery</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Alternative splicing of the receptor-like kinase Nt-Sd-RLK in tobacco cells responding to lipopolysaccharides: suggestive of a role in pathogen surveillance and perception?</article-title><source>FEBS letters</source><year>2016</year><volume>590</volume><issue>20</issue><fpage>3628</fpage><lpage>3638</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27657914</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R66"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sandoval</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Santiago</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In Vitro Analytical Approaches to Study Plant Ligand-Receptor Interactions</article-title><source>Plant physiology</source><year>2020</year><volume>182</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1697</fpage><lpage>1712</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7140929</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32034053</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.19.01396</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R67"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shu</surname><given-names>L-J</given-names></name><name><surname>Schäffer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Eschrig</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ranf</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><source>Low cost, medium throughput depletion-binding assay for screening S-domain-receptor ligand interactions using in planta protein expression</source><year>2021</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R68"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Snoeck</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Abramson</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></name><name><surname>Garcia</surname><given-names>AGK</given-names></name><name><surname>Egan</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name><name><surname>Michael</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name><name><surname>Steinbrenner</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evolutionary gain and loss of a plant pattern-recognition receptor for HAMP recognition</article-title><source>eLife</source><year>2022</year><volume>11</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9718524</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36377784</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.81050</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R69"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Snoeck</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmid</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Bender</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name><name><surname>Neeracher</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Fernández-Fernández</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Santiago</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zipfel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Leveraging coevolutionary insights and AI-based structural modeling to unravel receptor-peptide ligand-binding mechanisms</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source><year>2024</year><volume>121</volume><issue>33</issue><elocation-id>e2400862121</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11331138</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39106311</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.2400862121</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R70"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stahl</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Fernandez Martin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Glauser</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Guillou</surname><given-names>M-C</given-names></name><name><surname>Aubourg</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Renou</surname><given-names>J-P</given-names></name><name><surname>Reymond</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The MIK2/SCOOP Signaling System Contributes to Arabidopsis Resistance Against Herbivory by Modulating Jasmonate and Indole Glucosinolate Biosynthesis</article-title><source>Frontiers in plant science</source><year>2022</year><volume>13</volume><elocation-id>852808</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8984487</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35401621</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2022.852808</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R71"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MAP kinase cascades in plant development and immune signaling</article-title><source>EMBO reports</source><year>2022</year><volume>23</volume><issue>2</issue><elocation-id>e53817</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8811656</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35041234</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15252/embr.202153817</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R72"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tao</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Hahn</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regulatory roles of epigenetic modifications in plant-phytopathogen interactions</article-title><source>Crop Health</source><year>2023</year><volume>1</volume><issue>1</issue></element-citation></ref><ref id="R73"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tintor</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Paauw</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rep</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Takken</surname><given-names>FLW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The root-invading pathogen Fusarium oxysporum targets pattern-triggered immunity using both cytoplasmic and apoplastic effectors</article-title><source>The New phytologist</source><year>2020</year><volume>227</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>1479</fpage><lpage>1492</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7496899</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32323328</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/nph.16618</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R74"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tocquin</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Corbesier</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Havelange</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pieltain</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kurtem</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Bernier</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Périlleux</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A novel high efficiency, low maintenance, hydroponic system for synchronous growth and flowering of Arabidopsis thaliana</article-title><source>BMC plant biology</source><year>2003</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>2</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC150571</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12556248</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2229-3-2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R75"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van der Does</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Boutrot</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Engelsdorf</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Rhodes</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>McKenna</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Vernhettes</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Koevoets</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Tintor</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Veerabagu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Miedes</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Segonzac</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The Arabidopsis leucine-rich repeat receptor kinase MIK2/LRR-KISS connects cell wall integrity sensing, root growth and response to abiotic and biotic stresses</article-title><source>PLoS genetics</source><year>2017</year><volume>13</volume><issue>6</issue><elocation-id>e1006832</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5484538</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28604776</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1006832</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R76"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Voinnet</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Rivas</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mestre</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Baulcombe</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An enhanced transient expression system in plants based on suppression of gene silencing by the p19 protein of tomato bushy stunt virus</article-title><source>The Plant journal for cell and molecular biology</source><year>2003</year><volume>33</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>949</fpage><lpage>956</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12609035</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R77"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Albert</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Einig</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Fürst</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Krust</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Felix</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The pattern-recognition receptor CORE of Solanaceae detects bacterial cold-shock protein</article-title><source>Nature plants</source><year>2016</year><volume>2</volume><elocation-id>16185</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27892924</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R78"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Balaceanu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rufian</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Segonzac</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Morcillo</surname><given-names>RJL</given-names></name><name><surname>Macho</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An immune receptor complex evolved in soybean to perceive a polymorphic bacterial flagellin</article-title><source>Nature communications</source><year>2020</year><volume>11</volume><issue>1</issue><elocation-id>3763</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7387336</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32724132</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-020-17573-y</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R79"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Withers</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Post-translational regulation of plant immunity</article-title><source>Current opinion in plant biology</source><year>2017</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>124</fpage><lpage>132</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5644497</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28538164</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pbi.2017.05.004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R80"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wittmann</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Brancato</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Berendzen</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name><name><surname>Dreiseikelmann</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Development of a tomato plant resistant to Clavibacter michiganensis using the endolysin gene of bacteriophage CMP1 as a transgene</article-title><source>Plant Pathology</source><year>2016</year><volume>65</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>496</fpage><lpage>502</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R81"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fuels for ROS signaling in plant immunity</article-title><source>Trends in plant science</source><year>2023</year><volume>28</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>1124</fpage><lpage>1131</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37188557</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R82"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Chi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Di Wan</surname><given-names>Ni</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Hydrogen peroxide sensor HPCA1 is an LRR receptor kinase in Arabidopsis</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2020</year><volume>578</volume><issue>7796</issue><fpage>577</fpage><lpage>581</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32076270</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R83"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Wan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Jian</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiong</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Mechanistic study of SCOOPs recognition by MIK2-BAK1 complex reveals the role of N-glycans in plant ligand-receptor-coreceptor complex formation</article-title><source>Nature plants</source><year>2024</year><volume>10</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>1984</fpage><lpage>1998</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11649560</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39511418</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41477-024-01836-3</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R84"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yadeta</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Valkenburg</surname><given-names>D-J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanemian</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Marco</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomma</surname><given-names>BPHJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Brassicaceae-specific EWR1 gene provides resistance to vascular wilt pathogens</article-title><source>PloS one</source><year>2014</year><volume>9</volume><issue>2</issue><elocation-id>e88230</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3914955</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24505441</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0088230</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R85"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamaguchi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Huffaker</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bryan</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Tax</surname><given-names>FE</given-names></name><name><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>PEPR2 is a second receptor for the Pep1 and Pep2 peptides and contributes to defense responses in Arabidopsis</article-title><source>The Plant cell</source><year>2010</year><volume>22</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>508</fpage><lpage>522</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2845411</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20179141</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.109.068874</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R86"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Skłenar</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Aubourg</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sancho-Andrés</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Stahl</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Guillou</surname><given-names>M-C</given-names></name><name><surname>Gigli-Bisceglia</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>van Tran Canh</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Bender</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name><name><surname>Stintzi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Subtilase-mediated biogenesis of the expanded family of SERINE RICH ENDOGENOUS PEPTIDES</article-title><source>Nature plants</source><year>2023a</year><volume>9</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>2085</fpage><lpage>2094</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38049516</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R87"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Steidele</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Rössner</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Löffelhardt</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Kolb</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Leisen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Ludwig</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Felix</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Seidl</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Convergent evolution of plant pattern recognition receptors sensing cysteine-rich patterns from three microbial kingdoms</article-title><source>Nature communications</source><year>2023b</year><volume>14</volume><issue>1</issue><elocation-id>3621</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10279758</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37336953</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-023-39208-8</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R88"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Di Zhang</surname><given-names>Li</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The Brassicaceae-specific secreted peptides, STMPs, function in plant growth and pathogen defense</article-title><source>Journal of integrative plant biology</source><year>2020</year><volume>62</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>403</fpage><lpage>420</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31001913</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R89"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhai</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Rhodes</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zipfel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A peptide-receptor module links cell wall integrity sensing to pattern-triggered immunity</article-title><source>Nature plants</source><year>2024</year><volume>10</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>2027</fpage><lpage>2037</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39482527</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R90"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Bao</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>EWR1 as a SCOOP peptide activates MIK2-dependent immunity in Arabidopsis</article-title><source>Journal of Plant Interactions</source><year>2022</year><volume>17</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>562</fpage><lpage>568</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R91"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zipfel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Combined roles of ethylene and endogenous peptides in regulating plant immunity and growth</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source><year>2013</year><volume>110</volume><issue>15</issue><fpage>5748</fpage><lpage>5749</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3625303</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23530253</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1302659110</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R92"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zipfel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kunze</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Chinchilla</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Caniard</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>JDG</given-names></name><name><surname>Boller</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Felix</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Perception of the bacterial PAMP EF-Tu by the receptor EFR restricts Agrobacterium-mediated transformation</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2006</year><volume>125</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>749</fpage><lpage>760</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16713565</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R93"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zipfel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Robatzek</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Navarro</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Oakeley</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>JDG</given-names></name><name><surname>Felix</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Boller</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bacterial disease resistance in Arabidopsis through flagellin perception</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2004</year><volume>428</volume><issue>6984</issue><fpage>764</fpage><lpage>767</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15085136</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>fig. 1</label><caption><title>Elicitor-responsiveness and phylogeny of MIK2-clade genes in plants of different orders.</title><p><bold>(a-d)</bold> Accumulation of reactive oxygen species (ROS) measured in leaf discs from Brassicales species <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> and <italic>Brassica rapa</italic> (Pak Choi), Fabales species <italic>Glycine max</italic> (soybean), Solanales species <italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic> (tomato) and <italic>Nicotiana benthamiana</italic>, as well as Poales species <italic>Hordeum vulgare</italic> (barley) following elicitation with an enriched elicitor fraction from <italic>Fusarium oxysporum</italic> (EnFOE; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">Coleman <italic>et al</italic>. 2021</xref>), 200 nM <italic>At</italic>SCOOP12 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">Gully <italic>et al</italic>. 2019</xref>), 200 nM <italic>Foc</italic>SCOOPL<sup>FOXB_11846</sup> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R83">Wu <italic>et al</italic>. 2024</xref>) or 200 nM <italic>Foc</italic>SCOOPL<sup>F9F6H0</sup> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R59">Rhodes <italic>et al</italic>. 2021</xref>). Recorded values were normalized to background and mock-treated samples and summed up over a period of 60 mins (cum. ROS) and are given in relative light units (rlu). Data is pooled from 3 independent experiments, each with n = 4-12, bars indicate mean and standard deviation. <bold>(e)</bold> Miniaturized (circular) and simplified ML phylogeny of <italic>MIK2</italic> genes including representatives of major angiosperm lineages and Ginkgo (gymnosperm). An early duplication event separated the MIK2-clade (dark blue branches) from the MIK2-sister-clade (light blue branches). Genes are color-coded according to plant orders as per legend. Genes of species from other plant orders are colored in black, outgroup is colored in grey. Numbers indicate bootstrap support in %. A high-resolution representation of the tree can be found in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">fig. S1c</xref>. <bold>(f)</bold> Evolutionary relationship (order level) and copy number of genes belonging to the MIK2-clade (dark blue) and MIK2-sister-clade (light blue) found in the different plant species that were included in the phylogenetic analysis.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS205860-f001"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>fig. 2</label><caption><title>Analysis of MIK2-clade proteins from <italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic>.</title><p><bold>(a)</bold> Simplified phylogenetic tree of MIK2- and MIK2-sistern-clade proteins from <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> and <italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic> with gene identifiers and nomenclature used in this study. <bold>(b-c)</bold> EnFOE- and <italic>At</italic>SCOOP12-induced accumulation of reactive oxygen species (ROS) measured in leaf discs from <italic>Nicotiana benthamiana</italic> transiently over-expressing <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> MIK2 (<italic>At</italic>MIK2), a kinase-inactive version of <italic>At</italic>MIK2 (^km, K802A) or <italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic> proteins from the MIK2- and MIK2-sister-clades (<italic>Sl</italic>MIK2- A to -E, <italic>Sl</italic>MIK2-SISTER). Recorded values were normalized to background and mock-treated samples and summed up over a period of 60 mins (cum. ROS) and are given in relative light units (rlu). Data is pooled from 3 independent experiments, each with n = 4, bars indicate mean and standard deviation. Letters show significant differences (one-way ANOVA, Tukey’s test, ρ &lt; 0.0003). <bold>(d)</bold> Comparison of the contiguous <italic>MIK2</italic> locus in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> and <italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic>. Anchor, <italic>SlMIK2-A</italic> to <italic>-D, AtMIK2</italic>, and other genes are colored as per legend. BLAST hits are indicated with lines (e-value &lt;1e-02) with score according to grayscale gradient with darker grays indicating higher similarity. Gene orientation is depicted by the position above or below the line. Size of the genome regions can be compared on the right bottom and is given in kilobases (kb) <bold>(e)</bold> Graphical representation of predicted splice-variants 1 to 4 from <italic>SlMIK2-A</italic>. <bold>(f)</bold> EnFOE-induced accumulation of reactive oxygen species (ROS) measured in leaf discs from <italic>Nicotiana benthamiana</italic> transiently over-expressing <italic>At</italic>MIK2, <italic>At</italic>MIK2^km and different versions of <italic>Sl</italic>MIK2-A (genomic sequence, K791A mutated ^km version and coding sequence of individual splice variants). Recorded values were normalized to background and mock-treated samples and summed up over a period of 60 mins (cum. ROS) and are given in relative light units (rlu). Data is pooled from 4 independent experiments, each with n = 4, bars indicate mean and standard deviation. Letters show significant differences (one-way ANOVA, Tukey’s test, ρ &lt; 0.0001). <bold>(g)</bold> Western blot visualization of c-terminally Myc-tagged proteins corresponding to data of one experiment from fig. 2f and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">fig. S2d</xref>. Blots were probed with α-Myc antibodies. Approx. protein size is marked on the left edge and given in kilodalton (kDa). Equal protein loading was confirmed by Coomassie Brilliant Blue staining (CBB). <bold>(h)</bold> Induction of <italic>SlMIK2-A</italic> (splice variant 1) transcripts in whole hydroponically-grown <italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic> cv. M82 wildtype plants, 2 hours after EnFOE and chitin treatment (left) or in shoot stems of soil-grown plants 21 days after infection with <italic>Fusarium oxysporum</italic> f.sp. <italic>lycopersici</italic> strain <italic>Fol007</italic> (left). Values were normalized to the expression of the house-keeping gene <italic>SlEF1α</italic> and are shown as fold-change relative to respective mock-treated controls. Individual symbols show results from 3 (elicitor-treatment, dots) or 5 (<italic>Fol007</italic> infection, squares) biological replicates <bold>(i)</bold> Confocal microscopy pictures of GFP- (left) and mCherry- (middle) fluorescence detected in <italic>Nicotiana benthamiana</italic> leaves transiently co-expressing <italic>At</italic>MIK2-GFP and <italic>Sl</italic>MIK2-A-mCherry (splice-variant 1). Merge of GFP and mCherry-channels is shown on the left. White line in the merge picture indicates the ROI (region of interest) used to calculate fluorescence intensity shown in fig. 2j. <bold>(j)</bold> GFP- and mCherry fluorescence intensity in arbitrary units along the ROI line indicated in the merge image in fig. 2i.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS205860-f002"/></fig><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>fig. 3</label><caption><title>Ligand-induced receptor-complex formation and ligand-depletion assay.</title><p><bold>(a-b)</bold> Co-Immunoprecipitation of MIK2 and BAK1 proteins from <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> (<italic>At</italic>MIK2-cMyc, <italic>At</italic>BAK1-GFP) and respective orthologues of <italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic> (<italic>Sl</italic>MIK2-A-cMyc [splice-variant 1], <italic>Sl</italic>MIK2-B-cMyc, <italic>Sl</italic>SERK3a or 3b-GFP) transiently over-expressed in <italic>Nicotiana benthamiana</italic>, 20 min after elicitation with water (mock), an enriched elicitor fraction from <italic>Fusarium oxysporum</italic> (EnFOE) or <italic>At</italic>SCOOP12 (1 μM). Immunoprecipitation was performed using magnetic GFP-beads, western blots were probed with α-cMyc and α-GFP antibodies. Approx. protein sizes are labelled on the left and given in kilodalton (kDa). <bold>(c)</bold> Workflow for the ligand-depletion assay. TwinStrep affinity-tagged ectodomains of leucine-rich repeat receptor kinases (LRR-RKs) are transiently over-expressed in <italic>Nicotiana benthamiana</italic>, collected with apoplastic wash fluids and coupled to Strep-Tactin gravity-flow columns. Ligands of interest are filtered through the ectodomain-lined columns and resulting unbound fractions are subsequently analyzed for remaining elicitor-activity in a Ca<sup>2+-</sup>assay using apoaequorin-expressing <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> seedlings. Graphic was created with <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://&gt;BioRender.com">BioRender.com</ext-link>. <bold>(d-f</bold>) Cumulative cytosolic elevation of calcium ion concentration (cum. [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>cyt</sub>) in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> Col-0<sup>AEQ</sup> wildtype, <italic>mik2</italic><sup>AEQ</sup> and <italic>fls2</italic>-26<sup>AEQ</sup> mutant seedlings after elicitation with EnFOE [0.5 μg/mL] unbound, <italic>At</italic>SCOOP12 (25 nM) unbound or flg22 (25 nM) unbound. Unbound fractions resulted from filtering of respective ligands through columns lined with the ectodomains of <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> MIK2 (e<italic>At</italic>MIK2) and CLAVATA1 (e<italic>At</italic>CLV1) or <italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic> MIK2-A [splice-variant 1] and -B (e<italic>Sl</italic>MIK2-A/B). Data shown is pooled from three independent experiments, each with n=4. Values of individual seedlings (each plotted dot) were summed up over a period of 30 mins after elicitation. Relative calcium levels are presented as luminescence counts per second relative to total luminescence counts remaining (L/Lmax). Bars indicate mean and standard deviation. Letters indicate significant differences within individual data sets that are separated by the dotted line (one-way ANOVA, Tukey’s test, ρ &lt; 0.001).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS205860-f003"/></fig><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>fig. 4</label><caption><title>Elicitor-induced PTI responses and <italic>Fusarium oxysporum</italic> susceptibility of tomato <italic>Slmik2-A</italic> mutants.</title><p><bold>(a-b)</bold> Accumulation of reactive oxygen species (ROS) measured in leaf discs of two independent <italic>Solanum lycopersicum Slmik2-A</italic> CRISPR knock-out mutants (line #1 blue triangles, line #2 red squares) and the corresponding azygous wildtype control (gray dots) after elicitation with an enriched elicitor fraction from <italic>Fusarium oxysporum</italic> (EnFOE; 0.5 μg/mL) or chitin (50 μg/mL). Recorded values were normalized to mock-treated samples and summed up over a period of 120 mins (cum. ROS) and are given in relative light units (rlu). Data is pooled from 3 independent experiments, each with n = 8-16, bars indicate mean and standard deviation. Letters show significant differences (one-way ANOVA, Tukey’s test, ρ &lt; 0.0004). <bold>(c-e)</bold> Ethylene concentration emitted from leaf discs of genotypes stated in a-b, 3.5 h after treatment with EnFOE (0.5 μg/mL), chitin (500 μg/mL) or flg22 (1 μM). Values were normalized to water (mock) treated samples. Data is pooled from 4 independent experiments, each with n = 4, bars indicate mean and standard deviation. Letters indicate significant differences (one-way ANOVA, Tukey’s test, ρ &lt; 0.001). <bold>(f-g)</bold> Relative changes in fresh-weight and plant height of indicated tomato genotypes caused by 21 days of infection with <italic>Fusarium oxysporum</italic> f.sp. <italic>lycopersici</italic> (strain <italic>Fol007</italic>). Values were calculated relative to the average of respective mock-treated plants (100%) (left panels). Fresh-weight (in g) and plant height (in cm) of mock-treated plants included in the experiments are shown in the right panels. Data is pooled from 6 independent experiments, each with n = 5-15, bars show mean and standard deviation. Letters indicate significant differences within each panel (one-way ANOVA, Tukey’s test, ρ &lt; 0.03).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS205860-f004"/></fig></floats-group></article>