<!DOCTYPE article
 PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" article-type="preprint"><?all-math-mml yes?><?use-mml?><?origin ukpmcpa?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">bioRxiv</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>bioRxiv : the preprint server for biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2692-8205</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">EMS205717</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2025.05.14.653927</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="archive">PPR1022919</article-id><article-version-alternatives><article-version article-version-type="status">preprint</article-version><article-version article-version-type="number">1</article-version></article-version-alternatives><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Ambient Light Impacts Innate Behaviors of New-World and Old-World Mice</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Reinhard</surname><given-names>Katja</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN2">*</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CR1">#</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Vastenavondt</surname><given-names>Rani</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Crevits</surname><given-names>Benjamin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>De Boever</surname><given-names>Sybren</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN1">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>Po-Yu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tortella</surname><given-names>Lorenza</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Farrow</surname><given-names>Karl</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CR1">#</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/04sc67422</institution-id><institution>Neuroelectronics Research Flanders</institution></institution-wrap>, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/03xrhmk39</institution-id><institution>VIB</institution></institution-wrap>, <city>Leuven</city>, <country country="BE">Belgium</country></aff><aff id="A2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/05f950310</institution-id><institution>KU Leuven</institution></institution-wrap>, Department of Biology &amp; Leuven Brain Institute, <city>Leuven</city>, <country country="BE">Belgium</country></aff><aff id="A3"><label>3</label>Neuroscience Department, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/004fze387</institution-id><institution>Scuola Internazionale Superiore di Studi Avanzati</institution></institution-wrap>, <city>Trieste</city>, <country country="IT">Italy</country></aff><author-notes><corresp id="CR1">
<label>#</label>Corresponding authors: <email>katja.reinhard@sissa.it</email> and <email>karl.farrow@nerf.be</email></corresp><fn id="FN1" fn-type="present-address"><label>4</label><p id="P1">Current address: VIB-UGent, Ghent, Belgium</p></fn><fn id="FN2"><label>*</label><p id="P2">Lead contact</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted"><day>21</day><month>05</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="preprint"><day>18</day><month>05</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><permissions><ali:free_to_read/><license><ali:license_ref>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is licensed under a <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0 International license</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p id="P3">Animals encounter predators and prey under diverse lighting conditions that signal different risks and opportunities<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">4</xref></sup>, yet how ambient illumination shapes innate approach and avoidance behaviors remains poorly understood. Here we have systematically tested the visually guided behaviors of New-World (North American <italic>Peromyscus</italic>) and Old-World (Eurasian <italic>Mus</italic>) mice under conditions mimicking bright daylight or dim moonlit environments. We identified common and species-specific adaptations to the different lighting conditions. Across species, dim light enhanced the speed and vigor of escape responses to predator-like looming stimuli. However, species diverged in their reactions to non-threatening stimuli, with <italic>Mus musculus</italic> and <italic>Peromyscus polionotus</italic> increasing aversive behaviors under dim light, while <italic>Peromyscus maniculatus</italic> showed stronger avoidance under bright conditions. Finally, although ambient light levels had a common effect on exploratory behavior, these changes were not predictive of subsequent visually evoked behaviors. Our findings reveal that ambient lighting profoundly and differentially shapes innate behavioral strategies across species, and demonstrate that these context-specific survival responses are inherited rather than learned.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec id="S1" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p id="P4">In many vertebrates, including small rodents, avoiding threat and hunting prey is guided by vision<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref></sup>. In nature, rodents perform these essential behaviors under varying light conditions, which are commonly associated with different levels of risk of being attacked, or opportunities to find food. On the other hand, the behavior and success of predators also changes with lighting conditions. For instance, owls seem to be more efficient at capturing mice during a full-moon in comparison to darker nights<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">8</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref></sup>. Most small rodents, including species of <italic>Mus</italic> and <italic>Peromyscus</italic> are primarily active during the hours of darkness at night<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref></sup>, but also forage in brighter conditions during the hours of dawn and dusk. Independent of the time of day, mice experience a variety of lighting conditions that are dependent on where they are foraging (open exposed locations vs in the shadows), the weather conditions, and seasonal variations. At the same time, ambient light levels alter the foraging behavior with each species showing its own preference for increasing or decreasing foraging behavior in the presence of natural moon or artificial light<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref></sup>. In laboratory settings, innate aversive and orienting behavioral experiments are commonly performed using computer monitors that result in environments with photopic light levels similar to those experienced in indoor spaces or in the shade on a bright sunny day. Hence, our knowledge about visually-guided innate behaviors is limited to light conditions that exist at dawn, dusk, a cloudy day or when moving through dense vegetation. The effect of ambient light on behaviors such as escape or pursuit, and whether context-specific behaviors are learned or inherited, however, remains unclear.</p></sec><sec id="S2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="S3"><title>Old-World and New-World mice display a similar set of defensive behaviors</title><p id="P5">We set out to characterize and compare the visually triggered innate defensive behaviors of three rodent species under different lighting conditions. The rodents include two species of New-World mice, genus <italic>Peromyscus</italic> (<italic>Peromyscus maniculatus bairdii</italic>; N = 39 mice, subsequently referred to as <italic>P. maniculatus;</italic> and <italic>Peromyscus polionotus subgriseus;</italic> N = 41 mice, referred to as <italic>P. polionotus</italic>), and one Old-World rodent species (<italic>Mus musculus</italic>, C57Bl/6J; N = 26 mice, subsequently called <italic>M. musculus</italic>) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Suppl. Figure 1A</xref>). To assess their innate reaction to overhead visual threats, mice were placed in a box with two screens, one on the top and one along the long side, with a shelter placed at one end (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1A</xref>). A session began by placing one mouse in the arena and allowing it to acclimatize for a period of 10 minutes, after which one out of four visual “threat” stimuli was randomly presented on the screen above the arena each time the mouse entered the “threat zone”. Each session included no more than one presentation of each stimulus, which included either: 10 consecutive repetitions of a black looming disk (black looming), 5 repetitions of a white looming disk (white looming), 5 repetitions of a dimming disk (dimming) or a single presentation of a sweeping small disk (sweeping; see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="S11">Methods</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1B</xref>). Mice were filmed from below through the red plexiglass floor and DeepLabCut was used in combination with manual curation to track the mice and characterize their behavioral responses<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref></sup>.</p><p id="P6">The behavior of the mice was classified into one of four categories: stopping/freezing, running/escape, darting to safety and darts that did not end in safety (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="S11">Methods</xref> for definitions). Under standard experimental conditions (native monitor brightness), the typical avoidance behaviors (freezing and escape) were exhibited by each species (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1C-E</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Suppl. Figure 1C</xref>; Suppl. Video 1-2). In the two species of <italic>Peromyscus</italic>, we observed an additional darting behavior, which consisted of a series of sprints across the arena (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1F-G</xref>), similar to behavior that has been described previously in some mouse strains<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref></sup>. We separated darting trials into those that ended in safety (darts_sft’; ending at the short ends of the setup, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1F</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Suppl. Figure 1B</xref>; Suppl. Video 3) and those that did not (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1G</xref>; Suppl. Video 4). In <italic>Mus</italic> literature, escape behaviors are often defined as crossing of a speed threshold and ending in a shelter, but do not necessarily describe the precise trajectory. Such behaviors might be included both in our escape group (all escaping animals visited the safety zone) and in our ‘darts to safety’, although we did not observe any such behavior in <italic>Mus</italic> in our data set (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Suppl. Figure 1C</xref>). Instead, darts of either type were most commonly observed in <italic>Peromyscus</italic> responses to the black looming stimulus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1C</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Suppl. Figure 1C</xref>; 6 out of 14 trials for <italic>P. maniculatus</italic> and 9 out of 25 trials for <italic>P. polionotus</italic>). The fast, non-directed sprints that characterize darting behavior tended to be aligned to the onset of each loom with pauses or intermediate sprints during the time between looms. Because of this stimulus-locked behavior, oscillations can be observed in the mean speed for each bout of darting behavior (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1F and 1G</xref> top). This is also evident both in the peak around 1 Hz in the Fourier analysis of darts to safety trials, which matches the frequency of the looming and dimming stimuli (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1H</xref>), and the strong cross-correlation between the mice’ running speed and visual stimulation for lags of up to 10s (the duration of black looming stimuli) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1I</xref>). This stimulus locked behavior was not evident in the escape and no-behavior trials. The differences among the behavioral types were confirmed by automatic extraction of running bouts in each behavior category (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1J</xref>) and by comparing the maximum running speed with the duration of time spent sitting still (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1K</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Suppl. Fig. 1D</xref>). Taken together, parameterization of the behavior fits well our manual classification and matches the expected running-like responses for repeated full-contrast black looming stimuli at bright ambient light levels as previously reported both in <italic>Mus</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref></sup> and <italic>Peromyscus</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="S4"><title>Earlier and more vigorous response to looming under dim light conditions</title><p id="P7">To investigate the impact of ambient light on defensive behaviors, we exposed mice to the same set of visual stimuli at two light levels: 128 lux, bright light conditions, and 0.2 lux, dim light conditions (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="S11">Methods</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref> includes data from both conditions). The bright light condition corresponds to photopic environments experienced during a cloudy day, while the dim light condition reflects light levels experienced during a moonlit night. The order of exposure to the two lighting conditions was randomized such that approximately half of the mice were first exposed to dim conditions, and the other half to bright conditions, with a minimum of 5 days between the two sessions.</p><p id="P8">The most striking behavioral differences observed between the two lighting conditions were in response to the black looming stimulus. In all three species, we observed earlier and more vigorous responses under dim light conditions (<italic>M. musculus:</italic> Suppl. Video 2 vs. Suppl. Video 5; <italic>P. maniculatus:</italic> Suppl. Video 6 vs. Suppl. Video 7; <italic>P. polionotus:</italic> Suppl. Video 8 vs Suppl. Video 3). In each species, this was evident in the higher running speeds and the earlier onset of running bouts exhibited in the dim light condition (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2A-B</xref>). Comparable trends were observed in <italic>M. musculus</italic> for experiments performed at different institutes and in a different mouse line (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Suppl. Fig. 2A-B</xref>). The increased vigor of running behaviors at dimmer light levels was evident in the higher maximal running speed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2C</xref>), and the more frequent occurrence of dart behaviors in each species of <italic>Peromyscus</italic> (<italic>P. polionotus</italic>: dim 68% vs bright 39%; <italic>P. maniculatus</italic>: 60% vs 40%; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2D</xref>), which is also reflected in the stronger cross-correlation of their behavior at dim light levels with the black looming stimulus (<italic>P. maniculatus</italic> r = 0.26/0.18, (dim/bright), <italic>P. polionotus</italic> r = 0.13/0.09; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2A</xref> right). In all three species, running-like behaviors (escaping, darts to safety and other darts) started earlier under dim light conditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2E</xref>).</p><p id="P9">Although response vigor increased in each species under dim light conditions, we identified several differences between the species. For instance, independently of the light levels, most <italic>M. musculus</italic> individuals showed fewer running episodes to repeated looming than the two species of <italic>Peromyscus</italic> and ran more directly to the shelter (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2F-H</xref>; 12 out of 13 escaping <italic>M. musculus</italic> enter the shelter at dim light levels; 12 out of 13 at bright light) from where they did not exit for the remaining duration of the stimulus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2I</xref>). The <italic>Peromyscus</italic> mice visited the shelter as well, but did leave again during the same stimulus presentation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2G and 2I</xref>). Similar numbers of <italic>P. polionotus</italic> visited the shelter at both light levels (dim: 24 out of 29 escaping/darting mice; bright: 15 out of 21), but did so earlier in the dim light condition (mean latency to shelter dim: 3.1 s, bright: 5.4 s; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2H</xref>). On the other hand, <italic>P. maniculatus</italic> mice were more likely to enter the shelter under dim conditions (dim: 18/ 20 mice; bright: 6/11), but did so at similar latencies as during the bright light condition (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2H</xref>). The characteristics of darts were different both between the species and under the different lighting conditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2J-K</xref>). Under dim light conditions, darts to safety were more stimulus-locked, while also containing more intermediate sprints (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2J</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Suppl. Fig. 2E</xref>). <italic>P. polionotus</italic> mice produce d more stimulus-locked darts to safety than its sister-species, <italic>P. maniculatus</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2K</xref>). In summary, while the specifics of the behaviors were different between the three species, each of them responded earlier to a black looming stimulus under dim compared to bright conditions, and displayed a more vigorous behavior characterized by switches to darts and increased escape speeds.</p></sec><sec id="S5"><title>Reduced levels of habituation under dim light conditions</title><p id="P10">Animals, including mice, in the absence of consequence or reward tend to habituate to repeated exposure to the same stimulus<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">20</xref></sup>. To test whether ambient light had an impact on habituation, we exposed separate cohorts of <italic>P. polionotus</italic> (N = 10) and <italic>M. musculus</italic> (N = 7) to sets of 10 looms at every entry of the threat zone until the animal did not show any responses or remained in the shelter or corner for more than 10 minutes. At bright light, we observed the previously reported habituation to repeated looms in <italic>P. polionotus</italic> where the percentage of tested and reacting animals decreased after a few repetitions, which was much less pronounced under dim light conditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2L</xref>). Only for one <italic>P. polionotus</italic> the experiment at bright light was ended because it remained in the shelter for &gt;10 min, all other individual stopped reacting to the stimulus over time. In <italic>M. musculus</italic> the percentage of responding mice across stimulus repetitions decreased as well at bright light, however, not because the mice ignored the stimulus, but further testing was not possible because they remained in the shelter for too long (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Suppl. Fig. 2D</xref>). These prolonged, looming-induced shelter visits (&gt;10 min) were further enhanced under dim light conditions where some individuals remained in the shelter already after the first presentation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2L</xref>). Although the precise effects of dim light differed between the two species, these results suggest that darker ambient light not only increases responsivity of mice to looming predators, but also decreases habituation to such stimuli.</p></sec><sec id="S6"><title>Perceived threat level of visual stimuli changes with lighting condition</title><p id="P11">It has been regularly reported that, in comparison to black expanding/looming discs, white expanding/looming and dimming discs tend to trigger behaviors consistent with a reduced risk level<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">22</xref></sup>. It appears that both the contrast and the expansion property are important to elicit aversive reactions and stimuli with out these properties are often ignored, and sometimes approached and examined<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref></sup>. Having observed stronger reactions to dark looming stimuli under dim light conditions, we wondered whether changing the ambient light condition would also impact behavioral responses to putatively “non-threatening” stimuli. We hence exposed mice to white looming and dimming stimuli under dim and bright light conditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3A</xref>). In accordance with previous reports, we observed that, in bright conditions, all three species exhibited only occasional escape-like aversive behaviors in response to a white looming (<italic>M. musculus:</italic> 27% escape or darts; <italic>P. maniculatus</italic>: 8%; <italic>P. polionotus</italic>: 9%) or dimming stimulus (<italic>M. musculus:</italic> 20% escape or dart; <italic>P. maniculatus</italic>: 36%; <italic>P. polionotus</italic>: 28%, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3B</xref>). However, when exposing mice to the same stimuli under dim conditions, both <italic>P. polionotus</italic> and <italic>M. musculus</italic> exhibited strong aversive behaviors (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3B-C</xref>). White looming disks caused increases in escape or dart behavior in <italic>M. musculus</italic> (dim vs bright: 37% vs 20% of all trials) and in <italic>P. polionotus</italic> (31% vs 9%). Similarly, the presentation of a dimming disk under dim light conditions led to pronounced shifts from no reaction to aversive behaviors in <italic>M. musculus</italic> (escape: 50% dim vs 10% bright; see also <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Suppl. Figure 3A</xref>). In contrast, <italic>P. maniculatus</italic> does not follow this trend but appears to rather lose responses to dimming stimuli (10% vs 36% of escape/dart behavior under dim/bright light). In addition to stopping, escaping and darts, we also observed changes in ‘weak responses’ which include brief startles and rearing behavior, which were generally more prominent under brighter conditions. Interestingly, for overhead sweeping disks, considered a threat-like stimulus mimicking an overhead cruising predator, we found similar species-specific effects instead of a general light-dependent trend (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Suppl. Fig. 3B</xref>). In conclusion, in contrast to general light-specific responses to looming stimuli, we find species-specific changes in aversive reactions to ‘non-threat’ stimuli that depend on the lighting conditions. These experiments further demonstrate that stimuli previously considered to be non-threatening controls reliably elicit aversive reactions in mice under dim ambient lighting conditions.</p></sec><sec id="S7"><title>Approach behaviors in dim and bright environments</title><p id="P12">Hunting, like the avoidance behaviors discussed above, contains a number of innate components including the detection and approach phases<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref></sup>. To test whether these behaviors are affected by ambient light levels, we exposed mice to small ellipses (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3D</xref>) that when moving slowly at ground level have been shown to trigger orienting and approach behaviors, similar to those displayed by mice hunting a cricket<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref></sup>. The moving ellipse was presented each time the animal was close to the side from where the ellipse appeared and faced the screen. Approaches were defined as movements resulting in bringing the center of body mass within 10 cm of the ellipse (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3E</xref>). All three species showed clear approach behaviors in both dim and bright lighting conditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3F</xref>, Suppl. Video 9-11). We observed a small trend of less approaches in the dim light condition (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Suppl. Fig. 3C</xref>; mean successful presentations (dim vs. bright): <italic>M. musculus</italic>: 33% vs. 40%; <italic>P. maniculatus</italic>: 44% vs. 53%; <italic>P. polionotus</italic>: 56% vs. 62%). The duration of following and engagement with the moving ellipse was not affected by the change in ambient light, with <italic>P. polionotus</italic> consistently being the most persistent hunters (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Suppl. Fig. 3D</xref>). However, the latency to initiating an approach differed between the two lighting conditions in a species-specific manner (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3G</xref>). <italic>P. polionotus</italic> had a tendency to approach the moving ellipse earlier under bright conditions (median latency (dim/bright): 4.9 s / 1.9 s), whereas <italic>P. maniculatus</italic> approached the ellipse earlier under dim conditions (2.9 s / 10.7 s). In <italic>M. musculus</italic>, we observed a similar trend as in <italic>P. maniculatus</italic>, with shorter latencies under darker ambient light (6.3 s / 8.4 s). Overall, we found that ambient light had the strongest effect on <italic>P. maniculatus</italic> approach behavior with earlier approaches under dim light conditions, while it had little effect on the other two species.</p></sec><sec id="S8"><title>Light level affects pre-stimulus exploratory behavior</title><p id="P13">Finally, we asked whether spontaneous exploration in the arena differed between the two ambient light levels. To address this, we first compared the speed profiles of the mice during the 5 seconds immediately preceding each stimulus presentation. This corresponded with the time shortly before the mice entered the threat zone. We observed a general preference for movement at higher speeds during this pre-stimulus period of exploration in the dim condition for all three species (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4A</xref>). Indeed, light level was the best predictor of pre-stimulus speed (generalized linear model: pre_stimulus_speed ~ 1 + light_level + behavior + species; light_level p = 0.0003, behavior p = 0.18, species p = 0.28). Other characteristics describing the behavior before the stimulus, including time spent in the center, threat zone or shelter, were better explained by the species identity and not by the light level (generalized linear model for time spent in the center: species p &lt; 0.0001, other p &gt; 0.1; time spent in threat zone: species p &lt; 0.0001, other p &gt; 0.2; time spent in shelter: species p = 0.0008, light_level p = 0.2, behavior p = 0.03). In a subset of <italic>P. polionotus</italic> mice we also recorded their foraging behavior between stimulus presentations (N=10 mice, 2.5 min recordings before each stimulus). Interestingly, the majority of these mice moved slower under dim light levels (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4B</xref>), even though this subset of mice showed the same trend of higher pre-stimulus speed under dim conditions as the other individuals (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4C</xref>). Similar results were obtained with a separate cohort of <italic>M. musculus</italic> recorded at a different institute (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Suppl. Figure 4</xref>). Taken together, this suggests that while mice forage more slowly or less in dimly lit environments, when they explore spaces associated with an increased level of risk they do so at higher speeds.</p></sec><sec id="S9"><title>Light level but not pre-stimulus activity predicts behavior</title><p id="P14">We wondered whether the higher speeds observed during the pre-stimulus phase in the dim condition might facilitate the initiation of sprints during visually triggered escapes and darts. We found no consistent relationship between the running speed of mice during the pre-stimulus phase of the experiment and the behaviors triggered by the visual stimulus; except for <italic>P. maniculatus</italic> mice that showed a trend for running faster before an escape but not before darts (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4D</xref>). The weak relationship between pre-stimulus running and behavior was confirmed using a linear model where the type of elicited behavior is best predicted by ambient light levels (pre_stimulus_speed p = 0.18, light_level p = 0.02, species p = 0.06). Since the main change between looming responses at different light levels was the onset latency (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>), we tested whether pre-stimulus speed would predict escape latency rather than behavior type. In all three species, median pre-stimulus speed did not correlate with escape latency of the subsequent looming stimulus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4E</xref>; <italic>M. musculus</italic>: r = -0.23, p = 0.3, <italic>P. maniculatus</italic>: r = -0.1, p = 0.6, <italic>P. polionotus</italic>: r = -0.03, p = 0.8). Accordingly, a linear model showed that light level is the dominant predictor of escape latency, followed by species, but confirmed that there is no relationship between pre-stimulus speed and escape latency (pre_stimulus_speed p = 0.54, light_level p = 0.00005, species p = 0.004). In conclusion, overall pre-stimulus running speed as well as stimulus-triggered behavior type and latency are strongly dependent on the ambient light levels in all three species. However, pre-stimulus running speed before the loom ing stimulus is not predictive of the likelihood or latency of escape (see also <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="S10" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p id="P15">Here we demonstrate that ambient light levels shape the expression of innate avoidance and approach behaviors in three different species of mice. We identified both conserved and species-specific behavioral adaptations to visual threats and opportunities, revealing that lighting conditions can dynamically modulate inherited behavioral programs. In particular, all three species responded earlier and more vigorously to overhead predator-like stimuli under moonlight-like conditions, while species differed in their responses to non-threatening or prey-like cues. Importantly, we show that pre-stimulus exploratory behaviors are influenced by ambient light but do not predict subsequent visually evoked actions, suggesting that changes in behavior arise from central modulation of sensory-motor pathways rather than differences in arousal or activity. Together, these findings reveal that environmental light conditions are a critical, yet often overlooked, factor shaping innate behaviors, and highlight the need for careful consideration of naturalistic environmental variables when interpreting behavioral and neural data. More broadly, our work provides a tractable framework for studying how inherited neural circuits integrate dynamic environmental contexts to flexibly modulate survival behaviors.</p><p id="P16">In addition to carnivorous mammals, birds, including night-active owls, are common predators of both Eurasian and American mice<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">8</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">23</xref></sup>. Owls have been found to be more efficient hunters during a full-moon9, which corresponds to our dim or moonlight condition. The efficiency of their predators under these lighting conditions might be the reason for the fast onset and more vigorous reaction of all three rodent species to overhead black looming stimuli. In <italic>M. musculus</italic>, we observed shelter-directed escapes as the main behavior to an approaching threat. While this is the shortest way to safety it is also predictable. Many species from insects to mammals choose instead more varied and erratic (‘protean’) escape strategies<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref></sup> that result in them being more difficult to catch<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">26</xref></sup>. Moths, for instance, show directed escape when exposed to distant ultrasonic stimuli, but switch to chaotic flight paths when threats are imminent<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27">27</xref></sup>. We observed a similar strategy in the two <italic>Peromyscus</italic> species, which displayed darting behavior throughout the setup, in particular at low light levels. Especially in <italic>P. polionotus</italic>, whose natural habitat are exposed sandy dunes, erratic runs may be the best strategy to avoid predation.</p><p id="P17">We find that moonlight leads mice to be more cautious, particularly <italic>M. musculus</italic> and <italic>P. polionotus</italic>. This is reflected in a lower threshold to trigger avoidance responses to “non-threatening” stimuli, slower and less expansive exploration, and less habituation to repeated presentation of looming stimuli at these light levels. This apparent higher level of awareness of danger in dim conditions might also be why virtual crickets were approached slightly less often and for shorter periods of time than during daylight conditions. Similar to our results in <italic>P. polionotus</italic>, spontaneous foraging has been found to decrease during moonlit nights in wild populations of <italic>Peromyscus leucopus</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref></sup> and <italic>Peromyscus maniculatus</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">28</xref></sup> (but see<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">29</xref></sup>). However, it is important to note that all these studies compare foraging at moonlight to even darker conditions and not to daylight. While in the past mice may not have been very active under the low photopic light levels tested in our experiments as well as in most other laboratory studies, today’s light pollution in cities increases the likelihood of mice encountering brightly lit environments even during the night.</p><p id="P18">The neural mechanisms that allow modulation of fast and reflex-like innate behaviors are largely unknown. Innate aversive and orienting behaviors are mediated by circuits through the superior colliculus, which receives behavior-driving inputs from the retina, but also dozens of inputs from across the brain<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">30</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31">31</xref></sup>. Several potential mechanisms could modulate those circuits depending on ambient light. For instance, ambient light affects visual encoding beginning at the level of retinal output neurons<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32">32</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34">34</xref></sup>. Furthermore, direct or indirect melanopsin signaling (the retinal light integrator) to the superior colliculus may affect visuo-motor encoding<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35">35</xref></sup>. Recent publications have shown that decreased firing of colliculus-projecting GABAergic neurons in the ventrolateral geniculate nucleus (vLGN) increases aversive reactions and that vLGN activity increases with ambient light<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36">36</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37">37</xref></sup>. This poses one possible mechanism for the systematic behavior changes that we describe here, where we might see stronger escape at dim light levels due to decreased vLGN inhibition to the colliculus. However, how these circuits act in different species, especially in the light of the species-specific changes of responses to “non-threatening” and appetitive stimuli, remains unknown.</p><p id="P19">Animals will experience different ambient light levels both because of changes in the time of day, but also because of different weather conditions, changing seasons, when entering or leaving their burrow or when switching between open and shaded areas. While circadian rhythm affects a variety of rodent behaviors (forced-swim test performance, cutaneous sensitivity, long-term memory, vigilance, exploration in elevated mazes, conditioned contextual fear behavior and spontaneous escaping of small enclosures)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38">38</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42">42</xref></sup>, some behaviors, including open field exploration or active avoidance of electric shocks do not appear to change with the time of day<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38">38</xref></sup>. To our knowledge, the effect of circadian rhythm on innate aversive or predatory behaviors has not been studied, and it remains to be determined whether the light-dependent behaviors we describe here are due to related circadian time points or rather due to other associations with these light levels.</p><p id="P20">In conclusion, we find that innate behaviors are not rigid but can be adaptively modulated by ambient light conditions, and that these changes are inherited rather than learned. This insight has major implications for interpreting behavioral and neural responses to visual stimuli in laboratory settings, where lighting conditions often differ substantially from natural environments. Furthermore, these results show that evolutionary pressures have shaped both general and species-specific strategies for balancing foraging and predator avoidance under different illumination levels. Given the central role of subcortical circuits in driving innate behaviors, this work provides a novel, pragmatic framework for dissecting the neural circuit mechanisms that enable flexible modulation of hard-wired, survival-critical behaviors by environmental cues. More generally, our findings underscore the importance of integrating real-world conditions into experimental design to better understand how innate behaviors evolve and operate in the natural world.</p></sec><sec id="S11" sec-type="materials | methods" specific-use="web-only"><title>Material &amp; Methods</title><table-wrap id="T1" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Key resources table</title></caption><table frame="box" rules="all"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left">REAGENT or RESOURCE</th><th valign="top" align="left">SOURCE</th><th valign="top" align="left">IDENTIFIER</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="3"><bold>Experimental models: Organisms/strains</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left"><italic>Mus musculus:</italic> C57BL/6</td><td valign="top" align="left">The Jackson Laboratory</td><td valign="top" align="left">JAX: 00664</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left"><italic>Peromyscus maniculatus bairdii</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left">Hopi Hoekstra, Harvard University</td><td valign="top" align="left">BW</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left"><italic>Peromyscus polionotus subgriseus</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left">Hopi Hoekstra, Harvard University</td><td valign="top" align="left">PO</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="3"><bold>Software and algorithms</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">DeepLabCut</td><td valign="top" align="left">Mathis et al., 2018; Nath et al., 2019</td><td valign="top" align="left"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.mackenziemathislab.org/deeplabcut">http://www.mackenziemathislab.org/deeplabcut</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">Python Jupyter Notebook</td><td valign="top" align="left">Python Software Foundation</td><td valign="top" align="left"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://jupyter.org/">https://jupyter.org/</ext-link><break/><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.python.org/">https://www.python.org/</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">Matlab</td><td valign="top" align="left">The MathWorks, Inc.</td><td valign="top" align="left"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.mathworks.com/">https://www.mathworks.com/</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">Dabest</td><td valign="top" align="left">Ho et al. 2019</td><td valign="top" align="left"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://acclab.github.io/DABEST-python/">https://acclab.github.io/DABEST-python/</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">Psychtoolbox</td><td valign="top" align="left">Brainard 1997</td><td valign="top" align="left"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">Pylon</td><td valign="top" align="left">Basler</td><td valign="top" align="left"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.baslerweb.com/en/software/pylon">https://www.baslerweb.com/en/software/pylon</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">Bonsai</td><td valign="top" align="left">Lopes &amp; Monteiro, 2021</td><td valign="top" align="left"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://bonsai-rx.org/">https://bonsai-rx.org/</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">BonVision</td><td valign="top" align="left">Lopes et al. 2021</td><td valign="top" align="left"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://bonvision.github.io/">https://bonvision.github.io/</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">InkScape</td><td valign="top" align="left"/><td valign="top" align="left"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://inkscape.org/">https://inkscape.org/</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">ImageJ</td><td valign="top" align="left">Schneider et al., 2012</td><td valign="top" align="left"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://imagej.net/software/fiji/">https://imagej.net/software/fiji/</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="3"><bold>Other</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">Cameras</td><td valign="top" align="left">Basler</td><td valign="top" align="left">acA1300-60g mNIR</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">Objective bottom camera</td><td valign="top" align="left">Ricoh Lens</td><td valign="top" align="left">FL-CC0614A-2M</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">Objective top camera</td><td valign="top" align="left">Computar</td><td valign="top" align="left">8mm 1:1.4 2/3</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">LED light</td><td valign="top" align="left">Solarox</td><td valign="top" align="left">LED 850nm</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">Display monitors</td><td valign="top" align="left">LG</td><td valign="top" align="left">34UM69G-B</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">Neutral density filters</td><td valign="top" align="left">Lee</td><td valign="top" align="left">211 0.9 ND</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><sec id="S12"><title>Resource availability</title><sec id="S13"><title>Materials availability</title><p id="P21">This study did not generate new unique reagents.</p></sec></sec><sec id="S14"><title>Experimental Details</title><sec id="S15"><title>Animals</title><p id="P22">For the main data sets, we used 26 <italic>Mus musculus</italic> (C57BL/6J, Jax strain 00664), 41 + 10 <italic>Peromyscus polionotus subgriseus</italic> and 39 <italic>Peromyscus maniculatus bairdii</italic> (both obtained from Hopi Hoekstra, Harvard University) of both sexes at the age of at least 2 months to up to 6 months (<italic>Mus</italic>) or 9 months (<italic>Peromyscus</italic>). Mice were housed in the facilities of Neuroelectronics Research Flanders under a 12/12 dark/light cycle at 23°C and with access to standard mouse food and water ad libitum. All mice were housed in groups of at least 2 and maximal 5 mice. Mice were only briefly handled during the biweekly cage changes, but not during experiments. An additional 7 C57BL/6J mice and 15 Gad2-Cre<sup>+/+</sup> (Jax strain JAX10802) mice housed under comparable conditions in the facilities at Scuola Internazionale Superiore di Studi Avanzati were used for the data presented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1L</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Suppl. Figure 2D</xref> (C57BL/6J) and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Suppl. Figure 2A</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">3A</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">4</xref> (Gad2-Cre<sup>+/+</sup>). All experiments were approved by the Animal Ethics Committee of KU Leuven (protocol number 165/2018 and 219/2017) or the Italian Ministry of Health (authorization number 703/2023-PR).</p></sec><sec id="S16"><title>Behavior setup</title><p id="P23">The experimental setup consisted of a box (35 x 82.5 x 37 cm) with a red Plexiglas floor and a computer monitor (LG34UM69G) on the top and on one long side. The shelter, consisting of a red Plexiglas triangle, was placed in one corner. The entrance box to the setup was in the opposite corner of the same short side. One camera was placed under the setup to film the animal’s behavior at 30-67 Hz under the control of pylon software (Basler) or the BonVision<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43">43</xref></sup> package of Bonsai<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R44">44</xref></sup>. A second camera was placed on the top of the shelter-containing short side to detect the onset of the cricket stimulus. Deep red lights (850 nm) were placed under and at the top edge of the setup.</p></sec><sec id="S17"><title>Visual stimulation</title><p id="P24">Visual stimuli were generated using Octave (GNU Octave) and Psychtoolbox<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R45">45</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R46">46</xref></sup> or BonVision, and presented on either the top or side screen. Stimuli consisted of (1) a black looming disk shown on a grey background and expanding from 2 to 20° in 500 ms, followed by 500 ms of grey screen. The stimulus was shown in the center of the top screen and repeated 10x for each session. (2) a sweeping black disk of 2° visual angle moving at 21°/s in the center of the top screen along the long side from the shelter-opposite side towards the shelter. (3) a white looming disk with the same specifications as the black looming disk, but shown on a black background. The stimulus was repeated 5x. (4) a dimming disk of a size of 20° which dimmed from grey to black within 500 ms, followed by 500 ms of grey screen. The stimulus was repeated 5x. (5) a small ellipse of the size of 1 x 2 cm moving at 3 cm/s along the bottom of the side screen from the shelter towards to opposite side. The screen brightness (grey) was 128 lux, corresponding to a dim photopic light level. To achieve dim light conditions, three neutral density foils were taped to the screen to decrease the brightness to ~0.2 lux (mesopic).</p></sec><sec id="S18" sec-type="methods"><title>Experimental procedure</title><p id="P25">Mice were moved from the cage into the setup using a metal grid or transport box which they entered and left on their own. Mice were not touched by the experimenter before or during the experimental sessions. After 10 minutes (20 minutes for dim conditions) of acclimatization to the setup, the first visual stimulus was triggered as soon as the animal entered the farthest 1/3 of the setup opposite of the shelter (threat zone’). The order of stimuli was randomly chosen and each overhead stimulus was shown maximally once per session. Between each stimulus presentation, we waited at least 30-60 seconds (exact duration was randomly chosen). After this time, the next stimulus was triggered at the next entry into the threat zone. Stimuli were either triggered manually (using Matlab and Pylon) or automatically using online detection of threat zone entry (Bonsai). If the animal remained in the shelter or a corner for a prolonged time, stimuli that could not be presented yet were presented in a second session on another day. Approximately half of the mice were first exposed to moonlight conditions and the other half to daylight conditions. There were at least 5 days between the two different conditions. Cricket stimuli were shown in separate sessions from the threat stimuli and were repeated whenever the animal was facing the screen until the animal showed at least two approaches. Experiments were performed between 8 am and 5 pm (light on in the animal facility: 7 am to 7 pm).</p></sec><sec id="S19"><title>Data processing</title><p id="P26">DeepLabCut<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref></sup> was trained on the acquired videos to extract different positions on the mice including center of the body, paws, head, nose and tail (resnet50, 100000 iterations). Consensus among the different body parts was used to calculate the center of mass of the animal. Similarly, the stimulus position was tracked throughout the video. We used in-house written Python code to display and correct the extraction of the animal position 10 s before and during the stimulus. From the x and y position of the mice’ center of mass we calculated the position of the animal at each frame as sqrt(xˆ2 + yˆ2) and the speed by taking the difference of those positions. The speed data was then resampled to 30 Hz, smoothed with a smoothing window of 5 data points, and transformed into cm/s based on the pixel resolution and the setup size.</p></sec><sec id="S20"><title>Parameter extraction</title><p id="P27">In-house written Matlab code was used to extract the following parameters from the speed and position data and to produce graphs. Figures, including setup schematics, were assembled in InkScape. DABEST statistics were performed in Python.</p><sec id="S21"><title>Percent speed change</title><p id="P28">To visualize changes in the behavior after stimulus onset across species with very different baseline and evoked running speed, we calculated a z-score of the speed. The z-score was based on the mean and standard deviation of the speed in the 10 s before stimulus onset.</p></sec><sec id="S22"><title>Distance to shelter and shelter entry</title><p id="P29">The distance to shelter was calculated for each recorded frame by subtracting the edge x- and y-coordinates of the shelter from the x- and y-coordinates of the animal. To account for small movements of the shelter and the non-rectangular shape, shelter entry was defined as a distance of &lt;5 cm from the shelter corners.</p></sec><sec id="S23"><title>Running bouts</title><p id="P30">Running was defined as speeds &gt; 30 cm/s for at least 3 consecutive frames. This threshold was determined as the 97.5-percentile of baseline running speeds in <italic>Mus</italic> (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Suppl. Figure 1D</xref>). In Peromyscus, this threshold corresponds to the 92-percentile.</p></sec><sec id="S24"><title>Latency to running</title><p id="P31">Latency was defined as the time between stimulus onset and onset of a running bout.</p></sec><sec id="S25"><title>Number, latency and duration of cricket approach</title><p id="P32">Cricket approach was defined as distance of &lt;10 cm between the animal and the cricket stimulus for at least 10 frames (0.3 seconds).</p></sec><sec id="S26"><title>Maximal running speed</title><p id="P33">For validation of manually scored trials (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1K</xref>), maximal running speed was defined as the maximal speed in the first 5 seconds after stimulus onset.</p></sec><sec id="S27"><title>Stopping time</title><p id="P34">For validation of manually scored trials (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1K</xref>), the maximal number of consecutive frames below 5 cm/s was taken as the stopping time.</p></sec><sec id="S28"><title>Power spectrum of Fourier transform</title><p id="P35">To compute the Fourier transform, speed traces during the stimulus presentation were first detrended (the best straight-fit line was subtracted from the data) using the matlab function ‘detrend’. Then, the Fast Fourier Transform Y was calculated using the function ‘fft’. The Power spectrum was subsequently computed using the following steps:</p><p id="P36">P2 = abs(Y/L) with L being the length of the speed traces to create a two-sided spectrum</p><p id="P37">P1 = P2(:,1:L/2+1) to create a single-sided spectrum P1(:,2:end-1) = 2*P1(:,2:end-1) to calculate the root mean square amplitude per frequency</p><p id="P38">P1 = P1.ˆ2 to calculate the mean squared amplitude</p></sec><sec id="S29"><title>Pre-stimulus speed</title><p id="P39">Pre-stimulus speed was defined as the median speed during the 5 seconds preceding a stimulus presentation.</p></sec><sec id="S30"><title>Foraging speed</title><p id="P40">Foraging speed was defined as the median speed during the 2.5 minutes preceding a visual stimulus.</p></sec><sec id="S31"><title>Percent time in danger zone, center, shelter</title><p id="P41">For pre-stimulus behavior analysis, the danger zone was defined as the half of the setup on the opposite side of the shelter; the center was defined as the central half of the setup (X: length/4:length/(3/4); Y: width/4:width/(3/4)); and shelter zone was defined as a rectangle of 23 cm side length starting at the shelter corner of the setup. For each parameter, the time spent in these parts of the setup was calculated as a percentage of the pre-stimulus (5 sec) or foraging time (2.5 min).</p></sec><sec id="S32"><title>Safe zones</title><p id="P42">To identify darts that could have been included in previous definitions of escape behavior (speed threshold plus ending in shelter), we determined whether dart trials ended in a safe zone. Safe zones were defined as the zones along the short ends with a 20cm width on the shelter side (i.e., far from the stimulus eliciting zone) and with a 10cm width on the far end (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Suppl. Figure 1B</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="S33"><title>Manual scoring</title><p id="P43">Videos around each stimulus presentation were watched and scored manually into the main reaction to the stimulus. The 5 behavior categories were defined as follows:</p><sec id="S34"><title>Stopping</title><p id="P44">Complete halt or freezing (complete immobility of all body parts).</p></sec><sec id="S35"><title>Escaping</title><p id="P45">One strong, immediate run towards the shelter or in another direction followed by stopping. Trials where the mice stopped very briefly and then immediately ran away from the stimulus were also counted as escapes.</p></sec><sec id="S36"><title>Darts</title><p id="P46">Multiple instances of stopping, sprinting, stopping into different directions for each sprint. Darts were further split into those that ended in safety (within designated safe zones during the last second of the looming presentations) and darts that did not end in safety.</p></sec><sec id="S37"><title>Weak responses</title><p id="P47">Very brief startles, not followed by runs; and approaching movements including rearing towards the stimulus.</p></sec><sec id="S38"><title>None</title><p id="P48">The stimulus was in the visual field of the animal, but none of the reactions described above could be observed.</p></sec></sec><sec id="S39"><title>Exclusion criteria</title><p id="P49">We excluded all trials where the stimulus was not in the animal’s visual field. This could happen because the experimenter triggered the stimulus too late or because the animal had left the threat zone very quickly after entering it and before the stimulus appeared. Some additional trials had to be excluded due to technical issues that were only detected after the experiment such as incorrect lightning or stimulus parameters. Finally, some individuals did not complete all stimuli due to prolonged hiding in the shelter during multiple sessions.</p></sec><sec id="S40"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="P50">Statistical tests included Permutation Tests (performed using the ‘dabest’ package (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://acclab.github.io/DABEST-python/">https://acclab.github.io/DABEST-python/</ext-link>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R47">47</xref></sup>, Wilcoxon Ranksum tests (‘ranksum’ function in Matlab) with Bonferroni correction for multiple comparisons where indicated, and cross-correlation calculations:</p><p id="P51">Average speed plots (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>): xcorr’ in Matlab was used to calculate cross-correlations between the median speed during the looming stimulus presentation and the stimulus. The stimulus was represented as a sinusoidal function with the 1 Hz frequency of the looming stimulus.</p><p id="P52">Dart behavior (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>): A matrix was created with 0s and 1s where 1 indicates the presence of a running bout. The correlation between this matrix and a stimulus vector with 0s and 1s where 1 indicates the onset of each stimulus was calculated using the ‘xcorr’ function.</p><p id="P53">Escape latency vs. pre-stimulus speed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>): Correlation coefficients and corresponding p-values between escape latency and pre-stimulus speed were calculated using the ‘corrcoef’ function.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="SM"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1"><label>Supplemental Figures</label><media xlink:href="EMS205717-supplement-Supplemental_Figures.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" id="d50aAcEbB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack id="S41"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We would like to thank Hopi Hoekstra (Harvard University) for providing us with <italic>Peromyscus</italic> breeding pairs and for advice with <italic>Peromyscus</italic> handling and experimentation, and Jennifer Hoy (University of Reno) for advice with the cricket stimulus and valuable feedback. Further, we thank Anna Chrzanowska and Bram Nuttin (both NERF) for helping with the behavior setup and with DeepLabCut, Marco Gigante for building the setup at SISSA, and the Farrow Lab and Bonin Lab (both NERF) as well as Eugenio Piasini (SISSA) for helpful comments. This project has received funding from the European Union’s Horizon 2020 research and innovation programme under the Marie Skłodowska-Curie grant agreement No 665501 and from the European Research Council (ERC) (Grant agreement No. 101075848) as well as from FWO (12S7917N and 12S7920N) to KR. The views and opinions expressed are solely those of the authors and do not necessarily reflect those of the European Union, nor can the European Union be held responsible for them. KF is supported by the FWO (G094616N and G091719N) and the NIH (1R01EY032101).</p></ack><sec id="S42" sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data and code availability</title><p id="P54">X- and y- coordinates for each animal, stimulus and condition will be made available on a public repository upon publication.</p><p id="P55">Code used to create the figures will be made available on a public repository upon publication.</p></sec><fn-group><fn id="FN3" fn-type="con"><p id="P56"><bold>Author Contributions</bold></p><p id="P57">Conceiving the study: KR, KF, SDB</p><p id="P58">Pilot experiments: SDB, LT</p><p id="P59">Data collection &amp; processing: KR, RV, BC, PYL, LT</p><p id="P60">Analysis: KR, KF</p><p id="P61">Manuscript writing: KR, KF</p></fn><fn id="FN4" fn-type="conflict"><p id="P62"><bold>Declaration of Interests</bold></p><p id="P63">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><ref id="R1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Caro</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><source>Antipredator Defenses in Birds and Mammals</source><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Girling</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><publisher-name>University of Chicago Press</publisher-name><year>2005</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kotler</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hazardous duty pay and the foraging cost of predation</article-title><source>Ecology Letters</source><year>2004</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>999</fpage><lpage>1014</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1461-0248.2004.00661.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stankowich</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Blumstein</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fear in animals: a meta-analysis and review of risk assessment</article-title><source>Proceedings of the Royal Society B: Biological Sciences</source><year>2005</year><volume>272</volume><fpage>2627</fpage><lpage>2634</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1559976</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16321785</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rspb.2005.3251</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beier</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Effects of Artificial Night Lighting on Terrestrial Mammals</chapter-title><source>Ecological Consequences of Artificial Night Lighting</source><publisher-name>Island Press</publisher-name><year>2006</year><fpage>67</fpage><lpage>93</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yilmaz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Meister</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rapid innate defensive responses of mice to looming visual stimuli</article-title><source>Current Biology</source><year>2013</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>2011</fpage><lpage>2015</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3809337</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24120636</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2013.08.015</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hoy</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Yavorska</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Wehr</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Niell</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Vision Drives Accurate Approach Behavior during Prey Capture in Laboratory Mice</article-title><source>Current Biology</source><year>2016</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>3046</fpage><lpage>3052</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5121011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27773567</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2016.09.009</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Franceschi</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name><name><surname>Solomon</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Visual response properties of neurons in the superficial layers of the superior colliculus of awake mouse</article-title><source>Journal of Physiology</source><year>2018</year><volume>596</volume><fpage>6307</fpage><lpage>6332</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6292807</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30281795</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1113/JP276964</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kotler</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wirtz</surname><given-names>WO</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effects of owl predation on the foraging behavior of heteromyid rodents</article-title><source>Oecologia</source><year>1988</year><volume>76</volume><fpage>408</fpage><lpage>415</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28312021</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Moonlight’s influence on predator/prey interactions between short-eared owls (Asio flammeus) and deermice (Peromyscus maniculatus)</article-title><source>Behav Ecol Sociobiol</source><year>1983</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>205</fpage><lpage>209</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00299924</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Longland</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name><name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Direct Observations of Owls and Heteromyid Rodents: Can Predation Risk Explain Microhabitat Use?</article-title><source>Ecology</source><year>1991</year><volume>72</volume><fpage>2261</fpage><lpage>2273</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/1941576</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baumgardner</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Dewsbury</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diurnal patterning of eight activities in 14 species of muroid rodents</article-title><source>Animal Learning &amp; Behavior</source><year>1980</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>322</fpage><lpage>330</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3758/BF03199612</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Farnworth</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Innes</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Waas</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Converting Predation Cues into Conservation Tools: The Effect of Light on Mouse Foraging Behaviour</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2016</year><volume>11</volume><elocation-id>e0145432</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4711984</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26760039</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0145432</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jacob</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Matter</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><name><surname>Cameron</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Interactive effects of vegetation and illumination on foraging behavior of white-footed mice (Peromyscus leucopus)</article-title><source>Journal of Mammalogy</source><year>2017</year><volume>98</volume><fpage>804</fpage><lpage>814</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jmammal/gyx012</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kramer</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Birney</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of Light Intensity on Activity Patterns of Patagonian Leaf-Eared Mice, Phyllotis xanthopygus</article-title><source>Journal of Mammalogy</source><year>2001</year><volume>82</volume><fpage>535</fpage><lpage>544</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jmammal/82.2.535</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mathis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mamidanna</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Cury</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Abe</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Murthy</surname><given-names>VN</given-names></name><name><surname>Mathis</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Bethge</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>DeepLabCut: markerless pose estimation of user-defined body parts with deep learning</article-title><source>Nature Neuroscience</source><year>2018</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>1281</fpage><lpage>1289</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30127430</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nath</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Mathis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bethge</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mathis</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Using DeepLabCut for 3D markerless pose estimation across species and behaviors</article-title><source>Nat Protoc</source><year>2019</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>2152</fpage><lpage>2176</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31227823</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kafkafi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Pagis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lipkind</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Mayo</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Bemjamini</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Golani</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Elmer</surname><given-names>GI</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Darting behavior: a quantitative movement pattern designed for discrimination and replicability in mouse locomotor behavior</article-title><source>Behav Brain Res</source><year>2003</year><volume>142</volume><fpage>193</fpage><lpage>205</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12798281</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baier</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Reinhard</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Tong</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Murmann</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Farrow</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoekstra</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The neural basis of defensive behaviour evolution in Peromyscus mice</article-title><source>bioRxiv</source><year>2023</year><elocation-id>2023.07.04.547734</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2023.07.04.547734</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tafreshiha</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>van der Burg</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Smits</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Blömer</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Heimel</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Visual stimulus-specific habituation of innate defensive behaviour in mice</article-title><source>Journal of Experimental Biology</source><year>2021</year><volume>224</volume><elocation-id>jeb230433</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33568444</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tinbergen</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><source>The study of instinct</source><publisher-name>Clarendon Press</publisher-name><year>1989</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0169-5347(90)90013-4</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Visual Cue-Discriminative Dopaminergic Control of Visuomotor Transformation and Behavior Selection</article-title><source>Neuron</source><year>2016</year><volume>89</volume><fpage>598</fpage><lpage>612</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26804989</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Temizer</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Donovan</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Baier</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Semmelhack</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A Visual Pathway for Looming-Evoked Escape in Larval Zebrafish</article-title><source>Current Biology</source><year>2015</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>1823</fpage><lpage>1834</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26119746</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mammalogists</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name></person-group><source>The Smithsonian Book of North American Mammals</source><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruff</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><publisher-name>Smithsonian Inst Pr</publisher-name><year>1999</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Humphries</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Driver</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Erratic Display as a Device against Predators</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1967</year><volume>156</volume><fpage>1767</fpage><lpage>1768</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5629325</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruxton</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prey jitters; protean behaviour in grouped prey</article-title><source>Behavioral Ecology</source><year>2011</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>831</fpage><lpage>836</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/beheco/arr062</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Dickinson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Burman</surname><given-names>OHP</given-names></name><name><surname>Pike</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Unpredictable movement as an anti-predator strategy</article-title><source>Proc Biol Sci</source><year>2018</year><volume>285</volume><elocation-id>20181112</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6125907</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30135159</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rspb.2018.1112</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roeder</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The behaviour of free flying moths in the presence of artificial ultrasonic pulses</article-title><source>Animal Behaviour</source><year>1962</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>300</fpage><lpage>304</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0003-3472(62)90053-2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Falkenberg</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Microhabitat Use of Deer Mice: Effects of Interspecific Interaction Risks</article-title><source>Journal of Mammalogy</source><year>1998</year><volume>79</volume><fpage>558</fpage><lpage>565</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/1382986</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Upham</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name><name><surname>Hafner</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Do nocturnal rodents in the Great Basin Desert avoid moonlight?</article-title><source>Journal of Mammalogy</source><year>2013</year><volume>94</volume><fpage>59</fpage><lpage>72</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1644/12-MAMM-A-076.1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kühn</surname><given-names>NK</given-names></name><name><surname>Alkislar</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Dublanc</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Zemmouri</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Paesmans</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Reinhard</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Farrow</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pathway-specific inputs to the superior colliculus support flexible triggering of innate behaviors</article-title><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10468139</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37647395</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/sciadv.ade3874</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Benavidez</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name><name><surname>Bienkowski</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Garcia</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name><name><surname>Fayzullina</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Bowman</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Gou</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Khanjani</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Cotter</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Organization of the inputs and outputs of the mouse superior colliculus</article-title><source>Nature Communications</source><year>2021</year><volume>12</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8239028</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34183678</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-021-24241-2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Farrow</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Teixeira</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Szikra</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Viney</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Balint</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yonehara</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Roska</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ambient illumination toggles a neuronal circuit switch in the retina and visual perception at cone threshold</article-title><source>Neuron</source><year>2013</year><volume>78</volume><fpage>325</fpage><lpage>338</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23541902</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tikidji-Hamburyan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Reinhard</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Seitter</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hovhannisyan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Procyk</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Schenk</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lucas</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Munch</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Retinal output changes qualitatively with every change in ambient illuminance</article-title><source>Nature neuroscience</source><year>2015</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>66</fpage><lpage>74</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4338531</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25485757</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nn.3891</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Umino</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Solessio</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Barlow</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Speed, spatial, and temporal tuning of rod and cone vision in mouse</article-title><source>The Journal of neuroscience : the official journal of the Society for Neuroscience</source><year>2008</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>189</fpage><lpage>198</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2847259</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18171936</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.3551-07.2008</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Do</surname><given-names>MTH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Melanopsin and the Intrinsically Photosensitive Retinal Ganglion Cells: Biophysics to Behavior</article-title><source>Neuron</source><year>2019</year><volume>104</volume><fpage>205</fpage><lpage>226</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6944442</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31647894</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2019.07.016</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fratzl</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Koltchev</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Vissers</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name><name><surname>Marques-Smith</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Stempel</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name><name><surname>Branco</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hofer</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Flexible inhibitory control of visually evoked defensive behavior by the ventral lateral geniculate nucleus</article-title><source>Neuron</source><year>2021</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8648186</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34614420</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2021.09.003</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Salay</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name><name><surname>Huberman</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Divergent outputs of the ventral lateral geniculate nucleus mediate visually evoked defensive behaviors</article-title><source>Cell reports</source><year>2021</year><volume>37</volume><elocation-id>109792</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10954303</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34610302</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.celrep.2021.109792</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tsao</surname><given-names>C-H</given-names></name><name><surname>Flint</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>G-J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Influence of diurnal phase on behavioral tests of sensorimotor performance, anxiety, learning and memory in mice</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2022</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>432</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8748730</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35013366</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-021-03155-5</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Poirel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rhythmometric analyses of circadian variations of grooming behavior in the mouse: research perspectives in behavioral chronobiology</article-title><source>J Gen Psychol</source><year>1988</year><volume>115</volume><fpage>187</fpage><lpage>201</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3385416</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kelliher</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Connor</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Harkin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanchez</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Leonard</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Varying responses to the rat forced-swim test under diurnal and nocturnal conditions</article-title><source>Physiol Behav</source><year>2000</year><volume>69</volume><fpage>531</fpage><lpage>539</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10913793</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R41"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Easton</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Arbuzova</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Turek</surname><given-names>FW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The circadian Clock mutation increases exploratory activity and escape-seeking behavior</article-title><source>Genes, Brain and Behavior</source><year>2003</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>11</fpage><lpage>19</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12882315</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R42"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Poirel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Circadian periodicity of escape behaviour in the mouse: Preliminary chronobiological data</article-title><source>Behav Processes</source><year>1978</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>77</fpage><lpage>82</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24924377</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R43"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lopes</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Farrell</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Horrocks</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>C-Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Morimoto</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Muzzu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Papanikolaou</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodrigues</surname><given-names>FR</given-names></name><name><surname>Wheatcroft</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Zucca</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Creating and controlling visual environments using BonVision</article-title><source>eLife</source><year>2021</year><volume>10</volume><elocation-id>e65541</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8104957</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33880991</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.65541</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R44"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lopes</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Monteiro</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>New Open-Source Tools: Using Bonsai for Behavioral Tracking and Closed-Loop Experiments</article-title><source>Front Behav Neurosci</source><year>2021</year><volume>15</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8044343</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33867952</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fnbeh.2021.647640</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R45"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kleiner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Brainard</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Pelli</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Broussard</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolf</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Niehorster</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>What’s new in Psychtoolbox-3?</article-title><source>Perception</source><year>2007</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>S14</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1068/v070821</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R46"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brainard</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Psychophysics Toolbox</article-title><year>1997</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9176952</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R47"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Tumkaya</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Aryal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Claridge-Chang</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Moving beyond P values: data analysis with estimation graphics</article-title><source>Nat Methods</source><year>2019</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>565</fpage><lpage>566</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31217592</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><title>Innate aversive behaviors in mice.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Experimental setup for threat stimuli. (<bold>B</bold>) Visual threat stimuli. (<bold>C</bold>) Percentage of stopping, escape, darting to safety and other darts in response to black looming under bright light conditions. <italic>M. musculus</italic> (N = 14 mice), <italic>P. maniculatus</italic> (N = 14 mice), <italic>P. polionotus</italic> (N = 25 mice). (<bold>D</bold>) Example trajectory of a mouse reacting with stopping to a visual threat (left; see Suppl. Video 1). Right: All stopping response to any of the four overhead stimuli at all light levels and of all three tested species. Each row corresponds to a reaction by one mouse to one stimulus. Rows are sorted by onset of stopping. Gray bars on the left indicates the species for each reaction (<italic>M. musculus</italic>: black, <italic>P. maniculatus</italic>: dark gray, <italic>P. polionotus</italic>: light gray). Speed is given as z-score calculated from mean and standard deviation of the pre-stimulus movement speed. Above the heatmap: Mean speed change across all rows (orange) and mean distance from the shelter (gray). (<bold>E</bold>) Example trajectory of a mouse reacting with escape (Suppl. Video 2) and all escape trials sorted by escape onset. (<bold>F</bold>) Example trajectory of a mouse reacting with darts to safety (Suppl. Video 3) and all trials sorted by escape onset. (<bold>G</bold>) Example trajectory of a mouse reacting with darts not ending in safety (Suppl. Video 4) and all trials sorted by escape onset. (<bold>H</bold>) Power spectrum of the mean Fourier Transform of the running speed during darts (dark green; n = 27), darts to safety (green; n = 29) and escape (light green; n = 88) in response to any of the repetitive stimuli. (<bold>I</bold>) Cross correlation between running speed and visual stimulus for different behavior types and for all repetitive stimuli. Same trials as in I were included; no-behavior trials (gray; n = 106). (<bold>J</bold>) Numbers of running bouts for darts, darts to safety, escape, stopping (orange) and no behavior. (<bold>K</bold>) Maximal running speed and time spent without movement (&lt;5cm/s) for trials classified as no behavior (gray), stopping (orange), escaping (light green) and darts to safety (green) and other darts (dark green). Lines indicate 25% to 75% quantiles and cross at the median.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS205717-f001"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><title>Innate reactions to black looming are more vigorous under dim compared to bright conditions.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Speed changes in response to a black looming stimulus. Each row represents the response of one mouse during the visual stimulus. Running speed is normalized to the mean and standard-deviation of the speed in the 5 seconds before stimulus onset. Ticks on top of each heatmap indicate stimulus onsets. Mean absolute running speed for all mice is shown on the right for dim and bright conditions. <italic>Mus</italic>: N = 15/14 (dim/bright). <italic>P. maniculatus</italic>: N = 25/15. <italic>P. polionotus</italic>: N = 29/28. (<bold>B</bold>) Latency of first running bout (&gt;30cm/s) for the subset of mice that were tested and displayed running bouts at both light levels. Horizonal lines indicate medians. Mm: N = 9, Pm: N = 5, Pp: N = 19. (<bold>C</bold>) Maximum speed during first running bout for the same mice as in B. (<bold>D</bold>) Behavior types under dim and bright light. (<bold>E-I</bold>) Comparison of various parameters for running-like trials only (escape, darts to safety, darts). (<bold>E</bold>) Distribution of latency to running onset. (<bold>F</bold>) Number of running episodes. (<bold>G</bold>) Fraction of mice in the shelter during looming stimuli. (<bold>H</bold>) Latency to fist shelter entry. (<bold>I</bold>) Number of shelter entries. (<bold>J</bold>) Cross-correlation of darts in response to the black looming stimulus for dim and bright light conditions separately. (<bold>K</bold>) Power spectrum of Fourier transform for dart trials of <italic>P. maniculatus</italic> (solid; N = 7 for darts to safety, green, and N = 8 for other darts, dark green) and <italic>P. polionotus</italic> (dashed, N = 18 / N = 5) at dim light conditions. (<bold>L</bold>) Left: Percentage of <italic>P. polionotus</italic> tested and reacting to 12 repetitions of the looming stimulus (percentage indicates fraction of animals that did not stay for &gt;10 min under the shelter during the previous repetition and showed a reaction to the looming stimulus; 100% corresponds to N = 10 mice). Right: Number of looming repetitions that could be tested in each <italic>M. musculus</italic> (N = 7) without inducing prolonged shelter visits of &gt;10 min. * p &lt; 0.05, ** p &lt; 0.01, *** p &lt; 0.005 Permutation Test.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS205717-f002"/></fig><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><title>Species-specific responses to non-threat and virtual cricket stimuli.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Speed heatmaps during presentations of white looming and dimming stimuli. (<bold>B</bold>) Number of mice responding to black looming and non-threat stimuli (white looming and dimming). Strong responses include darts, escape and stopping. (<bold>C</bold>) Distribution of type of behaviors for weak and strong responses (black and dark gray in B). (<bold>D</bold>) Behavior setup with virtual cricket stimulus. (<bold>E</bold>) Example trajectory of a mouse reacting to the virtual cricket (Suppl. Video 9). Color indicates position and time. (<bold>F</bold>) Distance of the mouse to the cricket during all virtual cricket presentations for <italic>Mus</italic>, <italic>P. maniculatus</italic> and <italic>P. polionotus</italic> under dim and bright light conditions. Presentations are sorted by the time of the first approach. The cricket moved from the shelter side (0 cm) to the opposite short side (83 cm) at 3 cm/s. Number of mice for <italic>Mus</italic> (dim/bright): N = 12/12 (N = 11/12 with at least 1 approach, N = 7/11 with at least 2 approaches); <italic>P. maniculatus</italic>: N = 7/7 (N = 7/7, N = 7/7); <italic>P. polionotus</italic>: N = 7/7 (N = 7/7, N = 7/6). (G) Latency to the first approach. ** p &lt; 0.01 Permutation Test.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS205717-f003"/></fig><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><title>Ambient light predicts pre-stimulus behavior.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Median speed during the 5 seconds right before each stimulus onset (pre-stimulus speed) for each species and both light levels. Lines indicate medians. (<bold>B</bold>) Median speed during 2.5 minutes between each stimulus presentation for a subset of <italic>P. polionotus</italic> mice (N = 10). (<bold>C</bold>) Pre-stimulus speed for the same mice as in B. (<bold>D</bold>) Pre-stimulus speed for black looming stimuli only, separated by subsequent elicited behavior. (<bold>E</bold>) Pre-stimulus speed and latency to running onset for escape (filled) and dart (open) trials at dim (black) and bright (blue) light levels. * p &lt; 0.05, ** p &lt; 0.01 *** p &lt; 0.001 Wilcoxon Ranksum Test corrected for multiple comparisons.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS205717-f004"/></fig></floats-group></article>