<!DOCTYPE article
 PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" article-type="preprint"><?all-math-mml yes?><?use-mml?><?origin ukpmcpa?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">bioRxiv</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>bioRxiv : the preprint server for biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2692-8205</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">EMS207334</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2025.07.17.664873</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="archive">PPR1051912</article-id><article-version-alternatives><article-version article-version-type="status">preprint</article-version><article-version article-version-type="number">1</article-version></article-version-alternatives><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The ultrafine-bridge-associated endonuclease ANKLE1 is stimulated by tension in DNA to process branch-points</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ray</surname><given-names>Korak Kumar</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kaczmarczyk</surname><given-names>Artur P.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Freeman</surname><given-names>Alasdair D.J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Leow</surname><given-names>Faith</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>Timothy</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rueda</surname><given-names>David S.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CR1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lilley</surname><given-names>David M.J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CR1">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Single-Molecule Imaging Group, MRC-Laboratory of Medical Sciences, London, W12 0HS, UK</aff><aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Department of Infectious Disease, Faculty of Medicine, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/041kmwe10</institution-id><institution>Imperial College London</institution></institution-wrap>, <city>London</city>, <postal-code>W12 0HS</postal-code>, <country country="GB">UK</country></aff><aff id="A3"><label>3</label>School of Life Sciences, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/03h2bxq36</institution-id><institution>University of Dundee</institution></institution-wrap>, <city>Dundee</city>, <postal-code>DD1 5EH</postal-code>, <country country="GB">UK</country></aff><author-notes><corresp id="CR1">
<label>*</label>To whom correspondence should be addressed: <email>david.rueda@imperial.ac.uk</email> and <email>d.m.j.lilley@dundee.ac.uk</email>
</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted"><day>21</day><month>07</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="preprint"><day>19</day><month>07</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><permissions><ali:free_to_read/><license><ali:license_ref>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is licensed under a <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">CC BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p id="P1">Covalent linkages between chromosomes are naturally formed as a result of recombination or DNA replication. These can persist until late mitosis, resulting in interchromosomal ultrafine bridges, preventing cell division and causing genome instability. The endonuclease ANKLE1, localised at the cell midbody during cytokinesis and selective for DNA branchpoints, is ideally poised to act as an ‘enzyme of last resort’ to process interchromosomal bridges, enabling cell division to proceed. However, how ANKLE1 cleaves DNA under the tension existing in interchromosomal bridges during mitosis remains unexplored. Using optical tweezers, we show that ANKLE1 is a tension-stimulated endonuclease. High tension in DNA increases the ANKLE1 junction cleavage rate, with a twenty-fold increase at 60 pN. This indicates that ANKLE1 has evolved to respond to tension-induced DNA structural changes, thereby facilitating nucleolytic activity. This novel mechano-enzymological response of ANKLE1 reveals how it is well-suited to process ultrafine-bridges during late mitosis.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec id="S1" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p id="P2">DNA junctions arise as a natural consequence of recombination and DNA replication, covalently linking chromosomes together. If incompletely processed, these junctions lead to the formation of ultrafine DNA bridges linking chromosomes during mitosis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref>). Such DNA bridges can form in each cell cycle, their number increasing with DNA damage or inhibition of DNA replication (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">2</xref>). Interchromosomal bridges are thus a source of genome instability in cells—the persistence of a single linkage can prevent cell division or result in the mechanical rupture of DNA. Removing the DNA junctions that result in these bridges is so important that multiple pathways exist in eukaryotic cells for processing them. These include dissolution by BLM helicase and topoisomerase III or resolution by junction-selective nucleases, including the nuclear SLX4-SLX1-MUS81-EME1 complex and the cytoplasmic resolving enzyme GEN1 (reviewed in (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">4</xref>)). If junctions joining chromosomes have evaded processing by these pathways, one last enzyme can act late in the cell cycle to provide a final opportunity to process these remaining DNA branchpoints.</p><p id="P3">LEM-3 was first discovered as a GIY-YIG nuclease involved in DNA repair in <italic>C. elegans</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref>). Its mammalian (including human) ortholog, ANKLE1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref>), cleaves a variety of DNA junctions, including four-way Holliday junctions (4WJ), and three-way Y-junctions (i.e., a DNA duplex that separates into open single-stranded regions at one end) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1A</xref>). The Y-junction was found to be the best substrate for human ANKLE1, cleaving three times faster than the four-way junction. Recent genetic and cytological evidence suggest that the biological role of LEM-3/ANKLE1 is processing ultrafine DNA bridges in anaphase. LEM-3/ANKLE1 has been shown to interact genetically with other junction-selective endonucleases, such as MUS81, GEN1, SLX1 and SLX4 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>). Furthermore, LEM-3/ANKLE1 accumulates at the cell mid-body (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref>), a structure where the two daughter cells abscise from each other. Genetic evidence indicates that such localisation is important for LEM-3/ANKLE1 activity <italic>in vivo</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref>). Finally, chromosomal bridges induced by treatment with DNA-damaging agents persist in <italic>lem-3/ANKLE1</italic> mutants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref>). Thus, ANKLE1 is active at the right time, late mitosis, and present at the right location, the mid-body, to process remaining junctions. This suggests that ANKLE1 is the ‘enzyme of last resort’ in the processing of interchromosomal bridges to allow cell division to complete.</p><p id="P4">Segregation of chromosomes in anaphase requires pulling the unlinked chromosomes towards the spindle poles using pico-Newton (pN) mechanical forces generated by attached spindle fibres. The force generated to pull apart dividing chromosomes is estimated to be at least 50 pN (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref>). Any DNA bridging the separating chromosomes, thus must be under tension of a similar magnitude. To process these bridges, ANKLE1 must therefore act on DNA substrates under significant tension. Based on its suggested biological role, we hypothesised that the nuclease activity of ANKLE1 should respond to tension within its substrate. To test this, we used single-molecule optical tweezer experiments designed to study the ANKLE1-catalysed cleavage of DNA junctions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref>) as a function of tension.</p></sec><sec id="S2" sec-type="results | discussion"><title>Results and Discussion</title><p id="P5">We measured the cleavage rate of a 4WJ by ANKLE1 under tension using optical tweezers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref>). We utilised the hANKLE<sub>331–615 R492H</sub> nuclease domain of human ANKLE1 (referred to as ANKLE1) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1B</xref>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref>) and a 15 kbp central 4WJ construct with two 15 bp hairpins, as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref>), with individual DNAs tethered between two trapped beads. The 4WJ has been shown to rupture at ~20-25pN into a bubble due to loss of base pairing of the helical arms (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1C-D</xref>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref>). We observed a similar rupture under our conditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2A</xref>), with a rupture force <italic>F</italic><sub><italic>rupture</italic></sub>= 23 ± 2 pN (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2B</xref>).</p><p id="P6">Junction cleavage could be observed by holding the DNA at constant tension (force-clamp) and incubating with ANKLE1. The cleavage time (<italic>t</italic><sub><italic>cl</italic></sub>) was measured from when tension was applied until it dropped to zero, indicating double-stranded DNA (dsDNA) cleavage (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1E</xref>). We observed a marked dependence of <italic>t</italic><sub><italic>cl</italic></sub> on tension (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1F</xref>), which was not observed in the absence of ANKLE1 or with a catalytically inactive mutant (ANKLE1<sub>Y453F</sub>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1F</xref>). Therefore, ANKLE1 is a tension-sensitive endonuclease.</p><p id="P7">According to the Bell-Evans model (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref>), the application of external force (F) modulates the free-energy barrier (<italic>ΔG</italic><sup>‡</sup>), proportional to the logarithm of the cleavage rate (<italic>k</italic><sub><italic>cl</italic></sub> = 1/⟨ <italic>t</italic><sub><italic>cl</italic></sub> ⟩), by −<italic>F</italic>Δ<italic>x</italic><sup>‡</sup>, where Δ<italic>x</italic><sup>‡</sup> represents the distance between the reactant state and the transition state along the reaction coordinate. We observed two distinct tension-dependent behaviours (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2B</xref>). At low tension (&lt;20-25 pN), In <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>cl</italic></sub> decreases slightly with tension, characterised by Δ<italic>x</italic><sup>‡</sup> = − 0.4 ± 0.7 Å, indicative of a weak force dependence. By contrast, at higher tension (&gt;25 pN), we observed a larger positive force dependence, characterised by Δ<italic>x</italic><sup>‡</sup> = 2.5 ± 0.6 Å. At 60 pN, <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>cl</italic></sub> is ten-fold higher than at 20 pN. The inflection point between these behaviours occurs at 25 ± 5 pN, coinciding with the 4WJ rupture. This suggests that this inflection point arises from the 4WJ structure change, with the lower tension-dependence attributable to the intact 4WJ and the higher tension-dependence to the bubble (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2B</xref>).</p><p id="P8">To test this, we utilised a construct containing two central 24nt DNA strands incapable of base-pairing with each other, forming a ‘constitutive’ bubble even at low forces. This construct exhibited a linear In <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>cl</italic></sub> increase over the entire tension range, and a gradient corresponding to Δ<italic>x</italic><sup>‡</sup> = 2.4 ± 0.2 Å, nearly identical to the high-force regime for the four-way junction (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2C</xref>). The rates of cleavage of the cruciform junction and bubble constructs are closely similar at tension above 25 pN (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2C</xref>), indicating very similar activation parameters.</p><p id="P9">We expect the opening of the junction structure into an open bubble (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1D</xref>) to create structures similar to Y-junctions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1A</xref>) at the bubble extremities. To test the equivalence of the Y-junction and bubble substrates for ANKLE1, we conducted cleavage experiments in bulk solution for both structures using short substrates with the same dsDNA sequences (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="S4">Materials and Methods</xref>). The bubble substrate is cleaved identically to the Y-junction (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2D</xref>), with a <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>cl</italic></sub> = 0.16 min<sup>−1</sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2E</xref>). Thus, our experiments indicate that ANKLE1 cleaves the Y-junction-like structures formed at the end of bubbles (i.e., the best substrate for this nuclease) upon rupture of junctions under tension. We expect these ruptured junctions to be present in ultrafine bridges during cytokinesis.</p><p id="P10">Previous studies have shown that bubbles containing stretches of single-stranded DNA can also be formed in overstretched dsDNA, in particular, around catenations (<italic>i.e</italic>., braids formed between two intertwined dsDNA molecules) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref>). Such catenations form at the end of each round of DNA replication and can persist until anaphase, forming a separate, but equally prevalent class of ultrafine bridges (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref>). While not very active on dsDNA at zero force (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">8</xref>), ANKLE1 is capable of cleaving overstretched dsDNA held at forces above 60 pN (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2F</xref>) and at DNA catenations held at high forces of around 40 pN (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2G</xref>). This makes ANKLE1 an ideal endonuclease for the processing of all forms of anaphase bridges.</p><p id="P11">Finally, we see that the effect of tension on ANKLE1-mediated junction cleavage is not merely restricted to the formation of bubbles at elevated tension. If this were the case, we would expect the rate at which ANKLE1 cleaves junctions to plateau upon the formation of the bubble. Instead, <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>cl</italic></sub> increase with the applied tension well beyond the point we expect the junction to be disrupted, up to the tension believed to pull apart separating chromosomes. The sensitivity of ANKLE1 to tension is quite substantial. The rate of cleavage of the bubble increases 20-fold over the observed tension range.</p><p id="P12">We should emphasise that the observed change in rate with tension is that of a chemical reaction, the hydrolysis of phosphodiester bonds in the DNA. The origin of this rate acceleration is not known at present. The effect must result in an alteration in the reaction transition state that lowers the activation energy. Modulation of the active site structure likely results in ANKLE1 acting as a mechanosensitive endonuclease. It will be interesting to explore these changes in future studies.</p></sec><sec id="S3" sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="P13">ANKLE1 has been proposed as the enzyme of last resort for the processing of any junction linking chromosomes. All its previously described characteristics point towards this role: it cleaves a variety of branchpoints in DNA, and it acts at the right time and location consistent with the cleavage of inter-chromosomal bridges. We further show that ANKLE1 preferentially cleaves bubble structures in DNA, likely generated by ruptured junctions or overstretched catenated DNA. Such structures are expected to be very common within ultrafine bridges. The activity of ANKLE1 is markedly stimulated by the level of tension expected in the bridges. Intriguingly, the topoisomerase Top2α, involved in decatenating DNA catenations under low tension, is inactivated at similar high tension (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref>). This is, therefore, further evidence for the proposed biological role of ANKLE1 in resolving ultrafine bridges and thus allowing cell division.</p><p id="P14">The mechano-enzymological response of ANKLE1 to tension within its DNA substrate is, to the best of our knowledge, the first example of a nuclease regulated by mechanical force on the DNA. But Nature tends to repeat the use of mechanisms, so this is now a property that might be sought in other enzymes operating on DNA.</p></sec><sec id="S4" sec-type="materials | methods"><title>Materials and Methods</title><p id="P15">ANKLE1 was expressed in <italic>E. coli</italic> Arctic Express competent cells (Agilent) and purified using affinity and ion-exchange chromatography, as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref>). All optical tweezer experiments were performed as described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref>).</p><p id="P16">Extended methods are provided in SI Appendix.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="SM"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1"><label>Supplementary movie S1</label><media xlink:href="EMS207334-supplement-Supplementary_movie_S1.mp4" mimetype="video" mime-subtype="mp4" id="d59aAcEbB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD2"><label>Supplementary Information</label><media xlink:href="EMS207334-supplement-Supplementary_Information.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" id="d59aAcEcB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack id="S5"><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>We thank current and former members of the D.S.R. and D.M.J.L. labs for useful comments and discussions. D.S.R., K.K.R. and A.P.K. are supported by a core grant of the MRC-Laboratory of Medical Sciences (UKRI MC-A658-5TY10) and a Wellcome Trust Collaborative Grant (206292/Z/17/Z). D.M.J.L., A.D.J.F., F.L and T.W. were supported by a Cancer Research UK programme grant (A18604).</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="con" id="FN1"><p id="P17"><bold>Author Contributions:</bold> DSR and DMJL conceived initial studies. KKR, APK, ADJF, TW, DSR, and DMJL designed the experiments. KKR and APK performed optical tweezers experiments. KKR and DSR analysed the single-molecule data. ADJF and KKR purified the proteins. FL and TW prepared and purified the DNA. DMJL performed the bulk experiments. KKR, TW, DSR, and DMJL wrote the manuscript.</p></fn><fn fn-type="conflict" id="FN2"><p id="P18"><bold>Competing Interest Statement:</bold> Authors declare no competing interests.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><ref id="R1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Hickson</surname><given-names>ID</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>New insights into the formation and resolution of ultra-fine anaphase bridges</article-title><source>Semin Cell Dev Biol</source><year>2011</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>906</fpage><lpage>912</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21782962</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>YW</given-names></name><name><surname>Fugger</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>West</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Unresolved recombination intermediates lead to ultra-fine anaphase bridges, chromosome breaks and aberrations</article-title><source>Nat Cell Biol</source><year>2018</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>92</fpage><lpage>103</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41556-017-0011-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5742284</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29255170</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Freeman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Déclais</surname><given-names>A-C</given-names></name><name><surname>Gartner</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lilley</surname><given-names>DMJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biochemical and Structural Properties of Fungal Holliday Junction-Resolving Enzymes</article-title><source>Methods Enzymol</source><year>2018</year><fpage>543</fpage><lpage>568</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29458774</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sarbajna</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>West</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Holliday junction processing enzymes as guardians of genome stability</article-title><source>Trends Biochem Sci</source><year>2014</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>409</fpage><lpage>419</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25131815</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dittrich</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>LEM-3 – A LEM Domain Containing Nuclease Involved in the DNA Damage Response in C. elegans</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2012</year><volume>7</volume><elocation-id>e24555</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0024555</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3285610</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22383942</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brachner</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The endonuclease Ankle1 requires its LEM and GIY-YIG motifs for DNA cleavage in vivo</article-title><source>J Cell Sci</source><year>2012</year><volume>125</volume><fpage>1048</fpage><lpage>1057</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/jcs.098392</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4335191</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22399800</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Braun</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Meixner</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Brachner</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Foisner</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The GIY-YIG Type Endonuclease Ankyrin Repeat and LEM Domain-Containing Protein 1 (ANKLE1) Is Dispensable for Mouse Hematopoiesis</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2016</year><volume>11</volume><elocation-id>e0152278</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0152278</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4807109</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27010503</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Freeman</surname><given-names>ADJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Knebel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gartner</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lilley</surname><given-names>DMJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Human ANKLE1 Is a Nuclease Specific for Branched DNA</article-title><source>J Mol Biol</source><year>2020</year><volume>432</volume><fpage>5825</fpage><lpage>5834</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jmb.2020.08.022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7610144</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32866453</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Freeman</surname><given-names>ADJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Déclais</surname><given-names>A-C</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lilley</surname><given-names>DMJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biochemical and mechanistic analysis of the cleavage of branched DNA by human ANKLE1</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2023</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>5743</fpage><lpage>5754</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkad416</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10287932</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37216589</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>West</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>YW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Human Endonuclease ANKLE1 Localizes at the Midbody and Processes Chromatin Bridges to Prevent DNA Damage and cGAS-STING Activation</article-title><source>Adv Sci</source><year>2023</year><volume>10</volume><elocation-id>2204388</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/advs.202204388</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10131833</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36825683</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>LEM-3 is a midbody-tethered DNA nuclease that resolves chromatin bridges during late mitosis</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2018</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>728</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-018-03135-w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5820297</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29463814</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grishchuk</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name><name><surname>Molodtsov</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name><name><surname>Ataullakhanov</surname><given-names>FI</given-names></name><name><surname>McIntosh</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Force production by disassembling microtubules</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2005</year><volume>438</volume><fpage>384</fpage><lpage>388</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16292315</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rago</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheeseman</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The functions and consequences of force at kinetochores</article-title><source>J Cell Biol</source><year>2013</year><volume>200</volume><fpage>557</fpage><lpage>565</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.201211113</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3587826</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23460675</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kaczmarczyk</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Search and processing of Holliday junctions within long DNA by junction-resolving enzymes</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2022</year><volume>13</volume><elocation-id>5921</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-022-33503-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9547003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36207294</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Calderwood</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Forces and Bond Dynamics in Cell Adhesion</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2007</year><volume>316</volume><fpage>1148</fpage><lpage>1153</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17525329</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cutts</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name><name><surname>Saravanan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>GLM</given-names></name><name><surname>Rueda</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Aragon</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Substrate accessibility regulation of human TopIIa decatenation by cohesin</article-title><year>2023</year><comment>[Preprint]</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2023.11.20.567865v1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Finardi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Massari</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name><name><surname>Visintin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anaphase Bridges: Not All Natural Fibers Are Healthy</article-title><source>Genes</source><year>2020</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>902</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/genes11080902</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7464157</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32784550</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><bold>A</bold>) ANKLE1 substrates. <bold>B)</bold> Alphafold3-predicted structure of ANKLE1, highlighting Tyr453 (active-site), mutated in inactive ANKLE1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref>). <bold>C)</bold> Microfluidic chamber in optical tweezers with channels for (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref>) beads, (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">2</xref>) DNA, (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">3</xref>) buffer and (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">4</xref>) protein. <bold>D)</bold> 4WJ construct held between trapped beads showing 4WJ rupture. <bold>E)</bold> Representative tension-vs-time trajectories of 4WJ with ANKLE1 at low and high tension. Cleavage occurs where the tension falls to zero. <bold>F)</bold> Mean 4WJ cleavage time for WT ANKLE1 (N=78), inactive mutant (N=25) and buffer only (N=20). In the latter two, cleavage was sometimes not observed.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS207334-f001"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><bold>A)</bold> Representative force-extension plot of the 4WJ showing (inset) junction rupture at ~23pN. <bold>B)</bold> Rupture-force histogram (top) and In k<sub>cl</sub> vs tension for the 4WJ (bottom) with Bell-Evans fits. Shaded regions correspond to 23 ± 2 pN. <bold>C)</bold> In k<sub>cl</sub> vs force for constitutive bubble (dark) and the 4WJ (light) with Bell-Evans fits. <bold>D)</bold> Denaturing polyacrylamide gel of substrates and products of nucleolytic cleavage for Y-junction (Y-jxn) and bubble substrates after 5min ANKLE1 incubation. Arrows (right) indicate ANKLE1 cleavage sites. <bold>E)</bold> Denaturing polyacrylamide gel of substrates and products of ANKLE1 cleavage as a function of time (left) and quantification (right) fitted to a single-exponential. <bold>F)</bold> Mean cleavage time of overstretched λ-DNA (60 pN) with ANKLE1 (N=25) or buffer (N=14). <bold>G)</bold> Mean cleavage time of catenated λ-DNA (40 pN) with ANKLE1 (N=5) or buffer (N=3).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS207334-f002"/></fig></floats-group></article>