<!DOCTYPE article
 PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" article-type="preprint"><?all-math-mml yes?><?use-mml?><?origin ukpmcpa?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">bioRxiv</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>bioRxiv : the preprint server for biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2692-8205</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">EMS206981</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2025.06.14.659733</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="archive">PPR1038423</article-id><article-version-alternatives><article-version article-version-type="status">preprint</article-version><article-version article-version-type="number">1</article-version></article-version-alternatives><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Proximity-based super-resolution imaging 1 enabled by DNA base-stacking interactions</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Banerjee</surname><given-names>Abhinav</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yadav</surname><given-names>Saanya</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Vidwath</surname><given-names>Vedanth Shree</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kalita</surname><given-names>Simanta</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Agasti</surname><given-names>Sarit S.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Joshi</surname><given-names>Himanshu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CR1">#</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ganji</surname><given-names>Mahipal</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CR1">#</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Department of Biochemistry, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/04dese585</institution-id><institution>Indian Institute of Science</institution></institution-wrap>, <addr-line>Malleswaram</addr-line>, <city>Bangalore</city>-<postal-code>560012</postal-code>, <country country="IN">India</country></aff><aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Department of Biotechnology, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/01j4v3x97</institution-id><institution>IIT Hyderabad</institution></institution-wrap>, <city>Kandi</city>, <state>Telangana</state><postal-code>502284</postal-code>, <country country="IN">India</country></aff><aff id="A3"><label>3</label>New Chemistry Unit and Chemistry and Physics of Materials Unit, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/0538gdx71</institution-id><institution>Jawaharlal Nehru Centre for Advanced Scientific Research</institution></institution-wrap>, <city>Bengaluru</city>, <country country="IN">India</country></aff><author-notes><corresp id="CR1"><label>#</label>Corresponding authors. <email>ganji@iisc.ac.in</email>, <email>hjoshi@bt.iith.ac.in</email>.</corresp><fn id="FN1"><label>*</label><p id="P1">Equal contribution</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted"><day>11</day><month>07</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="preprint"><day>18</day><month>06</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><permissions><ali:free_to_read/><license><ali:license_ref>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is licensed under a <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">CC BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p id="P2">Super-resolution imaging has gained significant traction in recent years due to its unprecedented ability to visualize target biomolecules at nanometer resolution. Here, we demonstrate the capability to detect target pairs that are in close proximity by exploiting base-stacking interactions between two DNA strands, each labelling one target. Our DNA probes hybridize transiently with the each other only when both target molecules are proximal, thus creating a hybridization site for fluorophore-conjugated DNA strand, called imager. In this design, hybridization and co-axial base-stacking act synergistically to enable imager binding, with stacking interactions providing essential stabilization that allows for transient hybridization. This synergy generates the stochastic binding events required for DNA-PAINT imaging, which we call Stack-Proximity-PAINT (Stack-pPAINT). To gain mechanistic insights into hybridization of our probe, we performed atomistic equilibrium and steered molecular dynamics (MD) simulations. The simulations reveal that DNA base-stacking and fluorophore stacking together stabilize the imager. We utilized programmable DNA nanostructures to benchmark the applicability of Stack-pPAINT. As a cellular proof of concept, we visualized microtubular structures using Stack-pPAINT with antibodies targeting both alpha- and beta-tubulin molecules. This probe technology offers promising applications in cell biology research aimed at elucidating spatial interactomes at high resolution within cells.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>DNA base-stacking</kwd><kwd>DNA-PAINT</kwd><kwd>Super-resolution imaging</kwd><kwd>Molecular dynamics</kwd><kwd>DNA Origami</kwd><kwd>Kinetic analysis</kwd><kwd>Fluorescence</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="S1" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p id="P3">Every single functionality within a cell, be it prokaryotes or eukaryotes, is orchestrated by many protein molecules that closely interact with each other either directly or indirectly. These interactions occur at proximity to one another within the cell, thus enabling the intricate control over cellular processes. Detecting these interactions at greater spatiotemporal resolution has been a field that is actively evolving. Co-immunoprecipitation (Co-IP), yeast-two-hybrid, protein affinity chromatography and other such biochemical techniques have helped reveal great details on protein-protein interactions.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref></sup> These techniques excel in even detecting weaker interactions but fall short when one needs to understand the place within the cell where these interactions occur. With the advent of microscopy, FRET (Förster resonance energy transfer) based techniques allow for the detection of these interactions if the partners are present within a few nanometers (Förster Radii) from each other. This technique strongly relies on the ability to generate fluorescently labelled proteins or use antibodies with specific FRET pairs that can then be used to stain these proteins in fixed cells. This technique provides diffraction limited information for the exact position of the interacting pairs. Similarly, PLA (Proximity Ligation Assay) relies on DNA conjugated antibodies. These DNA strands get ligated with each other, enzymatically amplified, and would thus give signal if they are present within 30 – 40 nm from each other. This also allows for diffraction limited location information for the presence of protein interacting pairs. This low-resolution information, though valuable, keeps us in the dark regarding the density of these partners, separation between them and the finer distribution of these pairs within the cell.</p><p id="P4">Super-resolved microscopic tools to discern such partners at greater resolution would circumvent these drawbacks of FRET and PLA. Previous approaches have relied on exploiting DNA-PAINT (Points Accumulation for Imaging in Nanoscale Topography)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">2</xref></sup> with split docking strands, where the imager molecule binding is facilitated only when both parts of the docking strands hybridize via their stem portions to allow for a T-shaped platform for the imager to bind<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">3</xref></sup>, or a blocked docking site which is exposed by strand invasion by a nearby partner DNA<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">4</xref></sup>. These approaches are reliable strategies but bare unpredictable kinetics due to the role of multiple DNA strands that interact in a non-canonical manner.</p><p id="P5">In this study we outline a super-resolution imaging approach to detect protein-protein interaction pairs with the help of DNA-PAINT aided by stacking interactions to tune the detection of binding events. Conventionally, DNA-PAINT relies on the transient hybridization of DNA imager molecule with its complimentary docking strand for time durations that are detectable by a chip-based camera. We exploit the benefits provided by stacking interactions across a nick site adjacent to the site of DNA binding, that stabilizes the binding of imager molecules<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref></sup>. In the absence of this stacking interaction, the kinetics of this molecule is tuned such that there is no detectable signal upon binding between the docking strand and the imager molecule.</p><p id="P6">We have tuned the binding times such that only in the presence of the stacking pair, the binding event is stabilized sufficiently for it to be detected. To further explain the subtle but profound interactions occurring at the molecular level, we created all-atom models closely mimicking the experimental constructs and performed equilibrium and advanced sampling molecular dynamics (MD) simulations. Several microseconds long MD simulations enable us to visualize the nanoscale structures, dynamics and interactions of proximity-PAINT set up. As our approach takes advantage of stacking interactions to attain DNA-PAINT imaging of proximal molecules, we call it Stack-pPAINT (Stacking enabled Proximity-DNA-PAINT).</p><p id="P7">We validate the design of Stack-pPAINT using designer DNA nanostructures and then showcase their cellular application on the microtubular network composed of α-tubulin and β-tubulin heterodimers.</p></sec><sec id="S2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="S3"><title>Design principle of stacking-assisted proximity detection using DNA-PAINT imaging</title><p id="P8">Regular DNA-PAINT super-resolution imaging is carried out by acquisition of the transient binding events of fluorophore-attached DNA (imager) strand on its complementary (docking) strand for generating the required “blinking” events for super-resolved reconstruction of the data.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">2</xref></sup> Our recent study showed that an additional dinucleotide base-stacking interaction can significantly stabilize the imager strand (5- to 250-fold) on its docking strand in DNA-PAINT super-resolution imaging.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref></sup> In this report, we intended to design a super-resolution imaging sensor that specifically results in a detectable signal only when both docking strand and additional stacking interaction are present. To achieve this, we designed a six nucleotide (nt) docking strand which is too short to show any detectable imager binding. However, in the presence of an additional dinucleotide base-stacking interaction at the imager’s terminus via a stem DNA strand, we have fine-tuned interacting DNA strands that facilitate imager binding signal. As the detection is facilitated by DNA hybridization and base-stacking interactions, we named it Stacking-assisted Proximity-detection by DNA-PAINT (Stack-pPAINT) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1a</xref>).</p><p id="P9">In short, the docking strand in the Stack-pPAINT is constituted by two interacting DNA strands. First strand acts as regular docking strand of 6 nt in length but will not be sufficient on itself to allow detectable imager binding. The second strand upon hybridizing on docking strand creates the stem providing additional base-stacking interactions for the imager. Importantly, only when both strands are proximal to each other, we will detect the DNA-PAINT signal. Each strand can be used for encoding an individual biomolecule, enabling us to image the proximal molecules at high-resolution.</p><p id="P10">Each of the DNA strands are split into sections. The DNA sequence carrying the docking strand (pDS, proximity Docking Strand) is composed of a leash sequence, a stem sequence, and followed by a docking strand (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1b</xref>). The leash sequence serves as a freely extendable spacer allowing for a greater area of exploration. The stem region works as the AND operator, hybridizing to the complimentary strand carried by the interacting partner (pST, proximity Stem) when present at proximity to one another (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1b</xref>). This forms a platform for the imager strand to bind with both base-pairing and base-stacking interactions. The additional stacking interactions that arise from the recessed end of the stem are stabilizing in nature.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref></sup> This stabilization is tuned such that the presence of this interaction is essential for detectable binding events. In the absence of this interaction, the binding events would be extremely short lived thus would never be detected at the time scales of the camera’s frame rate and the extremely low signal-to-noise ratio that it would accompany.</p></sec><sec id="S4"><title>Molecular simulations highlight the interactions that drive proximity detection</title><p id="P11">To better understand the equilibrium conditions of Stack-pPAINT probe and study their relative stability across different designs, we carried out MD simulations using AMBER24<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref></sup>. We created four unique all-atom models (System 1: Proximity probe, System 2: Proximity probe without fluorophore, System 3: Proximity Probe with continuous strand and no nick between imager and stem, System 4: Proximity probe without stem for stacking interaction; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Figure 1</xref>) to study the effect of nick, site at which stacking interactions occur, and fluorophore on the imager on microscopic configurations of proximity detection system (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2a</xref>). To mimic the effect of distance constrains of the probe pair, we harmonically restrained O3’ and O5’ atoms of terminal nucleotide throughout the simulations with a spring constant of 1 kcal/mol/Å<sup>2</sup>. Two replicates of each all-atom models of DNA-dye constructs were simulated using NPT ensemble for 1 μs.</p><p id="P12">Starting with the fully hybridized conformations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2a</xref>), the double stranded (dsDNA) region containing 14 paired bases (System 1, 2, and 3) or 6 paired bases (System 4) largely remains stable during microseconds long equilibrium simulation. The root mean square deviations (RMSD) of the dsDNA with respect to the initially built structure saturates within 3 Å (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2b</xref>). Occasional breaking of two to three base pairs out of 14 was observed during the simulation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2c and 2d</xref>). As expected, the single stranded (14T) part of the models displays high flexibility adding significantly to RMSD of the entire DNA, 12Å- 14Å (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Figure MDS3</xref>). We notice that the base pairs of the dsDNA regions remain stacked throughout the simulation (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Movie 1</xref>), the other geometrical parameters, like helical twist, rise etc. also remain close to the canonical B-DNA conformations (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Figure 2</xref>).</p><p id="P13">The analysis of equilibrium simulation trajectory shows that the nick in the backbone between imager and stem (System 1) does not add any structural deviations compared to the non-nicked structure (System 3). The terminal bases remain stacked for throughout simulation (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Figure 2</xref>), suggesting that stacking interactions may be enough for maintaining the stability of the DNA duplex despite one nick on the backbone. The RMSD (2.8 Å) and average number of broken base pairs (0.59) are nearly identical for nicked and the non-nicked structures (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2b, 2c and 2d</xref>) affirming the strong base stacking interactions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">8</xref></sup>.</p><p id="P14">The dye-DNA interactions are interesting<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref></sup>, yet relatively less explored aspects of the hybridization kinetics of nucleotides. In all the systems containing the dye molecule, Cy3B is covalently conjugated to the overhanging 3' terminal nucleotide (DC3) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2a</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Figure 1</xref>) of imager and placed in an unstacked conformation at the beginning of simulation runs. During the simulations, the dye molecules exhibit a strong tendency to minimize solvent exposure by engaging in stacking interactions with the neighboring DNA bases likely driven by its polycyclic aromatic structure. Attributing to the strong stacking interaction of the dye to DNA, the dye containing systems show more structural stability compared to the non-dye DNA model (System 2) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2b, 2c and 2d</xref>). Principal component analysis of the backbone atoms from equilibrium MD simulations shows top three modes of conformational fluctuation in the DNA systems (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Figure 5</xref>) which corresponds to 60 % of the total motion.</p><p id="P15">To further understand the relative stabilities of the hybrids, we employed ASMD simulations where we pulled the imager away from the docking strands at a constant velocity of 0.5 Å/ns and measured the force-extension characteristics (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2e</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Figure 6</xref>). The work done by this external force is converted to free energy difference (ΔG) or potential of mean force (PMF) of the hybridized versus non-hybridized states using Jarzynski equality<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref></sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2f</xref>). During this 180 ns non-equilibrium simulations, (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary movie SM2</xref>), the number of hydrogen bonds between the imager and docking strand goes from 33 to 0, marking their complete detachment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2e and 2f</xref>). The estimated free energy (ΔG) to dissociate the imager from the docker ranges between 50 to 75 kcal/mol. The higher values of ΔG as compared to expected from nearest neighbor model<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref></sup> or experimentally measured free energy for similar systems<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref></sup>, could be due to ultrafast pulling velocities in simulations or due to notorious sampling problem. Nonetheless we believe the values qualitatively capture the trend correctly. The system 4 displays least stability in terms of ΔG which can be attributed to the missing stacking interaction between stem and imager (there is no stem). Comparing ΔG of system 1 and system 2, we find that that addition of dye stabilizes the system corroborating with the equilibrium simulations where extra stability from the dye was observed.</p></sec><sec id="S5"><title>Stacking interactions facilitate proximity detection</title><p id="P16">As an experimental platform, we utilized DNA origami-based nanostructures<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref></sup> to showcase the usability of Stack-pPAINT approach<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">3</xref></sup> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Figure 7</xref>). These modular structures allow for positioning of DNA strands in a myriad of ways at defined distances. We first designed staples where both the interacting partners emerge at distance of five nanometers from each other arranged in a 4×3 manner, where every pair is separated from one another by 20 nm (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3a and 3b</xref>). Under conditions where both pDS and pST are present, clear 4×3 grids are visible using the imager for Stack-pPAINT docking strands. In the absence of the pST, there are no signals visible from the Stack-pPAINT docking strand thus indicating the efficiency of our probes in enabling signal detection only under proximity of the target pair (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3c, 3d</xref>, and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Figure 8</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S6"><title>Leash and stem lengths dictate the efficiency of proximity detection</title><p id="P17">To establish the optimal leash and stem lengths for efficient proximity detection at varying distances between the two targets, we used DNA origami structures as molecular breadboards. We place the pDS and pST at varying distances with varying stem and leash lengths to quantitively establish their detection efficiency (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Figure 9</xref>). We observe that at a closest distance where pDS and pST are next to each other (0 nm), we achieve the highest efficiency in the absence of any leash nucleotides. By increasing the leash nucleotides at this length scale, we see a drop in the efficiency, likely caused by steric hindrance imposed by the additional nucleotides present in the local vicinity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3e(i)</xref>). When the targets are placed 10 nm apart, an interacting partner pair with a six-nucleotide stem is insufficient to allow any detection of proximity. Stem lengths of seven or longer start showing clear proximity detection signals with a nine-nucleotides stem showing the highest efficiency. This can be attributed to the tug of war between the interaction strength of the base-pairing in the stem and the inherent tendency of ssDNA to collapse due to shorter persistence lengths (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3e(ii)</xref>). A six-nucleotide stem would be entropically inefficient for such a weak duplex formation and would survive for shorter durations of time thus reducing the probability of stem formation and imager binding. A nine-nucleotide stem on the other hand is more stable which can overcome the entropic cost and thus would likely survive long enough to facilitate imager binding with stacking interactions. A similar but less pronounced effect is seen when the targets are placed 5 nm apart where a change from six-nucleotide to seven-nucleotide is sufficient to achieve almost maximum efficiency (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3e(iii)</xref>). Upon testing how nine-nucleotide stems affect detection with different leashes where the targets are placed 10 nm apart, we observe that a 15-nucleotide leash is necessary and sufficient to obtain maximum achievable detection efficiency (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3e(iv)</xref>).</p><p id="P18">To check if this combination of nine-nucleotide leash and 15-nucleotide stem facilitates non-specific target detection by facilitating non-proximity-based interactions, we placed the two targets 20 nm apart. Any signal from this condition can only potentially arise from the stable interactions between the two target pairs in solution prior to origami folding. We observe no detectable signal from this layout, prompting us to conclude that there aren’t any stable non-specific interactions occurring in solution that is driving the higher rates of proximity-detection (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3e(iv)</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S7"><title>Super-resolution imaging in cells using Stack-pPAINT</title><p id="P19">To extend this approach of proximity detection for use in cellular proximity detection, we labeled microtubule α-tubulin and β-tubulin subunits. For this, we used two different species of primary antibodies for labeling the individual subunits. Secondary antibodies of corresponding species were conjugated with pDS and pST. This brings a new hurdle where cooperative multi-strand interactions between the stem regions of the DNA could lead to non-proximity driven interactions between the secondary antibodies. This could lead to potential false detection of proximity where a single target is present at very high density. To circumvent this, (i) we conjugated secondary antibody to achieve a stochiometric average of three DNA strands per secondary antibody, (ii) we reduced the stem length from the most efficient number of nine nucleotides to eight nucleotides, where a majority of signal was still being detected. Next, we employed a rigorous chemical wash (30% DMSO in 1×PBS) to denature DNA hybridization to remove non-specifically bound antibodies via multivalent DNA hybridization. This step ensures to retain secondary antibodies directly bound to the primary antibodies but wash off secondary antibodies that were bound via DNA hybridization only (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4a</xref>).</p><p id="P20">We were ourselves warned about the multivalent interactions of the 8-nt stem formed between two secondary antibodies, which could stabilize them even in the absence of either of the primary antibodies, potentially leading to non-specific signals. As a control, we first stained cells with either of the primary antibodies to ensure only one of the subunits are stained (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4a</xref>). These served as negative controls where only one species of secondary antibody would have its target during staining. To directly assay the presence of the secondary antibody, we introduced orthogonal docking strands within the leash for pDS and pST. Under our stringent conditions – including washes with DMSO and fewer docking strands per antibody – we observe that, in cases where only one primary antibody was used, no signal from the Stack-pPAINT imager was detected, while signal from the secondary antibody in its cognate channel remained present (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4b</xref>).</p><p id="P21">In contrast, when both primary antibodies were present, we observe clear signals from the Stack-pPAINT probe. The measured width of the microtubular network was approximately 60 nm, comparable to values reported by other super-resolution imaging approaches (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Figure 10</xref>). This demonstrates the capability of our probe to resolve cellular heterodimeric populations with high-resolution (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4b</xref>). To further quantify the specificity of Stack-pPAINT, we assessed signal colocalization across the datasets where either primary antibody was omitted. Pearson’s <italic>r</italic> for the signal colocalization was very weak (below 0.1) in these controls, but strong (0.6-0.8) in the Stack-pPAINT condition (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4c</xref>), clearly indicating the specific and proximity detection enabled by our approach.</p></sec></sec><sec id="S8" sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="P22">We designed a novel DNA-PAINT probe that can detect cellular proximity with high-resolution and specificity with the help of DNA base-stacking interactions. We fine-tuned DNA probes design and stacking energies required for detectable binding of the imager with the docking strand only when two strands are proximal. We performed all-atom equilibrium and pulling MD simulations to quantify the binding energetics, and the interactions between the pDS and pST parts of the probe and the imager. The molecular level simulations reveal that the additional stacking interaction in the presence of the fluorophore provide a considerable stabilization, thus allowing for longer and detectable binding. We further showcase the usability of Stack-pPAINT in the cellular setting by imaging the microtubular network made up of α-tubulin and β-tubulin monomers. Our probe design can be readily adapted to visualize heterodimeric interactions within the cell at high-resolution. Utilizing qPAINT<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref></sup> along with Stack-pPAINT can further enhance the capabilities of this technique to extract quantitative information of heterodimeric interactions within cells.</p></sec><sec id="S9" sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec id="S10"><title>General Simulation Methodology</title><p id="P23">All-atom MD simulations were performed using the MD simulation program AMBER24<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref></sup>, periodic boundary conditions and particle mesh Ewald (PME)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref></sup> method to calculate the long range electrostatics. Cuda enabled pmemd.cuda<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref></sup> simulations were performed on RTX4080 machines. The Monte Carlo barostat<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref></sup> with isotropic position scaling and Langevin thermostat<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref></sup> with 1 ps<sup>-1</sup> collision frequency were used to maintain the constant pressure and temperature in the system. AMBER force fields<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref></sup> were used for describing the bonded and non-bonded interactions among DNA, water and ions. 8 Å cutoff was used to calculate van der Waals and short-range electrostatics forces. All simulations were performed using a 2 fs (femto-second) time step to integrate the equation of motion. SETTLE<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">20</xref></sup> algorithm was applied to keep water molecules rigid whereas RATTLE<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">21</xref></sup> algorithm constrained all other covalent bonds involving hydrogen atoms. The coordinates of the system were saved at an interval of 20 ps. The analysis and post processing the simulation trajectories were performed using VMD<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">22</xref></sup> and CPPTRAJ<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">23</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="S11"><title>All-atom model of Cy3B and its conjugation DNA backbone</title><p id="P24">Structure of Cy3B was taken from PubChem (CID: 44140555) and modified by adding amino linker – C3. The geometry of the molecule was subsequently optimized using Gaussian16<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref></sup> followed by vibrational frequency calculations to verify the optimized structure as a true minimum by checking for imaginary frequencies using Density Functional Theory<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">25</xref></sup>. B3LYP/6-31+G level of theory was chosen to balance computational efficiency and to include polarization functions to improve electron distribution description. The keywords iop(6/33=2,6/42=6) directives enable finer control over natural bond orbital and ensure correct charge distribution for subsequent computer simulations. Antechamber<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">26</xref></sup> program of AmberTools23<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref></sup> was used to make the covalent link between dye and DNA, and subsequently prepare input files for LEaP from gaussian output by using RESP charge fitting. Figure MD1A describe the covalent link of Cy3B to DNA backbone.</p></sec><sec id="S12"><title>Building of DNA Nanostructure</title><p id="P25">The nucleic acid builder (NAB)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27">27</xref></sup> module of AmberTools<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref></sup> was used to generate models of DNA with exact same sequence used in experiments. Poly-thymine within DNA were introduced using mutagenesis plugin of PyMOL<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">28</xref></sup> and the poly-thymine domain (31 bases on both strands) was further stretched and rotated in xLEaP to closely mimic the experimental setup. Mg<sup>2+</sup> counterions were added to neutralize the charge of DNA. Additionally, K<sup>+</sup> and Cl<sup>-</sup> ions were added to obtain 150 mM concentration of KCl using LEaP module that creates a coulombic grid of 1 Å around the solute and places the ions at lowest electrostatic potentials<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">29</xref></sup>. Finally, all the systems were solvated in a rectangular TIP3<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">30</xref></sup> waterbox ensuring 10 Å buffer around DNA. The all-atom topology and parameters were generated using xLeaP module of AmberTools<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31">31</xref></sup>. ff99SB<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32">32</xref></sup> DNA forcefield parameters with bsc1<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33">33</xref></sup> modification were used to describe the bonded and non-bonded interatomic potentials of nucleotides. GAFF<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34">34</xref></sup> module of AMBERTOOLs was used to parameterize the force field of Cy3B. Four such all-atom models were created namely System 1: Proximity probe, System 2: Proximity probe without fluorophore, System 3: Proximity Probe with continuous strand and no nick between imager and stem, System 4: Proximity probe without stem. Each system contained about 110K atoms and measured 10 x 10 x 10 nm <sup>3</sup> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 1</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S13"><title>Equilibrium MD simulations</title><p id="P26">Thus, assembled systems underwent 2000 steps energy minimization using a steepest-descent algorithm to remove any bad clashes in the system. Following the energy minimization, the systems were gradually heated up to 300 K in 1 ns MD simulation with 2 fs time step. While heating, all non-hydrogen atoms of DNA and Cy3B were harmonically restrained having 1 kcal/mol Å<sup>-2</sup> spring constants. Subsequently, we equilibrated systems for first 40 ns at 1 atm pressure and 300 K temperature to relax all water molecules and hydrogen atoms having same restrained atoms in heating at 1 kcal/mol and 0.1 kcal/mol. We constrained the O3’ and O5’ atoms of the docking stand and stem respectively in system 1-4 for whole simulation to mimic the immobilization to DNA origami surface (only O5’ in system 4 as there is no stem in this system) with a spring constant of 1 kcal/mol Å<sup>-2</sup>.</p><p id="P27">All systems were simulated with explicit water and ions at normal pressure (1 bar) and temperature (300 K) i.e. NPT ensemble. Two replicas of each system were simulated each lasting minimum 1 μs. Figure MD1(a) shows a typical snapshot of the systems at the beginning of the simulation. <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary movie SM1</xref> shows the all-atom MD trajectories of the simulated systems, water and ions are not shown.</p></sec><sec id="S14"><title>Adaptive Steered Molecular dynamics (ASMD)</title><p id="P28">After equilibrating the DNA systems for 20 ns with non-hydrogen atoms of DNA restrained, we performed adaptive steered MD simulation (ASMD)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35">35</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36">36</xref></sup> to study the unbinding of imager in all systems except system 3. We performed ASMD simulation with constant velocity of 0.5 Å/ns and a force constant (k<sub>spring</sub>) of 7.2 kcal mol–1 Å–2 on terminal oxygen atoms (O3’ of imager and O5’ of docking strand). These two atoms are highlighted in blue in figure MD1(f). We performed naïve ASMD<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37">37</xref></sup> in 9 stages pulling terminal oxygens from 14 Å to 104 Å, in each stage we ran 4 replicas. With the help of Jarzynski’s inequality<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref></sup> we determined the trajectory having work done closest to the Jarzynski average which was used for the next consecutive step. ASMD is useful in sampling large conformational space of hybridization along the direction of reaction coordinate while minimizing the computational cost. <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary movie SM2</xref> shows the steered MD trajectories of the simulated systems, water and ions are not shown for clarity.</p></sec><sec id="S15"><title>Buffers</title><p id="P29">10× Folding Buffer: 500 mM Tris-Cl pH 8.0 (Tris-Base, Sigma #77861; HCl, Fisher Scientific #29507), 125 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub> (SRL #) and 10 mM EDTA (SRL #35888).</p><p id="P30">Buffer A: 10 mM Tris-Cl pH 8.0 and 100 mM NaCl (SRL #41721).</p><p id="P31">Buffer A+: 10 mM Tris-Cl pH 8.0, 100 mM NaCl and 0.05% v/v Tween 20 (Sigma #P9416-100ML).</p><p id="P32">Buffer B: 50 mM Tris-Cl, pH 8.0, 10 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 1 mM EDTA.</p><p id="P33">Buffer B+: 50 mM Tris-Cl, pH 8.0, 10 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 1 mM EDTA, 0.05% v/v Tween 20.</p><p id="P34">Buffer I+: 50 mM Tris-Cl, pH 8.0, 10 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 0.2 mM EDTA, 0.05% v/v Tween 20.</p><p id="P35">PEM Buffer: 80 mM PIPES (SRL #49159), 5 mM EGTA (SRL #62858), 2 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, pH 6.8.</p><p id="P36">Cytoskeleton Extraction Buffer: 0.25% Triton X-100 (Sigma #T8787-250ML), 0.1% Glutaraldehyde (EMS #16020) in PEM, pre-heated to 37 °C.</p><p id="P37">Cytoskeleton Fixation Buffer: 0.25% Triton X-100, 0.5% Glutaraldehyde in PEM, pre-heated to 37 °C.</p><p id="P38">Ouenching Buffer: 0.1 mg/ml of NaBH<sub>4</sub> (Sigma #213462-25G) in 1× PBS.</p><p id="P39">Blocking Buffer: 3% w/v BSA (Sigma #A4503-50G), 0.05 mg/ml Salmon Sperm DNA (Invitrogen #15632011) and 0.25% v/v Triton X-100 in 1× PBS.</p><p id="P40">Antibody Incubation Buffer: 3% w/v BSA, 0.05 mg/ml Salmon Sperm DNA, 0.02% v/v Tween-20 and 1 mM EDTA in 1× PBS.</p><p id="P41">Buffer C: 1× PBS supplemented with 500 mM NaCl.</p></sec><sec id="S16"><title>Flow Cell Preparation</title><p id="P42">We prepared slides and coverslips for microscopic imaging of DNA origami nanostructures as described earlier.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref></sup> Five pairs of holes were drilled in slides (VWR #631-1550) using a diamond head drill bit (Meisinger #801-009-HP) on a drill gun (DigitalCraft #LRUXOR) mounted on a drill stand (Dremel #220-01 Workstation™). Slides and coverslips (Marienfeld #0107222) were washed with 5% v/v dish washing detergent and thoroughly rinsed with Milli-Q<sup>®</sup> water followed by 70% ethanol and once again with Milli-Q<sup>®</sup>. A double-sided tape (3M Scotch #136D MDEU) was sandwiched between slide and coverslip to assemble flow cells. Using quick setting epoxy (Araldite Klear), the open ends were sealed. All imaging experiments using DNA origami nanostructures were done using these flow cells.</p><p id="P43">We used tubing attached to the drills for the exchange of buffers and imagers in multiplexed origami imaging.</p></sec><sec id="S17"><title>PEGylation of slides for Efficiency Measurements</title><p id="P44">To minimize non-specific sticking of the imager strand on the glass surfaces, we utilized PEG passivated slides. PEGylation was performed as previously reported<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref></sup>. In brief, coverslips and drilled slides were washed with 5% dishwashing detergent prior to PEGylation. In case the slides are being reused, they are first sonicated (Bandelin # Sonorex Super RK 255 H) in Acetone (Supelco #1070212521) for 20 minutes. Slides and coverslips were then rinsed thoroughly with MilliQ<sup>®</sup> water then placed on a home built Teflon holder for further steps. The slides and coverslips were then sonicated in MilliQ<sup>®</sup> water for 5 minutes in a glass beaker where the Teflon holder is immersed. MilliQ<sup>®</sup> water was then replaced with 1 M KOH (SRL #84749) and sonicated for a minimum of 30 minutes. MilliQ<sup>®</sup> water was then used to thoroughly rinse the slides and coverslips for at least three times.</p><p id="P45">Piranha etching was then performed by adding about 225 ml of H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub> (Supelco #1934002521) to the empty glass beaker followed by 75 ml of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> (Oualigens #O15465). Caution is taken as this highly reactive mixture is dangerous and hazardous. The slides are etched in this solution for 30 minutes or until the reaction reaches temperatures below 50 °C.</p><p id="P46">Slides and coverslips are then rinsed with MilliQ<sup>®</sup> water thoroughly to remove all traces of piranha solution. Slides are then rinsed thrice with Methanol (Supelco Emparta #1070182521) and sonicated in methanol for about 20 minutes.</p><p id="P47">Next, aminosilanation is performed by adding the aminosilanation mixture containing 25 ml of APTES ((3-Aminopropyl)TriEthoxySilane) (TCI #A0439), 12.5 ml of Acetic Acid (Supelco #1930022521), and 262.5 ml of methanol prepared in a dedicated flask stored with methanol before and after every use; into the glass beaker containing the Teflon holder carrying slides and coverslips. Aminosilanation is performed for a maximum of 15 minutes following which the mixture is replaced with methanol at least thrice followed by MilliQ<sup>®</sup> water thrice. Slides and coverslips are then dried using compressed nitrogen gas.</p><p id="P48">These aminosilanated slides and coverslips are then passivated using mPEG-SVA (Layson Bio #mPEG-SVA-5000) and Biotin-PEG-SVA (Laysan Bio #Biotin-PEG-SVA-5000) dissolved in 0.5 M NaHCO<sub>3</sub> (Sigma #S5761) in a 4:1 ratio. 120 mg of mPEG-SVA and 30 mg of Biotin-PEG-SVA is dissolved in 960 μl of 0.5M NaHCO<sub>3</sub>. 60 μl of this solution is added to each slide and a dried coverslip is laid on it, sandwiching the added mixture. This setup is left overnight in a humidified box stored in a dark chamber.</p><p id="P49">The slides and coverslips are then rinsed thoroughly with MilliQ<sup>®</sup> water and then dried with compressed nitrogen gas before storing each pair in a 50 ml centrifuge tube ensuring that the PEG passivated slides are facing away from each other. The centrifuge tubes are then vacated and filled with inert nitrogen gas, sealed, and stored at -20 °C for up to 1 month.</p><p id="P50">Prior to use, the centrifuge tubes are placed and room temperature and are opened only after the temperature equilibrates. Flow cells are then prepared on these slides as mentioned above.</p></sec><sec id="S18"><title>DNA Origami Nanostructure Folding</title><p id="P51">All the staple sequences (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 2, 3 and 4</xref>) were generated using Picasso Design<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38">38</xref></sup> based on required design of DNA origami structures. All the DNA origami nanostructures were folded using an M13mp18 ssDNA (Bayou Biolabs #P107) scaffold. Origami structures were anchored to the surface via biotin-labeled oligonucleotide staples at 5’-end (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 2</xref>). Typically, we folded a 10 nM of scaffold DNA in a 30 μl of 1× folding buffer folding reactions with 100 nM of biotin and blank staples, 1 μM of staples extended with docking strands. The mix was incubated at 80 °C for five minutes before a stepwise cooling of 0.1 °C per every five seconds till room temperature in a thermocycler (Applied Biosystems™ ProFlex™ PCR System #4484073).</p><p id="P52">Excess staples from the folded origami nanostructures were removed using concentrator centrifugal spin filters (Sartorius Vivaspin<sup>®</sup> 500 #VS0132). The filters were wetted with Milli-Q<sup>®</sup> water and spun at 3000 ×g to remove water which was followed by 500 μl of 1× folding buffer. Freshly folded origami mix was diluted to 450 μl and applied to the column in 1× folding buffer and spun at 3000 ×g until the volume reached to below 50 μl. Another 450 μl of 1× folding buffer was added to the resultant, and this filtration was repeated three times to get rid of the excess staples. The origami structures were then collected and stored at -20 °C until use.</p><p id="P53">Each blank staple and biotin staple (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 2</xref>) was added in 10 molar excess to the scaffold. Staples for grid with direct extensions, 20 nm grid stack-pPAINT, and efficiency measurements were added in 100 molar excesses to the scaffold. Each blank staple is replaced by the corresponding grid, stack-pPAINT or efficiency staple as mentioned in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 3 and 4</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="S19"><title>Imager Fluorophore Conjugation and Purification</title><p id="P54">Fluorophore conjugation of DNA strands for preparing imager strands were done as per the published protocol.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref></sup> The imager sequences (Merck) were modified with amine at their 3’-end (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 5</xref>) and dissolved in Milli-Q<sup>®</sup> water.</p><p id="P55">Cy3B-MonoNHS-Ester (Cytiva #PA63101) was dissolved in DMSO (Sigma #D8418) at 13 mM concentration and Atto647N-MonoNHS-Ester (Sigma #18373-1MG-F) was dissolved at 11.8 mM concentration. Aliquots were stored at -20 °C. A 15 nanomoles of DNA in15 μl of 1× PBS and 0.1 M NaHCO<sub>3</sub> was mixed with five-fold excess of Cy3B-MonoNHS-Ester or Atto647N-MonoNHS-Ester. The reaction was run for overnight at 4 °C while gently shaking.</p><p id="P56">Excess fluorophore and the unconjugated DNA oligonucleotides were separated from the conjugated product using reverse phase HPLC (Agilent 1260 Infinity Series II, equipped with a quaternary pump system). An oligo column (Phenomenex #00B-4442-E0 Clarity<sup>®</sup> 5 μm Oligo-RP, 50 mm × 4.6 mm) was used for all the purification. The purification processes involved gradient flow of three solvents which included solvent A (0.1M TEAA + 5% ACN), solvent B (0.1M TEAA + 50% ACN) and solvent C (100% ACN). The fluorophore-conjugated DNA was then lyophilized, dissolved in Milli-Q<sup>®</sup>, and then stored at -20 °C for until its usage.</p></sec><sec id="S20"><title>Sample Preparation for DNA Origami Nanostructure Imaging</title><p id="P57">Microfluidic flow cells were assembled as described earlier.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38">38</xref></sup> First, a 10 to 15 μl of 1 mg/ml Biotinylated Bovine Serum Albumin (Sigma #A8549) diluted in Buffer A was incubated inside the channels. Next, the channel was washed Buffer A+. A 10 to 15 μl of 0.2 mg/ml of Neutravidin (Sigma #31000) dissolved Buffer A was incubated for around a minute. Excess neutravidin was washed with Buffer A+ thoroughly. Prior to imaging, the channel was washed with Buffer I+. Around 250 pM origami nanostructures diluted in Buffer I+ were introduced inside the flow cell and incubated for around 20 minutes. Unbound DNA origami structures were removed by washing with 600 – 800 μl of Buffer I+.</p><p id="P58">Gold Nanoparticles (Sigma #753688-25ML) were introduced into flow cell at a dilution of 1:10 in buffer I+ for 10 minutes and washed with 600 − 800 μl of Buffer I+ before performing imaging.</p></sec><sec id="S21"><title>Cell Culture</title><p id="P59">MEFs (Murine Embryonic Fibroblasts) were received as a generous gift from Dr. Kesavardana Sannula’s lab. They were grown in Dulbecco’s Modified Eagle Medium (DMEM Gibco #11995081) supplemented with 10% Fetal Bovine Serum (FBS Gibco #10270106) and 100 U/ml of Penicillin and 100 μg/ml of Streptomycin (Gibco #15140122) at 37 °C with 5% CO<sub>2</sub>. Cells were periodically maintained and split when they reached ~70% confluency. For DNA-PAINT imaging experiments, cells were trypsinized with 0.05% Trypsin-EDTA (Gibco #25300054) for 30 seconds to a minute at 37 °C. Cells were then resuspended in DMEM, centrifuged at 300 ×g at room temperature for 4 minutes and the supernatant was discarded. The pellet was then resuspended in 1 ml of DMEM and Countess™ 3 Automated Cell Counter (Thermofischer) was used to count the number of cells. 4000 cells were then seeded on an 8-well cover glass bottom chamber slide (CellVis #C8SB-1.5H) in DMEM. Cells were then grown overnight in the incubator.</p></sec><sec id="S22"><title>Antibody Conjugation and Staining</title><p id="P60">Antibody conjugation was performed as mentioned previously. In short, anti-mouse donkey (Jackson Immunoresearch #715-005-150) and anti-rabbit donkey (Jackson Immunoresearch #711-005-152) were used in all experiments (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 6</xref>). 100 μg of antibody was used for each conjugation reaction. Antibodies were buffer exchanged using 50 kDa spin filter (Sartorius VivaSpin<sup>®</sup> #VS0132) at 12000 ×g at 4 °C into 1× PBS at a concentration &gt;1.5 mg/ml. 5 molar excess of DBCO-PEG4-NHS Ester crosslinker (Jena # CLK-A134-10) which was dissolved in DMSO at a concentration of 1 μg/μl was added to the antibodies and incubated under a mild shaking condition on a shaker (Eppendorf #5382000023) for 2 hours at room temperature. The crosslinker was then separated using the same spin filters using 1× PBS with five rounds of repetition to dilute out the crosslinker. A conjugation ratio of about 1:3 for Antibody:DBCO is obtained. 5 molar excesses of Azide conjugated DNA strands were added to the respective antibodies (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 7</xref>) and incubated at 4 °C under a mild shaking condition on a shaker. Excess DNA was diluted out using similar steps as mentioned above.</p></sec><sec id="S23"><title>Cell fixation and staining</title><p id="P61">Cytoskeleton Extraction Buffer and Cytoskeleton Fixation Buffer were freshly prepared in PEM buffer prior to fixation. The cells grown on the glass bottom chamber slides were first pre-extracted with pre-warmed (37 °C) cytoskeleton extraction buffer for 30 – 45 seconds followed by fixation with pre-warmed (37 °C) cytoskeleton fixation buffer for 10 minutes inside the incubator (37 °C). Freshly made quenching buffer was then used to quench any free Glutaraldehyde for 7 minutes. The samples were then washed thrice with 1× PBS and stored at 4 °C for further processing. Blocking and Permeabilization is performed simultaneously with blocking buffer for 45 minutes to 1 hour. Primary antibodies (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 6</xref>) were incubated with cells in antibody incubation buffer overnight at 4 °C following which wells were washed with 1× PBS thrice. Similarly, secondary antibodies were incubated for 45 minutes at room temperature and washed with 1× PBS thrice. Cells were then incubated with a solution containing 30% DMSO in 1× PBS for 30 minutes at 30 °C. This step ensures all non-specific interactions mediated by the DNA molecules on the secondary antibodies are abolished. Cells were then washed with 1× PBS thrice.</p></sec><sec id="S24"><title>Stack-pPAINT Imaging and reconstruction</title><p id="P62">Both DNA origami structures and cellular samples were imaged on a Nikon Ti2E microscope body mated to a motorized H-TIRF unit and equipped with a Perfect Focus System (PFS). An oil immersion high NA TIRF lens (Nikon #Apo SR TIRF 100×, 1.49 NA, oil immersion) was used for TIRF (Total Internal Reflection Fluorescence) imaging along with the L6Cc laser combiner from Oxxius Inc, France for 561 nm and 640 nm excitation laser and a Teledyne Photometrics PRIME BSI sCMOS camera set at 16-bit readout sensitivity and 2×2 – pixel binning.</p><p id="P63">A 20× PCD (Protocatechuate 3,4-dioxygenase; Sigma #P8279-25UN) was prepared in 50 mM NaCl, 1mM EDTA, and 100 mM Tris-Cl, pH 8.0, and 50% glycerol to a concentration of 6 μM. The stock PCD was then divided into 10 μl aliquots and stored at -20 °C for future use.</p><p id="P64">A 40× PCA (Protocatechuic Acid / 3,4-Dihydroxybenzoic acid; Sigma #37580-100G-F) was made by dissolving 154 mg of PCA in 8 ml of Milli-Q<sup>®</sup> and 3 M NaOH (SRL #96311) was added dropwise and stirred until PCD completely dissolved. Volume was made up to 10 ml and 10 μl aliquots were stored at -20 °C for future use.</p><p id="P65">A 100× Trolox (6-hydroxy-2,5,7,8-tetramethylchroman-2-carboxylic acid; Sigma #238813-1G) was prepared by dissolving 100 mg of Trolox in 430 μl of methanol, 345 μl of 1 M NaOH and 3.2 ml of Milli-Q<sup>®</sup>. The solution was stored as 20 μl aliquots at -20 °C for future use.</p><p id="P66">For DNA origami structure imaging, 100 μl of imaging buffer composed of 1× PCD, 1× PCA and 1× Trolox was prepared in buffer I+. Imaging was performed with the 640 nm laser prior to 561 nm laser, both under TIRF illumination.</p><p id="P67">For cellular imaging, 200 μl of imaging buffer composed of 1× PCD, 1× PCA and 1× Trolox was prepared in buffer C. Imaging was performed with the 561 nm laser for all three rounds of imaging with an Exchange-PAINT<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39">39</xref></sup> modality. Between each round, sufficient wash with 1× PBS was until no localizations were observed in the absence of the imager.</p><p id="P68">Imager concentrations and imaging parameters are outlined in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 8</xref>.</p><p id="P69">Localizations were reconstructed and viewed using the Picasso<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38">38</xref></sup> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/jungmannlab/picasso">https://github.com/jungmannlab/picasso</ext-link>) suite of software. Cellular localizations were filtered to reduce noise based on photons, sx, and sy of the localizations. Filtering parameters are mentioned is <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 9</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="S25"><title>Stack-pPAINT efficiency measurement</title><p id="P70">DNA origamis nanostructures were picked based on the signal from the direct extension grids with a pick size of 1 pixel. Signal from the Stack-pPAINT channel was extracted from each picked location. The percentage of picks showing signal (minimum of 5 localizations within the pick area) from the Stack-pPAINT channel was calculated and plotted.</p></sec><sec id="S26"><title>Pearson’s r measurement for Stack-pPAINT</title><p id="P71">All three channels of signal from cellular localizations were aligned using RCC on Picasso Render. Localizations were binned into pixels of 65 × 65 nm. Number of localizations for each pixel was tabulated, and Pearson’s <italic>r</italic> was calculated across each set and plotted.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="SM"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1"><label>Supplementary Figures, Texts and Movies</label><media xlink:href="EMS206981-supplement-Supplementary_Figures__Texts_and_Movies.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" id="d17aAcEbB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack id="S27"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We acknowledge Department of Science and Technology, Ministry of Science and Technology, India DST-FIST Program funded Central Facility, Department of Biochemistry, IISc. This work has been supported by DBT/Wellcome India Alliance intermediate fellowship (IA/I/21/2/505928) to M.G. and the Department of Biotechnology (BT/PR40186/BTIS/137/3/2020) to M.G. We greatly acknowledge the support from Max-Planck Institute of Immunology and Epigenetics Freiburg, Germany in terms of partner group to Mahipal Ganji lab. A.B. acknowledges the support from the Prime Minister’s Research Fellowship (PMRF), Ministry of Education, Government of India. This work has also been supported by Anusandhan National Research Foundation fellowship (SRG/ 2022/002109) and the DST Inspire faculty fellowship (IFA20- PH-256) by the Govt of India to H.J. Supercomputing time was provided by PARAMSEVA through national supercomputing mission of Govt of India. S.Y. acknowledges the support received from Ministry of Education of Govt of India for her research fellowship. S.K. acknowledges the support received from Council for Scientific and Industrial Research, Ministry of Science and Technology, Government of India.</p></ack><fn-group><fn id="FN2" fn-type="con"><p id="P72"><bold>Author Contributions</bold></p><p id="P73">A.B. performed experiments, analyzed data, and wrote the manuscript; S. Y. perform MD simulations, analyzed data, and wrote the manuscript. V.S.V performed experiments and analyzed data; S. K. performed experiments; S. A. provided lab resources and supervised S.K.; H. J. designed simulations study, analyzed data and supervised S. Y., and wrote manuscript; M.G. conceived and supervised the study, interpreted data, and wrote the manuscript. All authors reviewed and approved the manuscript.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><ref id="R1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Akbarzadeh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Coşkun</surname><given-names>Ö</given-names></name><name><surname>Günçer</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Studying protein-protein interactions: Latest and most popular approaches</article-title><source>Journal of Structural Biology</source><year>2024</year><elocation-id>108118</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39214321</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jungmann</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Single-molecule kinetics and super-resolution microscopy by fluorescence imaging of transient binding on DNA origami</article-title><source>Nano Lett</source><year>2010</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>4756</fpage><lpage>4761</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20957983</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schueder</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Super-resolution spatial proximity detection with proximity-PAINT</article-title><source>Angewandte Chemie International Edition</source><year>2021</year><volume>60</volume><fpage>716</fpage><lpage>720</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/anie.202009031</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7839522</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32936507</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clowsley</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Detecting nanoscale distribution of protein pairs by proximity-dependent super-resolution microscopy</article-title><source>Journal of the American Chemical Society</source><year>2020</year><volume>142</volume><fpage>12069</fpage><lpage>12078</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32551615</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Banerjee</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Anand</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalita</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ganji</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Single-molecule analysis of DNA base-stacking energetics using patterned DNA nanostructures</article-title><source>Nature Nanotechnology</source><year>2023</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>1474</fpage><lpage>1482</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41565-023-01485-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10716042</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37591937</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Case</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>Amber 2024</source><publisher-name>University of California</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Case</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>AmberTools</article-title><source>Journal of Chemical Information and Modeling</source><year>2023</year><volume>63</volume><fpage>6183</fpage><lpage>6191</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.jcim.3c01153</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10598796</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37805934</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pieters</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Conformational and thermodynamic consequences of the introduction of a nick in duplexed DNA fragments: an NMR study augmented by biochemical experiments</article-title><source>Nucleic acids research</source><year>1989</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>4551</fpage><lpage>4565</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/17.12.4551</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC318014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2748334</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hübner</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Determining the In-Plane Orientation and Binding Mode of Single Fluorescent Dyes in DNA Origami Structures</article-title><source>ACS Nano</source><year>2021</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>5109</fpage><lpage>5117</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33660975</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jarzynski</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Equilibrium free-energy differences from nonequilibrium measurements: A master-equation approach</article-title><source>Physical Review E</source><year>1997</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>5018</fpage><lpage>5035</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>SantaLucia</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A unified view of polymer, dumbbell, and oligonucleotide DNA nearest-neighbor thermodynamics</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</source><year>1998</year><volume>95</volume><fpage>1460</fpage><lpage>1465</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.95.4.1460</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC19045</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9465037</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huguet</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Single-molecule derivation of salt dependent base-pair free energies in DNA</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</source><year>2010</year><volume>107</volume><fpage>15431</fpage><lpage>15436</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1001454107</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2932562</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20716688</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rothemund</surname><given-names>PWK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Folding DNA to create nanoscale shapes and patterns</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2006</year><volume>440</volume><fpage>297</fpage><lpage>302</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16541064</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jungmann</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Quantitative super-resolution imaging with qPAINT</article-title><source>Nature methods</source><year>2016</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>439</fpage><lpage>442</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.3804</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4941813</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27018580</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Darden</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>York</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Pedersen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Particle mesh Ewald: An N ⋅log(N) method for Ewald sums in large systems</article-title><source>The Journal of Chemical Physics</source><year>1993</year><volume>98</volume><fpage>10089</fpage><lpage>10092</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Salomon-Ferrer</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Gotz</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><name><surname>Poole</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Le Grand</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Routine microsecond molecular dynamics simulations with AMBER on GPUs. 2. Explicit solvent particle mesh Ewald</article-title><source>Journal of chemical theory and computation</source><year>2013</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>3878</fpage><lpage>3888</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26592383</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Berendsen</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Postma</surname><given-names>Jv</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Gunsteren</surname><given-names>WF</given-names></name><name><surname>DiNola</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Haak</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular dynamics with coupling to an external bath</article-title><source>The Journal of chemical physics</source><year>1984</year><volume>81</volume><fpage>3684</fpage><lpage>3690</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Loncharich</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Brooks</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name><name><surname>Pastor</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Langevin dynamics of peptides: The frictional dependence of isomerization rates of N -acetylalanyl- N '-methylamide</article-title><source>Biopolymers</source><year>1992</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>523</fpage><lpage>535</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1515543</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pérez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Refinement of the AMBER force field for nucleic acids: improving the description of alpha/gamma conformers</article-title><source>Biophysical journal</source><year>2007</year><volume>92</volume><fpage>3817</fpage><lpage>3829</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1529/biophysj.106.097782</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1868997</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17351000</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miyamoto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kollman</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Settle: An analytical version of the SHAKE and RATTLE algorithm for rigid water models</article-title><source>Journal of Computational Chemistry</source><year>1992</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>952</fpage><lpage>962</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Andersen</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rattle: A “velocity” version of the shake algorithm for molecular dynamics calculations</article-title><source>Journal of Computational Physics</source><year>1983</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>24</fpage><lpage>34</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Humphrey</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Dalke</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Schulten</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>VMD: Visual molecular dynamics</article-title><source>J Mol Graph</source><year>1996</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>33</fpage><lpage>38</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8744570</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roe</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheatham</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>PTRAJ and CPPTRAJ: Software for Processing and Analysis of Molecular Dynamics Trajectory Data</article-title><source>Journal of Chemical Theory and Computation</source><year>2013</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>3084</fpage><lpage>3095</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26583988</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Frisch</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>T</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name><name><surname>S</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name><name><surname>S</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name><name><surname>R</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>C</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Gaussian 16, Revision B.01</article-title></element-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Radom</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Harmonic Vibrational Frequencies: An Evaluation of Hartree-Fock, Møller-Plesset, Quadratic Configuration Interaction, Density Functional Theory, and Semiempirical Scale Factors</article-title><source>The Journal of Physical Chemistry</source><year>1996</year><volume>100</volume><fpage>16502</fpage><lpage>16513</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Kollman</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Case</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Automatic atom type and bond type perception in molecular mechanical calculations</article-title><source>Journal of Molecular Graphics and Modelling</source><year>2006</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>247</fpage><lpage>260</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16458552</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Macke</surname><given-names>TJCDA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Modeling Unusual Nucleic Acid Structures</article-title><source>ACS Symposium Series</source><year>2010</year><volume>47</volume><elocation-id>47-5657-5647-5657</elocation-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><source>The PyMOL Molecular Graphics System Version 4.6 Schrödinger</source><publisher-loc>LLC</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Joung</surname><given-names>IS</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheatham</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>III Determination of alkali and halide monovalent ion parameters for use in explicitly solvated biomolecular simulations</article-title><source>Journal of Physical Chemistry B</source><year>2008</year><volume>112</volume><fpage>9020</fpage><lpage>9041</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jp8001614</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2652252</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18593145</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jorgensen</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name><name><surname>Chandrasekhar</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Madura</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Impey</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparison of simple potential functions for simulating liquid water</article-title><source>The Journal of Chemical Physics</source><year>1983</year><volume>79</volume><fpage>926</fpage><lpage>935</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Case</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>Amber 2022</source><publisher-name>University of California</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco</publisher-loc><year>2022</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Cieplak</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kollman</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>How well does a restrained electrostatic potential (RESP) model perform in calculating conformational energies of organic and biological molecules?</article-title><source>Journal of Computational Chemistry</source><year>2000</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>1049</fpage><lpage>1074</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ivani</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Parmbsc1: a refined force field for DNA simulations</article-title><source>Nature Methods</source><year>2016</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>55</fpage><lpage>58</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.3658</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4700514</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26569599</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Man</surname><given-names>VH</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>T-S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A fast and high-quality charge model for the next generation general AMBER force field</article-title><source>The Journal of Chemical Physics</source><year>2020</year><volume>153</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1063/5.0019056</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7728379</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32962378</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ozer</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Valeev</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></name><name><surname>Quirk</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hernandez</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Adaptive Steered Molecular Dynamics of the Long-Distance Unfolding of Neuropeptide Y</article-title><source>Journal of Chemical Theory and Computation</source><year>2010</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>3026</fpage><lpage>3038</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26616767</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ozer</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Quirk</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hernandez</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Thermodynamics of Decaalanine Stretching in Water Obtained by Adaptive Steered Molecular Dynamics Simulations</article-title><source>Journal of Chemical Theory and Computation</source><year>2012</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>4837</fpage><lpage>4844</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26605636</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhuang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Bureau</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name><name><surname>Quirk</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hernandez</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Adaptive steered molecular dynamics of biomolecules</article-title><source>Molecular Simulation</source><year>2021</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>408</fpage><lpage>419</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schnitzbauer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Strauss</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Schlichthaerle</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Schueder</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Jungmann</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Super-resolution microscopy with DNA-PAINT</article-title><source>Nature protocols</source><year>2017</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>1198</fpage><lpage>1228</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28518172</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jungmann</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Multiplexed 3D cellular super-resolution imaging with DNA-PAINT and Exchange-PAINT</article-title><source>Nature methods</source><year>2014</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>313</fpage><lpage>318</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.2835</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4153392</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24487583</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Design of Stack-pPAINT probe.</title><p>(a) Base-stacking interactions facilitate detectable imager binding. (b) The split probe design includes pDS (proximity Docking Strand) and pST (proximity Stem).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS206981-f001"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Equilibrium and advanced sampling MD simulations show the effect of different components on probe stability.</title><p>(a) Left, a typical snapshot of the initial configuration (system 1) of dye conjugated DNA in solution. DNA atoms are shown using yellow (imager), red (hybridized with imager) and green (rest of the docking DNA) spheres. The volume occupied by water and ions is shown using transparent blue background. The dye molecule is shown is liquorish yellow. The covalent conjugation of the dye to DNA nucleotide (non-hydrogen atoms) is highlighted inside the dotted box. The atomic configuration of system 2 to 4 are shown without water for clarity. (b) RMSD distribution of dsDNA atoms (14 paired bases) with respect to initially built models. (c) Broken base pairs in the dsDNA region (14 bp long) as a function of simulation time for both the runs for various systems. (d) Boxplot showing the distribution of the total number of Watson-Crick hydrogen bonds between dsDNA. The simulation data from both the runs of respective system is concatenated for RMSD and hydrogen bonds shown in (b) and (d). (e) Instantaneous snapshot of the DNA illustrating various stages of ASMD. (f) (Top) Potential of mean force (PMF) and (bottom) number of hydrogen bonds between imager (yellow) and docking (green) strand as a function of the distance between oxygen atoms being pulled in ASMD simulations. The blue sphere highlights the terminal oxygens (O3’ of imaging strand and O5’ of docking strand) those were pulled apart.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS206981-f002"/></fig><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Stack-pPAINT efficiency.</title><p>(a) DNA origami design for assaying Stack-pPAINT modality. pDS is present in both the conditions. pST is either absent (left) or present (right) in either experiment, highlighting the need for stacking interactions in stack-pPAINT. Direct extension docking strands allow for visualization of the origamis with an orthogonal imager (Magenta) (b) Staple design for stack-pPAINT and expected location of signal. (c) Signal of Stack-pPAINT (yellow) in the absence (Left) and presence (Right) of pST at a distance of 5 nm to pDS. Origami locations were detected using direct docking strand extensions (Magenta), (d) Distribution of the number of localizations per origami with and without stacking interaction (pST present or absent). (e) (i) Efficiency with increasing leash length (L) at 0 nm distance (D) with Stem (S) length of C nt; (ii) Efficiency with increasing stem length (S) at 10 nm distance (D) with 15 nt Leash (L); (iii) Efficiency with increasing stem length (S) at 5 nm distance (D) with a Leash (L) of 15 nt; (iv) Efficiency with increasing leash length at 10 nm distance (D) and non-specific interaction control at 20 nm distance (D). Schematic of Stack-pPAINT (right).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS206981-f003"/></fig><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Stack-pPAINT in the cellular setup.</title><p>(a) Workffow for microtubule staining by Stack-pPAINT antibodies. (b) Secondary antibodies have internal strands to visualize each secondary antibody species. Only in the presence of both the primary antibodies does the Stack-pPAINT R5R imager show signal. (c) Pearson’s r of the localizations between each imager across all three experimental conditions.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS206981-f004"/></fig></floats-group></article>