<!DOCTYPE article
 PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" article-type="preprint"><?all-math-mml yes?><?use-mml?><?origin ukpmcpa?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">bioRxiv</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>bioRxiv : the preprint server for biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2692-8205</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">EMS206149</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2025.05.28.656555</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="archive">PPR1029139</article-id><article-version-alternatives><article-version article-version-type="status">preprint</article-version><article-version article-version-type="number">1</article-version></article-version-alternatives><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Integrating Alternative Fragmentation Techniques into Standard LC-MS Workflows Using a Single Deep Learning Model Enhances Proteome Coverage</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Levin</surname><given-names>Nikita</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Can Saylan</surname><given-names>Cemil</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lapin</surname><given-names>Joel</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Demyanenko</surname><given-names>Yana</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Kevin L.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sidda</surname><given-names>John</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nesvizhskii</surname><given-names>Alexey I.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wilhelm</surname><given-names>Mathias</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A6">6</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CR1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mohammed</surname><given-names>Shabaz</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A7">7</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A8">8</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CR1">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/01djcs087</institution-id><institution>Rosalind Franklin Institute</institution></institution-wrap>, <addr-line>Harwell Campus</addr-line>, <postal-code>OX11 0QX</postal-code><city>Didcot</city>, <country country="GB">U.K.</country></aff><aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Department of Pharmacology, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/052gg0110</institution-id><institution>University of Oxford</institution></institution-wrap>, <postal-code>OX1 3QT</postal-code><city>Oxford</city>, <country country="GB">U.K.</country></aff><aff id="A3"><label>3</label>Computational Mass Spectrometry, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/02kkvpp62</institution-id><institution>Technical University of Munich</institution></institution-wrap>, <postal-code>D-85354</postal-code><city>Freising</city>, <country country="DE">Germany</country></aff><aff id="A4"><label>4</label>Gilbert S. Omenn Department of Computational Medicine and Bioinformatics, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/00jmfr291</institution-id><institution>University of Michigan</institution></institution-wrap>, <city>Ann Arbor</city>, <state>MI</state>, <country country="US">USA</country></aff><aff id="A5"><label>5</label>Department of Pathology, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/00jmfr291</institution-id><institution>University of Michigan</institution></institution-wrap>, <city>Ann Arbor</city>, <state>Michigan</state><postal-code>48109</postal-code>, <country country="US">United States</country></aff><aff id="A6"><label>6</label>Munich Data Science Institute (MDSI), <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/02kkvpp62</institution-id><institution>Technical University of Munich</institution></institution-wrap>, <postal-code>D-85748</postal-code><city>Garching</city>, <country country="DE">Germany</country></aff><aff id="A7"><label>7</label>Department of Biochemistry, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/052gg0110</institution-id><institution>University of Oxford</institution></institution-wrap>, <postal-code>OX1 3QU</postal-code><city>Oxford</city>, <country country="GB">U.K.</country></aff><aff id="A8"><label>8</label>Department of Chemistry, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/052gg0110</institution-id><institution>University of Oxford</institution></institution-wrap>, <postal-code>OX1 3TA</postal-code><city>Oxford</city>, <country country="GB">U.K.</country></aff><author-notes><corresp id="CR1">
<label>*</label><email>mathias.wilhelm@tum.de</email>, <email>shabaz.mohammed@rfi.ac.uk</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted"><day>04</day><month>06</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="preprint"><day>01</day><month>06</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><permissions><ali:free_to_read/><license><ali:license_ref>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is licensed under a <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">CC BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p id="P1">We built and characterised a mass spectrometer capable of performing CID (both beam type and resonant type), UVPD, EID and ECD in an automated fashion during an LCMS type experiment. We exploited this ability to generate large datasets through multienzyme deep proteomics experiments for characterisation of these activation techniques. As a further step, motivated by the complexity generated by these dissociation techniques, we developed a single Prosit deep learning model for fragment ion intensity prediction covering all of these techniques. The generated model has been made publicly available and has been utilised in FragPipe within its MSBooster module. Rescoring allowed both data-dependent acquisition (DDA) and data-independent acquisition (DIA) to achieve on average more than 10% increase in protein identifications across all dissociation techniques and enzymatic digestions. We demonstrate that these alternative fragmentation approaches can now be used within standard data analysis pipelines and can produce data competitive to CID in terms of efficiency, but in the cases of EID and UVPD with far richer and more comprehensive spectra.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec id="S1" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p id="P2">Mass spectrometry is the key approach for proteomics analysis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref></sup> due to its specificity, sensitivity and speed. Information corresponding to the sequence is acquired by dissociating each proteolyzed protein peptide into fragments via an established process, recording the spectrum and identification by specialist software.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref></sup>Collision induced dissociation (both beam type and resonance based) has endured as the gold standard for peptide sequencing on account of its fragmentation explainability, reproducibility and outstanding speed.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">2</xref></sup> A variety of alternative dissociation techniques have been proposed as fragmentation techniques complementary to CID. These include, but are not limited to, ultraviolet photodissociation (UVPD) using photons of various wavelengths<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">3</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref></sup> and irradiation by electrons in a wide range of electron energies, such as electron capture dissociation (ECD),<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref></sup> hot-ECD,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref></sup> electron transfer dissociation (ETD),<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref></sup> and electron ionisation dissociation (EID).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref></sup> The electron-based methods, combined under an umbrella term ExD, differ from each other in the energy of electrons used and types of fragments generated. These techniques provide access to alternative fragmentation pathways that improve peptide sequence coverage and can allow for keeping CID-labile modifications intact. Among them, ETD and electron transfer/high-energy collisional dissociation (EThcD)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref></sup> were adopted in Tribrid Orbitrap instruments, advancing proteomics studies to a more accurate analysis of phosphorylated<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">20</xref></sup> and glycosylated<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">21</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">25</xref></sup> peptides. However, all of the alternatives (to CID) approaches have experienced anaemic uptake due to a catch-22 scenario: weak demand leading to less vendor attention on the development and subsequent delivery of complicated, compromised, low-efficiency and low-speed designs. As these techniques remain a niche, the motivation to build suitable data analysis software further exacerbate and lag against classical CID approaches.</p><p id="P3">In recent years, there has been significant progress in the development of more accurate tools for analysis of bottom-up proteomics data.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref></sup> In particular, it has been shown that using data-driven rescoring pipelines<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">26</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">30</xref></sup> based on predictions of peptide properties such as their retention time or fragmentation spectra greatly increase numbers of identifications compared to standard database searches.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31">31</xref></sup> However, while the focus of the proteomics community has been mainly set on developing experimental and analysis workflows for collisional data, the development of tools for UVPD and ExD data analysis is precluded by the scarcity of publicly available datasets for calibration of search algorithms. The generation of such data, in turn, requires a specialised, often custom, MS instrumentation. Recently, Papanastasiou and co-workers reported a novel instrument, Omnitrap, which represents a segmented ion trap allowing multiple ion-activation approaches within one mass spectrometry platform.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32">32</xref></sup> In collaboration, we built an Exploris-Omnitrap hybrid instrument that allows access to both common types of CID and multiple laser-and electron-based dissociation techniques and demonstrated it for top down proteomics.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33">33</xref></sup> Herein, we further developed this instrument to operate on an LCMS time scale in an automated fashion. We set out to generate a large dataset of UVPD, EID and ECD fragmentation of peptides which we will use to develop prediction models using the Prosit deep learning model<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27">27</xref></sup> with the intention of improving data analysis through spectra rescoring and opening up these dissociation techniques to newer MS operation approaches such as data-independent acquisition (DIA).</p></sec><sec id="S2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="S3"><title>Development of Omnitrap UVPD, ECD and EID LCMS methods</title><p id="P4">The results of our recent development and characterisation of UVPD, EID and ECD on the Omnitrap platform<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33">33</xref></sup> suggested that our configuration could be deployed in an LCMS data-dependent fashion for the analysis of complex peptide mixtures. As the conditions in direct-infusion experiments from our earlier work, such as number of available ions, injection times and ion transfer logistics, are typically more relaxed compared to automated LCMS analysis, an investigation is required to determine the optimal parameters for all dissociation techniques in LCMS experiments. Direct-infusion experiments reported previously<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33">33</xref></sup> were focused on higher resolution and signal/noise with no regard to duty cycle. As acquisition of spectra with this Orbitrap-Omnitrap configuration has limited parallelization potential (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. S1a</xref>), we initially concentrated on reducing the scan length to increase the number of recorded spectra as it is necessary to handle the complexity of proteomes. The Omnitrap design requires ions to be cooled through a gas pulse prior to any ion manipulation. The original design used a single gas valve that had a maximum repetition rate of 10 Hz (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. S1b</xref>). In order to improve the maximum rate of the Omnitrap we implemented the use of two valves, operating alternately, for gas injection, which results in potentially doubling speed (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. S1b</xref>). Subsequently, we optimised the direct current (DC) potentials for ion transfer within the Omnitrap to reduce the background collisional fragmentation (<xref ref-type="sec" rid="S22">Supplementary Notes</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. S2, S3</xref>). We then focussed on increasing the numbers of identifications in LCMS experiments through application of pragmatic parameters for spectra acquisition (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig 1a</xref>). We began with the characterisation of UVPD. As there are two parameters of UVPD that can be changed, namely, the number and energy of laser pulses, we first varied the number of laser pulses at a fixed energy of 3 mJ/pulse and then varied the energy for the same number of pulses. For data analysis, we started with using only <italic>b</italic> and <italic>y</italic> ions for identification, as they were previously shown to be the most abundant in UVPD of tryptic peptides.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34">34</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35">35</xref></sup> The analysis shows that increasing the number of laser pulses leads to greater numbers of identified PSMs and peptide sequences until a maximum is reached at four pulses (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1b</xref>). Further increasing the number of laser pulses used for dissociation results in an insignificant drop of identification rates, either due to secondary fragmentation or reduced scan rate. We selected four pulses for further investigation and varied the energy of each pulse. In this series of experiments, the maximum of identified PSMs and peptide sequences was observed at distinct energies depending on the type of fragment ions used for identification (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1c</xref>). Please see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 1</xref> for structures and definitions of all fragment ions considered in this work. Using only <italic>b</italic> and <italic>y</italic> fragments, the maximum is observed at 5 mJ/pulse, while when other types of fragments characteristic of UVPD are employed, namely <italic>a,c,x,z</italic>,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">4</xref></sup> the maximum is located at 6 mJ/pulse. As we reasoned that <italic>a,c,x,z</italic> in contrast to <italic>b</italic>,<italic>y</italic> are more unique to UVPD, we opted for using 6 mJ/pulse in future experiments.</p><p id="P5">Next, we studied the optimal reaction times for EID. In typical ExD experiments, ions are transferred into the reaction chamber and undergo irradiation by electrons emitted by a heated filament<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32">32</xref></sup> during a specified amount of time (<xref ref-type="sec" rid="S22">Supplementary notes</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. S4</xref>). In EID experiments, we varied the irradiation times from 25 ms to 150 ms and measured the numbers of identified PSMs and peptides. We observed that <italic>b</italic> and <italic>y</italic> ions can be the most prominent in EID. When using just these two ions for analysis, the numbers of PSMs and peptides reach their maximum values at 50 ms of irradiation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1d</xref>). At longer irradiation times, these numbers start to drop. Interestingly, the profile of peptide identification shows a much more distinctive dependence on the type of ions used for analysis compared to UVPD (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1d</xref>). At shorter irradiation times, <italic>a,c,x,z</italic> fragments are underrepresented compared to those of <italic>b,y</italic>, and the largest number of PSMs and peptides was observed at 75 ms (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1d</xref>). For the sake of absolute numbers of identifications, we chose to continue with 50 ms irradiation time. Finally, we optimised ECD where we used <italic>c</italic> and <italic>z</italic> type fragments for the data analysis and found 50 ms of irradiation to be optimal (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1e</xref>). We did not investigate other main-series types of fragments, as the absolute majority of products produced in ECD of relatively short peptides are <italic>c</italic> and <italic>z</italic> type ions.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">8</xref></sup> Since ECD is known to be a charge-dependent process favouring higher charge states, the value of 50 ms obtained using mainly doubly charged and less frequently triply charged precursors of tryptic peptides can be considered rather conservative. In order to characterize the fragmentation behaviour of ECD, UVPD and EID, a larger and more diverse range of peptides is required.</p></sec><sec id="S4"><title>Large-scale multi-enzyme Omnitrap-LCMS analysis</title><p id="P6">We increased diversity through use of more proteases, and we increased peptide depth by utilising offline fractionation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2a</xref>). We chose trypsin, LysC, GluC, chymotrypsin and LysN as they have been shown to produce complementary results in terms of peptide length, protein sequence coverage, and frequencies and positions of amino acid residues across the peptide backbone.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36">36</xref></sup> Next, we fractionated each digest<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37">37</xref></sup> into 20 pooled fractions and subjected all to ECD, EID, beam type CID (referred to as higher-energy collision induced dissociation or ‘HCD’ on Thermo instrumentation) and UVPD LCMS analyses. The choice of LC gradient time for the dissociation techniques was based on their maximal sequencing rate and to ensure they all produced similar numbers of scans.</p><p id="P7">The analysis of UVPD, EID and ECD data is not as straightforward as that of HCD data. The major products of HCD are well characterised, with <italic>a</italic>,<italic>b</italic>,<italic>y</italic> ions dominating data. In contrast, UVPD and EID are known to produce all main-series types of peptide fragments as well as some radical <italic>a+1</italic> and <italic>x+1</italic> ions,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38">38</xref></sup> with the latter two largely understudied. The average proportions of each type of main-series fragments have been reported for UVPD;<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34">34</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35">35</xref></sup> however, the effects of using these ions and their combinations in the automated data analysis have not been extensively discussed. We therefore analysed the acquired raw data using several unique combinations of the expected fragment types with the goal to maximise the numbers of identified PSMs while maintaining the same 1% false discovery rate (FDR). For ECD, the most important ions for robust identification were <italic>c</italic> and <italic>z</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2b</xref>). The addition of <italic>c-1</italic> or <italic>z+1</italic> had a minimal and slightly detrimental effect. Analogously, <italic>b</italic> and <italic>y</italic> were the dominant ion types for both EID and UVPD. However, <italic>a,a+1,c, z</italic> ions were beneficial for improving identification rates for EID, while <italic>b, y</italic> showed the best results in UVPD. The numbers when broken down to individual enzyme are similar to the global result, although tryptic and LysC peptides enhance the formation of <italic>z+1</italic> ions while impairing the formation of <italic>c-1</italic> in ECD and favour the generation of <italic>y</italic> ions in EID and UVPD compared to other enzymes (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. S5</xref>). The results for the UVPD and EID seem to be strongly dependent on <italic>y</italic> ions and to a smaller degree on <italic>b</italic> ions. While no extensive literature exists for EID, our UVPD data agrees with previous findings. Others also found that <italic>b</italic> and <italic>y</italic> fragments are the most abundant types of ions in 193 nm UVPD of tryptic peptides, and the ion current of <italic>y</italic> fragments is approximately double of that of <italic>b</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34">34</xref></sup> Similarly, <italic>b</italic> and <italic>y</italic> fragments dominate the spectra in 213 nm UVPD of tryptic peptides, and the average number of annotated <italic>y</italic> fragments is twice that of <italic>b</italic> ions.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35">35</xref></sup></p><p id="P8">All four fragmentation techniques produced similar numbers of PSMs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2c</xref>). In total, EID data had the least number of PSMs (approximately 900k), while UVPD, which has the fastest acquisition rate among all Omnitrap techniques studied here, had 1141k. Surprisingly, the charge-dependent ECD came closest to UVPD with 1070k PSMs, even though its scan rate was essentially the same as EID. HCD showed the highest numbers with 1160k PSMs. Pleasingly, the efficiency of peptide sequencing by EID and UVPD, expressed as the ratio between the numbers of PSMs and MS2 scans, is essentially the same as by HCD, and the efficiency of sequencing by ECD is higher by approximately 5% (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2c</xref>). This was surprising considering the relative inefficiency of ECD for doubly charged peptides which represent a substantial subset of identified peptides (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. S6</xref>).</p><p id="P9">The MSFragger hyperscore (generated for each PSM) can serve as an indirect measure of the number of fragments found in a spectrum in relation to the number of fragments expected for that peptide, akin to a spectrum quality score.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39">39</xref></sup> We plotted distributions of hyperscores of all unique precursors (<italic>i.e.</italic>, unique combinations of amino-acid sequences, charge states, and modifications, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. S7</xref>) per charge state using <italic>c,z</italic> fragments in ECD and <italic>b,y</italic> fragments in UVPD, EID and HCD (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2d</xref>). Expectedly, distributions of hyperscores in ECD are strongly charge-dependent, with doubly charged precursor assigned with substantially lower values. Furthermore, the hyperscore distributions for 3+ and 4+ precursors in ECD have an apparent maximum at 800 Th. A similar trend was reported earlier by Good <italic>et al.</italic> for ETD of tryptic and LysC peptides, where the percent of bonds cleaved by ETD begins to drop at approximately 600 Th for 3+ precursors and 650 Th for 4+ ones.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref></sup> When analysing solely <italic>b</italic> and <italic>y</italic> ion series, EID, UVPD and HCD all show very similar hyperscore distributions for the same charge states of precursors (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2d</xref>). The upper boundaries of hyperscore distributions for these dissociation techniques start to drop beyond approximately 2500 Da. We interpret these observations as the reduction of the signal-to-noise (S/N) ratio that follows the spreading of available fragment signal across larger numbers of produced fragments in spectra of long and highly charged peptides, <italic>i.e.</italic> signal splitting. The difference in number of identifications with same 1% FDR was marginal for UVPD and EID when we increased the number of fragment types all the way up to <italic>a,b,c,x,y,z</italic>, as long as <italic>b</italic> and <italic>y</italic> fragments were included (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2b</xref>). We therefore investigated how choice of types of fragments for analysis affects hyperscores (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2e</xref>). Clearly, increasing the search space by adding more types of fragments results in greatly improved hyperscores for both EID and UVPD, indicating larger numbers of dissociated bonds and data rich spectra.</p></sec><sec id="S5"><title>Deep learning modelling of UVPD, EID and ECD fragment intensities</title><p id="P10">Following data collection, we asked the question whether we can employ advance data analysis techniques to improve search results by making use of the high values of hyperscores produced in ECD, EID and UVPD. Scoring can be remarkably boosted if peptide-spectrum matching is performed against experimental or <italic>in-silico</italic> generated spectral libraries.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31">31</xref></sup> Deep learning models have demonstrated promising results in predicting CID-based spectra of peptides using just peptide sequence, charge state and collisional energy as input,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">26</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40">40</xref></sup> but no such models exist for other fragmentation techniques due to lack of data for training. We therefore set out to use the datasets generated in this work to train a deep learning algorithm for prediction of EID, ECD, HCD and UVPD fragmentation spectra. Training a deep model requires turning the raw data into a dataset containing correctly annotated peak intensities. This implies that we need to solve potential clashes such as, for example, <italic>a+1</italic> ion, which is a radical <italic>a</italic> ion coupled with an additional hydrogen atom, <italic>versus</italic> the <sup>13</sup>C peak for an <italic>a</italic> ion (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Tabe 1</xref>). For all datasets, we performed an automated annotation of major fragment types expected in EID, ECD and UVPD (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 1</xref>) in the Oktoberfest framework.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">30</xref></sup> The comparison of [<italic>a+1</italic>]/[<italic>a</italic>] ratio in HCD, EID and UVPD suggests that a high proportion of <italic>a+1</italic> in EID and UVPD spectra are ions originating from gas-phase electron-and photon-based chemistries (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3a</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. S8</xref>-<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">12</xref> and <xref ref-type="sec" rid="S22">Supplementary Notes</xref>). Annotated spectra in hand, we could define our model’s ion dictionary and curate training and validation datasets. The original Prosit model<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27">27</xref></sup> architecture was designed around a structured output space, <italic>i.e. b</italic> and <italic>y</italic> fragments with lengths 1-29 and charges +1, +2 and +3. By contrast, the model trained on our data has an unstructured output space, with fragment ions chosen based on frequency of occurrence (greater than or equal to 100 occurrences, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. S9</xref>-<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">12</xref>). Besides peptide sequence and precursor charge, the model also takes the categorical fragmentation type as input; since the HCD data was acquired on a single instrument, it was unnecessary to use collision energy as additional input to the model, as was performed for previous Prosit models.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27">27</xref></sup> Our model shares the similarity with the original Prosit model insofar that the sequence and metadata are separately encoded into latent spaces and combined in the interior of the network, but the metadata has slightly changed, and the model outputs the intensities of 815 fragments of various length, charge and fragment type (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3b</xref>). Results show very little overtraining: the median Pearson correlations for ECD, UVPD, HCD and EID are 0.919, 0.931, 0.950 and 0.897, respectively, on the training set, and the corresponding scores for the test set are only ~0.005 points behind for each fragmentation method (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3c</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. S13</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S14</xref>). We further observe that precursor charge is quite consequential for prediction performance, with precursor charges greater than 2 displaying an increasingly wide range of Pearson correlations, likely due to the sparsity of high charge precursors in the training set and increasingly complex fragment ions present in the spectra. Although the model outputs predicted intensities for fragments of all types, no matter the fragmentation method, we see that conditioned on the fragmentation method the model reliably assigns appreciable intensity only to those fragments expected for each fragmentation method, e.g. <italic>b</italic> and <italic>y</italic> for HCD and <italic>c</italic> and <italic>z</italic> for ECD (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3d</xref>,<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">e</xref>). The model is also able to predict intensities of <italic>b</italic>, <italic>y</italic> and minor fragments, such as <italic>a</italic>, <italic>a+1</italic>, <italic>x</italic>, <italic>x+1</italic>, <italic>c</italic>, <italic>z</italic>, in UVPD and EID, although the predictions of low-intensity ions for the latter seem slightly less accurate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3f</xref>,<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">g</xref>). With this model in hand, these activation methods can now benefit from any state-of-the-art processing, be it data-driven rescoring, DIA or proteome-wide spectral library searching.</p></sec><sec id="S6"><title>Rescoring of the UVPD, ECD and EID data using fragment intensities predictions</title><p id="P11">An efficient control of FDR in database searching is critical for identification of true positive peptide matches. Previously, we showed that data-driven rescoring of CID data using the Prosit deep learning model greatly improved numbers and accuracy of peptide identifications.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27">27</xref></sup> We hypothesized that predicting fragment intensities would be beneficial for improving the results of the database searches of UVPD, EID and ECD data as well. We started with a coarse and indirect estimate of the effect of predictions on the separation of target PSMs from decoys. Using the optimised MSFragger results we first calculated the ratios between the numbers of all observed and all possible theoretical fragment ions in each identified spectrum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4a</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. S15</xref>, upper distributions). The resulting distributions for target and decoy PSMs were heavily intermixed and shifted towards smaller ratios. EID and UVPD ratios were particularly small due to a large number of theoretical ions. We then calculated the same ratios but only allowed fragments predicted by Prosit (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4a</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. S15</xref>, lower distributions). Including only predicted fragments split the distribution of ratios of target PSMs, where the majority shifted towards higher values with a larger portion being above 0.8, and the remainder were essentially unchanged. At the same time, the ratios of decoy PSMs remained clustered at lower values. This indicates a substantial improvement in alignment between the observed and the predicted fragment ions.</p><p id="P12">Next, we applied data-driven rescoring using the Oktoberfest framework, which benefits from the here-developed fragment intensity prediction model by generating fragment intensity-dependent scores rather than only relying on the presence or absence of fragments. In combination with Percolator,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41">41</xref></sup> these scores are aggregated into a single score that maximizes the separation of correct and incorrect matches. The resulting Oktoberfest scores were then compared to the Percolator-derived scores from MSFragger (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4b</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. S16</xref>-<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">19</xref>), which do not include fragment intensity-based features. For MSFragger database searches, we chose the best combinations of ion types for each fragmentation method from <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2b</xref>, and for rescoring in Oktoberfest we employed all the most frequently annotated types of fragments (&gt;4% of annotated ions in a spectrum, averaged across all spectra) for each fragmentation technique (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. S8</xref>). Both sets of scores were filtered to 1% FDR using Percolator.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41">41</xref></sup> While rescoring led to remarkable separation of decoys from targets for the majority of enzyme-fragmentation method pairs (as exemplified in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig 4b</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. S16</xref>-<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">19</xref>), ECD in general demonstrated sufficient separation in database searches, such that rescoring only delivers marginal improvements in identifications (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. S16</xref>). This in part explains the highest identification rate identified for ECD in the initial database searches (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2c</xref>). We attribute this to the relative cleanliness of ECD spectra (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3a</xref>) that consist primarily of <italic>c</italic> and <italic>z</italic> type fragments, precursor ions and charge-reduced species, thus reducing chances for random false matches. Interestingly, ECD was the only technique where it was possible to discriminate the distributions of charge states among target PSMs, which reflects the distinct charge-dependent kinetics of this process (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. S20</xref>). Using rescoring, we were able to salvage a substantial number of PSMs in all combinations of enzyme and dissociation method (quadrant II in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig 4b</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. S16</xref>-<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">19</xref>). At the same time, a fair number of PSMs initially identified were discarded as false positives (quadrant IV in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig 4b</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. S16</xref>-<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">19</xref>).</p><p id="P13">To evaluate how this separation of scores translates into gains and losses of PSMs and peptides, we evaluated the results of the database search and rescoring at both 1% PSM-level (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4c</xref>) and 1% peptide-level FDR (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. S21</xref>). The number of gained PSMs varied depending on the enzyme and fragmentation method between approximately 3% and 40.5%, with chymotrypsin HCD data producing an exceptionally impressive gain of 40.5%. The latter observation is consistent with our previous findings.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27">27</xref></sup> Remarkably, chymotrypsin was also the main beneficiary of rescoring in UVPD and EID data. This demonstrates the usefulness of rescoring for expanded search spaces characterised by increased number of possible charge states, allowed missed cleavages and reduced enzyme specificity, all of which are typical for chymotrypsin (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. S6</xref>). Consistent with the score distributions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4b</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. S16</xref>-<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">19</xref>), ECD enjoyed the least numbers of gained PSMs and peptides regardless of protease among all fragmentation techniques (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4c</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. S21</xref>). To explore the reasons of the varying number of gains observed, we investigated the recovery of true positive (TP) PSMs at various FDR cutoffs. For that we compared the numbers of TPs identified in each method with the total possible number of TPs across a range of FDR thresholds before and after rescoring (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4d</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. S22</xref>). At 1% PSM-level FDR, rescored ECD, EID and UVPD recovered more than 97% of possible TPs, while the original database searches extracted approximately 95% in ECD, 87% in EID, 85% in UVPD and 84% in HCD. At a stricter FDRs of 0.01%, the results after rescoring still captured over 75% of all estimated possible TPs, with ECD showing the highest proportion approaching 85%. At the same FDR level, initial base searches identified less than 70% of possible TPs in ECD and less than 55% in all other dissociation methods (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4d</xref>). The analysis shows that data-driven rescoring using the pan-activation Prosit model recovers essentially all TPs from the initial MSFragger search results.</p><p id="P14">The rescoring data provided an opportunity to inspect the efficacy of each enzyme and dissociation technique for proteome analysis (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. S23a</xref>). Trypsin, as expected, identified the most PSMs, peptides and proteins for every fragmentation technique. Chymotrypsin demonstrated the next best result, with LysC and LysN a little further behind, replicating previous trends observed for CID and ETD data.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42">42</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43">43</xref></sup> The enzyme GluC clusters with LysN, appearing to be slightly superior or inferior depending on the dissociation technique. Average protein sequence coverage was similar for each fragmentation technique (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig S24</xref>). In order to assess complementarity at the protein sequence level we represented our data at the amino acid level. In general terms, when comparing the complementarity of trypsin against its alternatives, we saw substantial improvements in proteome coverage for all fragmentation techniques (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig S23b</xref>); in fact, the combined coverage for LysN, LysC, GluC and chymotrypsin was more than that for trypsin. It should be noted that a more exhaustive 2D LCMS analysis of the trypsin data would not significantly increase proteome coverage, and so the amount of analysis time between the other enzymes <italic>versus</italic> trypsin is not an important factor in the comparison. Further analysis of unique coverage for each fragmentation technique showed that UVPD produced the most amount of unique data, with HCD and ECD close behind, and EID the least (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig S24</xref>. However, UVPD had significant overlap with EID which might be a reason for weak unique proteome coverage result for EID (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Figure S23c</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S7"><title>Application of DIA with all activation techniques and Pan-activation Prosit Model</title><p id="P15">The spectral prediction model created in this work is portable and freely available as instance “Prosit_2025_intensity_MultiFrag” at the Koina model repository,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R44">44</xref></sup> and can be interfaced within any software suite. We implemented our model within FragPipe as part of MSBooster.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">29</xref></sup> Combined with the optimisation of search parameters in Fragpipe, we can now perform both DDA and DIA data analyses for all activation techniques. The ability to now utilise these activation techniques with DIA approaches led us to create DIA methodologies/routines for the Exploris-Omnitrap. The change in ion population, both in terms of ion density and distribution of charge states, required adjustments of the acquisition parameters for each dissociation technique both at the Exploris and Omnitrap level. We carried out LCMS analyses on a tryptic cell lysate digests from Human, Arabidopsis Thaliana and Escherichia coli cells. We introduced the latter 2 types of cells to assess the universality of the prosit model. To optimise duty cycle we chose to use the ‘normal isolation window’ approach with MS1 range bound to retention time.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R45">45</xref></sup> MSBooster, using the Prosit Multrifrag model, increased identification rates at PSM-, peptide- and protein-level for all three cell types. Arabidopsis and the Human lysate samples enjoyed the largest improvements, trading top position depending on exact context. On average ECD had the lowest gains across all samples with the worst result being 1.0%, 1.7% and 3.0% at the three levels for E.Coli while EID enjoyed the largest improvements across all three types of samples with the best result being 31.4%, 20.9% and 22.6% at the three levels for the Arabidopsis sample (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="S8" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p id="P16">The intrinsic challenges of proteome characterisation have meant a necessary focus on sensitivity and speed to reach biologically useful levels of proteome information. In the last few years, the field has been able to reach a relevant level of proteome coverage in minutes and on sample sizes as low as a single cell.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R46">46</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R47">47</xref></sup> However, the great variety of protein/peptide physicochemical properties embedded within the proteome places a hard limit on what modern proteomics approaches based on trypsin and CID can potentially observe. The blind spots of these approaches are well described, and alternatives such as complementary proteases and activation techniques have been introduced although not widely adopted. In this work, we demonstrated that UVPD, EID and ECD can generate equivalent levels of data as HCD from the same numbers of spectra, <italic>i.e.</italic> these approaches can reach similar levels of efficiency on a proteome scale across the most popular enzymes. These data allowed us to train a model that can predict spectra approximately as accurately as those for CID. The advent of predicting spectra will now allow the community to consider if alternative dissociation techniques are more appropriate for their protein characterisation needs. An advantage of EID and UVPD is that their spectra are richer and less affected by the properties of the sequence intended to be studied and will certainly make more challenging proteoforms more accessible for characterisation. We demonstrated that our model could be used for the improvement of database search results both from DDA and DIA sources, creating software parity with cutting edge modern proteomics pipelines. The Exploris-Omnitrap configuration as described in this manuscript is a potent characterisation instrument that is arguably the most capable for the widest gamut of protein types, but it is not optimised for speed or sensitivity at speed. Our work shows the characteristics of each fragmentation method, and others<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R48">48</xref></sup> have shown benefits. We hope that increasing the ability of the community to observe benefits of these activation approaches will increase demand and encourage vendors to consider implementation of more efficient designs allowing most if not all application types to be as successful on these activation platforms as the standard CID experiment, with the added advantage of far richer data and more confident characterisation.</p></sec><sec id="S9" sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec id="S10"><title>Chemicals, solvents, cell lines and proteases</title><p id="P17">Sodium dodecyl sulfate (SDS), dimethyl sulfoxide (DMSO), chloroacetamide (CAA), acetonitrile, ethanol, triethylammonium bicarbonate (TEAB), ethyl acetate, formic acid and urea were purchased from Sigma Aldrich. Tris(2-carboxyethyl)phosphine (TCEP), ultrapure water and Pierce BCA protein assay kit were obtained from Thermo Fisher Scientific. Magnetic carboxyl coated magnetic beads were acquired from Cytiva. Proteases were purchased from: Wako (LysC), ImmunoPrecise Antibodies (LysN), Promega (trypsin and GluC), Roche (chymotrypsin). Expi293F (human cell line based on HEK 293) cells were purchased from Thermo Fisher.</p></sec><sec id="S11"><title>Cell lysis</title><p id="P18">Expi293F or E.coli cell pellets were resuspended in 2% SDS, 50 mM TEAB (for proteolysis using trypsin, LysN and LysC) or 1% SDS, 50 mM TEAB (for proteolysis using chymotrypsin) or 6 M urea, 50 mM TEAB (for proteolysis using GluC) and sonicated using BioruptorPico (Diagenode) for 30 cycles (30 s on/off). Protein concentration was determined using BCA assay following the manufacturer’s protocol. Proteins were then reduced and alkylated with 10 mM TCEP and 50 mM CAA for 30 minutes.</p></sec><sec id="S12"><title>Protein extraction</title><p id="P19">Ground <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> seedlings were homogenised in 100 mM Tris buffer pH 7.6 containing 5.6% SDS, 1x Protease inhibitor cocktail (Roche), 1x PhosStop (Roche), 10 mM TCEP, 20 mg/ml PVPP beads (Alfa Aesar) in an ice-cold ultrasonic water bath for 30 min. The homogenised extract was then incubated for 2h in an orbital shaker (400 rpm) at room temperature and clarified by two 10-min room-temperature centrifugation steps at 17,000 g.</p></sec><sec id="S13"><title>Proteolysis</title><p id="P20">In proteolysis using trypsin, LysC and LysN, proteins were digested using a modified single-pot solid-phase assisted sample preparation method (SP3) using magnetic carboxyl coated magnetic beads at 4:1 w/w bead-to-protein ratio.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R49">49</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R50">50</xref></sup> Proteins were precipitated onto the beads using acetonitrile (80% final concentration) and incubated for 30 min with shaking. The beads were washed three times with 80% ethanol, followed by three washes with 100% acetonitrile before incubation with digestion buffer (50 mM TEAB), containing a protease (trypsin, LysN or LysC) at 1:25 enzyme-to-protein ratio for 4 hours. Supernatant was collected, beads were washed with 2% DMSO solution, and the wash was combined with supernatant before acidification with formic acid to 5% final concentration and centrifugation at 16,000 x g for 10 minutes. In proteolysis using chymotrypsin, proteins samples were diluted two-fold and digested with chymotrypsin at an enzyme-to-protein ratio of 1:50 for 4 hours. Peptides were then acidified with formic acid and washed with saturated ethyl acetate five times.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R51">51</xref></sup> In proteolysis using GluC, protein samples were diluted to adjust urea concentration to 0.8 M and digested with chymotrypsin at an enzyme-to-protein ratio of 1:35 for 4 hours. As a final step in all protocols, peptides were desalted on Oasis HLB cartridges (Waters) and eluted with 50% acetonitrile in ultrapure water. The eluent containing peptides was dried using Genevac EZ-2.</p></sec><sec id="S14"><title>UPLC fractionation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37">37</xref></sup></title><p id="P21">Digests of Expi293F proteins were reconstituted in water containing 5% formic acid and 5% DMSO and subjected to UPLC fractionation in a Water Acquity Plus system. The peptides were separated using a Waters ACQUITY UPLC peptide CSH C18 (1mm × 150 mm, 1.7 µm, 130Å) column. The composition of solvent B (80% acetonitrile, 20% water) changed from 12% to 40% over 55 minutes and then from 40% to 50% over 5 minutes. Solvent A comprised 10 mM TEAB (pH 8.0-8.2), 2% acetonitrile and 98% water. Each fraction was collected for 45 seconds (80 fractions in total). Fractions were concatenated as follows: fraction 1 was pooled with fractions 21, 41 and 61; other fractions were pooled in a similar fashion. Each pooled fraction contained approximately 6 µg of peptides in 200 µL of solvents. Each pooled fraction was then split into 10 aliquots, each aliquot was further diluted by adding 80 µL of 5% DMSO-5% formic acid to 20 µL of peptide mixture.</p></sec><sec id="S15"><title>LCMS analysis</title><p id="P22">LC-MS/MS data were acquired using an UltiMate 3000 nanoUHPLC system (Thermo Fisher Scientific) coupled either to an Orbitrap Exploris (Thermo Fisher Scientific) equipped with an Omnitrap (Fasmatech) or to an Orbitrap Ascend Tribrid (Thermo Fisher Scientific). The amount of material injected was 500 ng of each digest fraction except trypsin, for which 250 ng of each fraction were injected. For HCD analysis, the amount of material was further reduced by half for all proteases. The peptides were trapped on a C18 PepMap100 pre-column (300 µm i.d. x 5 mm, 100 Å, Thermo Fisher Scientific) using solvent A (0.1% formic acid in water), then separated on an in-house packed analytical column (50 µm i.d. x 50 cm in-house packed with ReproSil Gold 120 C18, 1.9 µm, Dr. Maisch GmbH). The composition of solvent B (0.1% formic acid in acetonitrile) changed from 10% to 33% over 30 min (for parameters optimisation), or from 10% to 33% over 60 min (for parameters optimisation and HCD analysis), from 8% to 28% over 120 min (UVPD, EID, ECD DDA; HCD DIA), or from 8% to 20% over 240 min (UVPD, EID, ECD DIA) at a flow rate of 100 nL/min. Full scan MS1 spectra were acquired in the Orbitrap (scan range 400-1300 m/z, resolution 60000, AGC target 300%). For DDA, top 20 (40 in HCD) most abundant peptides were selected each round for fragmentation. EID, UVPD and ECD DDA spectra were acquired in the Omnitrap. Their products were mass-analysed in the Orbitrap at 45000 resolving power, the AGC value was set to 200%, and the maximum injection time was set to 64 ms. ETciD DDA spectra were acquired in the linear ion trap of the Orbitrap Ascend. Products of ETciD were mass-analysed in the Orbitrap at 7500 resolving power, the AGC value was set to 200%, and the maximum injection time was set to 64 ms. HCD DDA spectra were acquired in the HCD cell of the Orbitrap Exploris. Products of HCD were mass-analysed in the Orbitrap at 7500 resolving power, the AGC value was set to 40%, and the maximum injection time was set to 64 ms. In DIA, scans were acquired using 4- or 8-m/z isolation windows in the 400-700 m/z range over 0-80 minutes, 500-700 m/z range over 80-160 minutes, and 600-900 m/z range over 160-240 min of a 240-min LC gradient. EID, UVPD and ECD DIA spectra were acquired in the Omnitrap. Their products were mass-analysed in the Orbitrap at 60000 resolving power, the AGC value was set to 2000%, and the maximum injection time was set to 50 ms. In DIA experiments, the amount of material injected was 400 ng of unfractionated tryptic digest of Expi293F cells, 1200 ng of tryptic digest of Arabidopsis thaliana and 300 ng of tryptic digest of E.coli.</p></sec><sec id="S16"><title>Database searches of DDA data</title><p id="P23">Spectra were searched using FragPipe (v22.0) MSFragger 4.1<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39">39</xref></sup> with standard ‘close’ search settings against Uniprot database (UPR_Homo sapiens_9606 accessed on 24.10.29). The number of missed cleavages was set to four when searching GluC and chymotrypsin data. Types of fragments searched by MSFragger were set in accordance with fragmentation techniques used in the corresponding experiments. Ions <italic>a+1</italic>, <italic>c-1</italic>, <italic>x+1</italic> and <italic>z+1</italic> were manually defined for searches. MSBooster<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">29</xref></sup> and all quantification parameters were disabled in all searches including HCD data. Mass calibration and parameter optimizations were enabled. Data filtering was performed using Percolator (v3.6.5) and Philosopher (v5.1.1), followed by ProteinProphet. Results were reported using sequential FDR estimation, with a 1% FDR threshold at the protein level.</p></sec><sec id="S17"><title>Spectra annotation</title><p id="P24">Every raw file and its corresponding pepxml file generated by MSFragger were read and merged into a single dataframe, containing amino-acid sequence, precursor charge, modifications (if any) and raw mass spectrum. For each PSM identified by MSFragger, its corresponding raw spectrum was annotated by matching with 10 ppm tolerance against a theoretical spectrum containing all ions with the following parameters: ion types <italic>a</italic>, <italic>a+1</italic>, <italic>b</italic>, <italic>c-1</italic>, <italic>c</italic>, <italic>x</italic>, <italic>x+1</italic>, <italic>y</italic>, <italic>z</italic>, <italic>z+1</italic>, fragment charges +1 to +3, and fragment lengths 1-29. See <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 1</xref> for ion type nomenclature. The annotation was carried out excluding all matches in a 2.4 Da window centred on the precursor ion’s <italic>m/z</italic>. For additional quality control, we explicitly annotate the first four isotopic precursor peaks, for both the precursor charge and charge+1, for the purpose of excluding them from a coincidental identification with another ion. Annotations for all PSMs are saved to one dataframe per fragmentation method, along with overall statistics enumerating the occurrences of each searched ion from our permutation.</p></sec><sec id="S18"><title>Creation of deep learning datasets</title><p id="P25">Datasets for the training of models were created as multiple parquet files from the annotated PSM datasets for all fragmentation methods. The PSM list was first cleaned of decoy sequences and sequences that contain no identified annotations. The output space/ion dictionary of the model was determined by only including annotated ions that occurred 100 or more times in the dataset. The PSMs were de-duplicated to unique sequence/charge/fragmentation method instances, retaining the instance with the highest hyperscore from MSFragger. The resulting unique PSM dataset was then shuffled, split into train/validation/test and written to parquet files. For the purposes of multithreading during dataloading, the train set was written to 8-12 separate files, all approximately having the same number of samples.</p><p id="P26">All dataset parquet files contain the original raw file name, scan number, modified peptide sequence, charge, fragmentation method, annotated ion strings and annotated ion intensities. The raw file names and scan numbers are sufficient to map any training/evaluation example back to its raw spectrum. Peptide sequences, charges and fragmentation methods were the inputs to the model; the target outputs for training were constructed from the ion strings and intensities. With a defined ion dictionary for the model, each ion string was mapped to its designated index, and its intensity was placed into a vector with the same length as the number of ions the model predicts (815). For ions that were the same length or longer than the peptide, or whose charge was greater than the precursor charge, a “-1” was assigned as the intensity and used to mask out these ions for training. All other unannotated ions got an intensity of 0. All non-negative entries in the target spectrum vector were max-scaled by the most intense ion, such that the intensities fall between 0 and 1.</p></sec><sec id="S19"><title>Deep learning training and models</title><p id="P27">We used the original GRU cell RNN network of Prosit, but with specific architectural tweaks in order to accommodate the different metadata and the unordered structure of its output space. The metadata, <italic>i.e.</italic> charge and fragmentation method were both represented as one-hot vectors, concatenated and then linearly projected into 256 units; collision energy was not used as input for this model. Whereas the original Prosit model projected the metadata and sequence representation together multiplicatively, followed by replicating the combined representation into 174 identical vectors (Prosit’s original output length), our sequence dimension retained the original maximum sequence length dimension (30 amino acids) and was multiplicatively combined with the 256-long metadata vector. This encoding was then passed to the RNN GRU cell bi-directional decoder layer. The final regressor then applied a linear transformation to our 815-ion output space, followed by a LeakyReLU activation function and mean pooling over the sequence dimension, yielding an 815-long vector of intensity predictions.</p><p id="P28">The model was trained by masked spectral distance. All indices of ions impossible to occur for a particular peptide were multiplied by 0 so that they do not contribute to the gradient during training. All models were trained for 30 epochs. The Adam optimizer was used with a learning rate of 1e-4, linearly warmed up for 20,000 steps at the beginning of training. Pytorch was used for implementation. The model is publicly available via the Koina prediction service under the title “Prosit_2025_intensity_MultiFrag”.</p></sec><sec id="S20"><title>Rescoring with Oktoberfest</title><p id="P29">To assess rescoring under 1% FDR control at both the PSM and peptide levels, spectra were searched with varied parameters, utilizing the same versions of FragPipe, MSFragger and the fasta file as in the initial data analysis. The number of missed cleavages was maintained as previously established, with the following ion types specified according to the fragmentation method: <italic>c</italic>,<italic>z</italic> for ECD, <italic>a</italic>,<italic>b</italic>,<italic>c</italic>,<italic>x</italic>,<italic>y</italic>,<italic>z</italic> for EID, and <italic>b</italic>,<italic>y</italic> for both HCD and UVPD. To ensure compatibility and reduce confounding factors in the comparison, we modified several parameters: mass calibration, parameter optimizations, N-terminal acetylation, MSbooster, ProteinProphet and all quantification settings were disabled, and the maximum peptide length was set to 30. The “pin” files generated by FragPipe were concatenated and utilized for Percolator to obtain 1% FDR control at both the PSM and peptide levels. The results were subsequently used for downstream comparisons with the rescoring results.</p><p id="P30">Rescoring was conducted using Oktoberfest and Percolator (v3.6.5) on 100% FDR search results. No calibration for collision energy was applied, and iRT predictions were made utilizing the “Prosit_2019_irt” model. Intensity predictions were performed for the following ion fragmentations: <italic>a+1</italic>,<italic>b</italic>,<italic>c-1</italic>,<italic>c</italic>,<italic>y</italic>,<italic>z</italic>,<italic>z+1</italic> for ECD; <italic>a</italic>,<italic>a+1</italic>,<italic>b</italic>,<italic>c</italic>,<italic>y</italic>,<italic>x</italic>,<italic>x+1</italic>,<italic>z</italic>,<italic>z+1</italic> for EID; <italic>a</italic>,<italic>b</italic>,<italic>y</italic> for HCD; and <italic>a</italic>,<italic>a+1</italic>,<italic>b</italic>,<italic>c</italic>,<italic>y</italic>,<italic>z</italic> for UVPD. Percolator was used to filter the data to 1% FDR at both the PSM and peptide levels.</p></sec><sec id="S21"><title>Database searches of DIA data</title><p id="P31">Spectra were searched using FragPipe (v23.0) with MSFragger-DIA 4.1<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R52">52</xref></sup> with standard ‘DIA_SpecLib_Quant’ search settings against Uniprot databases (“UPR_Homo sapiens_9606” accessed on 22.08.22, “UPR_ArabidopsisThaliana_3702” accessed on 22.08.22 and “UPR_EscherichiaColi” accessed on 22.09.07). EasyPQP library generation and DIA-NN quantification were turned off. Types of fragments searched by MSFragger were set in accordance with fragmentation techniques used in the corresponding experiments. Mass calibration and methionine oxidation variable modifications were turned on, and the maximum length of peptide was set to 30. The “Prosit_2019_irt” and “Prosit_2025_intensity_MultiFrag” models were used in MSBooster<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">29</xref></sup> via Koina<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R44">44</xref></sup> to predict peptide properties. Data filtering was performed using Percolator (v3.7.1) and Philosopher (v5.1.1), and results were reported at 1% PSM, 1% Peptide and 1% Proteins levels.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="SM"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1"><label>Supplementary Material</label><media xlink:href="EMS206149-supplement-Supplementary_Material.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" id="d35aAcEbB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack id="S22"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>N.L, Y.D and S.M. was supported by the EPSRC (V011359/1 (P)). J.S and S.M. was supported by BBSRC responsive mode (BB/T016272/1). A.I.N and K.L.Y were supported in part by NIH grants R01-GM-094231 and U24-CA210967 (to A.I.N.). J.L and M. W. was, in part, supported by an ERC Starting Grant (Grant No. 101077037). C.C.S was supported by the Elitenetzwerk Bayern (grant number F-6-M5613.6.K-NW-2021-411/1/1).</p></ack><fn-group><fn id="FN1" fn-type="conflict"><p id="P32"><bold>Conflict of Interest</bold></p><p id="P33">A.I.N. is the Founder of Fragmatics and serves on the scientific advisory boards of Protai Bio, Infinitopes, and Mobilion Systems. A.I.N. is also a paid consultant for Novartis. A.I.N. has a financial interest due to the licensing of MSFragger and IonQuant to commercial entities. M.W. is a founder and shareholder of MSAID GmbH with no operational role and member of the scientific advisory board of Momentum Biotechnologies. All other authors declare no competing financial interest.</p></fn><fn id="FN2" fn-type="con"><p id="P34"><bold>Author contributions</bold></p><p id="P35">N.L. and C. C. S. contributed equally. S.M. and M.W. conceived and supervised the project. N.L. and S.M. designed LCMS experiments and wrote the original draft. N.L. optimised parameters of Omnitrap-LCMS, performed LCMS experiments and initial data analysis. C.C.S. performed comprehensive data analysis and data post-processing. J.L. wrote the code for and inspected the Prosit Multifrag model. Y.D. and J.S. prepared samples. K.L.Y. and A.I.N. implemented the Prosit Multifrag model into FragPipe MSBooster. S.M., M.W. and A.I.N. acquired funding. All authors have revised the manuscript and have given approval to its final version.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><ref id="R1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Comprehensive Overview of Bottom-Up Proteomics Using Mass Spectrometry</article-title><source>ACS Measurement Science Au</source><year>2024</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>338</fpage><lpage>417</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11348894</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39193565</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acsmeasuresciau.3c00068</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brodbelt</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ion Activation Methods for Peptides and Proteins</article-title><source>Analytical Chemistry</source><year>2016</year><volume>88</volume><fpage>30</fpage><lpage>51</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5553572</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26630359</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.analchem.5b04563</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reilly</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ultraviolet photofragmentation of biomolecular ions</article-title><source>Mass Spectrometry Reviews</source><year>2009</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>425</fpage><lpage>447</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5056644</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19241462</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/mas.20214</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brodbelt</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ultraviolet Photodissociation Mass Spectrometry for Analysis of Biological Molecules</article-title><source>Chemical Reviews</source><year>2020</year><volume>120</volume><fpage>3328</fpage><lpage>3380</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7145764</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31851501</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.chemrev.9b00440</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Madsen</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Boutz</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Brodbelt</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ultrafast Ultraviolet Photodissociation at 193 nm and its Applicability to Proteomic Workflows</article-title><source>Journal of Proteome Research</source><year>2010</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>4205</fpage><lpage>4214</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2917496</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20578723</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/pr100515x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fort</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Implementation of Ultraviolet Photodissociation on a Benchtop Q Exactive Mass Spectrometer and Its Application to Phosphoproteomics</article-title><source>Analytical Chemistry</source><year>2016</year><volume>88</volume><fpage>2303</fpage><lpage>2310</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26760441</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kruger</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name><surname>Zubarev</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Horn</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>McLafferty</surname><given-names>FW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Electron capture dissociation of multiply charged peptide cations</article-title><source>International Journal of Mass Spectrometry</source><year>1999</year><volume>185-187</volume><fpage>787</fpage><lpage>793</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S13873806(98)14215-X</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zubarev</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reactions of polypeptide ions with electrons in the gas phase</article-title><source>Mass Spectrometry Reviews</source><year>2003</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>57</fpage><lpage>77</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12768604</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fort</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Exploring ECD on a Benchtop Q Exactive Orbitrap Mass Spectrometer</article-title><source>Journal of Proteome Research</source><year>2018</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>926</fpage><lpage>933</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5799867</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29249155</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.jproteome.7b00622</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baba</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Dissociation of Biomolecules by an Intense Low-Energy Electron Beam in a High Sensitivity Time-of-Flight Mass Spectrometer</article-title><source>Journal of the American Society for Mass Spectrometry</source><year>2021</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>1964</fpage><lpage>1975</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34080873</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kjeldsen</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Haselmann</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name><name><surname>Budnik</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Zubarev</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dissociative capture of hot (3–13 eV) electrons by polypeptide polycations: an efficient process accompanied by secondary fragmentation</article-title><source>Chemical Physics Letters</source><year>2002</year><volume>356</volume><fpage>201</fpage><lpage>206</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0009-2614(02)00149-5</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Syka</surname><given-names>JEP</given-names></name><name><surname>Coon</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Schroeder</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Shabanowitz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hunt</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Peptide and protein sequence analysis by electron transfer dissociation mass spectrometry</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</source><year>2004</year><volume>101</volume><fpage>9528</fpage><lpage>9533</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC470779</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15210983</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0402700101</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Good</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Wirtala</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>McAlister</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name><name><surname>Coon</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Performance Characteristics of Electron Transfer Dissociation Mass Spectrometry</article-title><source>Molecular &amp; Cellular Proteomics</source><year>2007</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>1942</fpage><lpage>1951</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17673454</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>M-S</given-names></name><name><surname>Pandey</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Electron transfer dissociation mass spectrometry in proteomics</article-title><source>PROTEOMICS</source><year>2012</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>530</fpage><lpage>542</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3664229</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22246976</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/pmic.201100517</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fung</surname><given-names>YME</given-names></name><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Zubarev</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Electron Ionization Dissociation of Singly and Multiply Charged Peptides</article-title><source>Journal of the American Chemical Society</source><year>2009</year><volume>131</volume><fpage>9977</fpage><lpage>9985</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19621955</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zubarev</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multiple Soft Ionization of Gas-Phase Proteins and Swift Backbone Dissociation in Collisions with ≤99 eV Electrons</article-title><source>Angewandte Chemie International Edition</source><year>2010</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>1439</fpage><lpage>1441</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20091726</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Voinov</surname><given-names>VG</given-names></name><name><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Barofsky</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Electron-Induced Dissociation of Peptides in a Triple Quadrupole Mass Spectrometer Retrofitted with an Electromagnetostatic Cell</article-title><source>Journal of the American Society for Mass Spectrometry</source><year>2015</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>752</fpage><lpage>761</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4446792</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25652934</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13361-014-1074-x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Frese</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Toward Full Peptide Sequence Coverage by Dual Fragmentation Combining Electron-Transfer and Higher-Energy Collision Dissociation Tandem Mass Spectrometry</article-title><source>Analytical Chemistry</source><year>2012</year><volume>84</volume><fpage>9668</fpage><lpage>9673</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23106539</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Molina</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Horn</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Mathivanan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Pandey</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Global proteomic profiling of phosphopeptides using electron transfer dissociation tandem mass spectrometry</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</source><year>2007</year><volume>104</volume><fpage>2199</fpage><lpage>2204</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1794346</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17287340</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0611217104</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Frese</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Unambiguous Phosphosite Localization using ElectronTransfer/Higher-Energy Collision Dissociation (EThcD)</article-title><source>Journal of Proteome Research</source><year>2013</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>1520</fpage><lpage>1525</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3588588</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23347405</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/pr301130k</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alley</surname><given-names>WR</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>Mechref</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Novotny</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of glycopeptides by combining collision-induced dissociation and electron-transfer dissociation mass spectrometry data</article-title><source>Rapid Communications in Mass Spectrometry</source><year>2009</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>161</fpage><lpage>170</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19065542</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Zampronio</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name><name><surname>Creese</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Higher Energy Collision Dissociation (HCD) Product Ion-Triggered Electron Transfer Dissociation (ETD) Mass Spectrometry for the Analysis of N-Linked Glycoproteins</article-title><source>Journal of Proteome Research</source><year>2012</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>4517</fpage><lpage>4525</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22800195</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name><name><surname>Go</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name><name><surname>Desaire</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterizing O-Linked Glycopeptides by Electron Transfer Dissociation: Fragmentation Rules and Applications in Data Analysis</article-title><source>Analytical Chemistry</source><year>2013</year><volume>85</volume><fpage>8403</fpage><lpage>8411</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3956444</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23909558</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/ac401814h</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Electron-Transfer/Higher-Energy Collision Dissociation (EThcD)-Enabled Intact Glycopeptide/Glycoproteome Characterization</article-title><source>Journal of the American Society for Mass Spectrometry</source><year>2017</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>1751</fpage><lpage>1764</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5711575</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28695533</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13361-017-1701-4</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Improved online LC-MS/MS identification of O-glycosites by EThcD fragmentation, chemoenzymatic reaction, and SPE enrichment</article-title><source>Glycoconjugate Journal</source><year>2021</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>145</fpage><lpage>156</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8052266</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33068214</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10719-020-09952-w</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tiwary</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>High-quality MS/MS spectrum prediction for data-dependent and data-independent acquisition data analysis</article-title><source>Nature Methods</source><year>2019</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>519</fpage><lpage>525</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31133761</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gessulat</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Prosit: proteome-wide prediction of peptide tandem mass spectra by deep learning</article-title><source>Nature Methods</source><year>2019</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>509</fpage><lpage>518</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31133760</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>W-F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>AlphaPeptDeep: a modular deep learning framework to predict peptide properties for proteomics</article-title><source>Nature Communications</source><year>2022</year><volume>13</volume><elocation-id>7238</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9700817</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36433986</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-022-34904-3</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>MSBooster: improving peptide identification rates using deep learning-based features</article-title><source>Nature Communications</source><year>2023</year><volume>14</volume><elocation-id>4539</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10374903</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37500632</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-023-40129-9</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Picciani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Oktoberfest: Open-source spectral library generation and rescoring pipeline based on Prosit</article-title><source>PROTEOMICS</source><year>2024</year><volume>24</volume><elocation-id>2300112</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37672792</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kalhor</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lapin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Picciani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilhelm</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rescoring Peptide Spectrum Matches: Boosting Proteomics Performance by Integrating Peptide Property Predictors Into Peptide Identification</article-title><source>Molecular &amp; Cellular Proteomics</source><year>2024</year><volume>23</volume><elocation-id>100798</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11269915</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38871251</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mcpro.2024.100798</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Papanastasiou</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The Omnitrap Platform: A Versatile Segmented Linear Ion Trap for Multidimensional Multiple-Stage Tandem Mass Spectrometry</article-title><source>Journal of the American Society for Mass Spectrometry</source><year>2022</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>1990</fpage><lpage>2007</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9850925</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36113052</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jasms.2c00214</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smyrnakis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Characterization of an Omnitrap-Orbitrap Platform Equipped with Infrared Multiphoton Dissociation, Ultraviolet Photodissociation, and Electron Capture Dissociation for the Analysis of Peptides and Proteins</article-title><source>Analytical Chemistry</source><year>2023</year><volume>95</volume><fpage>12039</fpage><lpage>12046</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10433246</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37534599</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.analchem.3c01899</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Greer</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name><name><surname>Brodbelt</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Impact of Protease on Ultraviolet Photodissociation Mass Spectrometry for Bottom-up Proteomics</article-title><source>Journal of Proteome Research</source><year>2015</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>2626</fpage><lpage>2632</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25950415</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kolbowski</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Belsom</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rappsilber</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ultraviolet Photodissociation of Tryptic Peptide Backbones at 213 nm</article-title><source>Journal of the American Society for Mass Spectrometry</source><year>2020</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>1282</fpage><lpage>1290</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7273743</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32352297</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jasms.0c00106</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sinitcyn</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Global detection of human variants and isoforms by deep proteome sequencing</article-title><source>Nature Biotechnology</source><year>2023</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>1776</fpage><lpage>1786</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10713452</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36959352</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41587-023-01714-x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Reversed-phase chromatography with multiple fraction concatenation strategy for proteome profiling of human MCF10A cells</article-title><source>PROTEOMICS</source><year>2011</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>2019</fpage><lpage>2026</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3120047</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21500348</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/pmic.201000722</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ly</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Loo</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Julian</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Electron-induced dissociation of protonated peptides yields backbone fragmentation consistent with a hydrogen-deficient radical</article-title><source>Rapid Communications in Mass Spectrometry</source><year>2009</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>2099</fpage><lpage>2101</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19489022</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name><surname>Leprevost</surname><given-names>FV</given-names></name><name><surname>Avtonomov</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Mellacheruvu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Nesvizhskii</surname><given-names>AI</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MSFragger: ultrafast and comprehensive peptide identification in mass spectrometry–based proteomics</article-title><source>Nature Methods</source><year>2017</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>513</fpage><lpage>520</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5409104</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28394336</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.4256</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>X-X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>pDeep: Predicting MS/MS Spectra of Peptides with Deep Learning</article-title><source>Analytical Chemistry</source><year>2017</year><volume>89</volume><fpage>12690</fpage><lpage>12697</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29125736</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R41"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>The</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>MacCoss</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Noble</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name><name><surname>Käll</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fast and Accurate Protein False Discovery Rates on Large-Scale Proteomics Data Sets with Percolator 3.0</article-title><source>Journal of The American Society for Mass Spectrometry</source><year>2016</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>1719</fpage><lpage>1727</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5059416</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27572102</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13361-016-1460-7</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R42"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Swaney</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Wenger</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Coon</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Value of Using Multiple Proteases for Large-Scale Mass Spectrometry-Based Proteomics</article-title><source>Journal of Proteome Research</source><year>2010</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>1323</fpage><lpage>1329</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2833215</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20113005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/pr900863u</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R43"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Trudgian</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Lemoff</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Yadavalli</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mirzaei</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Confetti: A Multiprotease Map of the HeLa Proteome for Comprehensive Proteomics*</article-title><source>Molecular &amp; Cellular Proteomics</source><year>2014</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>1573</fpage><lpage>1584</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4047476</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24696503</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/mcp.M113.035170</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R44"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lautenbacher</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Koina: Democratizing machine learning for proteomics research</article-title><source>bioRxiv</source><year>2024</year><elocation-id>2024.2006.2001.596953</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2024.06.01.596953</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R45"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pino</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name><name><surname>Just</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>MacCoss</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Searle</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Acquiring and Analyzing Data Independent Acquisition Proteomics Experiments without Spectrum Libraries</article-title><source>Molecular &amp; Cellular Proteomics</source><year>2020</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>1088</fpage><lpage>1103</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7338082</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32312845</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/mcp.P119.001913</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R46"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>HI</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Parallelized Acquisition of Orbitrap and Astral Analyzers Enables High-Throughput Quantitative Analysis</article-title><source>Analytical Chemistry</source><year>2023</year><volume>95</volume><fpage>15656</fpage><lpage>15664</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10603608</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37815927</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.analchem.3c02856</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R47"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bubis</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Challenging the Astral mass analyzer to quantify up to 5,300 proteins per single cell at unseen accuracy to uncover cellular heterogeneity</article-title><source>Nature Methods</source><year>2025</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>510</fpage><lpage>519</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11903296</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39820751</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41592-024-02559-1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R48"><label>48</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Volmer</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structural analysis of small to medium-sized molecules by mass spectrometry after electron-ion fragmentation (ExD) reactions</article-title><source>Analyst</source><year>2016</year><volume>141</volume><fpage>794</fpage><lpage>806</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26725919</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R49"><label>49</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moggridge</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sorensen</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name><name><surname>Morin</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name><name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Extending the Compatibility of the SP3 Paramagnetic Bead Processing Approach for Proteomics</article-title><source>Journal of Proteome Research</source><year>2018</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>1730</fpage><lpage>1740</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29565595</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R50"><label>50</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Single-pot, solid-phase-enhanced sample preparation for proteomics experiments</article-title><source>Nature Protocols</source><year>2019</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>68</fpage><lpage>85</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30464214</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R51"><label>51</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yeung</surname><given-names>Y-G</given-names></name><name><surname>Stanley</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rapid Detergent Removal from Peptide Samples with Ethyl Acetate for Mass Spectrometry Analysis</article-title><source>Current Protocols in Protein Science</source><year>2010</year><volume>59</volume><elocation-id>16.12.11-16.12.15</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2852680</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20155730</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/0471140864.ps1612s59</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R52"><label>52</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Analysis of DIA proteomics data using MSFragger-DIA and FragPipe computational platform</article-title><source>Nature Communications</source><year>2023</year><volume>14</volume><elocation-id>4154</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10338508</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37438352</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-023-39869-5</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Optimization of ECD, EID, and UVPD parameters in bottom-up experiments.</title><p><bold>a,</bold> Experimental workflow; <bold>b-e,</bold> numbers of peptide-spectrum matches (PSMs) and peptides identified in UVPD experiments using different numbers of UV laser pulses at 3 mJ/pulse (b), UVPD experiments using four laser pulses at different energies of each pulse, (c) EID experiments using different irradiation times at 25 eV of electron energy (d), ECD experiments using different irradiation times at ~1eV of electron energy (e). In UVPD and EID, <italic>b,y</italic> or <italic>a,b,c,x,y,z</italic> fragments were used for data analysis, <italic>c</italic> and <italic>z</italic> ions were using in the analysis of ECD data.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS206149-f001"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Large-scale bottom-up ECD, EID, UVPD, and HCD analysis.</title><p>a) Experimental workflow; b) total numbers of peptide-spectrum matches (PSMs) in ECD, EID, and UVPD experiments identified using different combinations of fragment types; c) highest numbers of PSMs from b) (blue) and total numbers of acquired MS2 scans (orange) in ECD, EID, UVPD, and HCD experiments; the rate of PSM identification is shown above each corresponding bar; d) scatter plots of hyperscore distributions of 2+, 3+, and 4+ charge states of unique PSMs (unique combination of amino-acid sequence, charge, and modification selected by highest hyperscore) acquired in ECD using <italic>c</italic> and <italic>z</italic> fragments and in EID, UVPD, and HCD using <italic>b</italic> and <italic>y</italic> fragments; e) scatter plots of hyperscore distributions for each unique PSM acquired in EID and UVPD using <italic>a,b,c,x,y,z</italic> fragments.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS206149-f002"/></fig><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Deep learning training pipeline, from annotation to evaluation.</title><p><bold>a,</bold> Heatmap of mean fragmention proportions in ECD, EID, HCD, and UVPD spectra acquired across all enzymes. Annotation was performed for 10 ion types: <italic>a</italic>, <italic>a+1</italic>, <italic>b</italic>, <italic>c-1</italic>, <italic>c</italic>, <italic>x</italic>, <italic>x+1</italic>, <italic>y</italic>, <italic>z</italic>, <italic>z+1</italic> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 1</xref>). <bold>b,</bold> The modified Prosit deep learning architecture for prediction of fragment ion intensities in ECD, EID, HCD, and UVPD spectra. The input parameters (peptide sequences, precursor charge state and fragmentation method) are encoded into a latent representation (latent space). This representation is then decoded to predict fragment ion intensities. <bold>c,</bold> Pearson correlation coefficients between predicted and experimental spectra in training (blue) and test (orange) sets separated by fragmentation method (left) and charge state (right). Horizontal white, red, and blue lines correspond to 25, 50, and 75% percentiles, respectively. Distributions protruding beyond 1.0 are plotting artefacts. <bold>d-g,</bold> Mirror plots of selected precursors in HCD (d), UVPD (e), ECD (f), and EID (g) data. Each mirror plot compares experimental (top) and predicted (bottom) fragment intensities, with each type of fragments uniquely colourised.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS206149-f003"/></fig><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Intensity prediction improves database search quality of ECD, EID, HCD, and UVPD data.</title><p><bold>a,</bold> Histograms of the ratios of experimentally observed ions to all theoretically possible fragment (upper distributions); Histograms of the ratios of experimentally predicted and observed ions to all predicted ions (lower distributions). <bold>b,</bold> Correlation of Percolator scores for all target (green) and decoy (orange) PSMs obtained from the rescoring of the MSFragger (top) and Oktoberfest (right) sets of scores for selected combinations of enzyme and fragmentation technique. The red solid lines indicate the 1% PSM-level FDR cutoffs. For database searches scores, the best combinations of fragment types from <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2b</xref> were used; for Oktoberfest scoring, most frequently annotated fragment types (&gt;4% of all annotated ions across all spectra) were used for each dissociation method (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 8</xref>). <bold>c,</bold> Numbers of shared (blue), gained (green), and lost (orange) PSMs identified at 1% PSM-level FDR using the Oktoberfest set of scores compared to original MSFragger search for each fragmentation technique per enzyme. The numbers correspond to the data from <bold>b</bold> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 16</xref>-<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">19</xref>. <bold>d,</bold> Proportions of the numbers of true positive PSMs to the estimated maximum number of true positive PSMs acquired using original MSFragger and Oktoberfest scores at different values of PSM-level FDR for each fragmentation technique, all enzymes combined.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS206149-f004"/></fig><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>Intensity prediction improves search quality of ECD, EID and UVPD DIA data.</title><p>Numbers of shared (blue), gained (green), and lost (orange) PSMs, peptides and proteins identified at 1% FDR with Prosit predictions implemented within MSBooster module of FragPipe in the UVPD, EID and ECD DIA data of unfractionated tryptic digests of Expi293F, Arabidopsis thaliana and E.coli proteins.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS206149-f005"/></fig></floats-group></article>