<!DOCTYPE article
 PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" article-type="preprint"><?all-math-mml yes?><?use-mml?><?origin ukpmcpa?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">bioRxiv</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>bioRxiv : the preprint server for biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2692-8205</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">EMS206056</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2025.05.26.656108</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="archive">PPR1027961</article-id><article-version-alternatives><article-version article-version-type="status">preprint</article-version><article-version article-version-type="number">1</article-version></article-version-alternatives><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>A BRC1-modulated switch in auxin transport accounts for the competition between Arabidopsis axillary buds</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nahas</surname><given-names>Zoe</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN1">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bridgen</surname><given-names>Anthony John</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Loman</surname><given-names>Torkel E.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN2">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Dillon</surname><given-names>Jean</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Abley</surname><given-names>Katie</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cano-Ramirez</surname><given-names>Dora L.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ticchiarelli</surname><given-names>Fabrizio</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Seale</surname><given-names>Madeleine</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Locke</surname><given-names>James C. W.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CR1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Leyser</surname><given-names>Ottoline</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CR1">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/02tdtzx53</institution-id><institution>Sainsbury Laboratory</institution></institution-wrap>, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/013meh722</institution-id><institution>University of Cambridge</institution></institution-wrap>, <city>Cambridge</city>, <postal-code>CB2 1LR</postal-code>, <country country="GB">UK</country></aff><author-notes><corresp id="CR1"><label>*</label><email>ol235@cam.ac.uk</email>, <email>james.locke@slcu.cam.ac.uk</email></corresp><fn fn-type="present-address" id="FN1"><label>2</label><p id="P1">Current address: Centre for Integrative Genomics, Faculty of Biology and Medicine, University of Lausanne, 1015 Lausanne, Switzerland</p></fn><fn fn-type="present-address" id="FN2"><label>3</label><p id="P2">Current address: Mathematical Institute, University of Oxford, Oxford, OX2 6GG, UK</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted"><day>31</day><month>05</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="preprint"><day>29</day><month>05</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><permissions><ali:free_to_read/><license><ali:license_ref>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is licensed under a <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0 International license</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p id="P3">As part of their modular development, plants continuously adapt their shoot branching architecture according to environmental conditions. This occurs by regulating the activity of axillary buds established in each leaf axil. Whether a bud grows into a shoot depends partly on the presence of other active shoots, which can inhibit bud activation. This systemic coordination is proposed to be mediated by the transport network of the plant hormone auxin, with buds competing to establish sustained transport of auxin, termed canalised auxin transport, into the main stem. A second hormone, strigolactone, tunes this competition by influencing the removal of the PIN1 auxin export protein from the plasma membrane, and hence the dynamics of canalisation. Strigolactone also regulates the expression of another key regulatory hub, the bud-expressed transcription factor <italic>BRANCHED1</italic> (<italic>BRC1</italic>). The interplay between auxin transport and BRC1 in regulating bud activity is poorly understood. Here, we investigate this interplay in the context of competition between buds, using Arabidopsis explants with two axillary buds as a minimal system. Using experimental data, we develop a mathematical model of bud-bud competition in which BRC1 influences the establishment of canalised auxin transport by regulating the basal rate of auxin efflux in buds. We identify single model parameters that plausibly correspond to the dual impact of strigolactone on <italic>BRC1</italic> expression and PIN1. We show that modulating these two parameters reproduces the dynamics of bud growth and bud-bud competition observed in relevant mutants and treatments. Our model produces testable hypotheses, which we validate by generating a chimeric PIN1 auxin transporter with impaired strigolactone sensitivity, helping us uncouple the effects of strigolactone on PIN1 and BRC1. These results support the hypothesis that BRC1 influences local bud competitiveness by tuning the basal rate of auxin efflux in buds. Together with the systemic feedbacks in the auxin transport network, this enables plants to adjust dynamically the number and location of growing branches.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec id="S1" sec-type="intro"><label>1</label><title>Introduction</title><p id="P4">Plants achieve extraordinary flexibility of form through their modular growth, allowing their body plan to adapt to the prevailing environmental conditions. Above ground, plants continuously tune their shoot architecture by regulating the activity of axillary buds, which are derived from meristems established in the axil of each leaf (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36">McSteen &amp; Leyser, 2005</xref>). Whether an axillary bud stays dormant or grows out into a shoot depends on the integration of external cues, such as nutrient availability and light quality, and internal cues, such as the activity of other shoot apices on the plant (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">Domagalska &amp; Leyser, 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">Barbier <italic>et al</italic>., 2019</xref>).</p><p id="P5">Two hubs have been identified that integrate bud regulatory signals. The first hub is the regulated expression of <italic>BRANCHED1</italic> (<italic>BRC1</italic>), a bud-expressed transcription factor that acts as a local inhibitor of bud activation, as evidenced by its highly branched mutant phenotype (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">Aguilar-Martínez <italic>et al</italic>., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R72">Wang <italic>et al</italic>., 2019</xref>). Among its many regulators (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R77">Yang <italic>et al</italic>., 2018</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">Gastaldi <italic>et al</italic>., 2024</xref>), <italic>BRC1</italic> expression is up-regulated by the plant hormone strigolactone (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig 1A</xref>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">Aguilar-Martínez <italic>et al</italic>., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">Braun <italic>et al</italic>., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">Dun <italic>et al</italic>., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">Bennett <italic>et al</italic>., 2016b</xref>). Strigolactone signals via its receptor D14, triggering the degradation of a small family of proteins, which in Arabidopsis are named SUPPRESSOR OF MAX2 (SMXL) 6,7, and 8 (hereafter SMXL678) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">Jiang <italic>et al</italic>., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R80">Zhou <italic>et al</italic>., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R65">Soundappan <italic>et al</italic>., 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R73">Wang <italic>et al</italic>., 2015</xref>). SMXL6 represses <italic>BRC1</italic> transcription directly (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R74">Wang <italic>et al</italic>., 2020</xref>).</p><p id="P6">Downstream of BRC1, several direct targets have been identified, including the <italic>MAX1</italic> gene, which encodes a strigolactone biosynthesis enzyme (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">Booker <italic>et al</italic>., 2005</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R70">Van Es <italic>et al</italic>., 2023</xref>), and several genes associated with the growth-inhibiting hormone abscisic acid (ABA) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">González-Grandío <italic>et al</italic>., 2013</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R78">Yao &amp; Finlayson, 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R70">Van Es <italic>et al</italic>., 2023</xref>). Although <italic>BRC1</italic> expression correlates strongly with bud inhibition, it is neither necessary nor sufficient for bud inhibition. In Arabidopsis, two paralogues, <italic>BRC1</italic> and <italic>BRC2</italic>, carry out the function, with <italic>BRC1</italic> playing a more significant role in bud inhibition. In the <italic>brc1brc2</italic> double mutant, whilst many buds activate, some remain dormant. Moreover, buds expressing high levels of <italic>BRC1</italic> can exhibit wild-type outgrowth (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R59">Seale <italic>et al</italic>., 2017</xref>). Hence, rather than straightforwardly inhibiting bud activation, <italic>BRC1</italic> may affect the bud activation potential (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R59">Seale <italic>et al</italic>., 2017</xref>).</p><p id="P7">The second hub for signal integration is the auxin transport network. Unlike local <italic>BRC1</italic>-based regulation, the auxin transport network acts systemically, enabling the coordinated activity of shoot apices across the plant (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R54">Sachs, 1969</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">Bennett <italic>et al</italic>., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R49">Prusinkiewicz <italic>et al</italic>., 2009</xref>). Auxin is largely synthesised in the young expanding leaves of active shoot apices (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33">Ljung <italic>et al</italic>., 2001</xref>), and is transported basipetally in the polar auxin transport stream (PATS). PATS activity is mediated by basally localised auxin transporters of the PIN-FORMED (PIN) family, particularly PIN1, primarily associated with stem vascular tissues (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27">Goldsmith, 1977</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R46">Okada <italic>et al</italic>., 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">Gälweiler <italic>et al</italic>., 1998</xref>).</p><p id="P8">Auxin export from the axillary buds into the main stem correlates with, and is thought to be necessary for, sustained bud activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41">Morris, 1977</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42">Morris &amp; Johnson, 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32">Li &amp; Bangerth, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R49">Prusinkiewicz <italic>et al</italic>., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">Balla <italic>et al</italic>., 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">2016</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">Chabikwa <italic>et al</italic>., 2019</xref>). The establishment of auxin export occurs early in bud activation, likely through the process of auxin transport canalisation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R52">Sachs, 1966</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R53">1968</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R55">1981</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">Balla <italic>et al</italic>., 2011</xref>). Auxin transport canalisation is hypothesised to be driven by an autocatalytic feedback between auxin flux and the polar accumulation of PIN1 auxin export proteins at the plasma membrane in the direction of the flux, promoting increased and polarised auxin flux (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R54">Sachs, 1969</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R58">Scarpella <italic>et al</italic>., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R57">Sauer <italic>et al</italic>., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34">Mazur <italic>et al</italic>., 2016</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35">2020</xref>). Through this mechanism, auxin moving passively from a source to a sink, through an initially broad field of cells, promotes the formation of progressively narrower files of cells with highly polar auxin transport (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39">Mitchison, 1980</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40">Mitchison <italic>et al</italic>., 1981</xref>).</p><p id="P9">In a canalisation-based model of bud regulation, buds are auxin sources and can establish canalised auxin transport from the bud into the stem, and hence activate, only if the stem is a strong enough sink for auxin (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R49">Prusinkiewicz <italic>et al</italic>., 2009</xref>). This happens for example, when the primary shoot apex, which exports auxin into the main stem, is removed, and hence auxin is depleted from the main stem. Conversely, high auxin in the main stem, coming from the primary apex and/or growing axillary shoots, makes the stem a poor sink for auxin, reducing auxin flux out of the bud, thereby preventing the establishment of canalised auxin transport from the bud into the stem (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41">Morris, 1977</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R47">Ongaro <italic>et al</italic>., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R49">Prusinkiewicz <italic>et al</italic>., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">Balla <italic>et al</italic>., 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">2016</xref>). Since auxin biosynthesis is under negative feedback control, failure to export auxin reduces auxin synthesis in the bud, capping bud auxin source strength (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33">Ljung <italic>et al</italic>., 2001</xref>).</p><p id="P10">Collectively, these properties of auxin transport generate a competitive bistable switch in bud activation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R49">Prusinkiewicz <italic>et al</italic>., 2009</xref>). Once past a tipping point, auxin transport canalisation is hard to reverse. Consistent with this, only small buds can be inhibited by high auxin in the main stem (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">Chatfield <italic>et al</italic>., 2000</xref>). At the level of bud growth dynamics, bud activation follows a slow-growing lag phase followed by a switch to rapid outgrowth (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig 1B</xref>). Buds lose sensitivity to apical auxin at the same time as they switch from the slow-growing lag phase to rapid outgrowth (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43">Nahas <italic>et al</italic>., 2024</xref>), suggesting that the lag phase corresponds to the time during which buds establish canalised auxin transport into the stem.</p><p id="P11">The competitive nature of the bud activation switch is clearly visible in 2-node explants, such as Arabidopsis stem segments with only two nodes and their associated axillary buds (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig 1C</xref>). These exhibit four alternative bud activity outcomes: (i) neither bud grows, (ii) only the top grows, (iii) only the bottom bud grows (iv) both buds grow out to produce branches (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R47">Ongaro et al., 2008</xref>), similar to classical 2-branch models (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R61">Snow, 1931</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R62">1932</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R52">Sachs, 1966</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32">Li &amp; Bangerth, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R47">Ongaro <italic>et al</italic>., 2008</xref>). The outcomes can be visualised by plotting the length of the top bud against the length of the bottom bud (so-called Mitchison plots) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig 1C</xref>). Where only a single bud grows, it quickly establishes dominance over the other bud, preventing its growth. Within a canalisation-based model, if one bud rapidly establishes auxin export, it can prevent the establishment of canalised auxin transport from the other bud, but if both buds establish canalised auxin transport near-simultaneously, then neither will be able to inhibit the other (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R49">Prusinkiewicz <italic>et al</italic>., 2009</xref>).</p><p id="P12">Further evidence supporting the auxin transport canalisation model of bud regulation comes from analysing the effect of strigolactone on PIN auxin transporters. Strigolactone, in addition to up-regulating <italic>BRC1</italic> expression, triggers the removal of PIN1 auxin transporters from the plasma membrane through an unknown transcription-independent mechanism (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig 1A</xref>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">Bennett <italic>et al</italic>., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R60">Shinohara <italic>et al</italic>., 2013</xref>). Given that the dynamics of the establishment of canalised auxin export are influenced by the relative rates of insertion and removal of PIN1 from the plasma membrane, the strigolactone-mediated removal of PIN1 could inhibit bud activity by making canalisation harder to achieve. Consistent with this idea, strigolactone inhibits the formation of the narrow PIN1-expressing files of cells typical of canalised tissue (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R79">Zhang <italic>et al</italic>., 2020</xref>). A computational model in which strigolactone increases PIN1 removal from the plasma membrane captures the highly branched phenotypes of strigolactone deficient mutants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R49">Prusinkiewicz <italic>et al</italic>., 2009</xref>). The model also explains non-intuitive branching phenomena, including the ability of strigolactone to promote or inhibit shoot branching, depending on the auxin transport status of the plant (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R60">Shinohara <italic>et al</italic>., 2013</xref>). Moreover this mode of action accounts for the observation that strigolactone supply to 2-two node explants results predominantly in a single active branch, rather than inhibition of both branches (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">Crawford <italic>et al</italic>., 2010</xref>).</p><p id="P13">Although it has been shown that <italic>BRC1</italic> and the auxin transport network act as hubs for signal integration in shoot branching control, with both being regulated by a wide range of factors, including strigolactone, it is poorly understood how they simultaneously regulate bud activity. We recently demonstrated that in isolated 1-node explants, <italic>BRC1</italic> influences the length of the lag phase during bud activation, suggesting that it may affect the rate of establishment of auxin transport canalisation out of the bud (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43">Nahas <italic>et al</italic>., 2024</xref>). Therefore, we developed a unified model incorporating this hypothesis and assessed whether it could capture the dynamics of growth and bud-bud competition in 2-node explants. We find that our computational model captures multiple bud behaviours across a wide range of genotypes and treatments, and generates testable predictions, which we largely validate. Taken together, this work integrates the <italic>BRC1</italic> and PIN1 regulatory hubs into a single model, combining systemic and local modes of shoot branching regulation.</p></sec><sec id="S2" sec-type="results"><label>2</label><title>Results</title><sec id="S3"><label>2.1</label><title>Strigolactone-mediated <italic>BRC1</italic> expression inhibits bud activation in 1-node explants</title><p id="P14">The dual action of strigolactone on <italic>BRC1</italic> and PIN1 provides an opportunity to assess the relationship between these two modes of bud regulation. Strigolactone signalling leads to the degradation of SMXL678 proteins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">Jiang <italic>et al</italic>., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R80">Zhou <italic>et al</italic>., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R73">Wang <italic>et al</italic>., 2015</xref>), such that the <italic>smxl678</italic> triple mutant has constitutively active strigolactone signalling, with high levels of <italic>BRC1</italic> expression and PIN1 removal from the plasma membrane (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R65">Soundappan <italic>et al</italic>., 2015</xref>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig 2A</xref>).</p><p id="P15">To test the impact of <italic>BRC1</italic> on bud outgrowth dynamics, we compared bud behaviours on 1-node explants of Col-0, <italic>brc1brc2, smxl678</italic>, and <italic>brc1brc2 smxl678</italic>. Buds were defined as active if their growth rate reached at least 2.5mm/day. Unlike on Col-0 and <italic>brc1brc2</italic> explants, <italic>smxl678</italic> buds did not activate within the timeframe of our experiment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig 2B</xref>). However, their activation was fully restored in the <italic>brc1brc2smxl678</italic> quintuple mutant, suggesting that the lack of growth of <italic>smxl678</italic> buds in 1-node assays is due primarily to high levels of <italic>BRC1</italic> expression. We calculated the duration of the initial slow-growing lag phase, defined as the number of days before bud growth rate exceeds 2.5mm/day (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig 2C</xref>). As previously reported, <italic>brc1brc2</italic> mutants have a shorter lag phase than Col-0 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43">Nahas et al., 2024</xref>), which was also the case for <italic>brc1brc2smxl678</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig 2C</xref>). Therefore with respect to early bud activation, <italic>brc1brc2</italic> is fully epistatic to <italic>smx678</italic> in this assay. Interestingly, branches on <italic>brc1brc2smxl678</italic> explants consistently stopped growing earlier than Col-0 or <italic>brc1brc2</italic> branches (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig 2B</xref>), suggesting that BRC1-independent strigolactone signalling influences sustained bud growth.</p></sec><sec id="S4"><label>2.2</label><title>Strigolactone-mediated regulation of bud-bud competition in 2-node explants is due to <italic>BRC1</italic>-dependent and independent effects</title><p id="P16">To explore the role of <italic>BRC1</italic> in mediating competition between buds, we assessed the behaviour of buds on 2-node explants of Col-0, <italic>brc1brc2, smxl678</italic>, and <italic>brc1brc2smxl678</italic>. The growth of buds on each explant is shown on Mitchison plots (introduced in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">fig 1C</xref>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig 2D</xref>). We use the relative growth index (RGI) of active explants (defined as explants with at least one active bud) to compare bud behaviour between genotypes. The RGI is the length of the longest bud as a ratio of the total length of both buds. An RGI of 0.5 indicates both buds growing equally, while an RGI of 1 indicates one bud dominating the other.</p><p id="P17">Col-0 explants exhibited all three possible outcomes for active explants (introduced in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig 1C</xref>), with either one or both buds activating in each explant (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2D</xref>). In <italic>brc1brc2</italic> explants, both buds activated on all explants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2D</xref>), resulting in a lower mean RGI than for Col-0, although here this difference is not statistically significant (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig 2E</xref>). This is consistent with previous results (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R59">Seale <italic>et al</italic>., 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R51">van Rongen <italic>et al</italic>., 2019</xref>), and with the high branching of <italic>brc1brc2</italic> plants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">Aguilar-Martínez <italic>et al</italic>., 2007</xref>). While <italic>smxl678</italic> buds did not activate in 1-node explants, interestingly one bud did activate in a substantial number of 2-node explants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig 2D</xref>), resulting in very high RGIs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig 2E</xref>).</p><p id="P18">Importantly, unlike for 1-node explants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig 2B</xref>), <italic>brc1brc2</italic> was not fully epistatic to <italic>smxl678</italic> in 2-node explants, but rather in <italic>brc1brc2smxl678</italic> explants, one bud often dominated the other, resulting in an RGI intermediate between that of <italic>brc1brc2</italic> and <italic>smxl678</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig 2D,E</xref>). As in 1-node explants, <italic>brc1brc2smxl678</italic> active apices stopped growing early. This was often followed by activation of the other bud, with this growth pattern clearly visible on the Mitchison plots (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig 2D</xref>), consistent with the ability of one bud to inhibit the other in this genotype. Taken together, these results indicate that the high RGI of <italic>smxl678</italic> is due to a combination of <italic>BRC1</italic>-dependent and -independent effects of strigolactone-mediated bud inhibition.</p></sec><sec id="S5"><label>2.3</label><title>Incorporating <italic>BRC1</italic> into a canalisation-based model of bud-bud competition</title><p id="P19">Bud-bud competition is hypothesised to be based on competitive auxin transport canalisation into the stem (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R63">Snow, 1937</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32">Li &amp; Bangerth, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R47">Ongaro <italic>et al</italic>., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R49">Prusinkiewicz <italic>et al</italic>., 2009</xref>), and we previously hypothesised that the lag phase of bud growth corresponds to the time during which canalised auxin transport is established (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43">Nahas <italic>et al</italic>., 2024</xref>). Given this, the impact of <italic>brc1brc2</italic> on the length of the lag phase and on the growth outcomes of buds in 2-node explants suggests that <italic>BRC1</italic> might influence auxin transport canalisation. The auxin transport network, and hence the developmental processes it regulates such as shoot branching, are heavily feedback-driven, making their dynamics difficult to intuit (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R69">Van Berkel <italic>et al</italic>., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R50">Ravichandran <italic>et al</italic>., 2020</xref>). Mathematical modelling is a powerful tool to test which interactions can account for observed phenomena (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R67">Tomlin &amp; Axelrod, 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38">Middleton <italic>et al</italic>., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">Cieslak <italic>et al</italic>., 2022</xref>). To test whether the hypothesis that <italic>BRC1</italic> influences the dynamics of auxin transport canalisation, can account for the behaviours we observe, we built a mathematical model of canalisation-based bud-bud competition in 2-node explants.</p><p id="P20">The model consists of two self-activating and mutually-inhibiting buds (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig 3A</xref>). It preserves the most conceptually important aspects of the auxin transport canalisation model for shoot branching from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R49">Prusinkiewicz <italic>et al</italic>., (2009)</xref>. These include a hysteretic bistable switch in bud activation caused by flux-regulated polar PIN accumulation dictated by a Hill function, combined with linear PIN removal. We simplified the formulation of auxin transport by using a formulation for the ratio of auxin influx to efflux (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">Cieslak <italic>et al</italic>., 2015</xref>), and by combining parameters referring to PIN and auxin concentration into one efflux term (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Mathematical appendix</xref>). This was possible because we abstracted the stem section joining the two buds, and assumed that buds have an equal and constant auxin concentration over time, given evidence of homeostatic feedback on auxin synthesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33">Ljung <italic>et al</italic>., 2001</xref>). We also abstracted the top and bottom bud positions, representing the explant as symmetrical. We obtain the following formulation for the flux of auxin, E and F, out of the top and bottom bud, respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig 3B</xref>): <disp-formula id="FD1"><mml:math id="M1"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable equalrows="true" equalcolumns="true"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>F</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mi>F</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="P21">The change in auxin efflux is described by: (i) <italic>v</italic>0, a basal rate of efflux, which corresponds to non-polar auxin transport and/or diffusion of auxin out of the bud, (ii) a Hill function that represents the positive feedback of auxin efflux on itself, mirroring previous models of canalisation, with <italic>v</italic> as the maximum rate of efflux for the Hill function, <italic>S</italic> the efficiency of feedback-driven auxin efflux, <italic>n</italic> the Hill exponent that influences the degree of nonlinearity in the feedback, and <italic>K</italic> a threshold parameter, and (iii) <italic>µ</italic>, a linear decrease in efflux, which relates to both the removal of PINs from the plasma membrane and the degradation of auxin. The auxin efflux from one bud, conceptually contributing to the auxin concentration in the stem, dampens its own auxin efflux and that of the other bud at a strength that is proportional to <italic>D</italic> and proportional to the sink strength of the main stem, which is determined by the sum of auxin efflux <italic>E</italic> and <italic>F</italic> from each bud. This captures the source/sink dynamics between the buds and the main stem.</p><p id="P22">To model bud growth rate, we postulate a relationship between growth and bud auxin efflux, captured by another Hill function: <disp-formula id="FD2"><mml:math id="M2"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mtext> and </mml:mtext><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="P23">N and M are the length of the top and bottom bud, respectively. <italic>Q</italic> is the Hill saturation coefficient and <italic>m</italic> is the Hill exponent that influences the degree of non-linearity between auxin efflux and growth rate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig 3B</xref>). This relationship is informed by our previous analysis which suggested a positive relationship between auxin transport and growth rate in 1-node explants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43">Nahas <italic>et al</italic>., 2024</xref>), though in some cases buds can grow rapidly with low steady state levels of auxin transport, for example in <italic>brc1brc2smxl678</italic> buds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R59">Seale <italic>et al</italic>., 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig 2</xref>). We therefore chose a parameter range where changes in steady state auxin efflux did not consistently cause a large change in growth rate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig 3C</xref>).</p><p id="P24">To represent the initial dormancy of buds in 2-node explants, simulated buds were assigned equal very low starting values of auxin efflux. For simulations with relevant parameters, the positive feedback on auxin efflux increases the auxin efflux out of both buds. Without stochasticity, both buds switch to high auxin export in all simulations. However, if the positive feedback on auxin efflux exhibits some stochasticity, both buds initially increase their efflux, but one bud may gain a small advantage in its auxin efflux, which is amplified by the positive feedback, enabling one bud to establish canalised auxin export first, and to inhibit the canalisation of the other bud (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig 3D,E</xref>). Given the known correlation between auxin transport and sustained bud activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41">Morris, 1977</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42">Morris &amp; Johnson, 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R49">Prusinkiewicz <italic>et al</italic>., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">Balla <italic>et al</italic>., 2011</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">2016</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">Chabikwa <italic>et al</italic>., 2019</xref>), and our previous hypothesis that the slow-growing lag phase corresponds to the time when buds establish canalised auxin transport (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43">Nahas <italic>et al</italic>., 2024</xref>), we chose parameters where the switch from slow to rapid growth coincides with an increase in auxin efflux (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig 3D</xref>). This also entailed that inhibited buds, which export low auxin, exhibit little to no growth, consistent with experimental observations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig 3D, E</xref>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R47">Ongaro <italic>et al</italic>., 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R48">Paterlini <italic>et al</italic>., 2021</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43">Nahas <italic>et al</italic>., 2024</xref>).</p><p id="P25">We next considered how to represent, in the model, the action of strigolactone on both PIN1 removal from the plasma membrane and <italic>BRC1</italic> expression. For the former, we postulated in a previous model that the parameter <italic>μ</italic> can be conceptualised as PIN1 removal (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig 3A, B</xref>), such that an increase in <italic>μ</italic> models strigolactone-mediated PIN1 removal from the plasma membrane (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R49">Prusinkiewicz <italic>et al</italic>., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">Crawford <italic>et al</italic>., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R60">Shinohara <italic>et al</italic>., 2013</xref>). To represent <italic>BRC1</italic>, we considered that <italic>BRC1</italic> influences the length of the lag phase, which we hypothesise corresponds to the time of canalisation establishment, and does not influence levels of bulk auxin transport through stem sections (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">Bennett <italic>et al</italic>., 2016a</xref>). Given this, we assessed which parameters affect the timing of the switch to high auxin efflux during canalisation, but not the steady state levels of auxin efflux (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Fig S1</xref>). Both parameters <italic>v0</italic> and <italic>K</italic> meet these criteria. We chose to focus on <italic>v</italic>0, influenced by our previous observations that mutation in the <italic>ABCB19</italic> auxin efflux protein can partially suppress branching in <italic>brc1brc2</italic> mutants, and ABCB19 plausibly contributes to <italic>v</italic>0 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R51">van Rongen <italic>et al</italic>., 2019</xref>). Taken together, we hypothesise that the dual action of strigolactone via PIN1 removal and <italic>BRC1</italic> up-regulation can be represented by a simultaneous increase in <italic>μ</italic> and decrease in <italic>v0</italic>.</p><p id="P26">We identified a region of parameter space where the range of bud activation behaviours in the model match those in our experimental data, and where the dynamics of bud activation capture the basic properties described above. A range of (<italic>v</italic>0, <italic>µ</italic>) slices deliver these core behaviours (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Fig S2A,B</xref>). After systematically exploring parameter space (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Fig S2, S3</xref>), we chose one (<italic>v</italic>0, <italic>µ</italic>) slice for detailed analysis.</p></sec><sec id="S6"><label>2.4</label><title>The model captures bud behaviours for a wide range of strigolactone-related genotypes and treatments</title><p id="P27">Strigolactone triggers PIN1 removal from the plasma membrane and promotes <italic>BRC1</italic> transcription, represented in the model by parameters <italic>µ</italic> and <italic>v</italic>0, respectively. To determine whether appropriate changes in <italic>v</italic>0 and <italic>µ</italic> were sufficient to capture the effects of relevant strigolactone mutations and treatments, we compared the behaviour of buds on 2-node explants with cognate changes in <italic>v0</italic> and/or <italic>µ</italic> in the selected (v0, <italic>µ</italic>) slice, with all other parameters held constant.</p><p id="P28">Mitchison plots of bud measurements from experiments show that genotypes and treatments with variation in PIN1 removal and/or <italic>BRC1</italic> expression, exhibit variation in the relative proportion of explants where two versus only one bud activates (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig 4A</xref>). In the strigolactone receptor mutant, <italic>d14</italic>, and in the <italic>brc1brc2</italic> mutant, both buds activate on all explants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig 4A</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R51">van Rongen <italic>et al</italic>., 2019</xref>). In Col-0 explants, either one or both buds grow (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig 4A</xref>). Basal supply of the synthetic strigolactone rac-GR24 (hereafter GR24) or the <italic>smxl678</italic> background, a constitutive strigolactone signalling triple mutant, increases the level of competition between buds, increasing the frequency with which only one bud activates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">Crawford <italic>et al</italic>., 2010</xref>). A qualitatively similar effect is seen with GR24 application and <italic>smxl678</italic> mutation in a <italic>brc1brc2</italic> mutant background, in which strigolactone is predicted to affect PIN1 removal from the plasma membrane and not <italic>BRC1</italic> expression (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig 4A</xref>).</p><p id="P29">To test whether our experimental data in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig 4A</xref> can be reproduced in the model via changes in <italic>v</italic>0 and <italic>μ</italic> only, we mapped our experimental data onto the selected (<italic>v0, μ</italic>) slice of parameter space (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig 4B</xref>(i)). Each pixel in the figure represents the modelled bud growth outcome at a given combination of <italic>v0</italic> and <italic>μ</italic> parameter values. Buds are described as active if they achieve canalised auxin export. The pixel colour quantitatively represents the outcomes: (i) both buds growing (yellow), (ii) one bud growing (blue) and (iii) neither bud growing (red). The black lines describe the boundaries between areas of parameter space that have a different number of possible outcomes (i.e. a different number of stable steady states). In zone 1 both buds always grow. Zone 2 has two possible behaviours, with either one bud growing or both. The proportion of simulations with both buds growing versus one bud growing varies within zone 2. To reflect this shifting probability distribution, the pixel intensity is assigned as the ratio of outcomes from 50 stochastic simulations at each point in parameter space. The only behaviour in zone 3 is one bud growing. In zone 4, either one bud grows, neither bud grows, or both buds grow, though for the starting values and timeframe of our simulations, the most common outcome is no buds growing, with occasionally one bud activating. The resulting (<italic>v</italic>0, <italic>μ</italic>) map of parameter space shows that <italic>v</italic>0 and <italic>μ</italic> have similar effects but with opposite polarities, with increasing values of <italic>μ</italic> and reducing values of <italic>v</italic>0 shifting the outcome from both buds growing, through to only one bud, and eventually fully inhibited explants.</p><p id="P30">We calculated the relative frequency of the various bud growth outcomes in the data. On the colour map, there is a distribution of points, broadly across the tristable region (zone 2), where the frequency of bud growth outcomes in the data is the same as in the model. We plotted this distribution for each genotype/treatment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig 4B(ii)</xref>). Given we represent PIN1 removal as <italic>μ</italic> and hypothesise that <italic>BRC1</italic> expression can be represented as <italic>v</italic>0, we could constrain the placement of each genotype/treatment by considering their known phenotypes in terms of PIN1 accumulation and <italic>BRC1</italic> expression levels: (i) Under our hypothesis that <italic>v</italic>0, the basal rate of auxin efflux, is negatively regulated by <italic>BRC1</italic>, the <italic>brc1brc2</italic> mutant must have a higher value of <italic>v</italic>0 than Col-0, and this high value will be common to all <italic>brc1brc2</italic> lines. (ii) PIN1:GFP membrane accumulation is the same in Col-0 and <italic>brc1brc2</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">Bennett <italic>et al</italic>., 2016b</xref>), and therefore their value of <italic>μ</italic> is likely also the same. (iii) Applying the synthetic strigolactone GR24 removes PIN1 from the membrane and increases <italic>BRC1</italic> expression (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">Aguilar-Martínez <italic>et al</italic>., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">Dun <italic>et al</italic>., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R60">Shinohara <italic>et al</italic>., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">Bennett <italic>et al</italic>., 2016b</xref>), so Col-0 +GR24 must have lower <italic>v</italic>0 and higher <italic>μ</italic> than Col-0. (v) Applying GR24 is assumed to increase <italic>μ</italic> by the same amount in Col-0 and <italic>brc1brc2</italic>, so Col-0 +GR24 and <italic>brc1brc2</italic> +GR24 are assumed to be on the same vertical line. (vi) <italic>smxl678</italic> and <italic>brc1brc2smxl678</italic> have the same high PIN1 removal, such that they should be located on the same vertical line at a higher <italic>μ</italic> value than Col-0. (vii) Given its constitutive active strigolactone signalling, <italic>smxl678</italic> is modelled as more effective than GR24 treatment at increasing <italic>μ</italic> and decreasing <italic>v</italic>0.</p><p id="P31">These relationships create three vertical bars determining a value of <italic>μ</italic> for (i) Col-0 and <italic>brc1brc2</italic>, (ii) GR24 treatments, and (iii) <italic>smxl678</italic> backgrounds. In addition, three horizontal bars represent (i) the value of <italic>v</italic>0 in <italic>brc1brc2</italic> mutant backgrounds, (ii) in Col-0, and (iii) after GR24 application, with <italic>smxl678</italic> plotted at an even lower <italic>v</italic>0 value. Given these relationships, the values of <italic>v</italic>0 and <italic>μ</italic> that best fit the pixel distribution are shown by the dark grey bars in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig 4B(ii)</xref>. The genotypes and treatments were placed at the intersection of these bars, each shown with a coloured dot (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig 4B(iii)</xref>). The strigolactone receptor mutant, <italic>d14</italic>, has very low <italic>BRC1</italic> expression and low PIN1 removal (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">Bennett <italic>et al</italic>., 2016b</xref>), so was placed at the same low <italic>v</italic>0 value as the <italic>brc1brc2</italic> mutants, with a lower <italic>μ</italic> value than Col-0.</p><p id="P32">Overall, the location of each genotype/treatment is on or near the distribution of points where the bud growth outcomes in the experimental data match those of the model. The resulting colour map in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig 4B(iv)</xref> shows the narrowed-down regions of the genotypes and treatments in parameter space. The simulations that generate these bud growth outcomes give similar Mitchison plots (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig 4C</xref>) to the experimental data (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig 4A</xref>), and produce associated bud growth dynamics, which we next compared to our experimental data.</p></sec><sec id="S7"><label>2.5</label><title>The model captures the effects of strigolactone on the duration of the lag phase during bud activation</title><p id="P33">We previously characterised bud activation as occurring in two phases: a slow-growing lag phase followed by a period of rapid outgrowth (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43">Nahas <italic>et al</italic>., 2024</xref>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig 1C</xref>). The parameters chosen to simulate our genotypes and treatments based on bud growth outcomes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig 4B</xref>) provide predictions about the length of the lag phase and the maximum growth rate (MGR) of each genotype/treatment for these parameters.</p><p id="P34">To test these predictions, we produced a heatmap for the duration of the lag phase in the same (<italic>v</italic>0, <italic>μ</italic>) slice of parameter space used to map the genotypes/treatments in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig 4B</xref> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig 5A</xref>). The genotypes and treatments in our experimental dataset were assigned the same <italic>v</italic>0 and <italic>μ</italic> values as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig 4B</xref>. The number of lag days for each set of (<italic>v</italic>0, <italic>µ</italic>) values are plotted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig 5B</xref>. In our model, a combined increase in <italic>µ</italic> and decrease in <italic>v</italic>0 progressively increase the length of the lag phase across <italic>d14</italic>, Col-0, Col-0 +GR24, and <italic>smxl678</italic>, which spans increasing strength in strigolactone signalling (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig 5B</xref>, blue data points). This successfully captures the changes in our experimental dataset, where increasing <italic>BRC1</italic> expression and PIN1 removal together progressively delay bud activation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig 5C</xref>, blue data points).</p><p id="P35">In the model, an increase in <italic>μ</italic> alone causes only a small delay in bud activation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig 5B</xref>, black data points). This matches our experimental observation that increasing PIN1 removal in a <italic>brc1brc2</italic> mutant background, either through application of GR24, or in a <italic>smxl678</italic> background, has respectively no or a small significant effect on the number of lag days (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig 5C</xref>, black data points). Overall, the model captures qualitatively the observed trends in number of lag days between genotypes and treatments. It is notable that we observe significant within and between-experiment variation in the timing of bud activation in <italic>smxl678</italic> lines (if bud activation is even observed within the timeframe of our experiment) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig 5C</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2E</xref>). Interestingly, simulated lag days at very low <italic>v</italic>0, representing <italic>smxl678</italic>, are sensitive to small changes in parameter values (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Fig S5A, B</xref>). Trends across our other genotypes/treatments are robust to such changes (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Fig S5A, B</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S8"><label>2.6</label><title>The model captures the effects of strigolactone on bud maximum growth rate</title><p id="P36">After the lag phase, buds switch into a period of rapid outgrowth (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43">Nahas <italic>et al</italic>., 2024</xref>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig 1C</xref>), which can be quantified by measuring the maximum growth rate (MGR). We generated a heatmap of the MGR across the previously used (<italic>v</italic>0, <italic>μ</italic>) slice (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig 6A</xref>). The parameter <italic>μ</italic> has a stronger influence on the MGR than <italic>v</italic>0, because it has a stronger influence on the steady state levels of auxin efflux (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Fig S1</xref>), which in the model, determines the growth rate of active buds (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig 3C</xref>). The plots of MGR for each simulated genotype/treatment show the expected decrease in MGR with increasing <italic>µ</italic> with or without simultaneous changes in <italic>v</italic>0 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig 6B</xref>). These trends are robust to small changes in parameter values (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Fig S5B, C</xref>).</p><p id="P37">To test whether this reflects the experimentally observed changes in MGR, we calculated the MGR across the same group of genotypes and treatments used previously (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig 6C</xref>). Simultaneously increasing <italic>BRC1</italic> expression and PIN1 removal lowers the MGR as can be seen across the <italic>d14</italic>, Col-0, Col-0 +GR24 strigolactone signalling gradient (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig 6C</xref>, blue data points). One discrepancy between the model and our experiments is that <italic>brc1brc2smxl678</italic> had the same MGR as Col-0 in the experimental data, while the model predicts a lower MGR (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig 6B, C</xref>). The predicted lower MGR was observed when <italic>brc1brc2</italic> 2-node explants are treated with GR24 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig 6B, C</xref>), indicating the model better captures the MGR of GR24 treatment than that of a <italic>smxl678</italic> background.</p></sec><sec id="S9"><label>2.7</label><title>The middle region of the hydrophilic loop is key for strigolactone-mediated effects on PIN1 but not on <italic>BRC1</italic></title><p id="P38">We have shown that changes in <italic>v</italic>0 and <italic>μ</italic> can capture a wide range of experimentally observed bud growth characteristics across different genotypes and treatments with altered levels of <italic>BRC1</italic> expression and/or PIN1 accumulation. While we can use the <italic>brc1brc2</italic> mutant to test the <italic>BRC1</italic>-independent effects of strigolactone on shoot branching, testing the PIN1-independent effects has so far not been possible, due to the pleiotropy of the <italic>pin1</italic> mutant phenotype, which includes failure to form lateral organs and axillary meristems. To overcome this limitation, we sought to generate a strigolactone-insensitive PIN1 by identifying the region of PIN1 responsible for its strigolactone sensitivity and replacing it with the cognate region from a strigolactone-insensitive PIN family member. Canonical PIN proteins consist of 10 helices functioning as 2 groups of 5 transmembrane domains, separated by a hydrophilic loop exposed to the cytosolic environment. The hydrophilic loop contains several phosphosites which are targeted by kinases to regulate PIN recycling, transport activity, and polarisation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">Barbosa <italic>et al</italic>., 2018</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">Bassukas <italic>et al</italic>., 2022</xref>), thereby influencing the properties of the auxin transport network. We hypothesised that the hydrophilic loop was a likely target for strigolactone-mediated PIN1 endocytosis.</p><p id="P39">To test this hypothesis, we performed domain swaps between sections of the PIN1 hydrophilic loop and equivalent regions of PIN3, which is insensitive to strigolactone (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig 7A</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R51">van Rongen <italic>et al</italic>., 2019</xref>). In particular, we swapped the middle region of the loop, which we termed L2, spanning residues 253 to 364 of PIN1. To assess the strigolactone sensitivity of the domain-swap constructs, we quantified the effect of GR24 on the accumulation of the chimeric PINs at the plasma membrane of xylem parenchyma cells. Transverse stem sections were incubated in 5μM GR24 or mock treatment for 6 hours before imaging. As expected, GR24 treatment reduced the accumulation of PIN1:GFP at the plasma membrane but did not affect that of PIN3. The fluorescence intensity of the PIN1::PIN3-PIN1<sub>L2</sub>:GFP construct, i.e. GFP-tagged PIN3 with the middle region of PIN1 driven from the <italic>PIN1</italic> promoter, was lower in the GR24 treatment than in mock treated stems, indicating that it is strigolactone sensitive. We named this construct <italic>STRIGOLACTONE SENSITIVE PIN3</italic> (<italic>SSP3</italic>). Conversely, the fluorescence intensity of PIN1::PIN1-PIN3<sub>L2</sub>:GFP, i.e. GFP-tagged PIN1 with the middle region of the PIN3 loop, was the same in mock and GR24 treatments, indicating that this construct has reduced strigolactone sensitivity compared to native PIN1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig 7A,B</xref>). We named it <italic>STRIGOLACTONE INSENSITIVE PIN1</italic> (<italic>SIP1</italic>). Overall, these results suggest that the L2 region of the PIN1 loop is necessary and sufficient for PIN strigolactone sensitivity.</p><p id="P40">Crossing SIP1 into the <italic>pin1</italic> mutant background rescued the formation of leaves, axillary buds and flowers (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Fig S6A</xref>). To assess the shoot branching phenotype conferred by <italic>SIP1pin1</italic>, we quantified branching in plants grown to terminal flowering in long day conditions (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Fig S6B, C</xref>). <italic>SIP1</italic> confers a modest increase in branching in both the <italic>pin1</italic> and <italic>smxl678pin1</italic> backgrounds, consistent with its strigolactone resistance. However, branching was not significantly increased in the <italic>brc1brc2</italic> background, such that the combination of <italic>brc1brc2</italic> with <italic>SIP1</italic> was unable to phenocopy the full branching phenotype of the <italic>d14</italic> strigolactone receptor mutant.</p><p id="P41">To assess further the effect of substituting PIN1 L2 for PIN3 L2, we quantified its accumulation on the plasma membrane of xylem parenchyma cells in transverse stem sections in several genetic backgrounds. The fluorescence intensity on <italic>SIP1pin1</italic> membranes was higher than that of PIN1:GFP in a <italic>pin1</italic> background, and its accumulation was not significantly reduced in the <italic>pin1smxl678</italic> background, which has very low accumulation of PIN1:GFP, even with the inclusion of <italic>max2</italic>, to which <italic>smxl678</italic> fully epistatic (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig 7C</xref>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R65">Soundapann <italic>et al</italic>., 2015</xref>). These results are consistent with strigolactone insensitivity of SIP1. However, accumulation of SIP1 in a wild-type background was not as high as that of PIN1:GFP in the <italic>d14</italic> background. It is therefore possible that SIP1 retains some strigolactone response.</p><p id="P42">To test the influence of SIP1 on auxin transport, we performed bulk auxin transport assays through <italic>SIP1pin1</italic> and <italic>SIP1pin1smxl678</italic> stem segments. <italic>SIP1pin1</italic> stems have significantly lower levels of bulk auxin transport than Col-0, despite the higher fluorescence intensity on the plasma membrane, and therefore presumably higher membrane accumulation of the protein (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig 7</xref>). Similarly, high SIP1 accumulation on the plasma membrane did not correlate with high bulk auxin transport activity in the <italic>smxl678</italic> background, with auxin transport levels as low in <italic>SIP1pin1smxl678</italic> as in <italic>smxl678</italic>.</p><p id="P43">Overall, these results confirm that strigolactone sensitivity of SIP1 is severely compromised, but also suggest that swapping the middle region of the PIN1 loop with that of PIN3 has other impacts beyond changes in strigolactone sensitivity, including impacts on the efficiency of auxin transport. This means that any effects of SIP1 could be due to its strigolactone resistant accumulation, or to these other changes. Furthermore, it is possible that some sensitivity to strigolactone is retained in SIP1.</p><p id="P44">To test whether SIP1 has any effect on <italic>BRC1</italic> expression, we performed qRT-PCR on RNA extracted from pools of small (presumed dormant) and big (presumed active) buds of Col-0, <italic>SIP1pin1, smxl678</italic>, and <italic>SIP1pin1smxl678</italic>. Consistent with previous results and its role suppressing bud growth, <italic>BRC1</italic> expression in Col-0 was higher in small than large buds (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig 7E</xref>). This trend was observed in all lines tested. In addition, as previously reported (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R65">Soundappan et al., 2015</xref>)), <italic>smxl678</italic> mutant buds had higher <italic>BRC1</italic> expression than Col-0. The expression level of <italic>BRC1</italic> in <italic>SIP1pin1</italic> and <italic>SIP1pin1smxl678</italic> was not consistently different to that in the cognate native PIN1 backgrounds (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig 7E</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">S7</xref>). This suggests that SIP1 does not affect <italic>BRC1</italic> expression, consistent with a model where strigolactone-mediated effects on <italic>BRC1</italic> expression and PIN1 removal are independent.</p></sec><sec id="S10"><label>2.8</label><title>The effect of strigolactone in <italic>SIP1pin1</italic> backgrounds can be predicted by changes in <italic>v0</italic></title><p id="P45">We sought to predict the 2-node bud growth phenotypes conferred by <italic>SIP1pin1</italic>. We account for the lower bulk auxin transport in <italic>SIP1pin1</italic> lines (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">fig 7D</xref>), by assigning a lower value of S, a parameter corresponding to the efficiency of feedback-driven auxin efflux. This places the <italic>SIP1pin1</italic> mutants on a different (<italic>v</italic>0, <italic>μ</italic>) slice than that used in the previously described simulations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig 8A</xref>). Predicting the location of <italic>SIP1pin1</italic> lines on this slice (and hence their phenotype) required estimating their <italic>v</italic>0 and <italic>μ</italic> values. Given no evidence of an effect of <italic>SIP1</italic> on <italic>BRC1</italic> expression (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7E</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">S7</xref>), we assigned the <italic>v</italic>0 value previously used for each genetic background and treatment. The second parameter <italic>μ</italic>, which corresponds to PIN1 removal from the plasma membrane, is not measured directly. Given that the strigolactone response of SIP1 is reduced compared to PIN1, and the steady state level of GFP accumulation on the plasma membrane is high, we assigned to the <italic>SIP1pin1</italic> lines the same value of <italic>μ</italic> as <italic>d14</italic>, which has no strigolactone-mediated removal of PIN1. We therefore predicted that <italic>SIP1pin1, SIP1pin1</italic> +GR24, and <italic>SIP1pin1smxl678</italic> should have the same low value of <italic>μ</italic>, but progressively lower <italic>v</italic>0 values.</p><p id="P46">Looking at bud growth outcomes, the model predicts a gradual increase in the proportion of explants with only one active bud across the <italic>SIP1pin1, SIP1pin1</italic> +GR24, <italic>SIP1pin1smxl678</italic> strigolactone signalling gradient (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig 8A,B</xref>), and thus an increasing RGI (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig 8D</xref>). To test this prediction, we performed 2-node assays on these genotypes, including Col-0, Col-0 +GR24 and <italic>d14</italic> as controls. From the Mitchison plots, we indeed found a gradual increase in explants with only one active bud across <italic>SIP1pin1, SIP1pin1</italic> +GR24, and <italic>SIP1pin1smxl678</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig 8C</xref>), which was reflected in the increased RGI (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig 8E</xref>). In <italic>SIP1pin1smxl678</italic>, one bud often dominated then stopped growing, followed by the activation of the second bud (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig 8C</xref>), leading to a low RGI despite strong mutual inhibition in this genotype (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig 8D</xref>). Like <italic>smxl678, SIP1pin1smxl678</italic> buds activated very slowly, so to track their growth we measured bud length for 19 days, while the other genotypes were measured for 12 days.</p><p id="P47">To assess bud activation dynamics, we produced a heatmap (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig 9A</xref>) and boxplot (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig 9B</xref>) of the number of lag days from model simulations using the parameters assigned for each genotype, with associated sensitivity analysis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5E, F</xref>). The simulations show that modelling SIP1 with low <italic>μ</italic>, wild-type lag days are expected. Gradually increasing <italic>v</italic>0 across the <italic>SIP1pin1, SIP1pin1</italic> +GR24, <italic>SIP1pin1smxl678</italic> series, predicts that bud activation is increasingly delayed. The experimentally observed number of lag days calculated from the data validates these predictions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">fig 9C</xref>), with a longer delay in bud activation of <italic>SIP1pinsmxl678</italic> than predicted. For MGRs, the simulations with low <italic>μ</italic>, produce a wild-type MGR, and gradually increasing <italic>v</italic>0 across the <italic>SIP1pin1, SIP1pin1</italic> +GR24, and <italic>SIP1pin1smxl678</italic> series predicts no effect on MGR (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig 9D,E</xref>). While the comparisons of <italic>SIP1pin1</italic> with <italic>SIP1pin1</italic> +GR24, and <italic>SIP1pin1</italic> +GR24 with <italic>SIP1pin1smxl678</italic>, are consistent with these predictions, we observe a statistically significant decrease in MGR between Col-0 and <italic>SIP1pin1smxl678</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig 8F</xref>).</p><p id="P48">Overall, we find that changes in <italic>v0</italic> only were largely sufficient to capture the phenotypes we observed across three <italic>SIP1pin1</italic> backgrounds with increasingly strong strigolactone signalling. This is consistent with our hypothesis that variation in <italic>v0</italic> corresponds to BRC1-mediated strigolactone signalling.</p></sec><sec id="S11"><label>2.9</label><title><italic>SIP1</italic> lines retain some strigolactone response independent of BRC1</title><p id="P49">If <italic>SIP1pin1</italic> is fully strigolactone resistant and strigolactone acts only via PIN1 L2 and <italic>BRC1</italic>, we would predict that <italic>SIP1pin1brc1brc2</italic> should have no strigolactone response. To test this prediction, we generated the <italic>SIP1pin1brc1brc2</italic> mutant. The <italic>brc1brc2</italic> mutant background did not affect <italic>SIP1</italic> membrane accumulation or bulk auxin transport as compared to <italic>SIP1pin1</italic> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Fig S8</xref>).</p><p id="P50">We performed a 2-node assay to compare the effect of GR24 on <italic>SIP1pin1brc1brc2</italic> to that on <italic>SIP1pin1</italic> and <italic>brc1brc2</italic> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Fig S9</xref>). With respect to the lag phase, GR24 extends the number of lag days in both the <italic>brc1brc2</italic> and <italic>SIP1pin1</italic> backgrounds. However, there was no significant effect of GR24 on the lag phase in the <italic>SIP1pin1brc1brc2</italic> background.</p><p id="P51">In contrast, we found that <italic>SIP1pin1brc1brc2</italic> buds retain a GR24 response with respect to RGI and MGR, with a small but significant increase observed in both measures (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Fig S9</xref>). These results are consistent with SIP1 retaining some strigolactone sensitivity, or with a PIN1, BRC1-independent mode of action of action for strigolactone. To assess whether this could be due to the presence of functional PIN7, which is also likely to be strigolactone responsive (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R51">van Rongen et al., 2019</xref>), we made <italic>SIP1pin1pin7</italic>. We observed the same branching phenotype in <italic>SIP1pin1pin7</italic> as for <italic>SIP1pin1</italic> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">FIg S6B,C</xref>). Buds in 2-node explants showed no difference in the responses to strigolactone in the <italic>SIP1pin1pin7</italic> background (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Fig S9</xref>). Therefore, the remaining strigolactone responsiveness is unlikely to be mediated by PIN7, but analysis of the <italic>SIP1pin1pin7brc1brc2</italic> would be required to rule this out definitively.</p></sec></sec><sec id="S12" sec-type="discussion"><label>3</label><title>Discussion</title><sec id="S13"><title>Multi-scale signal integration in the regulation of bud activity</title><p id="P52">Plants continuously integrate local and systemic inputs to tune shoot branching. Two regulatory hubs have been identified as central to this process, with the BRC1 transcription factor acting locally in the bud to repress outgrowth, and the auxin transport network systemically mediating competition between apices.</p><p id="P53">The competition between apices is hypothesised to occur via an autocatalytic feedback between auxin transport and its upregulation and polarisation in the prevailing transport direction. This creates competition for access to auxin transport in the main stem, with reinforcement through the autocatalytic feedback. Competition with reinforcement is a classical regulatory architecture for a self-organising system (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37">Meinhardt &amp; Gierer, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R71">Van Schijndel <italic>et al</italic>., 2022</xref>). Systemic modulation of the feedbacks in the auxin transport network allows the number of active apices across the shoot system to be tuned, for example according to nutrient availability (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R68">Umehara <italic>et al</italic>., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31">Kohlen <italic>et al</italic>., 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">De Jong <italic>et al</italic>., 2014</xref>), while exactly which buds activate can be influenced by local bud-acting factors such as light quality.</p><p id="P54">Local bud competitiveness is likely mediated in part by the BRC1 regulatory hub (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R59">Seale <italic>et al</italic>., 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R72">Wang <italic>et al</italic>., 2019</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R70">Van Es <italic>et al</italic>., 2023</xref>). How these local and systemic factors are integrated is not well understood. The analysis of the impacts of strigolactone signalling on shoot branching has provided important insights. Strigolactone acts on both hubs, through upregulating <italic>BRC1</italic> transcription in buds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">Aguilar-Martínez <italic>et al</italic>., 2007</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">Braun <italic>et al</italic>., 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">Dun <italic>et al</italic>., 2012</xref>), and through triggering rapid depletion of PIN1 from the plasma membrane in a transcription-independent manner (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">Crawford <italic>et al</italic>., 2010</xref>), which makes auxin transport canalisation more difficult for buds to achieve. This is consistent with the high branching of strigolactone receptor or biosynthesis mutants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R44">Napoli &amp; Ruehle, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R66">Stirnberg <italic>et al</italic>., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R64">Sorefan <italic>et al</italic>., 2003</xref>).</p><p id="P55">Further insights into the regulation of bud activity come from considering the impacts of mutations and treatments on the slow-growing lag and rapid growth phase in isolated 1-node explants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">Chatfield <italic>et al</italic>., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R48">Paterlini <italic>et al</italic>., 2021</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">Barbier <italic>et al</italic>., 2021</xref>). For example, strigolactone extends the lag phase during bud activation and reduces the MGR of active branches, and <italic>brc1brc2</italic> mutants are relatively strigolactone-resistant to effects on the former but not on the latter (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43">Nahas <italic>et al</italic>., 2024</xref>). This approach has enabled the dissection of the shoot branching regulatory network. It has provided evidence to support the ideas that (i) the establishment of auxin transport canalisation occurs during the slow-growing lag phase of bud activation, with the transition to rapid growth corresponding to fully canalised export, which is hard to reverse, (ii) BRC1 influences the length of the lag phase, and (iii) the rate of rapid growth is influenced by the level of auxin efflux from the bud.</p><p id="P56">Complementing results from isolated 1-node explants, 2-node explants are a powerful minimal system to study the impact of another bud on growth dynamics, thereby revealing some of the systemic properties of shoot branching regulation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R63">Snow, 1937</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41">Morris, 1977</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32">Li &amp; Bangerth, 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R47">Ongaro <italic>et al</italic>., 2008</xref>). After excision from the plant, typically both buds on 2-node explants enter the slow-growing lag phase. If both buds have strong self-activation and/or low mutual-inhibition, then both activate. Alternatively, if one bud establishes rapid growth quickly and inhibits the growth of the other, then the second bud will stop growing. This phenomenon can be quantified using the RGI. Even when both buds activate, the presence of another bud extends the lag phase of both buds, and reduces their maximum growth rate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43">Nahas <italic>et al</italic>., 2024</xref>). Strigolactone has the same effects on the lag and rapid growth phases as in 1-node explants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig 5</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>), and additionally increases the RGI, typically resulting in one bud rapidly dominating the other (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">Crawford <italic>et al</italic>., 2010</xref>). Hence analysing the effect of strigolactone at the scale of 2-rather than 1-node explants casts strigolactone as systemically tuning the level of bud-bud competition rather than simply inhibiting bud activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">Crawford <italic>et al</italic>., 2010</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R60">Shinohara <italic>et al</italic>., 2013</xref>). The RGI in <italic>brc1brc2</italic> is also increased by strigolactone, though to a lesser extent than in wild-type (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R59">Seale <italic>et al</italic>., 2017</xref>).</p><p id="P57">Combining <italic>brc1brc2</italic> with the <italic>smxl678</italic> constitutive strigolactone response mutant further elucidated the interplay between the two hubs in the strigolactone-mediated regulation of bud-bud competition (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig 2</xref>). In 1-node explants, <italic>smxl678</italic> buds are inhibited, while <italic>brc1brc2</italic> and <italic>brc1brc2smxl678</italic> buds have the same rapid bud activation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig 2B</xref>). However, <italic>brc1brc2</italic> and <italic>brc1brc2smxl678</italic> do not exhibit the same phenotype in 2-node explants, the level of bud-bud competition is higher in <italic>brc1brc2smxl678</italic> than <italic>brc1brc2</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig 2D, E</xref>). These observations can be explained within a canalisation-based model, where high PIN1 removal in <italic>smxl678</italic> and <italic>brc1brc2smxl678</italic> makes canalisation harder to establish (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R65">Soundappan <italic>et al</italic>., 2015</xref>). Bud activation may be possible despite high PIN1 removal only in more permissive contexts, as seen in 1-node explants of <italic>brc1brc2smxl678</italic> but not <italic>smxl678</italic>. In 2-node explants, high bud-bud competition in <italic>brc1brc2smxl678</italic> may emerge from a combination of low <italic>BRC1</italic> expression, creating a locally permissive environment in each bud, combined with a systemic canalisation-inhibitory environment from high PIN1 removal.</p><p id="P58">Taken together, the suite of assays, metrics, mutants and treatments presented above provide a powerful toolkit to understand the properties of the bud regulatory network, and to explore the relationship between systemic and local regulation, and the two known bud regulatory hubs.</p></sec><sec id="S14"><title>Computational models for understanding bud regulation</title><p id="P59">In addition to experimental work, computational modelling has been key to providing evidence that the proposed regulatory architecture is capable of delivering the wide range of behaviours and properties we observe. In particular, our previous model has demonstrated that many non-intuitive bud growth phenomena can be explained under the auxin transport canalisation-based model for bud activation, with strigolactone influencing PIN1 removal from the plasma membrane (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R49">Prusinkiewciz <italic>et al</italic>., 2009</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R60">Shinohara <italic>et al</italic>., 2013</xref>).</p><p id="P60">Here we describe an extension of this previous work. We incorporate the key features of the auxin transport canalisation-based model for bud activation into a simplified model representing the 2-node branching assay (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig 3</xref>). The model includes two new features based on the advances in our understanding of bud growth dynamics outlined above. First, we explicitly model bud growth rate, expressing it as a function of bud auxin export. Second, we model BRC1 as affecting background levels of auxin efflux. This latter hypothesis was motivated by the characteristic short lag phase for bud activation observed in <italic>brc1brc2</italic> mutant backgrounds, suggesting rapid auxin transport canalisation, along with the ability of the <italic>abcb19</italic> mutant to suppress many of the bud growth phenotypes of <italic>brc1brc2</italic> mutants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R51">van Rongen <italic>et al</italic>., 2019</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43">Nahas <italic>et al</italic>., 2024</xref>). The ABCB19 auxin efflux carrier is plausibly a major contributor to background levels of auxin efflux.</p><p id="P61">Using this simple model, with strigolactone acting through both PIN1 removal and BRC1-mediated reduction in basal levels of auxin efflux, we simulate a wide range of 2-node assay experimental results. We compare these simulations to empirical results for cognate mutant backgrounds and treatments. We focus on dissecting the dual activity of strigolactone using <italic>brc1brc2</italic> mutants and a PIN1 variant that has compromised strigolactone response.</p></sec><sec id="S15"><title>Two biologically relevant model parameters capture multiple properties of bud behaviour</title><p id="P62">Based on the above reasoning, we model <italic>BRC1</italic> as influencing basal auxin efflux via <italic>v0</italic>, and PIN1 removal as <italic>μ</italic>. Tuning these parameters to match the effects of a range of relevant loss of function mutations and strigolactone treatments successfully captures much of the cognate variation in bud behaviour in 2-node assays, including effects on the number of lag days, MGR, and growth outcomes.</p><p id="P63">For example, at high <italic>v0</italic> (low BRC1), changes in <italic>µ</italic> (PIN1 removal) modify 2-node growth outcomes without substantial effects on the number of lag days. This captures our observation that increasing PIN1 removal through strigolactone treatment or <italic>smx678</italic> mutation in a <italic>brc1brc2</italic> background leads to one bud more often dominating the other, while maintaining rapid bud activation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig 5C</xref>). Furthermore, an increase in <italic>µ</italic> creates a much greater delay in bud activation at low compared to high <italic>v0</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig 5A</xref>). The effect of one parameter therefore depends on the value of the other, matching the different impacts of <italic>smxl678</italic> mutation in <italic>brc1brc2</italic> and wild-type backgrounds.</p><p id="P64">The effectiveness of this simple model in capturing so many of the behaviours of buds on 2 node explants provides evidence that the hypotheses underlying the model are correct. In particular, the concordance between modelled and observed behaviours provides further evidence to support the canalisation-based model of bud activation, with buds competing to establish canalised auxin transport into the stem, and the lag phase corresponding to the canalisation period. Furthermore, the results support the two new hypotheses we propose here, namely that <italic>BRC1</italic> acts on the basal rate of auxin efflux and bud growth rate is influenced by the level of auxin efflux.</p></sec><sec id="S16"><title>Mechanisms of BRC1 action</title><p id="P65">If BRC1 influences the basal rate of auxin efflux, it may do so by influencing the activity of less-polar auxin transporters, which are collectively expressed more broadly than PIN1. These transporters, namely PIN3, PIN4, PIN7 (collectively PIN347) and ABCB19, are thought to be important in the early stages of canalisation, promoting auxin loading in the bud and background auxin flux between the bud and the stem. This enables the subsequent polarisation of PIN1, which drives the high-capacity, highly polar auxin transport characteristic of canalised tissue (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R45">O’Connor <italic>et al</italic>., 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">Bennett <italic>et al</italic>., 2016a</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R51">van Rongen <italic>et al</italic>., 2019</xref>). This hypothesis is consistent with the observation that BRC1 influences the length of the lag phase and not the MGR, because BRC1-mediated regulation of ABCB19/PIN347 would mainly influence the dynamics of auxin flux before PIN1 polarisation, regulating the timing of the transport switch but not the steady state levels of auxin transport, which are principally determined by PIN1.</p><p id="P66">Previous analyses of transcriptional changes downstream of BRC1 do not identify auxin transporters as BRC1 targets in Arabidopsis. BRC1-dependent regulation of PIN347/ABCB19 could occur post-transcriptionally for example via phosphoregulation. An effect could also occur via ABA. Three downstream targets of BRC1 are HD-ZIP transcription factors promoting ABA accumulation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">Gonzalez-Grandio <italic>et al</italic>., 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R70">Van Es <italic>et al</italic>., 2023</xref>), and ABA influences PIN2 accumulation in roots (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R76">Xie <italic>et al</italic>., 2021</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R75">Wu <italic>et al</italic>., 2022</xref>).</p><p id="P67">BRC1-mediated regulation of basal auxin efflux would provide a mechanism through which local environmental conditions in the bud, which influence BRC1 expression (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">González-Grandío <italic>et al</italic>., 2013</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">2017</xref>), can be integrated into the systemic canalisation-based regulation of bud activation. Buds along a stem would exhibit variation in their basal rate of efflux, enabling those in more favourable conditions to establish canalised auxin transport into the stem, while the feedbacks between auxin sink and source strengths would balance the number of active apices across the whole plant.</p></sec><sec id="S17"><title>PIN1-mediated action of strigolactone</title><p id="P68">Further tests of our model would benefit from the ability to prevent strigolactone action specifically via PINs. As a first step toward this, we identified the middle region of the PIN1 cytoplasmic hydrophilic loop as necessary and sufficient for strigolactone-mediated removal of PIN1 from the plasma membrane (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig 7</xref>). This allowed us to create SIP1, a chimeric PIN1 in which the middle L2 region of the PIN1 loop has been swapped for that of PIN3. GFP-tagged SIP1 remains on the membrane in the presence of strigolactone and in a <italic>smxl678</italic> background, confirming its strigolactone resistance at least with respect to accumulation at the plasma membrane.</p><p id="P69">It is important to note that SIP1 does not over-accumulate to the same degree as PIN1 in the strigolactone receptor mutant background <italic>d14</italic>, and it confers very low bulk auxin transport levels (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig 7</xref>). This makes the phenotypes associated with SIP1 difficult to interpret robustly. The very low auxin transport efficiency of SIP1 might impact all the phenotypes of interest independently of strigolactone-mediated PIN1 removal. For example, the whole plant phenotypes conferred by <italic>SIP1</italic> include a modest increase in branching, which contrasts to the highly branched phenotype of <italic>brc1brc2</italic>. This could indicate that strigolactone signalling via PIN1 has a relatively minor role in determining branching in whole plants. However, in the whole plant context, it is possible that the very low transport efficiency of SIP1 masks the impact of its strigolactone resistance on shoot branching. Furthermore, our analysis of SIP1, together with the residual strigolactone sensitivity of RGI and MGR in <italic>SIP1pin1brc1brc2</italic>, leaves open the possibility that strigolactone acts through additional PIN regions, or through an entirely different mechanism in addition to its PIN1 and BRC1-mediated effects, such as via sucrose (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">Bertheloot <italic>et al</italic>., 2020</xref>). Nonetheless, representing strigolactone action in our model solely via BRC1 and PIN1 removal was sufficient to capture multiple aspects of bud behaviour observed in the range of mutant and transgenic backgrounds and treatments we tested.</p><p id="P70">These results are consistent with the hydrophilic loop being a dense regulatory environment with multiple phosphorylation sites important for PIN1 activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">Bassukas <italic>et al</italic>., 2022</xref>). Further narrowing of the residues required for strigolactone-mediated PIN1 removal would allow progress not only with determining the role of strigolactone-mediated PIN1 removal in shoot branching, but also in understanding of the mechanisms of strigolactone signalling.</p><p id="P71">Despite their limitations, analysis of <italic>SIP1</italic> phenotypes helped to elucidate further the strigolactone-mediated regulation of bud activity. The observation that <italic>SIP1pin1brc1brc2</italic> was resistant to strigolactone-mediated effects on the number of lag days, places PIN1 L2 and <italic>BRC1</italic> as the two crucial regulators for the length of the lag phase. Moreover, as predicted, strigolactone increases both the number of lag days and RGI of <italic>SIP1pin1</italic>, further supporting the model.</p></sec><sec id="S18"><title>Discrepancies between model and data in <italic>smxl678</italic> backgrounds</title><p id="P72">While there is generally a close match between the model predictions and empirical results, there are also some discrepancies. These occured particularly in <italic>smxl678</italic> backgrounds. The MGR of <italic>brc1brc2smxl678</italic> and <italic>smxl678</italic>, and the number of lag days of <italic>SIP1pin1smxl678</italic>, were higher than predicted by the model; and the MGR of <italic>SIP1pin1smxl678</italic> was lower than predicted by the model. There are several explanations for this. The <italic>smxl678</italic> background may represent fully constitutive strigolactone signalling, and it is possible that the model simply does not adequately capture this extreme state. Alternatively, there may be some SMXL678-independent action of strigolactone, consistent with recent work showing D14 can be degraded independently of SMXL678 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R56">Sánchez Martín-Fontecha <italic>et al</italic>., 2024</xref>). For example, these effects may occur via trehalose-6-phosphate (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">Fichtner <italic>et al</italic>., 2020</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">2024</xref>).</p><p id="P73">The role of sugar in bud regulation may also account for the counterintuitive observation that <italic>smxl678</italic> buds grow out less often on 1-node compared to 2-node explants, despite the mutual inhibition between buds in the latter case. Sugar availability from leaves can influence bud release in pea and rose (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">Fichtner <italic>et al</italic>., 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">Bertheloot <italic>et al</italic>., 2020</xref>), and bud growth in Arabidopsis explants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">Barbier <italic>et al</italic>., 2021</xref>), such that the presence of a second leaf in 2-node explant could facilitate some degree of bud activation in <italic>smxl678</italic>.</p></sec></sec><sec id="S19" sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="P74">We propose a model that integrates <italic>BRC1</italic> and auxin transport, two previously independent hubs in shoot branching regulation. Our model captures and predicts the phenotype of plants with defects in either one or both hubs, at the level of both bud growth dynamics and bud-bud interactions. This supports the model formulation, namely that buds compete to establish canalised auxin transport into the main stem, with the competitive strength of each bud locally tuned by <italic>BRC1</italic>. This regulatory system enables both the number and location of growing branches to be coordinated across the whole shoot system. Future experimental work should continue to investigate the detailed mechanisms underlying these hypotheses. Our model also guided our inquiry into the strigolactone-mediated regulation of shoot branching, leading us to identify a region of the PIN1 hydrophilic loop key for strigolactone responsiveness, which should be studied in more detail in the future. Subsequent experimental findings obtained from these lines of research could be iteratively incorporated back into our model, to continue exploring the multi-scale regulatory logic through which plants dynamically tune their shoot architecture.</p></sec><sec id="S20" sec-type="materials | methods"><label>4</label><title>Material and Methods</title><sec id="S21"><label>4.1</label><title>Experiments</title><sec id="S22"><label>4.1.1</label><title>Plant material and growth conditions</title><p id="P75"><italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> (Arabidopsis) (L.) Heynh. Col-0 ecotype was used throughout. The following mutants have been described previously: <italic>brc1-2 brc2-1</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">Aguilar-Martínez <italic>et al</italic>., 2007</xref>), <italic>d14-1</italic> (Waters <italic>et al</italic>., 2012), <italic>smxl6-4 smxl7-3 smxl8-1, smxl6-4 smxl7-3 smxl8-1 max2-1</italic>, and <italic>smxl6-4 smxl7-3 smxl8-1 brc1-2 brc2-1</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R65">Soundappan et al., 2015</xref>).</p><p id="P76">To generate the chimeric PIN lines, <italic>SIP1</italic> and <italic>SSP3</italic>, the hydrophilic loop of PIN1 and PIN3 were split into 3 regions: L1 from residue 149 to 253, L2 from 253 to 364, and L3 from 364 to 468. The <italic>SIP1</italic> line was synthesised by generating a chimeric coding sequence (CDS), consisting of the entire PIN1 CDS with the L2 region of PIN1 substituted with that of PIN3, and GFP located in the L3 region (Xu et al., 2006). This chimeric CDS was flanked by the attL1 and attL2 sites at the 5’ and 3’ ends respectively. For the SSP3 construct, the entire <italic>PIN3</italic> coding region, including the <italic>GFP</italic> insertion, was amplified from a previously published reporter construct (Blilou et al. 2005) and cloned into pDONR221. This vector was used as a template to produce the chimeric construct. Coding sequences for the L2 region of the <italic>PIN1</italic> hydrophilic loop were amplified from a published <italic>PIN1-GFP</italic> line that was shown to be able to complement the <italic>pin1</italic> mutant (Xu et al. 2006). The L2 region of the <italic>PIN1</italic> loop, and the <italic>PIN3</italic> backbones missing the homologous L2 region, were amplified and recombined using sequence and ligation–independent cloning (SLIC) to generate the chimeric <italic>PIN3</italic> in the pDONR221 (Li and Elledge 2012). The expression of both constructs was driven by a region previously reported to complement the <italic>pin1</italic> mutant when driving <italic>PIN1</italic> expression (Heisler et al. 2005). This 3.5kb region was amplified from plasmid DNA and recombined into Gateway vector pDONR P4-P1R. To generate expression vectors, LR reactions were performed according to manufacturer’s instructions, using Gateway binary vector pH7m24GW as the destination. The resulting vectors were transformed into <italic>Agrobacterium tumefaciens</italic> and used to transform Arabidopsis thaliana via floral dip (Clough and Bent, 1998), and crossed into other mutant backgrounds to generate the homozygous mutant lines as needed.</p><p id="P77">Plants were grown on Levington F2 compost. Plants and explants were grown in Conviron growth chambers at 22°C/18°C and 16 h/8 h day/night cycles of temperature and light, respectively.</p></sec><sec id="S23"><label>4.1.3</label><title>Bud growth assays</title><p id="P78">1.5 ml lid-less Eppendorf tubes filled with liquid <italic>A. thaliana</italic> salts (ATS) media containing no sucrose (Wilson <italic>et al</italic>., 1990) were sealed with parafilm. Young Arabidopsis inflorescences were harvested, inserted into a tube and decapitated at day 0. Explants were decapitated above the lowest node and above the lowest two nodes for one and two-node explants, respectively. Bud length was measured manually. For strigolactone treatments, a stock solution of 10 mM GR24 (LeadGen Labs LLC) in 90% acetone was used at a final concentration of 5 μM. Mock solutions contained the same volume of acetone without GR24.</p></sec><sec id="S24"><label>4.1.4</label><title>qRT-PCR</title><p id="P79">Pools of at least 10 buds were harvested and immediately frozen in liquid nitrogen or dry ice. RNA was isolated using the Zymo Quick-RNA Miniprep Kit. RNA was quantified with NanoDrop One and 1 μg RNA was used for cDNA synthesis. All transcript levels were quantified relative to <italic>UBQ10</italic>. Relative transcript levels were quantified using the delta–delta-Ct method (Livak &amp; Schmittgen, 2001).</p></sec><sec id="S25"><label>4.1.5</label><title>Microscopy</title><p id="P80">Stems from 4-5 week old plants (inflorescence height of 5-10 cm) were harvested for imaging. The most basal 15mm segment was isolated and hand sectioned longitudinally with a razor blade to expose the xylem parenchyma. Bisected stem segments were immobilised with tape then immersed in water and imaged immediately, or immersed in 5µM GR24 or mock solution for 6 hours before imaging. Confocal images were captured on a Zeiss LSM 700 confocal microscope equipped with a 20x water immersion objective. Sample excitation was performed using solid-state lasers, a 488nm laser at 6.0% laser intensity, and a 639nm laser at 2.0% laser intensity. Image size was set to 1024x1024 pixels, with 4x line averaging. The pinhole was set to 1 airy unit. The fluorescence intensity at the plasma membrane was quantified using the Zeiss Zen 2012 Software. Polygons were drawn manually around the plasma membrane before calculating the mean intensity of the selected area. The signal intensity for each stem was acquired by averaging the signal from at least 5 individual cells.</p></sec><sec id="S26"><label>4.1.6</label><title>Auxin transport assays</title><p id="P81">For stem auxin transport assays, the most basal 15mm stem segment of the primary inflorescence, from plants at terminal flowering, was harvested. The apical end was placed into the well of a PCR plate with 22nM 3-H IAA and 0.005% Triton X-100. Plates were sealed and incubated in the light for 18 hours. The basal section of each stem was cut into two 2.5mm stem segments, both of which were placed in the well of a 96 well plate with 200 µL MicroScint-20 scintillation liquid (PerkinElmer). Samples were shaken for at least 4 hours at 450 RPM before scintillation counting.</p></sec><sec id="S27"><label>4.1.7</label><title>Branch quantification</title><p id="P82">Primary branching was quantified for each plant at terminal flowering, counting the number of first-order cauline and rosette branches &gt; 5 mm.</p></sec></sec><sec id="S28"><label>4.2</label><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="P83">All statistical analysis was carried out in R v.4.1.31 and RS<sc>TUDIO</sc> v.2022.02.1 + 461. Bud growth data was analysed by fitting a growth model from Tjorve &amp; Tjorve (2010) to each bud growth trace in R, as specified in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43">Nahas et al., 2024</xref>. The number of lag days and MGR is only shown for active buds (MGR &gt; 2.5mm).</p><p id="P84">For statistical testing, multi-level models were fitted to the data to account for random variation between experiments. A linear mixed model was used with either a normal distribution, or gamma distribution for non-normally distributed data. Estimated marginal means and pairwise comparisons between genotypes were adjusted using Bonferroni correction. The box for all boxplots spans the first to the third quartile range with the middle line showing the median, and the superimposed black dot showing the mean. The minimum and maximum whisker values are calculated as Q1/Q3 (first or third quartile) ± 1.5*interquartile range.</p></sec><sec id="S29"><label>4.3</label><title>Computational modelling</title><sec id="S30"><label>4.3.1</label><title>Model implementation</title><p id="P85">The formulation and derivation of the model is detailed in the model <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">appendix</xref>. The model was implemented in Julia version 1.7.2. The following packages were used: Catalyst.jl for model generation (Loman et al., 2023), DifferentialEquations.jl for numeric simulations (Rackauckas and Nie, 2017), Plots.jl for figures, ImplicitEquations.jl for nullcline calculation, HomotopyContinuation.jl (Breiding &amp; Timme 2018) and LinearAlgrebra.jl for steady state analysis. To implement stochasticity, the Catalyst modelling software was used, which automatically generates stochastic differential equations from chemical reaction network models. A noise parameter was added to scale linearly the magnitude of the noise introduced to the Chemical Langevin Equation (Loman &amp; Locke 2022).</p></sec><sec id="S31"><label>4.3.2</label><title>Simulations</title><p id="P86">Stochastic differential equations were used to simulate the auxin efflux and growth of 2-node explants. The implicit Euler-mauruana numerical method was used, as previously (Loman and Locke, 2023). We used the implementation from the StochasticDiffEq.jl package (Rackauckas and Nie, 2017).</p><p id="P87">All simulations were performed with identical starting conditions for both buds: 0.01 for E and F, and 0.1 for N and M. Simulations were run for the number of time steps indicated. Parameters remained constant during the simulations.</p></sec><sec id="S32"><label>4.3.4</label><title>Steady state analysis</title><p id="P88">The steady states of auxin efflux were obtained numerically using the HomotopyContinuation.jl package. The solutions were categorised into stable and unstable steady states using a standard method (Strogatz, 1994). The steady state analysis was performed on the equations for auxin efflux, but they are also interpreted at the level of bud growth, because, for the parameters of interest, switching from low to high efflux is necessary for bud growth. Model behaviours were categorised based on the number and value of the stable steady states (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Fig S2A</xref>). A steady state value of 0.4 was used to threshold between a steady state that corresponds to both buds activating compared to neither buds activating (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Fig S2A</xref>, behaviours 1 vs 6). In behaviours 2 and 4 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Fig S2A</xref>), both buds can reach the same steady state value, but this corresponds to an active and an inactive state, respectively. A threshold value of 0.24 was used to distinguish between these two cases.</p></sec><sec id="S33"><label>4.3.4</label><title>Colour maps</title><p id="P89">Colour maps were obtained by classifying model behaviour based on steady state analysis (Loman et al., 2025). To generate the non-stochastic colour maps (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">fig S2B</xref>), a pixel value was assigned based on the model behaviour for a combination of (<italic>v0</italic>,<italic>µ</italic>) values. The colour map was obtained by plotting the pixel value obtained for each parameter combination.</p><p id="P90">To generate the stochastic colour maps (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">figs 4B</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">S3</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8A</xref>), steady state analysis was performed for a combination of 25281 (v0,µ) values. In the mono and bistable regions (when both buds grow, only one bud grows, or neither grow), stochasticity does not influence the number of stable steady states reached in a simulation. Parameter combinations leading to only one of these three outcomes were assigned a unique colour. In the tristable and quadrastable regions, stochasticity does influence the value of the steady state reached. To represent this effect, in these regions, 100 stochastic simulations were performed for each set of parameters for 120 time steps. The pixel value was calculated based on the growth outcomes in these simulations. For example, if certain parameters lead to 70% of simulations with both buds growing and 30% with only either the top or bottom bud growing, the pixel intensity was calculated as follows: RGB(point) = 0.7 x RGB(yellow) + 0.3 x RGB(blue), where RGB(point) refers to the pixel value (i.e., colour) on the colour map representing the outcome of competition for specific parameter values. The outcome of one bud growing was defined as occurring if the length of one bud was more than three times the length of the other. The colour map was obtained by plotting the pixel value obtained for each parameter combination. In some rare occurrences, the function that calculates the stable steady state fails. In this case, the pixel was assigned the same value as that of the neighbouring pixels if these are all identical, otherwise the pixel was assigned a value equal to the mean of all neighbouring values. To visualise the boundaries between the region of parameter space with a different number of stable states, a black colour was assigned to all pixels which had more than one neighbouring pixel with a different number of stable steady states.</p></sec><sec id="S34"><label>4.3.5</label><title>Heatmaps of number of lag days and MGR</title><p id="P91">100 simulations were run for 12 time steps for 25281 combination of parameter values. We then calculate the number of lag days and MGR for each simulation where buds activated. Buds were considered active if growth rate &gt; 0.02 during the simulation. The number of lag days was calculated as the number of days before growth reaches 0.02. To categorise bud activity and obtain the MGR, we first smooth the noise from the stochastic simulation then extract the maximum value of the first derivative.</p></sec><sec id="S35"><label>4.3.6</label><title>Sensitivity analysis</title><p id="P92">For sensitivity analysis, the steady states and growth outcomes (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Fig S3</xref>) or MGR, number of lag days, and RGI (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Fig S5</xref>) were calculated from simulations with a systematic decrease or increase of 5% in all parameter values.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="SM"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1"><label>Mathematical appendix</label><media xlink:href="EMS206056-supplement-Mathematical_appendix.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" id="d29aAcFbB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD2"><label>Supplementary Figures</label><media xlink:href="EMS206056-supplement-Supplementary_Figures.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" id="d29aAcFcB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack id="S36"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank Chris Whitewoods for critical reading of the manuscript, as well as Geneviève Hines and Graeme Mitchison for valuable discussions underpinning the project. ZN, AB, FT, JD, MS, OL were supported by the Gatsby Charitable Foundation No. GAT3272C awarded to OL. KA, DCB, TL, JL were supported by Gatsby Charitable Foundation No. GAT3395/PR5 awarded to JL, with the work in JL lab also supported by BBSRC grants award no. BB/V006088/1 and BB/X020126/1.</p></ack><sec id="S37" sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p id="P93">Complete data and code will be provided.</p></sec><fn-group><fn fn-type="con" id="FN3"><p id="P94"><bold>Author contributions</bold></p><p id="P95">OL and JL supervised the project and obtained funding. ZN, KA, JL, and OL developed the concepts and designed the research. ZN performed the experiments and data analysis except confocal imaging of <italic>SIP1</italic> stems after strigolactone application (AB), RNA extraction and cDNA synthesis for qPCR (DCR), and the initial <italic>smxl678</italic> 1-node assay (MS). FT and AB generated the <italic>SSP3pin1</italic> and <italic>SIP1pin1</italic> lines, respectively. JD crossed the <italic>SIP1pin1</italic> into further mutant backgrounds and provided technical assistance. ZN, KA, TL developed the mathematical model. ZN performed simulations with input from TL. ZN, JL, OL wrote the manuscript.</p></fn><fn fn-type="conflict" id="FN4"><p id="P96"><bold>Conflict of interest</bold></p><p id="P97">The authors declare no conflict of interest.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>Bibliography</title><ref id="R1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aguilar-Martínez</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Poza-Carrión</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Cubas</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Arabidopsis BRANCHED1</italic> Acts as an Integrator of Branching Signals within Axillary Buds</article-title><source>The Plant Cell</source><year>2007</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>458</fpage><lpage>472</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1867329</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17307924</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.106.048934</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Balla</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalousek</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Reinöhl</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Friml</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Procházka</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Competitive canalization of PIN-dependent auxin flow from axillary buds controls pea bud outgrowth: Competitive canalization of auxin flow</article-title><source>The Plant Journal</source><year>2011</year><volume>65</volume><fpage>571</fpage><lpage>577</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21219506</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Balla</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Medveďová</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalousek</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Matiješčuková</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Friml</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Reinöhl</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Procházka</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Auxin flow-mediated competition between axillary buds to restore apical dominance</article-title><source>Scientific Reports</source><year>2016</year><volume>6</volume><elocation-id>35955</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5099894</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27824063</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep35955</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barbier</surname><given-names>FF</given-names></name><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Fichtner</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Weiste</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Perez-Garcia</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Caradeuc</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Le Gourrierec</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakr</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Beveridge</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>HEXOKINASE1 signalling promotes shoot branching and interacts with cytokinin and strigolactone pathways</article-title><source>New Phytologist</source><year>2021</year><volume>231</volume><fpage>1088</fpage><lpage>1104</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33909299</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barbier</surname><given-names>FF</given-names></name><name><surname>Dun</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kerr</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Chabikwa</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name><name><surname>Beveridge</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An Update on the Signals Controlling Shoot Branching</article-title><source>Trends in Plant Science</source><year>2019</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>220</fpage><lpage>236</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30797425</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barbosa</surname><given-names>ICR</given-names></name><name><surname>Hammes</surname><given-names>UZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwechheimer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Activation and Polarity Control of PIN-FORMED Auxin Transporters by Phosphorylation</article-title><source>Trends in Plant Science</source><year>2018</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>523</fpage><lpage>538</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29678589</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bassukas</surname><given-names>AEL</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwechheimer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phosphorylation control of PIN auxin transporters</article-title><source>Current Opinion in Plant Biology</source><year>2022</year><volume>65</volume><elocation-id>102146</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34974229</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hines</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>van Rongen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Waldie</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Sawchuk</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Scarpella</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Ljung</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Leyser</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Connective Auxin Transport in the Shoot Facilitates Communication between Shoot Apices</article-title><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Reed</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><source>PLOS Biology</source><year>2016a</year><volume>14</volume><elocation-id>e1002446</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4847802</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27119525</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.1002446</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Seale</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Müller</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Leyser</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Strigolactone regulates shoot development through a core signalling pathway</article-title><source>Biology Open</source><year>2016b</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>1806</fpage><lpage>1820</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5200909</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27793831</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/bio.021402</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Sieberer</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Willett</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Booker</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Luschnig</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Leyser</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Arabidopsis MAX Pathway Controls Shoot Branching by Regulating Auxin Transport</article-title><source>Current Biology</source><year>2006</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>553</fpage><lpage>563</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16546078</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bertheloot</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Barbier</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Boudon</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Perez-Garcia</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Péron</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Citerne</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Dun</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Beveridge</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Godin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakr</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sugar availability suppresses the auxin-induced strigolactone pathway to promote bud outgrowth</article-title><source>New Phytologist</source><year>2020</year><volume>225</volume><fpage>866</fpage><lpage>879</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31529696</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Booker</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sieberer</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Williamson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Willett</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Stirnberg</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Turnbull</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Srinivasan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Goddard</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Leyser</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MAX1 Encodes a Cytochrome P450 Family Member that Acts Downstream of MAX3/4 to Produce a Carotenoid-Derived Branch-Inhibiting Hormone</article-title><source>Developmental Cell</source><year>2005</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>443</fpage><lpage>449</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15737939</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Braun</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>de Saint Germain</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pillot</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Boutet-Mercey</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Dalmais</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Antoniadi</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Maia-Grondard</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Le Signor</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bouteiller</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The pea TCP transcription factor PsBRC1 acts downstream of Strigolactones to control shoot branching</article-title><source>Plant Physiology</source><year>2012</year><volume>158</volume><fpage>225</fpage><lpage>238</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3252107</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22045922</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.111.182725</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chabikwa</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name><name><surname>Brewer</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name><name><surname>Beveridge</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Initial Bud Outgrowth Occurs Independent of Auxin Flow from Out of Buds</article-title><source>Plant Physiology</source><year>2019</year><volume>179</volume><fpage>55</fpage><lpage>65</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6324225</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30404820</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.18.00519</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chatfield</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Stirnberg</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Forde</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name><name><surname>Leyser</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The hormonal regulation of axillary bud growth in Arabidopsis</article-title><source>The Plant Journal</source><year>2000</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>159</fpage><lpage>169</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11069691</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cieslak</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Owens</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Prusinkiewicz</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Computational Models of Auxin-Driven Patterning in Shoots</article-title><source>Cold Spring Harbor Perspectives in Biology</source><year>2022</year><volume>14</volume><elocation-id>a040097</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8886983</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34001531</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/cshperspect.a040097</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cieslak</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Runions</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Prusinkiewicz</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Auxin-driven patterning with unidirectional fluxes</article-title><source>Journal of Experimental Botany</source><year>2015</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>5083</fpage><lpage>5102</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4513925</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26116915</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/erv262</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crawford</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Shinohara</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Sieberer</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Williamson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>George</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Hepworth</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Müller</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Domagalska</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Leyser</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Strigolactones enhance competition between shoot branches by dampening auxin transport</article-title><source>Development</source><year>2010</year><volume>137</volume><fpage>2905</fpage><lpage>2913</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20667910</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>De Jong</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>George</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Ongaro</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Williamson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Willetts</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Ljung</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>McCulloch</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Leyser</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Auxin and Strigolactone Signaling Are Required for Modulation of Arabidopsis Shoot Branching by Nitrogen Supply</article-title><source>Plant Physiology</source><year>2014</year><volume>166</volume><fpage>384</fpage><lpage>395</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4149722</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25059707</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.114.242388</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Domagalska</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Leyser</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Signal integration in the control of shoot branching</article-title><source>Nature Reviews Molecular Cell Biology</source><year>2011</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>211</fpage><lpage>221</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21427763</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dun</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>De Saint Germain</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rameau</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Beveridge</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antagonistic Action of Strigolactone and Cytokinin in Bud Outgrowth Control</article-title><source>Plant Physiology</source><year>2012</year><volume>158</volume><fpage>487</fpage><lpage>498</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3252097</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22042819</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.111.186783</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fichtner</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Barbier</surname><given-names>FF</given-names></name><name><surname>Annunziata</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Feil</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Olas</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Mueller-Roeber</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Stitt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Beveridge</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lunn</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of trehalose 6-phosphate in shoot branching – local and non-local effects on axillary bud outgrowth in arabidopsis rosettes</article-title><source>Plant Biology</source><year>2020</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fichtner</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Barbier</surname><given-names>FF</given-names></name><name><surname>Feil</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Annunziata</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Chabikwa</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name><name><surname>Höfgen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Stitt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Beveridge</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lunn</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Trehalose 6-phosphate is involved in triggering axillary bud outgrowth in garden pea (Pisum sativum L)</article-title><source>The Plant Journal</source><year>2017</year><volume>92</volume><fpage>611</fpage><lpage>623</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28869799</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fichtner</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Humphreys</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Barbier</surname><given-names>FF</given-names></name><name><surname>Feil</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Westhoff</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Moseler</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lunn</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Beveridge</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Strigolactone signalling inhibits trehalose 6-phosphate signalling independently of BRC1 to suppress shoot branching</article-title><source>New Phytologist</source><year>2024</year><elocation-id>nph.20072</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39187924</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gälweiler</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Müller</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wisman</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Mendgen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yephremov</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Palme</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regulation of Polar Auxin Transport by AtPIN1 in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> Vascular Tissue</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1998</year><volume>282</volume><fpage>2226</fpage><lpage>2230</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9856939</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gastaldi</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Nicolas</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Muñoz-Gasca</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Cubas</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonzalez</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Lucero</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Class I TCP transcription factors TCP14 and TCP15 promote axillary branching in Arabidopsis by counteracting the action of Class II TCP BRANCHED1</article-title><source>New Phytologist</source><year>2024</year><volume>243</volume><fpage>1810</fpage><lpage>1822</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38970467</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goldsmith</surname><given-names>MHM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Polar Transport of Auxin</article-title><source>Annual Review of Plant Physiology</source><year>1977</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>439</fpage><lpage>478</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>González-Grandío</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Pajoro</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Franco-Zorrilla</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Tarancón</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Immink</surname><given-names>RGH</given-names></name><name><surname>Cubas</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Abscisic acid signaling is controlled by a <italic>BRANCHED1/HD-ZIP I</italic> cascade in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> axillary buds</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</source><year>2017</year><volume>114</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5240681</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28028241</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1613199114</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>González-Grandío</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Poza-Carrión</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Sorzano</surname><given-names>COS</given-names></name><name><surname>Cubas</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>BRANCHED1</italic> Promotes Axillary Bud Dormancy in Response to Shade in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></article-title><source>The Plant Cell</source><year>2013</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>834</fpage><lpage>850</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3634692</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23524661</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.112.108480</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiong</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>DWARF 53 acts as a repressor of strigolactone signalling in rice</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2013</year><volume>504</volume><fpage>401</fpage><lpage>405</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5802366</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24336200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature12870</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kohlen</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Charnikhova</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Bours</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Domagalska</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Beguerie</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Verstappen</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Leyser</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Bouwmeester</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruyter-Spira</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Strigolactones Are Transported through the Xylem and Play a Key Role in Shoot Architectural Response to Phosphate Deficiency in Nonarbuscular Mycorrhizal Host Arabidopsis1[C][W][OA]</article-title><source>Plant Physiology</source><year>2011</year><volume>155</volume><fpage>974</fpage><lpage>987</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3032481</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21119045</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.110.164640</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>C-J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bangerth</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Autoinhibition of indoleacetic acid transport in the shoots of two-branched pea (Pisum sativum) plants and its relationship to correlative dominance</article-title><source>Physiol Plant</source><year>1999</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ljung</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhalerao</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name><surname>Sandberg</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sites and homeostatic control of auxin biosynthesis in Arabidopsis during vegetative growth: Auxin biosynthesis and distribution in Arabidopsis</article-title><source>The Plant Journal</source><year>2001</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>465</fpage><lpage>474</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11737783</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mazur</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Benková</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Friml</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Vascular cambium regeneration and vessel formation in wounded inflorescence stems of Arabidopsis</article-title><source>Scientific Reports</source><year>2016</year><volume>6</volume><elocation-id>33754</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5030676</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27649687</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep33754</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mazur</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Gallei</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Adamowski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Robert</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name><surname>Friml</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Clathrin-mediated trafficking and PIN trafficking are required for auxin canalization and vascular tissue formation in Arabidopsis</article-title><source>Plant Science</source><year>2020</year><volume>293</volume><elocation-id>110414</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32081263</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McSteen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Leyser</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Shoot branching</article-title><source>Annual Review of Plant Biology</source><year>2005</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>353</fpage><lpage>374</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15862100</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R37"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meinhardt</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Gierer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pattern formation by local self-activation and lateral inhibition</article-title><source>BioEssays</source><year>2000</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>753</fpage><lpage>760</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10918306</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R38"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Middleton</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Farcot</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Owen</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Vernoux</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Modeling Regulatory Networks to Understand Plant Development: Small Is Beautiful</article-title><source>The Plant Cell</source><year>2012</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>3876</fpage><lpage>3891</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3517225</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23110896</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.112.101840</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R39"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mitchison</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A model for vein formation in higher plants</article-title><year>1980</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R40"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mitchison</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanke</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Sheldrake</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Brenner</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolpert</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The polar transport of auxin and vein patterns in plants</article-title><source>Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society of London B, Biological Sciences</source><year>1981</year><volume>295</volume><fpage>461</fpage><lpage>471</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R41"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transport of exogenous auxin in two-branched dwarf pea seedlings (Pisum sativum L.): Some implications for polarity and apical dominance</article-title><source>Planta</source><year>1977</year><volume>136</volume><fpage>91</fpage><lpage>96</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24420232</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R42"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of auxin efflux carriers in the reversible loss of polar auxin transport in the pea (Pisum sativum L.) stem</article-title><source>Planta</source><year>1990</year><volume>181</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24196683</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R43"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nahas</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Ticchiarelli</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Rongen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dillon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Leyser</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The activation of Arabidopsis axillary buds involves a switch from slow to rapid committed outgrowth regulated by auxin and strigolactone</article-title><source>New Phytologist</source><year>2024</year><volume>242</volume><fpage>1084</fpage><lpage>1097</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38503686</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R44"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Napoli</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruehle</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>New Mutations Affecting Meristem Growth and Potential in Petunia hybridaVilm</article-title><source>Journal of Heredity</source><year>1996</year><volume>87</volume><fpage>371</fpage><lpage>377</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R45"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>O’Connor</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Runions</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sluis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bragg</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Vogel</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Prusinkiewicz</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hake</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A Division in PIN-Mediated Auxin Patterning during Organ Initiation in Grasses</article-title><source>PLOS Computational Biology</source><year>2014</year><volume>10</volume><elocation-id>e1003447</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3907294</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24499933</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003447</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R46"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Okada</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ueda</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Komaki</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Shimura</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Requirement of the Auxin Polar Transport System in Early Stages of Arabídopsis Floral Bud Formation</article-title><source>The Plant Cell</source><year>1991</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>677</fpage><lpage>684</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC160035</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12324609</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.3.7.677</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R47"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ongaro</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Bainbridge</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Williamson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Leyser</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Interactions between Axillary Branches of Arabidopsis</article-title><source>Molecular Plant</source><year>2008</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>388</fpage><lpage>400</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19825548</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R48"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Paterlini</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Dorussen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Fichtner</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>van Rongen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Delacruz</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Vojnović</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Helariutta</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Leyser</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Callose accumulation in specific phloem cell types reduces axillary bud growth in Arabidopsis thaliana</article-title><source>New Phytologist</source><year>2021</year><volume>231</volume><fpage>516</fpage><lpage>523</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33864687</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R49"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Prusinkiewicz</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Crawford</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ljung</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ongaro</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Leyser</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Control of bud activation by an auxin transport switch</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</source><year>2009</year><volume>106</volume><fpage>17431</fpage><lpage>17436</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2751654</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19805140</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0906696106</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R50"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ravichandran</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Linh</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><name><surname>Scarpella</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The canalization hypothesis – challenges and alternatives</article-title><source>New Phytologist</source><year>2020</year><volume>227</volume><fpage>1051</fpage><lpage>1059</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32285457</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R51"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van Rongen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ticchiarelli</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Leyser</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Connective auxin transport contributes to strigolactone-mediated shoot branching control independent of the transcription factor BRC1</article-title><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Hake</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><source>PLOS Genetics</source><year>2019</year><volume>15</volume><elocation-id>e1008023</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6433298</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30865619</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1008023</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R52"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sachs</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Senescence of Inhibited Shoots of Peas and Apical Dominance</article-title><source>Annals of Botany</source><year>1966</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>447</fpage><lpage>456</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R53"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sachs</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>On the Determination of the Pattern of Vascular Tissue in Peas</article-title><source>Annals of Botany</source><year>1968</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>781</fpage><lpage>790</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R54"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sachs</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Polarity and the Induction of Organized Vascular Tissues</article-title><source>Annals of Botany</source><year>1969</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>263</fpage><lpage>275</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R55"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sachs</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>The Control of the Patterned Differentiation of Vascular Tissues</chapter-title><source>Advances in Botanical Research</source><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name><year>1981</year><fpage>151</fpage><lpage>262</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R56"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sánchez Martín-Fontecha</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Cardinale</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Bürger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Prandi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Cubas</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Novel mechanisms of strigolactone-induced DWARF14 degradation in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Foo</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><source>Journal of Experimental Botany</source><year>2024</year><volume>75</volume><fpage>7145</fpage><lpage>7159</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11630080</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39196982</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/erae365</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R57"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sauer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Balla</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Luschnig</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Wiśniewska</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Reinöhl</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Friml</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Benková</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Canalization of auxin flow by Aux/IAA-ARF-dependent feedback regulation of PIN polarity</article-title><source>Genes &amp; Development</source><year>2006</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>2902</fpage><lpage>2911</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1619939</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17043314</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gad.390806</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R58"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scarpella</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Marcos</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Friml</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Berleth</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Control of leaf vascular patterning by polar auxin transport</article-title><source>Genes &amp; Development</source><year>2006</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>1015</fpage><lpage>1027</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1472298</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16618807</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gad.1402406</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R59"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seale</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Leyser</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>BRC1</italic> expression regulates bud activation potential, but is not necessary or sufficient for bud growth inhibition in Arabidopsis</article-title><source>Development</source><year>2017</year><elocation-id>dev.145649</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5450845</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28289131</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/dev.145649</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R60"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shinohara</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Leyser</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Strigolactone Can Promote or Inhibit Shoot Branching by Triggering Rapid Depletion of the Auxin Efflux Protein PIN1 from the Plasma Membrane</article-title><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Scheres</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><source>PLoS Biology</source><year>2013</year><volume>11</volume><elocation-id>e1001474</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3558495</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23382651</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.1001474</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R61"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Snow</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Experiments on growth and inhibition</article-title><source>Royal society publishing</source><year>1931</year><volume>108</volume></element-citation></ref><ref id="R62"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Snow</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Experiments on growth and inhibition</chapter-title><source>Part III—Inhibition and growth promotion</source><publisher-name>Royal society publishing</publisher-name><year>1932</year><volume>111</volume></element-citation></ref><ref id="R63"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Snow</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>ON THE NATURE OF CORRELATIVE INHIBITION</article-title><source>New Phytologist</source><year>1937</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>283</fpage><lpage>300</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R64"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sorefan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Booker</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Haurogné</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Goussot</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bainbridge</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Foo</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Chatfield</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Beveridge</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Rameau</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title><italic>MAX4</italic> and <italic>RMS1</italic> are orthologous dioxygenase-like genes that regulate shoot branching in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> and pea</article-title><source>Genes &amp; Development</source><year>2003</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>1469</fpage><lpage>1474</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC196077</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12815068</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gad.256603</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R65"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Soundappan</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Morffy</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Stanga</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Abbas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Leyser</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>SMAX1-LIKE/D53 Family Members Enable Distinct MAX2-Dependent Responses to Strigolactones and Karrikins in Arabidopsis</article-title><source>The Plant Cell</source><year>2015</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>3143</fpage><lpage>3159</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4682302</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26546447</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.15.00562</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R66"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stirnberg</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>van De Sande</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Leyser</surname><given-names>HMO</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MAX1 and MAX2 control shoot lateral branching in Arabidopsis</article-title><source>Development (Cambridge, England)</source><year>2002</year><volume>129</volume><fpage>1131</fpage><lpage>1141</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11874909</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R67"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tomlin</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Axelrod</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biology by numbers: mathematical modelling in developmental biology</article-title><source>Nature Reviews Genetics</source><year>2007</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>331</fpage><lpage>340</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17440530</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R68"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Umehara</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanada</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Magome</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Takeda-Kamiya</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamaguchi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Contribution of Strigolactones to the Inhibition of Tiller Bud Outgrowth under Phosphate Deficiency in Rice</article-title><source>Plant and Cell Physiology</source><year>2010</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>1118</fpage><lpage>1126</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2900824</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20542891</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/pcp/pcq084</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R69"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van Berkel</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>De Boer</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Scheres</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Ten Tusscher</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Polar auxin transport: models and mechanisms</article-title><source>Development</source><year>2013</year><volume>140</volume><fpage>2253</fpage><lpage>2268</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23674599</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R70"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van Es</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name><surname>Muñoz-Gasca</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Romero-Campero</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><name><surname>González-Grandío</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>De Los Reyes</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Tarancón</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Dijk</surname><given-names>ADJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Esse</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Pascual-García</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Angenent</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A gene regulatory network critical for axillary bud dormancy directly controlled by Arabidopsis BRANCHED1</article-title><source>New Phytologist</source><year>2023</year><elocation-id>nph.19420</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38009929</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R71"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van Schijndel</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Snoek</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name><name><surname>Ten Tusscher</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Embodiment in distributed information processing: “Solid” plants versus “liquid” ant colonies</article-title><source>Quantitative Plant Biology</source><year>2022</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>e27</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10095861</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37077985</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/qpb.2022.22</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R72"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Le Moigne</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bertheloot</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Crespel</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Perez-Garcia</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Ogé</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Demotes-Mainard</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamama</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Davière</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakr</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>BRANCHED1: A Key Hub of Shoot Branching</article-title><source>Frontiers in Plant Science</source><year>2019</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>76</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6379311</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30809235</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2019.00076</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R73"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Strigolactone Signaling in Arabidopsis Regulates Shoot Development by Targeting D53-Like SMXL Repressor Proteins for Ubiquitination and Degradation</article-title><source>The Plant Cell</source><year>2015</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>3128</fpage><lpage>3142</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4682305</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26546446</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.15.00605</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R74"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kou</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Shao</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiong</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Transcriptional regulation of strigolactone signalling in Arabidopsis</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2020</year><volume>583</volume><fpage>277</fpage><lpage>281</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32528176</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R75"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Abscisic acid employs NRP-dependent PIN2 vacuolar degradation to suppress auxin-mediated primary root elongation in Arabidopsis</article-title><source>New Phytologist</source><year>2022</year><volume>233</volume><fpage>297</fpage><lpage>312</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34618941</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R76"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Essemine</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Pang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Abscisic Acid Regulates the Root Growth Trajectory by Reducing Auxin Transporter PIN2 Protein Levels in Arabidopsis thaliana</article-title><source>Frontiers in Plant Science</source><year>2021</year><volume>12</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7982918</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33763094</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2021.632676</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R77"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Nicolas</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Cubas</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The TIE1 transcriptional repressor controls shoot branching by directly repressing BRANCHED1 in Arabidopsis</article-title><source>PLOS Genetics</source><year>2018</year><volume>14</volume><elocation-id>e1007296</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5884558</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29570704</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1007296</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R78"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Finlayson</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Abscisic Acid Is a General Negative Regulator of Arabidopsis Axillary Bud Growth</article-title><source>Plant Physiology</source><year>2015</year><volume>169</volume><fpage>611</fpage><lpage>626</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4577412</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26149576</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.15.00682</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R79"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mazur</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Balla</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gallei</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalousek</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Medveďová</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Prát</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Vasileva</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Strigolactones inhibit auxin feedback on PIN-dependent auxin transport canalization</article-title><source>Nature Communications</source><year>2020</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>3508</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7360611</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32665554</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-020-17252-y</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R80"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Shabek</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Gan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>D14-SCFD3-dependent degradation of D53 regulates strigolactone signaling</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2013</year><volume>504</volume><fpage>406</fpage><lpage>410</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4096652</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24336215</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature12878</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>2-node explants capture key properties of bud regulation.</title><p>(A) A stem segment with two axillary buds illustrates two regulatory hubs controlling shoot branching (i) local expression of the transcription factor BRC1, a repressor of bud activation, and (ii) systemic regulation of the auxin transport network. A canalisation-based model of shoot branching postulates that bud activation requires the establishment of canalised auxin transport from the bud into the main stem, the dynamics of which is influenced by autocatalytic feedback in auxin flow between the bud and the stem, and the relative auxin source and sink strengths of the bud and stem, respectively. The relationship between BRC1- and auxin-transport-mediated regulation is not known. (B) Arabidopsis bud activation occurs in at least two phases: a slow-growing lag phase, then a switch to rapid outgrowth. Typical timescale 10-12 days. Modified from <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43">Nahas et al., (2024)</xref>. (C) Diagram illustrating the four possible growth outcomes for bud activation on 2-node explants, and their representation in a Mitchison plot. Mitchison plots present the length of the top bud versus that of the bottom bud over time in each explant. Explants where at least one bud grows are termed active, otherwise, they are inactive. Within active explants, there are three possible outcomes: both buds grow, or only either the top or the bottom bud activates.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS206056-f001"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Fig 2</label><caption><title>The inhibition of <italic>smxl678</italic> buds is rescued by <italic>brc1brc2</italic> in 1-node but not in 2-node explants.</title><p>(A) PIN1 removal and BRC1 expression phenotype in Col-0, <italic>brc1brc2, smxl678</italic>, and <italic>brc1brc2smxl678</italic>. (B) Bud length on 1-node explants measured daily for 10 days. Active buds (blue) are defined as those with a maximum growth rate (MGR) &gt; 2.5 mm/day, <italic>n</italic> = 41 - 72. (C) Number of lag days (number of days before growth rate &gt; 2.5mm/day) for active buds, <italic>n</italic> = 41-72 (D) Mitchison plots of top versus bottom bud lengths on 2-node explants, measured daily for 10 days. The final length of buds is shown with a blue dot, <italic>n = 33 - 67</italic>. (E) Percentage of active explants (explants with at least one active bud) from three experimental repeats (where only one percentage is indicated, it is the same across the repeats). Below, relative growth index (RGI) of active explants at day 10. The RGI is defined as the length of the longest bud divided by the total length of both buds. The orange dot indicates the mean, <italic>n</italic> = 15 - 58). Letters represent statistically significant differences for <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05 from a multi-level model of three experimental replicates with pairwise comparisons and Bonferroni correction.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS206056-f002"/></fig><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Branching behaviours of 2-node explants can be captured by a model with self-activating and mutually-inhibiting buds.</title><p>(A) and (B) Model conceptualisation and mathematical formulation. The interaction between two buds in a 2-node explant can be considered as a set of self-activating and mutually-inhibiting feedbacks on auxin efflux. Each bud promotes its own auxin efflux and inhibits efflux from the other bud. The auxin efflux E and F from the top and bottom bud, respectively, is influenced by three components (i) a basal rate of auxin efflux <italic>v0</italic> (ii) a Hill function which creates a positive feedback on auxin efflux, where <italic>v</italic> sets the maximum rate of auxin efflux, <italic>S</italic> the strength of auxin efflux, <italic>K</italic> the Hill saturation coefficient, <italic>n</italic> the degree of non-linearity of the Hill function, <italic>D</italic> the strength of the mutual inhibition between the auxin efflux of the two buds, and (iii) a linear decrease in auxin efflux, the strength of which is set by <italic>µ</italic>. E and F influence bud lengths N and M, respectively. The relationship between auxin efflux and growth rate is a Hill function, where <italic>m</italic> influences the degree of nonlinearity, and <italic>Q</italic> is the saturation coefficient. (C) Steady state growth rate as a function of the steady state of auxin efflux, for different values of <italic>Q</italic> and <italic>m</italic>. Three grey vertical lines mark three steady states of auxin efflux at 0.25, 0.5, and 0.75. (D) and (E) Three stochastic simulations illustrating the model behaviours. Each set of simulations is represented with a different colour. (F) Deterministic simulation showing the change in auxin efflux E over time for 5 different values of <italic>v0</italic>: 0.01, 0.03, 0.05, 0.07, 0.09.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS206056-f003"/></fig><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Variation in two model parameters, representing <italic>BRC1</italic> expression and PIN1 removal, captures variation in bud growth outcomes in 2-node explants for a range of genotypes and treatments.</title><p>(A) Mitchison plots with traces coloured by growth outcome (yellow-both bud active, blue-one bud active), across genotypes and treatments with known effects on <italic>BRC1</italic> expression and/or PIN1 removal. Buds were measured daily for 10 -12 days, except <italic>smxl678</italic> which was measured for 19 days due to its slow bud activation, <italic>n</italic> = 33 - 94. (B) (i) stochastic colour map showing the change in growth outcomes across one (<italic>v0, μ</italic>) slice of parameter space, made from a grid of 159 x 159 (<italic>v0, μ</italic>) parameter combinations. The values of the other parameters remain constant. Each pixel represents the bud growth outcome for a combination of (<italic>v0, µ</italic>) values. Black boundaries distinguish regions with a different number and/or value of stable steady states. In regions with two possible behaviours (both buds growing (yellow) or only one bud growing (blue) in region 2; only one bud growing or neither bud growing (red) in region 4), the pixel intensity is calculated based on the relative occurrence of each outcome, obtained from 50 stochastic simulations. (ii) First step of the data-fitting process for 2-node data from seven known lines with variations in PIN1 removal and/or <italic>BRC1</italic> expression, mapped as variations in <italic>μ</italic> and/or <italic>v0</italic>, respectively. For each genotype/treatment, there is a distribution of points in region 2 (tristable region) where the frequency of bud growth outcomes in the data matches the model. This distribution is superimposed onto the colour map from panel (i). The distribution for each genotype/treatment is plotted in a different colour, indicated next to the label for each genotype/treatment, and these colours do not relate to the ones used to categorise the bud growth outcome in (i). (iii) Superimposed dark grey horizontal and vertical bars were positioned based on experimental evidence for <italic>BRC1</italic> expression and PIN1 removal in each genetic background/treatment, which constrained the position of each genotype/treatment in parameter space. A coloured dot was placed at the intersection of these parameter-constraining bars to assign parameters to each mutant/treatment. (iv) Same colour map as in panel (i), now with these locations of the genotypes and treatments of interest across the (<italic>v0, μ</italic>) slice. (C) Simulated Mitchison plots of genotypes and treatments with variation in <italic>v0</italic> and <italic>µ</italic>, the values of which were assigned in panel B, <italic>n</italic> = 50. Traces are coloured according to their growth outcome. Simulations were run for 120 time steps for <italic>smxl678</italic> parameters and 80 for the others.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS206056-f004"/></fig><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>Variation in two model parameters, representing <italic>BRC1</italic> expression and PIN1 removal, captures variation in the duration of the bud activation lag phase on 2-node explants for a range of genotypes and treatments.</title><p>(A) Heatmap of the number of lag time steps for 25281 combinations of parameters <italic>v0</italic> and <italic>μ</italic> (159 x 159 grid). The pixel colour intensity reflects the mean number of lag days from 50 simulations run for 120 time steps. The genotypes/treatments are assigned the same parameter values as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">figure 4B(iii and iv)</xref>. (B) Boxplot of the simulated number of lag time steps calculated for each of the genotypes indicated in panel A. The number of lag times steps was calculated from 100 simulations run for 120 time steps. (C) Number of lag days calculated as the number of days before growth rate &gt; 2.5mm/day for the same dataset as <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">fig 4A</xref>. In the left hand plot, buds were measured for 12 days, except <italic>smxl678</italic> which was measured for 19 days. In the right hand plot, all buds were measured for 10 days, <italic>n</italic> = 12 - 72. Below, the percentage of active explants, defined at least one active bud, <italic>n</italic> = 43 - 74. The series of genotypes/treatment with a gradual increase in BRC1/<italic>v0</italic> and PIN1 removal/<italic>µ</italic> are shown in light blue. Data and simulations are shown for the longest bud of active explants. Letters represent statistically significant differences for <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05 from a multi-level model with pairwise comparisons and Bonferroni correction.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS206056-f005"/></fig><fig id="F6" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title>Variation in two model parameters, representing <italic>BRC1</italic> expression and PIN1 removal, captures variation in the maximum growth rate (MGR) of buds on 2-node explants for a range of genotypes and treatments.</title><p>(A) Heatmap of the MGR for 25281 combinations of parameters v0 and μ (159 x 159 grid). The pixel colour intensity reflects the mean MGR from 50 simulations run over 120 time steps. The genotypes/treatments are assigned the same parameter values as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">figure 4B(iii and iv)</xref>.(B) Simulated MGR for each of the genotypes indicated in panel A. The MGR was calculated from 100 simulations run for 120 time steps. (C) MGR calculated from the same dataset as <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">figure 4A</xref>. In the left hand plot, buds were measured for 12 days, except <italic>smxl678</italic> which was measured for 19 days. In the right hand plot, all buds were measured for 10 days, <italic>n</italic> = 12 - 72. The series of genotypes/treatment with a gradual increase in BRC1/v0 and PIN1 removal/µ are shown in light blue. Data and simulations are shown for the longest bud of active explants. Letters represent statistically significant differences for <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05 from a multi-level model with pairwise comparisons and Bonferroni correction.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS206056-f006"/></fig><fig id="F7" position="float"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><title>The middle region of the PIN1 hydrophilic loop confers strigolactone sensitivity.</title><p>(A) Fluorescence intensity of basal plasma membranes of xylem parenchyma cells of stems expressing GFP-tagged PIN variants after 6h mock treatment or treatment with 5µM GR24. For each stem, the mean fluorescence intensity represents the mean of the 5 brightest membranes for that stem, <italic>n</italic> = 14-24. Statistical comparisons were performed using multi-level ANOVA on log-transformed data. (B) Fluorescence intensity of basal plasma membranes of xylem parenchyma cells for stems expressing GFP-tagged PIN variants of each genotype. For each stem, the mean fluorescence intensity represents the mean of the 5 brightest membranes for that stem, <italic>n</italic> = 28-37. (C) Representative images for dataset presented in panel B. PIN1:GFP visible in green and chlorophyll autofluorescence in magenta. (D) Bulk stem auxin transport in basal inflorescence stem internodes of plants at terminal flowering for the genotypes indicated. Transport was determined as accumulation of radiolabeled auxin in the basal 5mm of 15mm stem segments after 16 hours incubation with apical 22nM 3H-IAA, <italic>n</italic> = 56-68. (E) Relative expression of <italic>BRC1</italic> as measured by qRT-PCR in Col-0, <italic>SIP1pin1, smxl678 and SIP1pin1smxl678</italic> in small buds (&gt;2.5mm, presumed inactive) and big buds (&lt; 5mm, presumed active). Buds were harvested from cauline nodes of whole Arabidopsis plants. Each point represents a biological replicate, with the larger point, with bars, representing the mean and associated standard error. Each biological replicate corresponds to the expression level measured in at least 10 pooled buds. Statistical comparisons were made on the log transformed data, using two-way ANOVA with Bonferroni correction. In all panels, different letters indicate statistically significant differences at <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05. Unless otherwise stated, statistical analysis involved a multilevel model with Bonferroni corrections.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS206056-f007"/></fig><fig id="F8" position="float"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><title>Model predictions for <italic>SIPpin1</italic> bud growth outcomes largely match experimental data.</title><p>(A) Stochastic colour map of the bud growth outcomes for the (<italic>v0, µ</italic>) slice used previously (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig 4</xref>), with parameter values for genotypes and treatments in black (as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig 5A</xref>); and (<italic>v0, µ</italic>) slice at a 20% lower value of the parameter <italic>S</italic>, to account for the lower bulk auxin transport in <italic>SIP1pin1</italic> lines, with the predicted location in parameter space of each <italic>SIP1</italic> line shown with a green dot. (B) Mitchison plots of predicted (top) and (C) empirical (bottom) bud growth phenotypes. Predictions show 50 stochastic simulations per genotype/treatment run for 80 time steps, except those of <italic>smxl678</italic> run for 120 time steps. For the experimental data, <italic>SIP1pin1smxl678</italic> buds were measured for 19 days and the other genotypes were measured for 12 days. (D) Predicted and (E) empirical RGI for the genotypes/treatments indicated. Data and simulations of Col-0, Col-0 +GR24, and <italic>smxl678</italic> are the same as those from <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">fig 4A and C</xref>. The RGI is obtained by calculating the length of the longest bud divided by the combined length of both buds, and is shown only for active explants (those with at least one active bud), <italic>n =</italic> 50 for predictions and 12-80 for experimental data. Letters indicate statistically significant differences at <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05 obtained from multi-level model with Bonferroni corrections.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS206056-f008"/></fig><fig id="F9" position="float"><label>Figure 9</label><caption><title>Model predictions for <italic>SIPpin1</italic> bud activation dynamics largely match experimental data.</title><p>(A) and (D) Heatmaps of the number of lag days and MGR from the (<italic>v0, µ</italic>) slice used previously (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig 4</xref>), with parameter values for genotypes and treatments in black (as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig 5A</xref>) (left); and (<italic>v0, µ</italic>) slice at a 20% lower value of parameter S to account for the lower bulk auxin transport in <italic>SIP1pin1</italic> lines, with the predicted parameter values for <italic>SIP1pin1</italic> lines shown in green. Heatmaps are obtained by calculating the number of lag time steps or MGR for 25281 combinations of parameters <italic>v0</italic> and <italic>μ</italic> (159 x 159 grid). (B) and (E) Predictions for the lag time steps and MGR for genotypes and treatments using the parameter values in A and D, each obtained from 100 simulations run for 120 time steps. (C) and (F) Experimentally determined number of lag days and MGR calculated from 2-node explants in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">fig 8B</xref>, where bud length was measured over 12 days, or 19 days for <italic>smxl678</italic> and <italic>SIP1pin1smxl678, n</italic> = 12 - 80. The percentage of active explants is calculated as the percentage of explants with at least one active bud, <italic>n</italic> = 43 - 96. Letters indicate statistically significant differences at <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05 obtained from multi-level models with Bonferroni corrections.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS206056-f009"/></fig></floats-group></article>