<!DOCTYPE article
 PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" article-type="preprint"><?all-math-mml yes?><?use-mml?><?origin ukpmcpa?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">bioRxiv</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>bioRxiv : the preprint server for biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2692-8205</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">EMS207393</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2025.07.16.665091</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="archive">PPR1052418</article-id><article-version-alternatives><article-version article-version-type="status">preprint</article-version><article-version article-version-type="number">1</article-version></article-version-alternatives><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Subcellular proteomics of <italic>Paradiplonema papillatum</italic> reveals digestive capacity of the cell membrane and the plasticity of peroxisomes across euglenozoans</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hammond</surname><given-names>Michael</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CR1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Iorillo</surname><given-names>Orsola</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Faktorová</surname><given-names>Drahomíra</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Svobodová</surname><given-names>Michaela</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Akiyoshi</surname><given-names>Bungo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Licknack</surname><given-names>Tim</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Poh</surname><given-names>Yu-Ping</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lukeš</surname><given-names>Julius</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wideman</surname><given-names>Jeremy G.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CR1">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Institute of Parasitology, Biology Centre, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/053avzc18</institution-id><institution>Czech Academy of Sciences</institution></institution-wrap>, <city>České Budějovce (Budweis)</city>, <country country="CZ">Czech Republic</country></aff><aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Faculty of Science, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/033n3pw66</institution-id><institution>University of South Bohemia</institution></institution-wrap>, <city>České Budějovce (Budweis)</city>, <country country="CZ">Czech Republic</country></aff><aff id="A3"><label>3</label>Center for Mechanisms of Evolution, Biodesign Institute, School of Life Sciences, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/03efmqc40</institution-id><institution>Arizona State University</institution></institution-wrap>, <city>Tempe</city>, <state>Arizona</state>, <country country="US">USA</country></aff><aff id="A4"><label>4</label>Institute of Cell Biology, School of Biological Sciences, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/01nrxwf90</institution-id><institution>University of Edinburgh</institution></institution-wrap>, <city>Edinburgh</city>, <country country="GB">UK</country></aff><author-notes><corresp id="CR1">
<label>*</label>Corresponding authors</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted"><day>22</day><month>07</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="preprint"><day>20</day><month>07</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><permissions><ali:free_to_read/><license><ali:license_ref>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is licensed under a <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0 International license</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p id="P1">Diplonemids are among the most diverse and abundant protists in the deep ocean, have extremely complex and ancient cellular systems, and exhibit unique metabolic capacities. Despite this, we know very little about this major group of eukaryotes. To establish a model organism for comprehensive investigation, we performed subcellular proteomics on <italic>Paradiplonema papillatum</italic> and localized 4,870 proteins to 22 cellular compartments. We additionally confirmed the predicted location of several proteins by epitope tagging and fluorescence microscopy. To probe the metabolic capacities of <italic>P. papillatum</italic>, we explored the proteins predicted to the cell membrane compartment in our subcellular proteomics dataset. Our data revealed an accumulation of many carbohydrate active enzymes (CAZymes). Our predictions suggest that these CAZymes are exposed to extracellular space, supporting proposals that diplonemids may specialize in breaking down carbohydrates in plant and algal cell walls. Further exploration of carbohydrate metabolism revealed an evolutionary divergence in the function of glycosomes (modified peroxisomes) in diplonemids versus kinetoplastids. Our subcellular proteome provides a resource for future investigations into the unique cell biology of diplonemids.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Diplonemids</kwd><kwd>subcellular proteomics</kwd><kwd>cell membrane</kwd><kwd>metabolism,</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="S1" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p id="P2">Diplonemids are unicellular, heterotrophic eukaryotes, which constitute one of the most abundant and species-rich protist groups within the world’s oceans (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">Flegontova, et al. 2016</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">Gawryluk, et al. 2016</xref>). In addition, recent investigations show a comprehensive distribution of diplonemids in freshwater environments (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31">Mukherjee, et al. 2020</xref>), as well as in all pelagic zones of the ocean (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33">Obiol, et al. 2020</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">Lax, et al. 2024</xref>). Global metabarcoding estimates &gt; 67,000 species of diplonemids worldwide, and therefore, they are presumed to be key ecological players in all marine ecosystems (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42">Tashyreva, et al. 2022</xref>).</p><p id="P3">Despite their importance, our knowledge of diplonemid nutrition strategies, ecological roles as well as their molecular and cellular biology remains limited. Beyond general heterotrophy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38">Prokopchuk, et al. 2022</xref>), investigating their lifestyles and specific feeding modes remains challenging, partly due to the difficulty in observing diplonemid behavior in nature. By contrast, the relative ease by which diplonemids can be established in stable axenic cultures (typically in protein-rich media) is promising, and makes them amenable to an expanding range of genomic, transcriptomic and proteomic experiments (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R50">Škodová-Sveráková, et al. 2021</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R48">Valach, Moreira, et al. 2023</xref>). Such techniques are necessary to further characterize diplonemids’ cellular and ecological functions.</p><p id="P4">A high-quality nuclear genome is available for the diplonemid <italic>Paradiplonema papillatum</italic> (formerly <italic>Diplonema</italic>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R48">Valach, Moreira, et al. 2023</xref>), with two recent assemblies now available for <italic>Diplonema japonicum</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41">Tashyreva, Faktorová, Stříbrná, et al. 2025</xref>) and <italic>Rhynchopus euleeides</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40">Tashyreva, Faktorová, Horák, et al. 2025</xref>), in addition to several previously existing transcriptomes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42">Tashyreva, et al. 2022</xref>). However, <italic>P. papillatum</italic> remains the only genetically tractable diplonemid, enabling functional investigations by gene deletion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">Faktorová, Kaur, et al. 2020</xref>), endogenous tagging of proteins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">Akiyoshi, et al. 2025</xref>), and immunoprecipitation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R46">Valach, Benz, et al. 2023</xref>). Such tractability has allowed the investigation of <italic>P. papillatum</italic> respiratory complexes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R47">Valach, et al. 2018</xref>), mitochondrial ribosomes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R46">Valach, Benz, et al. 2023</xref>), and kinetochores (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">Benz, et al. 2024</xref>). Diplonemids retain many genes that can be traced to the last eukaryotic common ancestor (LECA), including rare, restricted homologs referred to as jotnarlogs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R49">Záhonová, et al. 2025</xref>). Thus, diplonemids may prove particularly informative for understanding the complexities of the ancestral eukaryote (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39">Richards, et al. 2024</xref>).</p><p id="P5">Among the many protein-coding genes predicted from its genome, an unexpected finding in <italic>P. papillatum</italic> was the identification of several hundred carbohydrate active enzymes (CAZymes), with the capacity to digest pectin, cellulose, and β-1,3 glycans among other carbohydrates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R48">Valach, Moreira, et al. 2023</xref>). This expanded CAZyme repertoire is particularly prominent compared to their relatives, Euglenida and Kinetoplastea (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R48">Valach, Moreira, et al. 2023</xref>). Such presence implies a proclivity of <italic>P. papillatum</italic> (and potentially other diplonemids) towards digestion of cell wall components of plants and algae. However, it is unclear how these organisms can specifically digest the cell walls of photosynthetic eukaryotes. Osmotrophy has been proposed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38">Prokopchuk, et al. 2022</xref>), through secreting enzymes to their exterior, as well as phagotrophy, internally ingesting components of their prey. Though <italic>P. papillatum</italic> is a tractable species, tagging and visualizing hundreds of CAZymes to determine their localization is unrealistic. We therefore sought to perform subcellular proteomics to localize CAZymes to various intracellular compartments.</p><p id="P6">Here, we use a subcellular proteomics workflow similar to localization of organelle proteins by isotope tagging <italic>via</italic> differential ultracentrifugation (LOPIT-DC) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">Geladaki, et al. 2019</xref>), to produce the first subcellular proteome of a diplonemid. With our data, we classified 4,870 proteins to 22 cellular compartments in <italic>P. papillatum</italic>. We validated several predicted locations by epitope and fluorescent tagging. Our subcellular proteome provided a clearly resolved cluster of cell membrane proteins enriched with secreted CAZymes. We suggest these enzymes can actively degrade plant and algal cell walls, initially at the cell’s exterior. We also show an ability for internal carbohydrate processing with various secreted CAZymes distributed to the lysosomal compartments, and expand on traditional carbohydrate metabolism across glycosomes and the cytoplasm, demonstrating their diverged compartmentalization from their sister clade Kinetoplastea (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35">Opperdoes and Michels 1993</xref>). Finally, we reveal an extensive mitochondrial capacity for varied amino acid digestion, foregrounding the metabolic versatility of this model diplonemid. Our localization of thousands of <italic>P. papillatum</italic> proteins provides a repository of information that will extend our knowledge of diplonemids, facilitating an exploration of their unusual cell biology and function.</p></sec><sec id="S2" sec-type="results | discussion"><title>Results and Discussion</title><sec id="S3"><title>Subcellular proteomics allows predictive clustering of <italic>P. papillatum</italic> proteins into 22 distinct compartments</title><p id="P7">To obtain a subcellular map of <italic>P. papillatum</italic>, we used a modified workflow adapted from a LOPIT-DC protocol described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">Geladaki, et al. 2019</xref>). Briefly, cells were grown axenically in ‘Diplo’ media (sea water supplemented with 10% Fetal Bovine Serum and 1 g tryptone). Approximately 9.9 x 10<sup>8</sup> cells per sample were collected and lysed in detergent-free lysis buffer in a nitrogen cavitator (250 psi for 10 min). Cell lysates underwent differential centrifugation resulting in 11 distinct fractions, including initial unlysed cells. We used western blot analysis using antibodies against ATP synthase subunit β from <italic>Trypanosoma brucei</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R51">Šubrtová, et al. 2015</xref>), mammalian Grp75 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">Joseph, et al. 2013</xref>) and Grp78 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">Chou, et al. 2020</xref>) to ensure fractional proteomic profiles were distinct (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Suppl. Fig. 1</xref>).</p><p id="P8">Label-free quantification (LFQ) analysis was followed by peptide data analysis in ProteomeDiscoverer (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36">Orsburn 2021</xref>) and with R, primarily <italic>via</italic> the pRoloc package (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">Breckels, et al. 2016</xref>). Data was quantified against the nuclear and mitochondrial genomes of <italic>P. papillatum</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R48">Valach, Moreira, et al. 2023</xref>). After quality control, 4,870 unique proteins were detected in this dataset. Following normalization, proteins lacking peptide coverage in all fractions underwent and imputation <italic>via</italic> ‘neighbor averaging’ (1,285 proteins) as well as ‘zero’ methods (2,073 proteins).</p><p id="P9">To predict cellular localization for the <italic>P. papillatum</italic> subcellular proteome, we manually curated a set of 368 proteins constituting markers with canonical localizations (e.g. mitochondrion, flagellum, cytosol), specific functions (e.g. membrane trafficking compartments) or those with inferred localization data, corresponding to a total of 22 distinct subcellular compartments or protein complexes (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table S1</xref>). Using a median svm cutoff (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table S2</xref>), we predicted sub-localization of 2,435 proteins (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1A,B</xref>), with the remainder additionally classified to these compartments with lower confidence (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table S3</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Suppl. Fig. 2</xref>). To further corroborate our designated clusters, we mapped predicted target signals and protein features onto the t-SNE distributions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1C</xref>). Mitochondrial target peptides (mTP, predicted <italic>via</italic> TargetP2.0) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">Armenteros, et al. 2019</xref>) are abundant across the three mitochondrial clusters—matrix, protein complexes and membrane-enriched. Signal peptides, predicted <italic>via</italic> SignalP6.0 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R45">Teufel, et al. 2022</xref>) show enrichment across soluble lysosome, cell membrane, endoplasmic reticulum (ER)/Golgi clusters, as well as endocytic and multivesicular membrane trafficking compartments. Finally, transmembrane domains (TMD), predicted via DeepTMHMM (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">Hallgren, et al. 2022</xref>) correlate to the various membrane-enriched clusters of the diplonemid cell.</p><p id="P10">Next, we highlighted proteins that exhibit differences in abundance when <italic>P. papillatum</italic> was grown in different media: ‘Diplo’ versus ‘Hemi’ media (sea water supplemented with 10 ml inactivated horse serum and 1 ml/L LB medium), and oxygen abundant <italic>versus</italic> depleted conditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1D</xref>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R50">Škodová-Sveráková, et al. 2021</xref>). Cells grown in nutrient-rich ‘Diplo’ medium show enrichment for proteins predicted to the cytosolic ribosome and cell membrane clusters, including sodium/potassium exchangers and sterol transporters. The nutrient-poorer ‘Hemi’ medium showed notable enrichment across multiple clusters, including the proteasome, cytosol, soluble lysosome and mitochondrial regions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1D</xref>). Equally, aerobic conditions resulted in the enrichment of several hypothetical cell membrane components, subunits of mitochondrial complex IV, as well as various soluble lysosomal proteases. By contrast, anaerobic conditions induced enrichment across clusters of the cytosol, cytosolic ribosomes, mitochondrial matrix, and translation initiation factors 2 and 3 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1D</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S4"><title>Endogenous tagging confirms subcellular localizations inferred from proteomic data</title><p id="P11">To validate designated clusters, we successfully performed endogenous tagging with either V5 or YFP epitopes on 12 proteins predicted or classified to various cell compartments, which typically lack both annotation and homologs outside diplonemids (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>). Such proteins were ultimately located to the flagella (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2A</xref>), cytoplasm (B,C), mitochondrion (D,E), ER/Golgi (F), nucleus (G,H,I), nucleolus (J), endocytic membrane trafficking (K) and, finally, the cell membrane (L), encompassing nine defined clusters in total (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table S4</xref>).</p><p id="P12">Mitochondrial proteins DIPPA_24150 and DIPPA_15120 co-localize with the organellar DNA within this reticulated mitochondrion (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Suppl. Fig. 3</xref>) at the cell periphery (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs. 2D and E</xref>). In turn, the tagged ER/Golgi candidate DIPPA_04811 shows a signal surrounding the nuclear DNA, while also branching and extending into the cell posterior (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2F</xref>). Next, we validated four proteins assigned to the nucleus, which show different sub-localizations by immunofluorescence analysis (IFA) within this compartment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs. 2G-J</xref>). The first nuclear candidate (DIPPA_16310) has a patchy distribution on the outermost periphery of the nuclear DNA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2G</xref>). Unlike the novel ER/Golgi protein (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2F</xref>), this candidate does not extend beyond the nucleus, and hence, likely constitutes a novel nuclear membrane component. A second nuclear candidate (DIPPA_32825) co-localizes with the chromatin signal of the nucleus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2H</xref>), similar to the general nuclear signal of a third selected nuclear protein (DIPPA_24937) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2I</xref>). The last nuclear candidate (DIPPA_00315) displays a confined distribution within the nucleus, corresponding to the nucleolus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2J</xref>). Similarly, this protein’s uncharacterized homolog within the kinetoplastid <italic>T. brucei</italic> (Tb927.3.2750) also displays a nucleolus-like signal when tagged <italic>via</italic> green fluorescent protein (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">Billington, et al. 2023</xref>).</p><p id="P13">One protein (DIPPA_21158) classified to the ‘endocytic membrane trafficking’ compartment, seemingly exhibits dual localization, with an ER-like pattern similar to DIPPA_04811 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2F</xref>), while also showing enrichment towards and encompassing the cell cytopharynx (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2K</xref>). Finally, a protein predicted to the cell membrane cluster (DIPPA_16504) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>), shows a signal enriched across the cell outline, excepting the apical papilla (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2L</xref>). This protein possesses a signal peptide and a TMD, both of which are enriched for proteins predicted to the cell membrane (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1C</xref>). This cell membrane cluster also exhibits an accumulation of predicted signal peptides in tandem with glycosylphosphatidylinositol (GPI)-attachment domains (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Suppl. Fig. 4</xref>), further supporting the validity of this newly defined cluster.</p></sec><sec id="S5"><title>Secreted CAZymes localize to the cell membrane and lysosomes</title><p id="P14">Carbohydrate-Active Enzymes (CAZymes) are particularly abundant in <italic>P. papillatum</italic>, suggesting complex digestive capabilities against plant and algal cell wall carbohydrates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R48">Valach, Moreira, et al. 2023</xref>). Through our subcellular dataset, we show a notable proportion of CAZymes enriched with signal peptides localized with high confidence to the cell membrane and the lysosome (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>). Schematic diagrams of these cell membrane CAZymes show the presence of a C-terminal TMD and/or GPI anchor sites, preceded by the catalytic domains of associated enzymes. This topology indicates that the CAZyme domains are exposed to extracellular space and thus expected to digest external carbohydrate substrates (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3A</xref>). Enzymatic domains present include pectin esterase, pectin lyase and glycosyl hydrolases, from which we construct a digestion pathway on the cell membrane to externally degrade methylated pectin to galacturonic acid monomers (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3A</xref>). Some CAZymes of the cell membrane lack the predicted TMDs or GPI anchors, such as glycosyl hydrolase, which degrades hemicellulose to glucose, xylose and galactose. It remains a possibility that such CAZymes are released into the extracellular space or simply lack identifiable motifs for cell anchorage.</p><p id="P15">Candidate sugar transporters, recently identified through genome analysis(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R48">Valach, Moreira, et al. 2023</xref>), were not localized to the cell membrane cluster, rather being assigned to the ER/Golgi and glycosome compartments (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table S3</xref>). Thus, we propose that instead of being passaged directly to the cytoplasm across the cell membrane, digested or partially digested carbohydrate substrates are engulfed through the cytopharynx, leading to trafficking through the endocytic vesicles, which have been observed prominently budding off from this distinctive structure in diplonemids (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43">Tashyreva, et al. 2023</xref>). Within the endocytic membrane trafficking cluster of this dataset, we also identified one secretory CAZyme (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3B</xref>). Endocytosed contents are typically passaged to the lysosomal compartments, for which we also define a corresponding cluster of soluble proteins containing numerous signal peptide-bearing CAZymes, with the ability to digest various forms of pectin and other polysaccharide chains, such as sucrose and glycosides (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3C</xref>). We additionally predict one sugar transporter (DIPPA_16016.mRNA.1) to the multivesicular membrane trafficking body, enriched for V-type ATPases and other membranous components of the lysosome, suggesting eventual saccharide transport from these organelles to the cytosol and possibly other compartments.</p><p id="P16">Given that these analyzed cells were grown in the protein-rich ‘Diplo’ medium, we did not necessarily expect an abundance of CAZymes in our extractions. Nonetheless, we detected a total of 94 different enzymes across our subcellular dataset, 55 of which were not recorded in previous studies (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table S5</xref>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R50">Škodová-Sveráková, et al. 2021</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R48">Valach, Moreira, et al. 2023</xref>). The proteomic presence of these enzymes in a mostly carbohydrate-depleted medium suggests that most CAZymes are permanently expressed regardless of substrate availability. We further note that in previous cultivation studies, the lysosomal CAZymes identified in this study showed conditional enrichment, while the newly identified CAZymes of the cell membrane do not change in the face of different conditions or media (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1D</xref>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R50">Škodová-Sveráková, et al. 2021</xref>). Such constitutive presence supports suggestions recently made for plants and algae being the primary food source of <italic>P. papillatum</italic> in nature, potentially making use of both carbohydrates on the external cell walls, as well as the internal proteinaceous energy sources (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R48">Valach, Moreira, et al. 2023</xref>).</p><p id="P17">The soluble lysosome contains a chitinase (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3C</xref>), while in the endocytic trafficking compartment we documented a complementary glucuromannan-digesting GH92, which combined suggests a proclivity for fungal cell wall digestion (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3B</xref>). The single observation of <italic>P. papillatum</italic> regarding its <italic>in natura</italic> behavior comes from its initial isolation from drifting eelgrass (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37">Porter 1973</xref>), a plant that is known to harbor various fungal cohabitants on its surface (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32">Newell 1981</xref>). This documented enzymatic sub-localization appears consistent with such a supposition for varied sources of prey. Interestingly, a single CAZyme member, xylan-α-glucuronidase, is predicted with high confidence to the cytosol, despite the presence of an N-terminal signal sequence. This enzyme is additionally predicted to have been acquired <italic>via</italic> horizontal gene transfer from a bacterial endosymbiont, for which diplonemids have shown a propensity for acquisition (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">George, et al. 2022</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R44">Tashyreva, Votýpka, et al. 2025</xref>), though absent from the extant <italic>P. papillatum</italic>.</p></sec><sec id="S6"><title>Subcellular distribution of glycolysis/gluconeogenesis enzymes reveals novel glycosomal insights for <italic>P. papillatum</italic></title><p id="P18">Diplonemids and their sister lineage, the mostly parasitic kinetoplastids, are categorized as glycomonads due to their shared compartmentalization of part of their glycolytic pathways in specialized peroxisomes called glycosomes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">Michels, et al. 2006</xref>), yet the extent to which these organelles retain the same function in both lineages is unclear. Kinetoplastids localize the first seven steps of glycolysis to glycosomes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35">Opperdoes and Michels 1993</xref>), while in diplonemids peroxisomal targeting signals (PTS) are predicted in six enzymatic steps suggesting a similar metabolic arrangement, although only five enzyme have been experimentally confirmed to colocalize with known peroxisomal proteins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27">Makiuchi, et al. 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">Morales, et al. 2016</xref>). Here, we use our subcellular proteomics dataset to partly confirm and expand on previous analyses (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>). As our glycosome showed fractional similarity with other organelle clusters, we only confirmed two enzymatic steps to this organelle, one of which (step III) representing a newly described designation in <italic>P. papillatum</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4A</xref>). However, we confirmed the cytosolic localization of four enzymes, glyceraldehyde 3-phosphate dehydrogenase (GADPH, step VI), phosphoglycerate mutase (PGAM, step VIII), enolase (step IX) and pyruvate kinase (Step Xa) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">Morales, et al. 2016</xref>).</p><p id="P19">Certain enzymes were not detected in previous investigations; thus, it came as a surprise that we detected in the glycosome both phosphofructokinase (PFK) and fructose 1,6-biphosphatase (FBP), which typically participate in glycolysis (IIIa) and gluconeogenesis (IIIb), respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4A</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Suppl. Fig. 5</xref>). Their localization demonstrates a capacity for this organelle to mediate both directions of this pathway (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4A</xref>). The genome of <italic>P. papillatum</italic> encodes two PFKs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">Morales, et al. 2016</xref>), with PFK1 (DIPPA_21987) being a PPi-dependent variant horizontally acquired from a bacterium (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R50">Škodová-Sveráková, et al. 2021</xref>), which is typically able to function in an ATP-poor environment. PFK1 also shows the potential to engage in gluconeogenesis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R50">Škodová-Sveráková, et al. 2021</xref>), which along with FBP further supports the capacity of <italic>P. papillatum</italic> ‘glycosomes’ to perform steps of gluconeogenesis. We further note the prediction of a TMD in PFK1, the presence of which represents an unusual feature for enzymes of this pathway (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4A</xref>), though not without precedent (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">Jirsová, et al. 2025</xref>). We propose that the N-terminal TMD allows insertion of the enzyme from within the glycosome, exposing its enzymatic domains to the organellar lumen (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Suppl. Fig. 6A</xref>). While previous transcriptome analysis recorded an additional PTS1-lacking PFK with presumable cytosolic residence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R50">Škodová-Sveráková, et al. 2021</xref>), a survey of the now complete genome confirmed only the presence of PFKs furnished with PTS (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R48">Valach, Moreira, et al. 2023</xref>).</p><p id="P20">One copy (DIPPA_70192) of fructose-biphosphate aldolase (FBA, step IV) was previously localized to the glycosomes and indeed shows a corresponding fractional pattern in our dataset (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4A</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Suppl. Fig. 5</xref>). A second FBA (DIPPA_30805), also bearing a PTS2 motif, displays a more subdued profile with less similarity to the cytosolic and glycosomal fractional profiles (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Suppl. Fig. 6B</xref>). We interpret this as co-localization in both compartments, a phenomenon described for several peroxisomal proteins across eukaryotes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">Freitag, et al. 2018</xref>). Moreover, while in ‘Hemi’ media, the PTS1-bearing copies of G6P and TIM have been localized to the glycosomes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">Morales, et al. 2016</xref>), in our dataset they occupy an ambiguous position that similarly implies a dual localization, which contrasts with their confidently placed cytosolic counterparts which lack a PTS (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4A</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Suppl. Fig. 6C,D</xref>).</p><p id="P21">We additionally localized multiple copies of PTS-lacking GADPH distributed to either the cell membrane or the mitochondrion, as described elsewhere (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">Bártulos, et al. 2018</xref>). We demonstrate a convincing cytosolic localization for four additional paralogues of enzymes lacking a PTS, namely glucose 6-phophate isomerase (G6P, step II), triosephosphate isomerase (TIM, step V), phosphoglycerate kinase (PGK, step VII) and PGAM (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4A</xref>). While such cytosolic localizations may facilitate the glycolytic processing from glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate to pyruvate, they alternatively reveal the potential for partial cytosolic gluconeogenesis initiated by processing oxaloacetate to phosphoenolpyruvate <italic>via</italic> cytosol-localized PEP carboxykinase (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4A</xref>). Along with other reversible steps of glycolysis, proteomic enrichment was reported for this enzyme from cells grown in the glucose-depleted ‘Hemi’ medium (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R50">Škodová-Sveráková, et al. 2021</xref>), reflecting an increased use of gluconeogenesis under such conditions (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table S6</xref>).</p><p id="P22">Metabolically adjacent to glycolysis and gluconeogenesis is the pentose phosphate pathway (PPP), which facilitates the interconversion of simple carbohydrates of different sizes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4B</xref>). In kinetoplastids, several PPP enzymes possess a PTS, producing a glycosomal or dual glycosomal and cytosolic localization (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">Kovárová and Barrett 2016</xref>). However, <italic>P. papillatum</italic> encodes only a single PTS1-possessing enzyme, phosphogluconolactonase (step II) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4B</xref>). Despite its targeting signal, our dataset suggests the enzyme localizes to the cytoplasm (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Suppl. Fig. 6E</xref>), demonstrating that, similar to the localizations of certain proteins in <italic>T. brucei</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">Güther, et al. 2014</xref>), the presence of a PTS does not guarantee peroxisomal targeting (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4B,C</xref>). While ribulose-5-phosphate 3-epimerase (step IV of PPP) and trans-aldolase (step VI of PPP) are classified to the soluble lysosome, considering the fractional similarity of this cluster to that of the cytosol, we regard them as cytosolic (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4A-C</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Suppl. Fig. 5</xref>). By contrast, a copy of glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase (step I of PPP) shows a fractionation profile consistent with that of the endocytic membrane trafficking cluster, which warrants future investigation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4B,C</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Suppl. Fig. 6F</xref>).</p><p id="P23">In summary, our localization of individual steps for glycolysis/gluconeogenesis supports the hypothesis that diplonemids separated from kinetoplastids prior to the complete transfer of the first seven steps of these pathways into the glycosomes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">Morales, et al. 2016</xref>), leaving step VI in the cytosol for diplonemids. Moreover, in these flagellates the cell membrane-embedded versions of GAPDH underlines compartmentalization of this enzyme distinct from that of its homologs in kinetoplastids (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">Moloney, et al. 2023</xref>). A further distinction is represented by PEP carboxykinase, which in <italic>P. papillatum</italic> remains cytosolic and lacks a PTS, with its glycosomal compartmentalization evolved in the kinetoplastid clade only secondarily. The presence of a PTS1 in just a single PPP enzyme likely signifies a remnant of the ancestral trend in glycomonads towards compartmentalization of this pathway which, unlike in kinetoplastids, did not continue to progress in diplonemids.</p></sec><sec id="S7"><title>Versatile amino acid digestive capabilities within the mitochondrion</title><p id="P24">Gluconeogenesis in <italic>P. papillatum</italic> is presumably supplied by substrates from the amino acid (AA) catabolism (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">Morales, et al. 2016</xref>), which we endeavored to resolve with our subcellular dataset. Accordingly, we show this protist’s capacity to digest a broad range of AA’s, primarily within the mitochondrion, reminiscent of similar capabilities demonstrated in the mitochondrion of its fellow euglenozoan, <italic>Euglena gracilis</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">Hammond, et al. 2020</xref>) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Suppl. Fig. 7</xref>). Ultimately, the mitochondrion of <italic>P. papillatum</italic> appears capable of metabolizing arginine, aspartate, histidine, glutamate, glycine, isoleucine, leucine, proline, serine, threonine and valine into metabolites that can directly feed into the tricarboxylic acid (TCA) cycle, as well as glutamine and cysteine with initial cytosolic processing (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Suppl. Fig. 7</xref>). We additionally reveal the ability of diplonemids to process the fatty acid propanoate to propanoyl-CoA, which allows incorporation into AA intermediate-processing pathways within the mitochondrion, representing a functional distinction from kinetoplastids (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Suppl. Fig. 7</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="S8" sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="P25">Previous work has demonstrated the global distribution, relative importance, abundance, and diversity of marine diplonemids (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42">Tashyreva, et al. 2022</xref>), underscoring the value in clarifying their ecological roles and biology. Only recently has <italic>P. papillatum</italic> emerged as a genetically tractable species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">Faktorová, Kaur, et al. 2020</xref>), opening the entire clade to inquiry <italic>via</italic> cellular and molecular methods. Our subcellular proteomics dataset is complementary to these efforts and provides a pathway towards hypothesis-driven research, thereby accelerating our understanding of these ecologically and evolutionary important protists (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R46">Valach, Benz, et al. 2023</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">Benz, et al. 2024</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">Akiyoshi, et al. 2025</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R49">Záhonová, et al. 2025</xref>). In total, our data enabled us to localize thousands of proteins to 22 distinct subcellular compartments in <italic>P. papillatum</italic>. The confidence of our data is strengthened by the endogenous tagging of selected proteins.</p><p id="P26">From this wealth of data, we focused specifically on the confidently predicted cluster of cell membrane proteins. In this cluster, we identified an expanded family of CAZymes, supporting recent predictions that <italic>P. papillatum</italic> primarily preys on plant and algae <italic>via</italic> degrading their cell walls. CAZymes were also localized to the lysosome, further suggesting active ingestion of complex carbohydrates. The fact that we supplied <italic>P. papillatum</italic> with protein-rich, carbohydrate-limited media represents an intriguing question for future analysis: why are CAZymes expressed in the absence of carbohydrates? We speculate that they are produced in anticipation of interacting with these substrates, and hope that <italic>in natura</italic> studies may now be used to definitively clarify the ecological role for this and other diplonemids.</p><p id="P27">In conclusion, we have sub-localized thousands of proteins in a model species representing a major protist group. Given the scarcity of available marine protists that are genetically tractable and can be investigated with relative ease (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">Faktorová, Nisbet, et al. 2020</xref>), our data provide a novel and rich resource to explore diplonemids’ unique cell biology and to map ancestral traits in this free-living heterotrophic flagellate.</p></sec><sec id="S9" sec-type="materials | methods"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="S10"><title>Key Resource Table</title><p id="P28"><table-wrap id="T2" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"><table frame="box" rules="all"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left">REAGENT or RESOURCE</th><th valign="top" align="left">SOURCE</th><th valign="top" align="left">IDENTIFIER</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="3">Antibodies</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">Rabbit anti-ATP Synthase-β</td><td valign="top" align="left">Zíková et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R51">Šubrtová, et al. 2015</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">Mouse anti-GRP 75</td><td valign="top" align="left">Enzo</td><td valign="top" align="left">Cat# SPS-826D, RRID:AB_2120451 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.antibodyregistry.org/AB_212_0451">https://www.antibodyregistry.org/AB_212_0451</ext-link>)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">GRP 78</td><td valign="top" align="left">Novus</td><td valign="top" align="left">Cat#NB100-56413, RRID:AB_838320 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.antibodyregistry.org/AB_838320">https://www.antibodyregistry.org/AB_838320</ext-link>)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">Goat anti-Rabbit IgG (H+L) Secondary Antibody, HRP</td><td valign="top" align="left">Invitrogen</td><td valign="top" align="left">Catalog# 31460 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.thermofisher.com/antibody/product/Goat-anti-Rabbit-IgG-H-L-Secondary-Antibody-Polyclonal/31460">https://www.thermofisher.com/antibody/product/Goat-anti-Rabbit-IgG-H-L-Secondary-Antibody-Polyclonal/31460</ext-link>)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">Goat anti-Mouse IgG (H+L) Secondary Antibody, HRP</td><td valign="top" align="left">Invitrogen</td><td valign="top" align="left">Catalog# 31430 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.thermofisher.com/antibody/product/Goat-anti-Mouse-IgG-H-L-Secondary-Antibody-Polyclonal/31430">https://www.thermofisher.com/antibody/product/Goat-anti-Mouse-IgG-H-L-Secondary-Antibody-Polyclonal/31430</ext-link>)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">Mouse anti-V5 Monoclonal Antibody (2F11F7)</td><td valign="top" align="left">Invitrogen</td><td valign="top" align="left">Catalog# 37-7500-A555, RRID:AB_2610631 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.antibodyregistry.org/AB_261">https://www.antibodyregistry.org/AB_261</ext-link>)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">Rabbit anti-V5 Polyclonal Antibody</td><td valign="top" align="left">Sigma-Aldrich</td><td valign="top" align="left">Catalog# V8137, RRID:AB_261889 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.antibodyregistry.org/AB_261889">https://www.antibodyregistry.org/AB_261889</ext-link>)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">Goat anti-Mouse IgG (H+L) Cross-Adsorbed<break/>Secondary Antibody, Alexa Fluor™ 555</td><td valign="top" align="left">Invitrogen</td><td valign="top" align="left">Catalog# A-21422 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.thermofisher.com/antibody/product/Goat-anti-Mouse-IgG-H-L-Cross-Adsorbed-Secondary-Antibody-Polyclonal/A-21422">https://www.thermofisher.com/antibody/product/Goat-anti-Mouse-IgG-H-L-Cross-Adsorbed-Secondary-Antibody-Polyclonal/A-21422</ext-link>)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">Goat anti-Rabbit IgG (H+L) Cross-Adsorbed<break/>Secondary Antibody, Alexa Fluor™ 488</td><td valign="top" align="left">Invitrogen</td><td valign="top" align="left">Catalog# A-110087 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.thermofisher.com/antibody/product/Goat-anti-Rabbit-IgG-H-L-Cross-Adsorbed-Secondary-Antibody-Polyclonal/A-11008">https://www.thermofisher.com/antibody/product/Goat-anti-Rabbit-IgG-H-L-Cross-Adsorbed-Secondary-Antibody-Polyclonal/A-11008</ext-link>)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="3">Chemicals, peptides, and recombinant proteins</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left"/><td valign="top" align="left"/><td valign="top" align="left"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left"/><td valign="top" align="left"/><td valign="top" align="left"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left"/><td valign="top" align="left"/><td valign="top" align="left"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left"/><td valign="top" align="left"/><td valign="top" align="left"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left"/><td valign="top" align="left"/><td valign="top" align="left"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="3">Critical commercial assays</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">Pierce™ Dilution-Free™ Rapid Gold BCA Protein Assay</td><td valign="top" align="left">Thermo Scientific</td><td valign="top" align="left">Catalog# A55860</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">Pierce™ Quantitative Peptide Assays &amp; Standards</td><td valign="top" align="left">Thermo Scientific</td><td valign="top" align="left">Catalog# 23290</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left"/><td valign="top" align="left"/><td valign="top" align="left"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left"/><td valign="top" align="left"/><td valign="top" align="left"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left"/><td valign="top" align="left"/><td valign="top" align="left"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="3">Deposited data</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">Raw peptide data</td><td valign="top" align="left">PRIDE</td><td valign="top" align="left">XXXX</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">For protein predictions and annotations see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table S3</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left"/><td valign="top" align="left"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left"/><td valign="top" align="left"/><td valign="top" align="left"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left"/><td valign="top" align="left"/><td valign="top" align="left"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left"/><td valign="top" align="left"/><td valign="top" align="left"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="3">Experimental models: Cell lines</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left"><italic>Paradiplonema papillatum</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left">Porter(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37">Porter 1973</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left">ATCC50162</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left"/><td valign="top" align="left"/><td valign="top" align="left"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left"/><td valign="top" align="left"/><td valign="top" align="left"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left"/><td valign="top" align="left"/><td valign="top" align="left"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left"/><td valign="top" align="left"/><td valign="top" align="left"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="3">Experimental models: Organisms/strains</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">For cell lines generated for this study see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table S4</xref></td><td valign="top" align="left"/><td valign="top" align="left"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left"/><td valign="top" align="left"/><td valign="top" align="left"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left"/><td valign="top" align="left"/><td valign="top" align="left"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left"/><td valign="top" align="left"/><td valign="top" align="left"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left"/><td valign="top" align="left"/><td valign="top" align="left"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left"/><td valign="top" align="left"/><td valign="top" align="left"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="3">Oligonucleotides</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">For primers used in this study see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Suppl. File 2</xref>.</td><td valign="top" align="left"/><td valign="top" align="left"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left"/><td valign="top" align="left"/><td valign="top" align="left"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left"/><td valign="top" align="left"/><td valign="top" align="left"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left"/><td valign="top" align="left"/><td valign="top" align="left"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left"/><td valign="top" align="left"/><td valign="top" align="left"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="3">Recombinant DNA</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">pBA3294 vector</td><td valign="top" align="left">Akiyoshi et al.(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">Akiyoshi, et al. 2025</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">pDP011 vector</td><td valign="top" align="left">Genebank</td><td valign="top" align="left">OQ547858</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left"/><td valign="top" align="left"/><td valign="top" align="left"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left"/><td valign="top" align="left"/><td valign="top" align="left"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left"/><td valign="top" align="left"/><td valign="top" align="left"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="3">Software and algorithms</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">Micosoft Excel</td><td valign="top" align="left">Microsoft</td><td valign="top" align="left"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.microsoft.com">https://www.microsoft.com</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">R and Rstudio</td><td valign="top" align="left">Rstudio</td><td valign="top" align="left"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://posit.co/download/rstudio-desktop/">https://posit.co/download/rstudio-desktop/</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">pROLOC</td><td valign="top" align="left">Crook et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">Crook, et al. 2019</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">Fiji (Image J)</td><td valign="top" align="left">Fiji</td><td valign="top" align="left"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://fiji.sc/">https://fiji.sc/</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">Signal P 6.0</td><td valign="top" align="left">Teufel et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R45">Teufel, et al. 2022</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://services.healthtech.dtu.dk/services/SignalP-6.0/">https://services.healthtech.dtu.dk/services/SignalP-6.0/</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">Target P 2.0</td><td valign="top" align="left">Armenteros et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">Armenteros, et al. 2019</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://services.healthtech.dtu.dk/services/TargetP-2.0/">https://services.healthtech.dtu.dk/services/TargetP-2.0/</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">DeepTMHMM</td><td valign="top" align="left">Hallgren et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">Hallgren, et al. 2022</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://services.healthtech.dtu.dk/services/DeepTMHMM-1.0/">https://services.healthtech.dtu.dk/services/DeepTMHMM-1.0/</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">DeepLOC 2.1</td><td valign="top" align="left">Odum et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34">Odum, et al. 2024</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://services.healthtech.dtu.dk/services/DeepLoc-2.1/">https://services.healthtech.dtu.dk/services/DeepLoc-2.1/</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">NetGPI 1.1</td><td valign="top" align="left">Gíslason et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">Gíslason, et al. 2021</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://services.healthtech.dtu.dk/services/NetGPI-1.1/">https://services.healthtech.dtu.dk/services/NetGPI-1.1/</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">Ghost KOALA</td><td valign="top" align="left">Kaneisha et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">Kanehisa, et al. 2016</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.kegg.jp/ghostkoala/">https://www.kegg.jp/ghostkoala/</ext-link></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left"/><td valign="top" align="left"/><td valign="top" align="left"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left"/><td valign="top" align="left"/><td valign="top" align="left"/></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p></sec><sec id="S11"><title>Resource availability</title><p id="P29">Further information and requests for reagents should be directed to and will be fulfilled by the lead contact, Michael Hammond (<email>michael.hammond@paru.cas.cz</email>).</p></sec><sec id="S12"><title>Materials availability</title><p id="P30">Vectors and novel cell lines generated for this study are available from lead contact upon request.</p></sec><sec id="S13"><title>Experimental model and study participant details</title><p id="P31"><bold><italic>P. papillatum</italic></bold> (ATCC50162) served as the cell line for both proteomic analysis and cell line generation.</p></sec><sec id="S14"><title>Strain, culture conditions and preparation for lysis</title><p id="P32"><italic>Paradiplonema papillatum</italic> (ATCC50162) cells were cultivated axenically in Diplo media (36 g/L sea salts [Sigma], with 1g Tryptone and 10 ml Fetal Bovine Serum [Sigma], 0.22 μm filter sterilized) at 22°C. Cell cultures were harvested in a combined volume of 750 ml per sample, harvested at ~2.5 x10<sup>6</sup> cells/ml, processed in triplicates. Cell cultures were concentrated by centrifugation (900xg for 10 min) and pellets were resuspended in 6 ml detergent free lysis buffer (0.25 M sucrose, 10 mM HEPES, pH 7.4, 2 mM EDTA, 2 mM Mg(OAc) with Halt™ Protease and Phosphatase Inhibitor Cocktail, pre-chilled to 4°C.</p></sec><sec id="S15"><title>Cell lysis and fractionation</title><p id="P33">Cell suspension underwent lysis <italic>via</italic> nitrogen cavitation at 250 psi for 10 min (Parr 4639, Parr Instrument Co.). Cell lysate was gently released from the chamber to minimize foaming, with collected sample undergoing differential centrifugation following a previously established protocol (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">Geladaki, et al. 2019</xref>). Briefly, cell lysate underwent centrifugation at speeds (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>), and the supernatant was transferred to fresh 2 ml centrifuge tubes and subjected to subsequent centrifugation steps, with pellets from previous spins stored at -80°C after collection, in addition to the supernatant fraction from final spin. Pelleted cell lysate was additionally collected and stored for proteomic analysis.</p></sec><sec id="S16"><title>Fractional assessment</title><p id="P34">To assess the distribution and enrichment of proteins across <italic>P. papillatum</italic> fractions, immunoblotting was performed using antibodies against ATP synthase subunit β (kindly provided by A. Zíková) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R51">Šubrtová, et al. 2015</xref>), Grp75 (Enzo) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">Joseph, et al. 2013</xref>)and Grp78 (Novus) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">Chou, et al. 2020</xref>). Pellets were resuspended in 2x Laemmli buffer (0.125 M Tris-HCl, pH 6.8, 4% SDS, 20% glycerol, 0.004% bromophenol blue) without DTT. Fractional samples were quantified using the Pierce™ BCA Protein Assay (Thermo Fisher Sci.).</p><p id="P35">10 μg of protein was loaded onto an SDS-PAGE gel (Invitrogen Bolt Bis-Tris Plus Mini Protein Gels, 4-12%, 1.0 mm, WedgeWell™ format) along with a protein marker (Amersham™ ECL™ Rainbow™ Marker - Full Range). The gel was run for 1 hour at 130 V, briefly washed in 1x PBS buffer, and transferred onto a methanol-activated PVDF membrane (iBlot™ 2 Transfer Stacks, PVDF, Invitrogen) using the iBlot 2 Western Blot Transfer Device (Invitrogen). The membrane was blocked in 5% non-fat dry milk and 1x PBS buffer for 1 hour at room temperature, followed by incubation with relevant antibodies diluted (1:10000 for ATP-β, and 1:1000 for Grp75 and Grp78) in blocking solution (5% non-fat dry milk in 1x PBS buffer). Blots were incubated at room temperature for 1 hour, then overnight at 4°C. The following day blots were washed three times for 10 min each in 1x PBS, probed with HRP-linked secondary antibodies (31460/31430, Invitrogen) diluted 1:1000 in blocking solution for 1 hour at room temperature, and rinsed again three times for 10 min each in 1x PBS-T. Detection was performed using the Pierce ECL Western Blotting Substrate (Thermo Fisher Sci.), and imaging was conducted with the Azure 600 (Biosystems).</p></sec><sec id="S17"><title>Sample preparation and LC-MS Analysis</title><p id="P36">Native protein pellets obtained from differential centrifugation were digested and desalted following the protocol for the S-Trap Micro Column (ProtiFi, USA). Protein concentration was quantified using the BCA assay (Thermo Fisher Sci.), while peptide concentration was measured using a fluorometric kit (Thermo Fisher Sci.).</p></sec><sec id="S18"><title>Liquid-chromatography tandem mass spectrometry</title><p id="P37">LC-MS/MS analyses were performed at the Biosciences Mass Spectrometry Core Facility, Arizona State University. Data-dependent mass spectra were collected in positive mode using an Orbitrap Fusion Lumos mass spectrometer coupled with an UltiMate 3000 UHPLC (Thermo Fisher Sci.). Peptides were fractionated on an Easy-Spray LC column (50 cm × 75 μm ID, PepMap C18, 2 μm, 100 Å) with an upstream trap column. Each sample was analyzed in technical triplicate. LC-MS settings: electrospray potential 1.6 kV, ion transfer tube temperature 300°C, and the “Universal” peptide analysis method. Full MS scans (375–1500 m/z) were acquired at a resolution of 120,000 with three sec cycles. The RF lens was set to 30%, AGC to “Standard,” and monoisotopic peak determination included charge states 2–7. Dynamic exclusion was 60 sec with a 10 ppm mass tolerance. MS/MS spectra were acquired in centroid mode with a quadrupole isolation window of 1.6 m/z and CID energy of 35%. Peptides were eluted over a 240-min gradient at 0.25 μL/min using 2–80% acetonitrile/water: 0–3 min (2%), 3–75 min (2–15%), 75–180 min (15–30%), 180–220 min (30–35%), 220–225 min (35–80%), 225–240 min (80–85%).</p><p id="P38">LC-MS/MS analysis of the digested peptides was performed on an EASY-nLC 1200 (Thermo Fisher Sci.) coupled to an Orbitrap Eclipse Tribrid mass spectrometer (Thermo Fisher Sci.). Peptides were separated on an Aurora UHPLC column (25 cm × 75 μm, 1.6 μm C18, AUR2-25075C18A, Ion Opticks) with a flow rate of 0.35 μL/min for a total duration of 135 minionized at 1.6 kV in the positive ion mode. The gradient was composed of 2% solvent B (5 min), 2-6% B (7.5 min), 6-25% B (82.5 min), 25–40% B (30 min), 40-98% B (1min) and 98% B (15min); solvent A: 2% ACN and 0.2% FA in water; solvent B: 80% ACN and 0.2% FA. MS1 scans were acquired at the resolution of 120,000 from 350 to 1,600 m/z, AGC target 1e6, and maximum injection time 50 ms. MS2 scans were acquired in the ion trap using fast scan rate on precursors with 2-7 charge states and quadrupole isolation mode (isolation window: 0.7 m/z) with higher-energy collisional dissociation (HCD, 30%) activation type. Dynamic exclusion was set to 30 s. The temperature of ion transfer tube was 300°C and the S-lens RF level was set to 30.</p></sec><sec id="S19"><title>Raw data processing and quantification</title><p id="P39">The LFQ analysis was performed using Proteome Discoverer 2.4 (Thermo Fisher Sci.) based on the composite database: <italic>P. papillatum’s</italic> predicted proteome, and mitochondrial ORFs, Raw files were searched with SequestHT using Trypsin as the enzyme, allowing up to three missed cleavages. Peptide length was set to 6–144 amino acids, with precursor ion mass tolerance at 20 ppm, fragment mass tolerance at 0.5 Da, and a minimum of one peptide identified. Carbamidomethyl (C) was a fixed modification, while Acetyl (N-terminus), Met-loss (N-terminus), and oxidation of Met were dynamic modifications. A target/decoy strategy and 1.0% FDR were calculated using Percolator. Data were imported into Proteome Discoverer 2.4, and features were detected using the Minora Feature Detector algorithm. The area-under-the-curve for aligned ion chromatograms was calculated to determine relative abundances. The RAW data have been deposited to the ProteomeXchange Consortium via the PRIDE partner repository with the dataset identifier XXXXXX.</p><p id="P40">Proteins and their corresponding LFQ abundance values were imported into the R programming language and converted into MSnset object using the Bioconductor packages MSnbase (v 2.24.2) and pRoloc (v 1.38.2) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">Crook, et al. 2019</xref>). The data was examined and proteins with low confidence (PSM &lt; 3 and without unique peptides) were filtered out. Triplicates were averaged to generate a 33rd dimensional dataset of relative protein abundance. The datasets were split into their respective experiments (i.e., 1-11, 12-22, 23-33) to perform hybrid imputation and sum-normalization across rows.</p><p id="P41">Missing data were imputed first by nearest-neighbor averaging and then imputing zeros for all remaining empty cells. Principal component analysis and t-distributed Stochastic Neighbor Embedding (t-SNE) were applied for dimensional reduction and data visualization.</p></sec><sec id="S20"><title>Supervised and unsupervised classification</title><p id="P42">268 manually curated marker proteins (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table S1</xref>) were used as the training set for a support vector machine (SVM) model with the ‘svmOptimization’ and ‘svmClassification’ functions in pRoloc package. Initially, 100 rounds of five-fold cross-validation were performed to optimize the SVM parameters based on the marker protein abundance profiles. The optimal parameters for the SVM classifier were then applied to all proteins in the dataset with a corresponding SVM score whose range is 0-1 with 1 being the score of marker proteins. The SVM classifier was then applied to unlabeled data (i.e., non-marker proteins) with corresponding weights applied to each marker class. Each protein was thus classified to one compartment, and any protein whose classification fell below the global median SVM score was reset to ‘unknown’ while the other half of the dataset was considered “predicted” to its corresponding compartment due to their higher SVM scores (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table S3</xref>).</p><p id="P43">Unsupervised clustering was performed using the K-means (KM) algorithm implemented in the MLearn function from the MLInterfaces package in Rstudio (version 1.78.0). KM generates k random centroids and includes surrounding data points iteratively such that all data points are included in one of the k clusters and the size of each centroid is minimized. K-means clusters were generated with 22 clusters corresponding to number Rof marker groups (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table S3</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S21"><title>Targeting signal prediction, annotation, and conditional enrichment analysis</title><p id="P44"><italic>P. papillatum</italic> protein database was annotated via blast search against CDS of parasitic kinetoplastid <italic>Trypanosoma brucei</italic> 927 (v66) and free-living <italic>Bodo saltans</italic> (v66) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://tritrypdb.org/tritrypdb/app">https://tritrypdb.org/tritrypdb/app</ext-link>) as well as baker’s yeast <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> (559292) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://blast.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Blast.cgi">https://blast.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Blast.cgi</ext-link>), with a threshold of E<sup>-5</sup>. Metabolic pathway analysis was also performed via GhostKoala (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">Kanehisa, et al. 2016</xref>).</p><p id="P45">Signal P version 6.0 was used for the prediction of signal peptides, using a confidence threshold of <underline>&gt;</underline>0.9 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1C</xref>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R45">Teufel, et al. 2022</xref>), with NetGPI 1.1 additionally used on this subset to determine proteins that additionally possessed predicted C-terminal GPI anchors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">Gíslason, et al. 2021</xref>) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table S3</xref>). Target P 2.0 was used for prediction of mitochondrial target peptides (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">Armenteros, et al. 2019</xref>), with DeepTMHMM (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">Hallgren, et al. 2022</xref>) used for predictions of TMD (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig.1C</xref>) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table S3</xref>). Peroxisomal target signal prediction was conducted using a custom regex script designed by Prof. Fred Oppoerdoes against a broad range of AA combinations with PTS1 determined by the script: [SAGCNP][RHKSNQ][LIVFAMY]$, and PTS2 via ^M.[1,10],[RK][LVI].....[HQ][ILA] (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table S3</xref>), which were then manually inspected for specific enzymes of relevance (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table S5-7</xref>). DeepLoc2.1 was additionally used to assess protein localization predictions and membranous status (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34">Odum, et al. 2024</xref>) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table S3</xref>).</p><p id="P46">Protein enrichment data for media and conditional cultivation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R50">Škodová-Sveráková, et al. 2021</xref>) was displayed across dataset, including proteins that displayed enrichment status of any capacity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1D</xref>) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table S3</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S22"><title>Endogenous tagging and <italic>P. papillatum</italic> microscopy</title><p id="P47">Endogenous C-terminal tagging of cell lines corresponding to 12 proteins within supervised protein clusters were generated to verify predictions (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table S4</xref>).</p><p id="P48">Proteins DIPPA_11651.mRNA.1, DIPPA_15120.mRNA.1, DIPPA_04811.mRNA.1, DIPPA_32825.mRNA.1, DIPPA_00315.mRNA.1 underwent tagging via yellow fluorescent protein, using vector pBA3294 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">Akiyoshi, et al. 2025</xref>). <italic>Pac</italic>I and <italic>Asc</italic>I restriction sites of pBA3294 were used to insert two ~2 kb homology arms that were amplified from genomic DNA by PCR using KOD one polymerase (Merck). Primer sequences are provided in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Suppl. File 2</xref>. The first fragment corresponds to downstream of the gene ORF (starting just after its stop codon) surrounded with <italic>Pac</italic>I and <italic>Not</italic>I restriction sites, while the second fragment corresponds to the 2 kb DNA fragment starting from 2kb upstream of the stop codon and ending just before the stop codon surrounded with <italic>Not</italic>I and <italic>Asc</italic>I. After cutting the fragments with respective restriction enzymes, the two DNA fragments were ligated into pBA3294 that were cut with <italic>Pac</italic>I and <italic>Asc</italic>I. Plasmids were validated by nanopore whole plasmid sequencing (Plasmidsaurus). Tagging constructs were linearized by <italic>Not</italic>I, transfected into <italic>P. papillatum</italic> cells by electroporation, and selected by the addition of 75 μg/mL G418.</p><p id="P49">Cells were pelleted by centrifugation at 1300 x g for 5 min and fixed by 4% formaldehyde solution diluted in PBS for 5 min. Cells were washed with 1 mL PBS twice, resuspended in a small volume of DABCO mounting media (1% w/v 1,4-diazabicyclo[2.2.2]octane, 90% glycerol, 50 mM sodium phosphate pH 8.0) with 100 ng/mL DAPI, and mounted onto glass slides. Images were captured on an Axioimager.Z2 microscope (Zeiss) installed with ZEN using a Hamamatsu ORCA-Flash4.0 camera with 63x objective lenses (1.40 NA). Typically, 25 z sections spaced 0.24 μm apart were collected.</p><p id="P50">Proteins DIPPA_07493.mRNA.1, DIPPA_20982.mRNA.1, DIPPA_24150.mRNA.1, DIPPA_16310.mRNA.1, DIPPA_24837.mRNA.1, DIPPA_21158.mRNA.1, DIPPA_16504.mRNA.1 underwent tagging via 3xV5 epitope, using vector pDP011 (GeneBank OQ547858) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">Faktorová, et al. 2023</xref>) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table S4</xref>). A fusion PCR strategy using Q5 High-Fidelity DNA Polymerase (NEB Biolabs, M0491S) was used to design and obtain the above DNA constructs, as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">Kaur, et al. 2018</xref>). Used primers and product sizes are listed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Suppl. File 2</xref>. 1-5 μg of gel-purified and ethanol-precipitated DNA constructs were electroporated into 5 x 10<sup>7</sup> cells/ml <italic>P. papillatum</italic> cells as described elsewhere (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">Kaur, et al. 2018</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">Faktorová, Kaur, et al. 2020</xref>). 24 h after electroporation, transfected cells underwent selection in a 24-well plate at 27°C, under increasing concentrations of hygromycin (100-225 μg/mL). After 3 weeks, transfectants were selected and expanded into a volume of 10 ml before downstream analyses.</p><p id="P51">To address subcellular localization of the tagged proteins, an immunofluorescence assay was performed as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">Faktorová, et al. 2023</xref>). Briefly, 20 to 30 ml of a log phase culture was harvested by centrifugation at 1,700 x g for 10 min, resuspended in 500 μl of 4% paraformaldehyde (dissolved in sea water), and fixed for 15 min on Superfrost plus slides (Thermo Fisher Sci.) at room temperature. After removing the fixative with 1x PBS, cells were permeabilized in ice-cold methanol for 10 min and rinsed with 1x PBS. From this point on, the slides were kept in a humid chamber. Next, the slides were blocked in 5.5% (w/v) fetal bovine serum in PBS-T for 45 min at room temperature, and the blocking solution was removed by washing the cells two times with 1x PBS. The slides were incubated with either mouse anti-V5 or rabbit anti-V5 primary antibody diluted (1:500; Thermo Fisher Sci.) in 3% (w/v) bovine serum albumin (Sigma), at 4°C overnight, covered with parafilm. Afterwards, the primary antibody was removed by washing the slides three times with PBS-T and twice with 1x PBS. AlexaFluor555-labelled goat anti-mouse (1:1000; Invitrogen) or AlexaFluor488-labelled goat anti-rabbit (1:1000; Invitrogen) secondary antibody was added and incubated at room temperature for 1 hour in the dark, covered with parafilm. After that, the slides were rinsed three times with PBS-T and twice with 1x PBS. All slides were coated with ProLong Gold Antifade Mountant with DNA Stain DAPI (Life Technol.) and mounted. Samples were imaged with an Olympus BX63 automated fluorescence microscope equipped with an Olympus DP74 digital camera. Pictures were acquired with the cellSens Dimension software (Olympus) and processed through the ImageJ software.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="SM"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1"><label>Supplementary Figures, Files and Tables</label><media xlink:href="EMS207393-supplement-Supplementary_Figures,_Files_and_Tables.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" id="d47aAcEbB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack id="S23"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank A. Zíková (Biology Centre) for the anti-ATP synthase subunit β antibodies. This work is supported by the National Science Foundation BII: Mechanisms of Cellular Evolution DBI-2119963 (to J.W.), the Czech Grant Agency grants 23-06479X and 25-15298S (to J.L.) and a Wellcome Discovery Award 227243/Z/23/Z (to B.A.).</p></ack><fn-group><fn id="FN1" fn-type="con"><p id="P52"><bold>Author contributions</bold></p><p id="P53">Conceptualization, M.H, J.L and J.G.W.; Methodology, M.H, D.F, B.A, and J.G.W.; Software, M.H, Y.P and T.L.; Validation, M.H.; Formal Analysis, M.H.; Investigation, M.H, O.I, D.F, M.S and B.A.; Data Curation, M.H and Y.P.; Writing – Original Draft, M.H, O.I, D.F, M.S, B.A, J.L, J.G.W.; Writing – Review &amp; Editing, M.H, J.L and J.G.W.; Visualization, M.H.; Supervision, M.H, D.F, J.L and J.G.W.; Project Administration, M.H and J.G.W.; Funding Acquisition, M.H, B.A, J.L and J.G.W.</p></fn><fn id="FN2" fn-type="conflict"><p id="P54"><bold>Declaration of interests</bold></p><p id="P55">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><ref id="R1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Akiyoshi</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Faktorová</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Lukeš</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Discovery of unique mitotic mechanisms in <italic>Paradiplonema papillatum</italic></article-title><source>bioRxiv</source><year>2025</year><elocation-id>2025.2003.2021.644664</elocation-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Armenteros</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Salvatore</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Emanuelsson</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Winther</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>von Heijne</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Elofsson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Detecting sequence signals in targeting peptides using deep learning</article-title><source>Life Sci Alliance</source><year>2019</year><volume>2</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.26508/lsa.201900429</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6769257</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31570514</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Benz</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Raas</surname><given-names>MWD</given-names></name><name><surname>Tripathi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Faktorová</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Tromer</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name><name><surname>Akiyoshi</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Lukeš</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>On the possibility of yet a third kinetochore system in the protist phylum Euglenozoa</article-title><source>mBio</source><year>2024</year><volume>15</volume><elocation-id>e02936-02924</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/mbio.02936-24</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11633173</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39475241</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Billington</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Halliday</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Madden</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Dyer</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Barker</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Moreira-Leite</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Carrington</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Vaughan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hertz-Fowler</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Dean</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genome-wide subcellular protein map for the flagellate parasite <italic>Trypanosoma brucei</italic></article-title><source>Nature Microbiology</source><year>2023</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>533</fpage><lpage>547</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41564-022-01295-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9981465</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36804636</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Breckels</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Holden</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wojnar</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Mulvey</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Christoforou</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Groen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Trotter</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kohlbacher</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Lilley</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Gatto</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Learning from heterogeneous data sources: An application in spatial proteomics</article-title><source>PLos Comput Biol</source><year>2016</year><volume>12</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1004920</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4866734</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27175778</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bártulos</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Gentekaki</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Brinkmann</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Cerff</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Liaud</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hehl</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Yarlett</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Gruber</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Mitochondrial glycolysis in a major lineage of Eukaryotes</article-title><source>Genome Biol and Evol</source><year>2018</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>2310</fpage><lpage>2325</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/gbe/evy164</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6198282</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30060189</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chou</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Sher</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ying</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hung</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The stabilization of PD-L1 by the endoplasmic reticulum stress protein GRP78 in triple-negative breast cancer</article-title><source>Am J Cancer Res</source><year>2020</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>2621</fpage><lpage>2634</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7471351</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32905506</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crook</surname><given-names>OM</given-names></name><name><surname>Breckels</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lilley</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kirk</surname><given-names>PDW</given-names></name><name><surname>Gatto</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A Bioconductor workflow for the Bayesian analysis of spatial proteomics</article-title><source>F1000Res</source><year>2019</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>446</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.12688/f1000research.18636.1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6509962</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31119032</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Faktorová</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaur</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Valach</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Graf</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Benz</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Burger</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Lukeš</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Targeted integration by homologous recombination enables <italic>in situ</italic> tagging and replacement of genes in the marine microeukaryote <italic>Diplonema papillatum</italic></article-title><source>Environ Microbiol</source><year>2020</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>3660</fpage><lpage>3670</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32548939</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Faktorová</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Nisbet</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Robledo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Casacuberta</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Sudek</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ares</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Aresté</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Balestreri</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Barbrook</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genetic tool development in marine protists: emerging model organisms for experimental cell biology</article-title><source>Nature Methods</source><year>2020</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>481</fpage><lpage>494</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41592-020-0796-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7200600</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32251396</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Faktorová</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Záhonová</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Benz</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Dacks</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Field</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lukeš</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Functional differentiation of Sec13 paralogues in the euglenozoan protists</article-title><source>Open Biol</source><year>2023</year><volume>13</volume><elocation-id>220364</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rsob.220364</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10264103</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37311539</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Flegontova</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Flegontov</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Malviya</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Audic</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wincker</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>de Vargas</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bowler</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Lukeš</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Horák</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Extreme diversity of diplonemid eukaryotes in the ocean</article-title><source>Curr Biol</source><year>2016</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>3060</fpage><lpage>3065</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27875689</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Freitag</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Stehlik</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Stiebler</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Bölker</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The obvious and the hidden: Prediction and function of fungal peroxisomal matrix proteins</article-title><source>Subcell Biochem</source><year>2018</year><volume>89</volume><fpage>139</fpage><lpage>155</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30378022</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gawryluk</surname><given-names>RMR</given-names></name><name><surname>Del Campo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Okamoto</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Strassert</surname><given-names>JFH</given-names></name><name><surname>Lukeš</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Richards</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Worden</surname><given-names>AZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Santoro</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Keeling</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Morphological identification and single-cell genomics of marine diplonemids</article-title><source>Curr Biol</source><year>2016</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>3053</fpage><lpage>3059</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27875688</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Geladaki</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Britovšek</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Breckels</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Vennard</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Mulvey</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Crook</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Gatto</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Lilley</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Combining LOPIT with differential ultracentrifugation for high-resolution spatial proteomics</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2019</year><volume>10</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-018-08191-w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6338729</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30659192</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>George</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name><name><surname>Tashyreva</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kwong</surname><given-names>WK</given-names></name><name><surname>Okamoto</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Horák</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Husnik</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Lukeš</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Keeling</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gene transfer agents in bacterial endosymbionts of microbial eukaryotes</article-title><source>Genome Biol Evol</source><year>2022</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>7</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/gbe/evac099</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9254644</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35738252</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gíslason</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Armenteros</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Johansen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prediction of GPI-anchored proteins with pointer neural networks</article-title><source>Curr Res in Biotech</source><year>2021</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>6</fpage><lpage>13</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Güther</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Urbaniak</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tavendale</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Prescott</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferguson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>High-confidence glycosome proteome for procyclic form <italic>Trypanosoma brucei</italic> by epitope-tag organelle enrichment and SILAC proteomics</article-title><source>Journal of Proteome Res</source><year>2014</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>2796</fpage><lpage>2806</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/pr401209w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4052807</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24792668</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hallgren</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsirigos</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Pederson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Armenteros</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Marcatili</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Krogh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Winther</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>DeepTMHMM predicts alpha and beta transmembrane proteins using deep neural networks</article-title><year>2022</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hammond</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nenarokova</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Butenko</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Zoltner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dobáková</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Field</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lukeš</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A uniquely complex mitochondrial proteome from <italic>Euglena gracilis</italic></article-title><source>Mol Biol and Evol</source><year>2020</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>2173</fpage><lpage>2191</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/molbev/msaa061</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7403612</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32159766</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jirsová</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Licknack</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Poh</surname><given-names>YP</given-names></name><name><surname>Qiu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Quan</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Chou</surname><given-names>TF</given-names></name><name><surname>Karr</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Lynch</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wideman</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Subcellular proteomics of <italic>Paramecium tetraurelia</italic> reveals mosaic localization of glycolysis and gluconeogenesis</article-title><source>bioRxiv</source><year>2025</year><elocation-id>2025.2004.2024.650466</elocation-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Joseph</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Adhihetty</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Wawrzyniak</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Wohlgemuth</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Picca</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kujoth</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Prolla</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Leeuwenburgh</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dysregulation of mitochondrial quality control processes contribute to sarcopenia in a mouse model of premature aging</article-title><source>PLos One</source><year>2013</year><volume>8</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0069327</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3720551</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23935986</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kanehisa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Morishima</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>BlastKOALA and GhostKOALA: KEGG Tools for functional characterization of genome and metagenome sequences</article-title><source>J Mol Biol</source><year>2016</year><volume>428</volume><fpage>726</fpage><lpage>731</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26585406</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kaur</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Valach</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Peña-Diaz</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Moreira</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Keeling</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Burger</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Lukeš</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Faktorová</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transformation of <italic>Diplonema papillatum</italic>, the type species of the highly diverse and abundant marine microeukaryotes Diplonemida (Euglenozoa)</article-title><source>Environ Microbiol</source><year>2018</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>1030</fpage><lpage>1040</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29318727</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kovárová</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Barrett</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The pentose phosphate pathway in parasitic trypanosomatids</article-title><source>Trends Parasitol</source><year>2016</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>622</fpage><lpage>634</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27174163</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lax</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Okamoto</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Keeling</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phylogenomic position of eupelagonemids, abundant, and diverse deep-ocean heterotrophs</article-title><source>ISME J</source><year>2024</year><volume>18</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ismejo/wrae040</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10987973</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38457644</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Makiuchi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Annoura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hashimoto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hashimoto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Aoki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Nara</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Compartmentalization of a glycolytic enzyme in <italic>Diplonema</italic>, a non-kinetoplastid Euglenozoan</article-title><source>Protist</source><year>2011</year><volume>162</volume><fpage>482</fpage><lpage>489</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21377422</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Michels</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Bringaud</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Herman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hannaert</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Metabolic functions of glycosomes in trypanosomatids</article-title><source>Biochimi Biophys Acta-Mol Cell Res</source><year>2006</year><volume>1763</volume><fpage>1463</fpage><lpage>1477</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17023066</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moloney</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Barylyuk</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Tromer</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Crook</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Breckels</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Lilley</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Waller</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>MacGregor</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mapping diversity in African trypanosomes using high resolution spatial proteomics</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2023</year><volume>14</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-023-40125-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10361982</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37479728</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morales</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hashimoto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirawake-Mogi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Makiuchi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsubouchi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaga</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Taka</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujimura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Koike</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Differential remodelling of peroxisome function underpins the environmental and metabolic adaptability of diplonemids and kinetoplastids</article-title><source>Proc R Soc B-Biolog Sci</source><year>2016</year><volume>283</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rspb.2016.0520</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4874719</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27170716</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mukherjee</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Salcher</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Andrei</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kavagutti</surname><given-names>VS</given-names></name><name><surname>Shabarova</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Grujcic</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Haber</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Layoun</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hodoki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakano</surname><given-names>SI</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A freshwater radiation of diplonemids</article-title><source>Environ Microbiol</source><year>2020</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>4658</fpage><lpage>4668</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32830371</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Newell</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fungi and bacteria in or on leaves of Eelgrass (<italic>Zostera marina</italic> L.) from Chesapeake Bay</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>1981</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>1219</fpage><lpage>1224</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/aem.41.5.1219-1224.1981</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC243892</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16345773</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Obiol</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Giner</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Sánchez</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Duarte</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Acinas</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name><surname>Massana</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A metagenomic assessment of microbial eukaryotic diversity in the global ocean</article-title><source>Mol Ecol Resour</source><year>2020</year><volume>20</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32065492</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Odum</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Teufel</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Thumuluri</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Armenteros</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Johansen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Winther</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>DeepLoc 2.1: multi-label membrane protein type prediction using protein language models</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2024</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>W215</fpage><lpage>W220</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkae237</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11223819</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38587188</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Opperdoes</surname><given-names>FR</given-names></name><name><surname>Michels</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The glycosomes of the Kinetoplastida</article-title><source>Biochimie</source><year>1993</year><volume>75</volume><fpage>231</fpage><lpage>234</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8507685</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Orsburn</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Proteome discoverer-A community enhanced data processing suite for protein informatics</article-title><source>Proteomes</source><year>2021</year><volume>9</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/proteomes9010015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8006021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33806881</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R37"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Porter</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Isonema papillatum</italic> sp. n., a new colorless marine flagellate: A light- and electronmicroscopic study</article-title><source>J Protozool</source><year>1973</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>351</fpage><lpage>356</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R38"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Prokopchuk</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Korytár</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Juricová</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Majstorovic</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Horák</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Šimek</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Lukeš</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Trophic flexibility of marine diplonemids-switching from osmotrophy to bacterivory</article-title><source>ISME J</source><year>2022</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>1409</fpage><lpage>1419</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41396-022-01192-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9039065</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35042972</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R39"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Richards</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Eme</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Archibald</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Leonard</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Coelho</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>de Mendoza</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Dessimoz</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Dolezal</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Fritz-Laylin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Gabaldon</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Reconstructing the last common ancestor of all eukaryotes</article-title><source>Plos Biol</source><year>2024</year><volume>22</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.3002917</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11627563</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39585925</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R40"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tashyreva</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Faktorová</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Horák</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lukeš</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Archibald</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Oatley</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Sinclair</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Paulini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Aunin</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The genome sequences of the diplonemid protist <italic>Rhynchopus euleeides</italic> YPF1915 and its bacterial endosymbiont Candidatus Syngnamydia salmonis (Chlamydiota)</article-title><source>Wellcome Open Res</source><year>2025</year><volume>10</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.12688/wellcomeopenres.24014.1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12171722</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40528998</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R41"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tashyreva</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Faktorová</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Stříbrná</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Horák</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lukeš</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Archibald</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Oatley</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Sinclair</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Aunin</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Gettle</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The genome sequences of the diplonemid protist <italic>Diplonema japonicum</italic> YFP1604 and its bacterial endosymbiont Ca</article-title><source>Cytomitobacter primus and Ca Nesciobacter abundans</source><year>2025</year><volume>10</volume></element-citation></ref><ref id="R42"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tashyreva</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Simpson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Prokopchuk</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Škodová-Sveráková</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Butenko</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hammond</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>George</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Flegontova</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Záhonová</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Faktorová</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Diplonemids-a review on “new” flagellates on the oceanic block</article-title><source>Protist</source><year>2022</year><volume>173</volume><elocation-id>125868</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35339983</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R43"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tashyreva</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Týc</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Horák</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lukeš</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ultrastructure and 3D reconstruction of a diplonemid protist (Diplonemea) and its novel membranous organelle</article-title><source>mBio</source><year>2023</year><volume>14</volume><elocation-id>e01921-01923</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/mbio.01921-23</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10653844</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37737610</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R44"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tashyreva</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Votýpka</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Yabuki</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Horák</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lukeš</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Description of new diplonemids (Diplonemea, Euglenozoa) and their endosymbionts: Charting the morphological diversity of these poorly known heterotrophic flagellates</article-title><source>Protist</source><year>2025</year><volume>177</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40009938</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R45"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Teufel</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Armenteros</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Johansen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gíslason</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pihl</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsirigos</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Winther</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Brunak</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>von Heijne</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>SignalP 6.0 predicts all five types of signal peptides using protein language models</article-title><source>Nat Biotechnol</source><year>2022</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>1023</fpage><lpage>1025</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41587-021-01156-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9287161</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34980915</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R46"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Valach</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Benz</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Aguilar</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Gahura</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Faktorová</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Zíková</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Oeffinger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Burger</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lukeš</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Miniature RNAs are embedded in an exceptionally protein-rich mitoribosome via an elaborate assembly pathway</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2023</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>6443</fpage><lpage>6460</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkad422</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10325924</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37207340</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R47"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Valach</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Léveillé-Kunst</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Burger</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Respiratory chain Complex I of unparalleled divergence in diplonemids</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2018</year><volume>293</volume><fpage>16043</fpage><lpage>16056</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.RA118.005326</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6187644</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30166340</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R48"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Valach</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Moreira</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Petitjean</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Benz</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Butenko</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Flegontova</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Nenarokova</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Prokopchuk</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Batstone</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Lapébie</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Recent expansion of metabolic versatility in <italic>Diplonema papillatum</italic>, the model species of a highly speciose group of marine eukaryotes</article-title><source>BMC Biol</source><year>2023</year><volume>21</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12915-023-01563-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10161547</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37143068</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R49"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Záhonová</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Lukeš</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Dacks</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diplonemid protists possess exotic endomembrane machinery, impacting models of membrane trafficking in modern and ancient eukaryotes</article-title><source>Curr Biol</source><year>2025</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>1508</fpage><lpage>1520</lpage><elocation-id>e1502</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40088893</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R50"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Škodová-Sveráková</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Záhonová</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Juricová</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Danchenko</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Moos</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Baráth</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Prokopchuk</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Butenko</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lukácová</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Kohútová</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Highly flexible metabolism of the marine euglenozoan protist <italic>Diplonema papillatum</italic></article-title><source>BMC Biol</source><year>2021</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>251</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12915-021-01186-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8611851</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34819072</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R51"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Šubrtová</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Panicucci</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Zíková</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>ATPaseTb2, a unique membrane-bound FoF1-ATPase component, is essential in bloodstream and dyskinetoplastic trypanosomes</article-title><source>PLoS Pathog</source><year>2015</year><volume>11</volume><elocation-id>e1004660</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1004660</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4340940</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25714685</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><title>Clustered protein predictions of <italic>Paradiplonema papillatum</italic> align with predicted protein features and clarify conditional enrichment trends.</title><p><bold>A</bold> Neighbor-average imputed t-SNE of dataset displaying clustered predictions displayed for 2,797 proteins across 22 cell compartments. Predictions were generated via support vector modelling conducted on fractional profiles of marker proteins, applied to the remaining dataset. <bold>B</bold> Selected fractional abundances of marker proteins across one replicate of this experiment, representing distinct profiles that facilitate predictive clustering (SUP, Supernatant). <bold>C</bold> Software prediction for protein features of signal peptides, transmembrane domains and mitochondrial target peptides across dataset, demonstrating accumulation across certain defined compartments. <bold>D</bold> Proteins determined to be enriched in varying nutrient media (Diplo or Hemi) or cultivation conditions (aerobic or anaerobic) from a conditional study of <italic>P. papillatum</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R50">Škodová-Sveráková, et al. 2021</xref>). Additional information for all proteins available in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table S1 and S3</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS207393-f001"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><title>Endogenous tagging of novel proteins confirms supervised cluster predictions.</title><p>Tagged proteins highlighted (black) among relevant predicted clusters, resolved on neighbor-averaged imputed t-SNE. Individual cell lines were generated via endogenous tagging and imaged through fluorescence microscopy for comparison with the compartment relevant protein was predicted to. Merged microscopy images showing protein signal (green) merged with nuclear and mitochondrial DNA (blue). All imaged cells are oriented with their apical regions facing right and posterior facing left, cell membrane outlines are traced for all images except for <bold>L</bold>, showing only trace of the papilla, which lacks signal. Scale bar represents 5μm. Proteins <bold>A, E, G</bold> and <bold>J</bold> are resolved in zero and neighbor-averaged imputed t-SNE in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Suppl. Fig. 3</xref>, for which separate channels of each cell line are also shown. Further information on cell lines is available in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table S4</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS207393-f002"/></fig><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><title>Secreted Carbohydrate Active Enzymes (CAZymes) primarily localized on cell membrane and lysosomes.</title><p>Distribution of signal peptide-enriched CAZymes, which are predicted with high confidence on neighbor-average imputed t-SNE, corresponding to highlighted cluster predictions of the cell membrane (<bold>A</bold>), endocytic membrane trafficking (<bold>B</bold>), lysosome (<bold>C</bold>) and cytosol (<bold>D</bold>). Proteins of cell membrane (<bold>A</bold>) have schematic representations showing software predictions for signal peptides, transmembrane domains (TMD) and/or GPI attachment sites, which demonstrate extracellular exposure of CAZyme domains in accordance with conventional membrane topology. Bordered outlines indicate separate enzymatic reactions for CAZymes, with carbohydrate substrates and products in black. Further information on CAZymes of <italic>P. papillatum</italic> is available in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table S5</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS207393-f003"/></fig><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><title>Metabolic reconstruction of glycolysis/gluconeogenesis and pentose phosphate pathway demonstrates altered glucose metabolism in <italic>P. papillatum</italic>.</title><p>Localization of relevant enzymes across glycolysis/gluconeogenesis (<bold>A</bold>) and pentose phosphate pathway (<bold>B</bold>), resolved on neighbor-average imputed t-SNE (<bold>C</bold>) with relevant localization clusters highlighted. Peroxisomal target sequences (PTS), mitochondrial target peptides (mTP) and transmembrane domains (TMDs) are indicated. Proteins previously localized via anti-sera immunolocalizations indicated with *, metabolite shunts between two pathways indicated with dotted arrows. Split coloring of proteins represents their manual designations to the cytosol (24,25,38) or indicates the possibility of glycosomal dual localizations between the cytosol and glycosomes (1,2,5,9,12,20), based on inspection of fractionation profiles (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Suppl. Fig. 6</xref>) and targeting signals. Protein numbers highlighted in white represent those only resolved on zero and neighbor-average imputed t-SNE (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Suppl. Figure 5</xref>). Further information is available in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table S6</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS207393-f004"/></fig><table-wrap id="T1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Fractional protocol for centrifugation as used in this study, adapted from LOPIT-DC protocol (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">Geladaki, et al. 2019</xref>).</title></caption><table frame="box" rules="all"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left">Fraction</th><th valign="top" align="left">Centrifuge speed (x g)</th><th valign="top" align="left">Spin time (min)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left">Cell Lysate</td><td valign="top" align="left">200</td><td valign="top" align="left">5</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">1</td><td valign="top" align="left">1,000</td><td valign="top" align="left">10</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">2</td><td valign="top" align="left">3,000</td><td valign="top" align="left">10</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">3</td><td valign="top" align="left">5,000</td><td valign="top" align="left">10</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">4</td><td valign="top" align="left">9,000</td><td valign="top" align="left">15</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">5</td><td valign="top" align="left">12,000</td><td valign="top" align="left">15</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">6</td><td valign="top" align="left">15,000</td><td valign="top" align="left">15</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">7</td><td valign="top" align="left">30,000</td><td valign="top" align="left">20</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">8</td><td valign="top" align="left">79,000</td><td valign="top" align="left">43</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">9</td><td valign="top" align="left">120,000</td><td valign="top" align="left">45</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">Supernatant</td><td valign="top" align="left">NA</td><td valign="top" align="left">NA</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></floats-group></article>