<!DOCTYPE article
 PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" article-type="preprint"><?all-math-mml yes?><?use-mml?><?origin ukpmcpa?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">bioRxiv</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>bioRxiv : the preprint server for biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2692-8205</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">EMS206472</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2025.06.09.658643</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="archive">PPR1035688</article-id><article-version-alternatives><article-version article-version-type="status">preprint</article-version><article-version article-version-type="number">1</article-version></article-version-alternatives><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Tracking polygenic adaptation: phenotypic stasis after rapid adaptation in large populations of <italic>Drosophila</italic></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ramirez-Lanzas</surname><given-names>Claudia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">a</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Dolezal</surname><given-names>Marlies</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Signor</surname><given-names>Sarah</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">d</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Schlotterer</surname><given-names>Christian</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Barghi</surname><given-names>Neda</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">e</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CR1">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1"><label>a</label>Institut Für Populationsgenetik, Vetmeduni Vienna, Vienna 1210, Austria</aff><aff id="A2"><label>b</label>Vienna Graduate School of Population Genetics, Vetmeduni Vienna, Vienna 1210, Austria</aff><aff id="A3"><label>c</label>Plattform Bioinformatik und Biostatistik, Vetmeduni Vienna, Vienna 1210, Austria</aff><aff id="A4"><label>d</label>Department of Biological Sciences, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/05h1bnb22</institution-id><institution>North Dakota State University</institution></institution-wrap>, <city>Fargo</city>, <state>North Dakota</state><postal-code>58104</postal-code></aff><aff id="A5"><label>e</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/0534re684</institution-id><institution>Max Planck Institute for Evolutionary Biology</institution></institution-wrap>, <city>Plön</city><postal-code>24306</postal-code>, <country country="DE">Germany</country></aff><author-notes><corresp id="CR1"><label>*</label>Corresponding author, <email>barghi@evolbio.mpg.de</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted"><day>15</day><month>06</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="preprint"><day>12</day><month>06</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><permissions><ali:free_to_read/><license><ali:license_ref>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is licensed under a <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">CC BY-NC 4.0 International license</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p id="P1">Most adaptive traits have a polygenic basis, and their evolution in response to environmental change results from the cumulative effect of many underlying loci. Theoretical studies predict two phases of phenotypic evolution: an initial directional phase, characterized by shifts in the mean of the trait towards a new optimum; and a subsequent stabilizing phase, in which the mean phenotype remains in equilibrium. However, there is limited empirical evidence to confirm these predictions. We exposed six replicate populations of <italic>Drosophila simulans</italic>, each with 100,000 individuals, to a new high-protein diet for 31 generations. Using time-series, high-order and molecular phenotypes, we characterized the phases of polygenic adaptation and inferred the transition between the directional and stabilizing selection phases empirically. The initial (directional) phase was characterized by a rapid phenotypic response, followed by a plateau after seven generations of adaptation, suggesting proximity to the new trait optimum (i.e. the stabilizing phase). The phenotypic responses were highly parallel among the replicate populations throughout the experiment. The contribution of pleiotropic loci to adaptive phenotypic evolution varied across the different phases of adaptation. Adaptation was facilitated by genes with low-to-intermediate pleiotropy whereas highly pleiotropic genes played a significant role in the rapid phase of adaptation. Parallel evolutionary responses across the replicate populations were also driven by genes with low-to-intermediate pleiotropy. Our findings support the predictions of theoretical models and is the first empirical inference of directional and stabilizing phases.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec id="S1" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p id="P2">Most studied traits are quantitative, with a continuous and typically normal distribution, and are under natural selection (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref>). The collective findings of many QTL mapping, GWAS, and evolution studies in species ranging from <italic>Drosophila</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">2</xref>) to humans (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">3</xref>) have shown that these quantitative traits are complex and determined by many underlying loci. Most quantitative traits are under stabilizing selection (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">3</xref>) which stabilizes the population’s mean on an optimal trait value, known as trait optimum. As a result, adaptation of a quantitative trait after a sudden environmental change which shifts the trait’s optimum would occur through the collective, often small, frequency changes across many of the underlying alleles, i.e. polygenic adaptation. Theoretical (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref>) and simulation studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref>) predict that adaptation of quantitative traits has at least two phases, each with distinct genomic and phenotypic characteristics. Right after a shift in optimum, due to the frequency change of adaptive alleles the population’s mean phenotype changes toward the new optimum. This initial phase of adaptation is rapid, resembling directional selection (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref>). In the second phase, after the population’s mean phenotype nears the new optimum, the combined effects of stabilizing selection and genetic drift result in the fixation and loss of alleles (alleles with effects aligned with the shift, as well as alleles with opposing effects, could be fixed or lost, see (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">4</xref>)) while the phenotype’s mean phenotype stabilizes on the new optimum.</p><p id="P3">Empirical data supporting theoretical predictions remain limited for several reasons. First, most theoretical models assume a stable environment after an initial shift in trait optimum, allowing stabilizing selection to act. However, natural populations often experience seasonal fluctuations which contradicts this assumption. Second, the trait under selection and its new optimum are often unknown in most (experimental and natural) populations. These factors hinder our ability to determine when the populations reach the new optimum and to distinguish between directional and stabilizing phases of adaptation.</p><p id="P4">Predicted adaptation patterns (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref>) suggest that detection methods should reflect the temporal phenotypic and genomic features. Temporal genomic and phenotypic data are essential for testing the predictions of theoretical models. To align with the model assumptions, a stable environment should follow the initial change. Experimental evolution provides an ideal framework for testing the theoretical predictions by allowing the collection of temporal data in controlled and constant environments across replicate populations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref>).</p><p id="P5">Predictions of allele frequencies during complex traits adaptation depend on trait polygenicity, allele frequency and effect size, and the magnitude of trait optimum shift. Theoretical studies have assumed different optimum shifts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">8</xref>) and trait polygenicity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref>). Despite differing genomic predictions, a consistent pattern across all studies is that as the phenotypic mean plateaus as populations near the new optimum. Simulations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref>) show that temporal phenotypic patterns can distinguish directional from stabilizing phases of adaptation. Identifying this transition helps pinpoint when populations approach the new optimum, even without knowing the selected trait.</p><p id="P6">To characterize the temporal patterns of phenotypic changes after a shift in the trait optimum we exposed unprecedentedly large populations of <italic>Drosophila simulans</italic> to a novel selection regime with a high-protein diet in the laboratory for 40 non-overlapping generations. We quantified phenotypic changes at multiple time points in evolving populations by collecting data across different levels of the biological hierarchy, including molecular traits (gene expression) and high-order phenotypes (lipid content, weight, and fecundity, as a fitness component). We characterized the temporal patterns of adaptive phenotypic change and identified the transition from the directional phase to the stabilizing selection phase. This is the first empirical test of polygenic adaptation models showing rapid adaptation followed by phenotypic stagnation.</p></sec><sec id="S2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><p id="P7">We performed round-robin crosses using 93 <italic>Drosophila simulans</italic> inbred lines, maintained them for 15 generations, and established a founder population by combining equal proportions of these crosses (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD11">Fig. S1</xref>). Six replicate populations each with 100,000 individuals were set up from the founder population, and exposed them to a novel selection regime that consists of a high-protein (protein:carbohydrate ratio 1:1) diet for 40 non-overlapping generations (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD11">Fig. S1</xref>). Although in a laboratory environment, the populations were maintained in an environment where the selection regime was complex, consisting of multiple selection pressures. Exposure to high-protein diet, maintenance at 25 °C with a 12-days developmental time imposed a selection pressure on the populations. Adaptation to high-protein diet (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>), temperature (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref>) and developmental time (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref>) are all polygenic traits. Thus, this complex selection regime changed the optimal phenotype of the populations, i.e. trait optimum, for multiple polygenic traits.</p><sec id="S3"><title>Rapid change of high-order and molecular phenotypes</title><p id="P8">To determine the phenotypic changes as populations evolve on the high-protein diet, we measured the phenotypic status of the founder population and that of the evolving populations after 7 and 31 generations. Each population was maintained in a common garden for 2 generations on high-protein diet with controlled density before phenotyping to reduce maternal effects (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD11">Fig. S1</xref>). This also assured that the phenotypic differences observed between the founder and evolved populations reflected adaptation to the new environment, not phenotypic plasticity. First, we assessed the adaptive response of the evolved populations by measuring female fecundity, which is a proxy of fitness. The evolved populations at generations 7 and 31 were significantly more fecund, hence fitter, than the founder population (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1A</xref>). Weight, a high-order phenotype, also showed a rapid response, with significant decreases in weight observed in both females and males after only 7 generations (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD11">Fig. S3</xref>). The direction of the change reversed for both sexes.</p><p id="P9">As many of the genetic variants underlying complex traits are located in regulatory regions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref>), adaptation may manifest through changes in the expression of adaptive genes. Therefore, we investigated changes in the gene expression as the underlying molecular basis of high-order phenotypic changes. We measured the gene expression of males in the founder population and in the evolved populations at generations 7 and 31, after maintenance in a common garden on high-protein diet for 2 generations. The principal component analysis (PCA) of the global transcriptomic variation using 10,197 expressed genes showed a clear differentiation of the founder population from the evolved populations (PC1, 26.19%, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD11">Fig. S4A</xref>). However, the expression variation which distinguishes the evolved populations at generation 7 and 31 is small (PC3, 7.89%, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD11">Fig S4B</xref>). A total of 6,354 genes had significant changes in their expression in the evolved populations when compared to the founder population. Of these, a total of 4,867 genes (76.6%) were shared between generations 7 and 31 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>). A fraction of the differentially expressed genes (710 genes, 11.17%) was identified only at generation 7 (‘complete-reverse’ group) while 777 genes (12.2%) showed a significant expression change only at generation 31 (‘late-response’ group, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>).</p><p id="P10">To understand the biological functions of the differentially expressed genes (DEGs) we performed gene ontology (GO), pathway and tissue enrichment analyses (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Table S2</xref>). DEGs were enriched in several GO terms, such as ‘proteolysis’ (GO:0006508), ‘siRNA processing’ (GO:0030422), ‘sexual reproduction’ (GO:0019953), and (GO:0015031) ‘protein transport’ (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Table S2A</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD11">Fig. S5</xref>). Several pathways related to protein metabolism, e.g. ‘beta-alanine metabolism’ and ‘valine, leucine and isoleucine degradation’, ‘carbohydrate metabolism’, and ‘lipid metabolism’ were also enriched (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Table S2</xref>B, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD11">Fig. S6</xref>). DEGs were also enriched in several tissues including fat body, midgut, malpighian tubule, heart and testis (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Table S2C</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD11">Fig. S7</xref>). Collectively, the enrichment analyses showed a diverse response during adaptation to the selection environment involving many biological processes, tissues and pathways. This is expected given that the new environment required adaptation to a new diet, temperature regime and developmental time. In particular, enrichment of pathways related to protein metabolism and transport were expected as exposure to a high-protein diet was one of the main factors in the new selection regime.</p></sec><sec id="S4"><title>Stasis of high-order and molecular phenotypes</title><p id="P11">Theoretical models of polygenic adaptation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">4</xref>) predict that after an environmental change, the population’s mean phenotype changes rapidly before slowing down to a pause when it nears the new optimum. We expect to observe stasis in phenotypes if the evolved populations are close to the optimal phenotype. At the high-order phenotype level, no significant difference was observed in the fecundity of evolved populations between generations 7 and 31 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1A</xref>). Therefore, following an initial rapid increase in 7 generations, the fecundity of the evolved populations had stabilized until generation 31. At the gene expression level, a considerable number of DEGs were shared between temporally separated evolved populations at generations 7 and 31 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>). Furthermore, the magnitude and direction of the gene expression changes in the at generation 7 were highly correlated with those at generation 31 (Pearson correlation coefficient of log<sub>2</sub>FC = 0.96). These results suggest that the changes in molecular phenotypes have remained highly stable in evolved populations assayed 24 generations apart. The temporal patterns of gene expression (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>) are consistent with the patterns of fitness change (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1A</xref>), suggesting that after a rapid and pronounced change, the phenotype of populations stabilized after generation 7.</p><p id="P12">Although the selected traits are not known, transcriptome-wide expression profiling will capture the dynamics of genes that contribute to the selected traits. We predict that the expression pattern of these genes reflects the dynamics of the selected traits. After a rapid response during the first generations, the expression of genes will stabilize and reach a plateau. To identify the genes matching this predicted expression pattern, we first identified DEGs by contrasting gene expression in the founder population with that in evolved populations in generations 7 and 31 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>). Next, we classified the DEGs into 5 groups according to their conserved co-expression patterns. The DEGs shared between generations 7 and 31 were classified into 3 groups: ‘plateau’, ‘monotonic’, and ‘incomplete-reverse’ (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD11">S8-9</xref>). Additionally, DEGs identified only in generation 7 or 31 were classified as ‘complete-reverse’ and ‘late-response’, respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>-<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD11">S8-9</xref>).</p><p id="P13">We define the ‘plateau’ group as those genes that, after a significant expression change at generation 7, do not show significant change in expression between generations 7 and 31. The majority of DEGs (4,113 genes, 64.73%) belonged to the ‘plateau’ group (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD11">S8-9</xref>). The large number of genes with plateaued expression supports the high correlation between the transcriptomic profiles in the evolved populations that were phenotyped 24 generations apart (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD11">S4B</xref>). A total of 417 DEGs (6.56%) showed a monotonous change in their expression until generation 31 (‘monotonic’ group, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>); the expression change (either increase or decrease) of this group in the evolved populations was in the same direction in generations 7 and 31, and significantly different from that in the founder population. The ‘incomplete-reverse’ group (337 genes, 5.30%) exhibited a reversal in the direction of expression change after generation 7 toward the founder population (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD11">S8-9</xref>); although the gene expression at generation 31 remained significantly different from that of the founder population. Identification of the other two groups of DEGs (‘complete-reverse’ and ‘late-response’) were possible using the expression data from the intermediate time point (generation 7) and provides interesting insights into the transient gene regulatory responses during the early directional phase of adaptation. A total of 710 DEGs, (11.17%), classified as ‘complete-reverse’ group, were initially up (or down) regulated in the evolved populations after 7 generations, but reverted to the expression level that was not significantly different from the founder population at generation 31 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD11">S8-9</xref>). Additionally, the expression changes of 777 genes (12.2%), ‘late-response’ group, were in the same direction at generations 7 and 31 compared to the founder population, but a significant change was only identified at generation 31 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>-<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD11">S8-9</xref>).</p><p id="P14">The expression pattern of the ‘monotonic’ and ‘complete-reverse’ groups resembles that of the ‘late-response’ and ‘incomplete-reverse’ groups, respectively (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD11">Fig. S8</xref>). Despite the slight similarity of the expression trajectories of these groups, the PCA showed different patterns of differentiation between the founder and evolved populations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD11">S9</xref>). Additionally, the ‘monotonic’ and ‘late-response’ groups, as well as the ‘incomplete-reverse’ and ‘complete-reverse’ groups, showed significant differences in expression variance (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD11">Fig. S10</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD3">Table S3</xref>) and pleiotropy at the levels of gene connectivity and tissue specificity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD11">S15</xref>). The proportion of these five groups remained consistent even when only genes with absolute log<sub>2</sub>FC &gt; 0.32 were considered, i.e. genes with an absolute change of at least 25% (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD11">Fig S11</xref>). This finding indicates that the predominant pattern was not driven by genes with small expression change.</p><p id="P15">Functional analysis revealed a large number of GO terms with diverse biological functions in each group (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Table S2A</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD11">Fig. S5</xref>-S7). Genes in the ‘plateau’ group were enriched for GO terms such as ‘sexual reproduction’ (GO:0019953), ‘cytoplasmic translation’ (GO:0002181) and ‘renal system process’ (GO:0003014) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Table S2C</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD11">Fig. S5</xref>). In addition, the expression of the ‘plateau’ genes was enriched in rectal pads and testis (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Table S2C</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD11">Fig. S7</xref>). Female fecundity increased significantly after 7 generations, followed by a plateau (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1A</xref>). The enrichment of ‘plateau’ genes for reproduction-related GO categories and male reproductive tissue, i.e. testis, is synchronized with the stabilization of female fecundity that was observed in the evolved populations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1A</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S5"><title>Adaptation through diverse patterns of co-expression in differentially expressed genes</title><p id="P16">While ‘plateau’ group comprises the majority of expression changes, other conserved co-expression patterns also contribute to adaptation. The functional analysis of the monotonic genes showed enrichment of GO terms related to lipid metabolism such as ‘lipid catabolic process’ (GO:0016042), ‘fatty acid catabolic process’ (GO:0009062) and ‘fatty acid beta-oxidation using acyl-CoA oxidase’ (GO:0033540) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Table S2A</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD11">Fig. S5</xref>). To test whether the lipid content in the evolved populations has changed as predicted by the changes in expression of monotonic genes, we measured total lipid content in the founder and evolved populations from the same common garden experiment as the transcriptomic analysis. The lipid content in males in the evolved populations, similar to the expression pattern of the ‘monotonic’ group, had a gradual decrease compared to the founder population (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1C</xref>). On the other hand, the trade-off between fat storage and reproductive investment is demonstrated across various species, including both mammals and insects (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref>). Given the rapid and pronounced increase in fecundity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1A</xref>), we expected to observe a reduction in the fat storage. The decrease in lipid content in females demonstrated a comparable pattern to males, however the lipid content in the evolved populations was not statistically significant from the founder population (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1B</xref>). The significant increase in the female fecundity and decrease in the lipid content (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>) matched the widely observed relationship between reproduction investment and fat storage.</p><p id="P17">Unlike other groups, the expression trajectory of the ‘incomplete-reverse’ and ‘complete-reverse’ groups was altered after the initial phase of adaptation with expression in generation 31 resembling that of the founder population (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD11">S8-9</xref>). This pattern may be indicative of adaptation in response to the selection pressures experienced right after the environmental change. If the fitness costs of genes in ‘incomplete-reverse’ and ‘complete-reverse’ groups are high, their contribution could be substituted by other genes after the initial phase of adaptation. Overall, the expression trajectories of these genes demonstrate the robustness of gene regulatory networks. Interestingly, the trajectories of these genes have a comparable pattern to the changes in weight in both females and males (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD11">Fig. S3</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S6"><title>Temporal magnitude of phenotypic evolutionary change</title><p id="P18">We determined the magnitude of phenotypic changes from the onset of environmental shift across high-order and molecular phenotypes between different time points using Darwin’s numerator (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref>). Darwin quantifies the rate of change in a trait as the difference in the natural logarithm of population mean per million years. The time intervals between our phenotypic assays are different (7 generations between the founder and evolved population at generation 7 versus 24 generations between the evolved populations at generations 7 and 31). Since the phenotypic changes over longer time intervals is slower (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref>), instead of Darwin’s value, we present the absolute values of Darwin’s numerator, i.e. the difference between log-transformed phenotypic means at different time points.</p><p id="P19">The magnitude of phenotypic changes for the high-order traits in the first 7 generations was greater than changes in other <italic>Drosophila</italic> evolution experiments (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref>) in which smaller populations evolved 39 to 103 generations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4A</xref>). The phenotypic changes for the high-order traits were comparable (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4A</xref>) to the ones observed in evolution studies with large populations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref>). We also observed heterogeneity in the magnitude of phenotypic response across traits (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4A</xref>) as changes in fecundity were greater than changes in the weight and lipid content measured in females. Transcriptomic changes in our study were more pronounced than in other evolution experiments, including those on the same species adapting to new temperature regimes over 30–100 generations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref>) and a directional selection experiment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">20</xref>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4B</xref>). While gene expression continued to shift under ongoing directional selection in Souto-Maior et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">20</xref>) our populations showed rapid changes until generation 7, followed by a plateau through generation 31, indicating transcriptomic convergence (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4B</xref>).</p><p id="P20">Among the DEGs with conserved co-expression patterns ‘incomplete-reverse’, ‘plateau’, and ‘monotonic’ groups had the highest phenotypic change in the first 7 generations followed by a reduction until generation 31 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4C</xref>). The decrease in phenotypic change was especially pronounced for the ‘plateau’ group (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4C</xref>). The greater phenotypic change in the ‘monotonic’ and ‘incomplete-reverse’ groups from generations 7 and 31 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4C</xref>) is because of the continued change in expression levels (‘monotonic’ group) or a reversal in the direction of expression (‘incomplete-reverse’ group) relative to earlier time points. Interestingly, ‘incomplete-reverse’ group showed the largest early phenotypic change (first 7 generations) before the shift in the direction of expression toward the founder population level (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4C</xref>). This suggests the ‘incomplete-reverse’ group had a transient role in adaptation and contributed to transcriptomic resilience. In contrast, ‘late-response’ genes showed the smallest phenotypic change in the early phase of adaptation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4C</xref>), but the phenotypic changes remained consistent afterwards. Overall, the phenotypic changes were rapid after the environmental shift, followed by stagnation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S7"><title>Highly parallel adaptive responses among replicate populations</title><p id="P21">As populations evolve towards the new optimal phenotype, a different set of adaptive alleles may be selected in each replicate. This results in low similarity, i.e. parallelism, among the replicates at the genomic level (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">21</xref>). However, different sets of adaptive loci would lead to phenotypic convergence among replicates (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">22</xref>). Therefore, the degree of parallelism among replicates at the phenotypic level remains relatively stable when populations are close to the new optimum (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref>). We used temporal changes in parallelism among replicates as a proxy for proximity to the new optimum. If the replicates are near the optimum by generation 7 - as suggested by high-order (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1A</xref>) and molecular phenotypes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>-<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>) - then parallelism should remain stable between generations 7 and 31.</p><p id="P22">For the high-order phenotypes, i.e. fecundity and weight, replicates converged after 7 generations (except 2 replicates), and there was no significant difference between six replicates at generation 31 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD11">Fig. S12</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD4">Table S4</xref>). To compute the similarity, i.e. parallelism, of the DEGs between replicates, we first contrasted each replicate’s expression response to the founder population independently. Then, we computed similarity in DEGs between pairs of replicates using the Jaccard index, JI (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">23</xref>). The number of DEGs shared across all six replicates (2413 and 2399 genes at generation 7 and 31, respectively) are considerably higher than those that are specific to 1 to 5 replicates (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5A</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD11">S13</xref>). The average pairwise similarity between the replicates was relatively high at generations 7 (mean JI = 0.6665) and 31 (mean JI = 0.6640) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5B</xref>). Moreover, parallelism among replicates did not differ significantly between generations 7 and 31 (two-tailed Wilcoxon Rank sum test, <italic>p</italic>-value = 0.54) suggesting that the replicates were already close to the new optimal phenotype as early as generation 7. To test whether the high degree of parallelism among replicates was driven by the number of DEGs, we generated a null distribution using delete-D jackknifing. The observed mean Jaccard index among replicates significantly exceeded the null expectation (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD11">Fig. S14</xref>), confirming that the parallelism was not due to the number of DEGs.</p><p id="P23">As the identification of DEGs depends on the significance threshold of the differential expression tests, we additionally compared the magnitude and direction of gene expression change among the six replicates using Pearson’s coefficient of correlation (r). Transcriptomic responses were highly correlated between replicate pairs at each timepoint, with no significant difference between generations 7 and 31 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5C</xref>), supporting strong phenotypic parallelism.</p></sec><sec id="S8"><title>Contribution of pleiotropic genes to different phases of adaptation</title><p id="P24">Orr’s model of adaptation predicts that adaptation of a population towards a new fixed optimum occurs in steps of decreasing sizes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref>); the large effect alleles contribute to adaptation when the populations are far from the optimal phenotype, and that the contribution of small effect alleles increases as populations near the trait optimum. Orr’s model considers adaptation driven by successive fixations of de novo mutations. Recent theoretical works (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref>) have predicted the contribution of loci of varying effect sizes from standing genetic variants during polygenic adaptation, a scenario which matches our experiment. Hayward and Sella (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">4</xref>) demonstrated that the early directional phase was driven by moderate-to-large effect alleles, while the late stabilizing phase was shaped by moderate-to-small effect alleles. The overall response of the high-order (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1A</xref>) and molecular phenotypes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>-<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>) allowed us to differentiate the early phase of adaptation (i.e. the first 7 generations) from the late phase (from generation 7 to 31).</p><p id="P25">To test whether the contribution of genes with larger effects is higher in the early phase of adaptation we used the degree of pleiotropy of DEGs as a proxy for their effect sizes. Pleiotropy genes affect multiple traits, and highly pleiotropic genes have a larger per-trait effect, thus a higher overall effect size (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">26</xref>). We used two independent measures as proxies for pleiotropy for each gene: tissue specificity and level of connectivity in gene regulatory networks. Pleiotropic genes are less tissue-specific as they are involved in multiple functions in different tissues (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27">27</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">28</xref>). Pleiotropic genes also affect the expression of other genes thus have a higher number of connections in gene regulatory networks (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">29</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">30</xref>). Using two measures of pleiotropy provided a complementary approach for estimating pleiotropy, enabling us to evaluate the robustness of the observed patterns to the proxy used. Genes in the ‘complete-reverse’ group, which contributed to adaptation only until generation 7 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>) were significantly more pleiotropic than other groups using both proxies of pleiotropy (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6B</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD11">S15B</xref>). On the other hand, the ‘monotonic’ group where the change in expression level of genes did not reach a plateau even until generation 31, had significantly lower degree of pleiotropy (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6B</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD11">S15B</xref>). Apart from slight differences, tissue specificity and gene connectivity showed similar patterns (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6B</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD11">S15B</xref>). Taken together, these results, align with theoretical predictions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref>) and support that genes with a higher degree of pleiotropy (‘complete-reverse’ group) contribute solely to the early phase of adaptation when the population is far from the optimum. However, the contribution of highly pleiotropic genes is transient and restricted to early phase of adaptation compared to genes with lower pleiotropy (‘monotonic’, incomplete-reversed’, and ‘plateau’ groups) which maintained their modified expression levels until generation 31.</p></sec><sec id="S9"><title>Low-to-intermediate pleiotropy drives parallel adaptation</title><p id="P26">The contribution of highly pleiotropic genes to early adaptation prompted us to examine their overall contribution in adaptive phenotypic change. Pleiotropy is ubiquitous (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">3</xref>) but its role in adaptation is highly debated. Orr’s model of adaptation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31">31</xref>), which builds on Fisher’s geometric model (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32">32</xref>), assumes universal pleiotropy, and predicts that in complex organisms new mutations are more likely to reduce the overall fitness because they may negatively impact many traits, leading to slower adaptation. In other words, there is a cost to complexity/pleiotropy. However, due to greater per-trait effects of the highly pleiotropic genes and the high modularity of gene-trait relationship, pleiotropic genes can facilitate adaptation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">26</xref>). In our study, the change in expression of many genes have contributed to phenotypic evolution, and we assessed the extent to which pleiotropic genes contribute to this adaptation.</p><p id="P27">Based on the above theoretical predictions, we expected genes with stronger pleiotropic effects to be less favoured by selection (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31">31</xref>), but an intermediate level of pleiotropy would be beneficial (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">26</xref>). Thus, we tested the following hypotheses: 1) genes that do not change in expression (non-DEGs) and have not contributed to adaptation will have a higher degree of pleiotropy than DEGs, 2) the magnitude of gene expression changes will be smaller for more pleiotropic genes, and 3) less pleiotropic genes will contribute to adaptation by changing expression in more replicates, and thus have more repeatable patterns of gene expression across the replicates. First, the non-DEGs are significantly more pleiotropic than genes with significant expression changes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6A</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD11">S15</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD5">Table S5</xref>). Second, there was a negative correlation between the magnitude of change in gene expression and the degree of pleiotropy (both tissue specificity and gene connectivity) for all DEGs groups (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD11">Fig. S16</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD6">Table S6</xref>). In particular, groups with lower levels of pleiotropy (‘monotonic’ and ‘plateau’) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6B</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD11">S15B</xref>) had more pronounced phenotypic evolution (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>), while groups with the highest levels of pleiotropy (‘complete-reverse’ and ‘late-response’) showed less phenotypic change. Third, the genes with lower levels of pleiotropy, i.e. less constraints, had more parallel expression patterns across replicates (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6C</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD11">S15C</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD7">Table S7</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="S10" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p id="P28">Adaptation of a population after a sudden change in the trait optimum occurs through an exponential change in the phenotypic mean toward the new optimal value (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33">33</xref>). Adaptation of polygenic traits is predicted to occur in two phases (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref>); after a shift in the trait optimum, the mean phenotype changes rapidly towards the new trait optimum (directional phase). But the phenotypic change slows down to a pause when the population’s mean phenotype nears the optimum (stabilizing phase). Empirical studies to support these predictions should have temporal phenotypic data to trace the changes in population’s phenotypic mean, and keep the environment stable after the initial environmental shift. Additionally, replicates evolving in the same environment are needed to validate the repeatability of the phenotypic changes. Our evolution experiment was designed to meet these criteria.</p><p id="P29">We examined the phenotypic states of the populations before and after the environmental change in six replicates of <italic>D. simulans</italic> with an unprecedented population size of 100,000 individuals. Using temporal high-order and molecular phenotypic data we identified the adaptive phenotypic patterns from the onset of environmental change, and confirmed the predictions of phenotypic changes under the polygenic model of adaptation. The directional phase of adaptation after the environmental shift was characterized by the fast phenotypic changes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>). After the rapid phenotypic changes, the stabilizing phase of adaptation was marked by a decrease in the magnitude of phenotypic changes for both fecundity and gene expression. This indicates that the traits stabilized at values close to a new optimum (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4)</xref>.</p><p id="P30">The large proportion of ‘plateau’ genes (65%) suggests the proximity of the evolving populations to the new trait optimum, and hence a reduction in the strength of selection. In a truncation selection experiment where selection is constant throughout the experiment, the fraction of ‘plateau’ genes is expected to be smaller. Classification of the DEGs in a truncation selection experiment in <italic>D. melanogaster</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">20</xref>) based on their patterns of co-expression showed that the phenotypic changes were underlain by a large number of ‘late-response’ genes (55-61%), while the fraction of ‘plateau’ genes was rather small (12-15%) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD11">Fig S18</xref>). The different proportions of the ‘plateau’ and ‘late-response’ genes in these two experiments supports our hypothesis that the populations may be at different distances to their optimal phenotypes.</p><p id="P31">Overall, the phenotypic plateau of the evolving populations observed only seven generations after the optimum shift is supported by several lines of evidence: 1) the adaptive fecundity, i.e. fitness, increase reaches a plateau after 7 generations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1A</xref>), 2) a substantial fraction of DEGs (~4,000 genes, 65%) have reached stable expression levels at generation seven, 3) the mean magnitude of gene expression change (measured as the Darwin’s numerator, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4B</xref>) remain constant between generations 7 and 31, and 4) the degree of parallelism among replicates has stabilized (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD11">S12</xref>). We note that while we detected significant changes in fecundity and gene expression at generation 7, these changes may have occurred earlier. In contrast, the lack of stabilization of expression changes for ‘monotonic’ and ‘late-response’ genes may suggest that these genes contribute to the traits for which their optimal values have not yet been reached, e.g. lipid content (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1B</xref>). Furthermore, these genes may play a role in fine-tuning gene expression and the phenotypic state of populations that are close to, but not quite at, the new phenotypic optimum.</p><p id="P32">The magnitude of evolutionary changes varied among different high-order traits e.g. fecundity, weight, and lipid content (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>). This may be due to trait-specific biological or physiological constraints, or to the different distances to their respective optima. Interestingly, the rate of evolution of fecundity was faster than of other high-order female phenotypes, supporting the idea that fitness components are highly evolvable (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34">34</xref>). The value of a quantitative trait in a population at the fitness peak may represent the optimal phenotype in the environment (i.e. it may not be the maximum achievable value) or be constrained due to trade-offs with other phenotypes. We suspect that the observed stasis in fecundity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1A</xref>) is less likely to be due to constraints. Firstly, the maximum fecundity measured in our study (18-20 eggs/female/day, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD11">Fig. S17</xref>) is lower than the reported fecundity in <italic>Drosophila</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35">35</xref>). Secondly, the fecundity of one replicate at generation 7 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD11">Fig. S12</xref>) was significantly higher than that of other replicates, which then converged by generation 31.</p><p id="P33">The large population size of 100,000 individuals in each replicate and the experimental set-up, e.g. round-robin crossing of the founder population, may have contributed to the highly parallel response among the replicates. The adaptive responses are expected to be more parallel in larger populations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36">36</xref>). Rapid adaptation has been observed previously in large experimental populations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref>). Additionally, the round robin crossing scheme employed in the generation of the founder population may have led to more homogenous fitness values among individuals as maintenance of genetic variation can be maximized by crossing the founder lines (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37">37</xref>). Altogether, using large population sizes has improved our ability to infer the phenotypic patterns of polygenic adaptation in short evolutionary timescales as has been demonstrated by simulations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref>).</p><p id="P34">The contribution of pleiotropic genes to adaptation varied in short- versus long-term. The ‘complete-reverse’ group, with significantly higher pleiotropy than other groups, contributed to phenotypic changes immediately following environmental change (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6B</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD11">S15B</xref>). In contrast, ‘monotonic’ group, with consistent expression changes even during the stasis phase of adaptation, has significantly lower pleiotropic levels (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6B</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD11">S15B</xref>). Highly pleiotropic genes have a greater per-trait effect (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">26</xref>). Thus, our findings support the predictions of theoretical models (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref>) that large-effect alleles mainly contribute to adaptation when the populations are far from the optimal phenotype, and that the contribution of small-effect alleles, i.e. less pleiotropic gene, increases as populations approach the new trait optimum. This finding is consistent with a previous study (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38">38</xref>), which found that the early adaptation was driven by highly pleiotropic genes.</p><p id="P35">The contribution of genes with varying degrees of pleiotropy to the two phases of adaptive phenotypic evolution (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6A</xref>) supports different theories about the role of pleiotropy in adaptation. On the one hand, our results suggest that cost of pleiotropy has imposed constraints on adaptation. First, the genes without expression change had higher level of pleiotropy than differentially expressed genes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6A</xref>). A similar pattern was observed in another evolution experiment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39">39</xref>). DEGs genes across multiple tissues in several species of <italic>Drosophilids</italic> were also more tissue-specific, i.e. less pleiotropic, than genes with conserved expression (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40">40</xref>). Second, genes with higher level of pleiotropy have smaller magnitude of expression change when compared to other groups of genes at the same time point (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD11">Fig. S16</xref>). Previous studies have reported a similar pattern (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41">41</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42">42</xref>). Third, differential expression of genes with higher level of pleiotropy are less repeatable across replicates (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6C</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD11">S15C</xref>). This is because the likelihood that the expression of the same gene will change in independent replicates, i.e., the degree of parallelism, may also be reduced by the cost of complexity. On the other hand, adaptive phenotypic changes in evolving populations were mainly driven by genes with low-to-intermediate levels of pleiotropy (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6B</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD11">S15B</xref>), which is in line with the predictions of Wang et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">26</xref>). Gene-trait networks are highly modular (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">26</xref>), and this modularity can alleviate some of the costs associated with pleiotropy because related traits can be affected synergistically. Therefore, pleiotropic genes can facilitate adaptation, especially when the fitness effects on focal and non-focal traits are positively correlated (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42">42</xref>).</p><p id="P36">In some study systems, such as plants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43">43</xref>), sticklebacks (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R44">44</xref>) and <italic>Drosophila</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39">39</xref>), parallel evolution has been driven by genes with high levels of pleiotropy. Meanwhile, genes with low levels of pleiotropy have been repeatedly selected in replicate plant populations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R45">45</xref>). These positive and negative relationships between pleiotropy and parallelism have been attributed to local and global adaptation, respectively (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43">43</xref>). For example, in small experimental populations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39">39</xref>), strong drift favours selection of highly pleiotropic loci, potentially leading to different trait optima across replicates. Therefore, selection of large-effect pleiotropic loci would be more repeatable across replicates. In contrast, larger populations (as in this study) experience weaker drift, allowing convergence on a shared trait optimum using genes with intermediate-to-low pleiotropy. However, other reasons could also explain the contradictory observations in evolution experiments. Firstly, the repeatability of selection for highly pleiotropic genes in independent replicates may depend on their synergistic or antagonistic effects. Highly pleiotropic genes with synergistic effects on multiple traits can facilitate adaptation in replicates, while genes with antagonistic effect would constrain it. However, if the antagonistic effects of pleiotropic genes significantly impact fitness, then the repeated patterns of adaptation may be driven by low-to-intermediate level pleiotropic genes instead. Secondly, if the shift in optimum is not equal for the selected traits during adaptation, their covariance may change, which could determine the contribution of genes with certain levels of pleiotropy. Typically, several traits are under selection during adaptation. If these traits have high covariance and therefore undergo similar shifts in optimum, highly pleiotropic genes would be advantageous and could lead to a more consistent evolutionary response. However, a greater trade-off arises if the magnitude of the shift in optima differs across the selected traits. Therefore, highly pleiotropic loci would not be repeatedly selected in replicates.</p></sec><sec id="S11" sec-type="materials | methods"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="S12"><title>Founder population</title><p id="P37">The outcrossed founder population was set up from 93 inbred lines from a North American <italic>Drosophila simulans</italic> panel (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R46">46</xref>) following a two-way round-robin crossing scheme (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD11">Fig. S1</xref>). A total of 93 crosses were set up from all inbred lines. Each cross was maintained in a bottle with roughly 100 individuals and were let to randomly mate for 15 generations to facilitate recombination and generation of new haplotypes. The crosses were maintained on a standard high-carbohydrate diet with a protein to carbohydrate (P:C) ratio of 1:4 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD11">Fig. S2</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table S1</xref>) at 25°C, and a light cycle of 12:12 hrs light and dark. A total of 1075 individuals from each cross (total of 93 crosses) were pooled to establish the founder population with 100,000 individuals.</p></sec><sec id="S13"><title>Evolution experiment</title><p id="P38">The founder population was exposed to a novel high-protein diet with protein to carbohydrate (P:C) ratio of 1:1 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD11">Fig. S2</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table S1</xref>). Six replicates were established from the founder population through sequential egg-laying periods as follows; the founder population with 100,000 individuals were allowed to lay eggs on 30 trays (3.6x15x 22cm depth, WEBER®) of high-protein (1:1 P:C) food for 2 days. After 2 days, the trays of food were used to set up one replicate. After establishing 3 replicates, the egg-laying period was extended to 3 days due to a decrease in fecundity as individuals aged. A total of 6 replicates were set up from the founder population. Each replicate was maintained with a census size of 100,000 individuals in a large mesh cage (120x60x60 cm, BugDorm-6M620 Insect Rearing Cage, Bugdorm) at 25°C, with a light cycle of 12:12 hrs light and dark, with non-overlapping generations. The cages were maintained in a room with controlled temperature and humidity (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD11">Fig. S19</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S14"><title>Times-series phenotypic assays</title><sec id="S15"><title>Common garden experiments</title><p id="P39">We performed several phenotypic assays on 1) the founder population before exposure to the high-protein diet at generation 0 (gen0), 2) the replicates after 7 (gen7) and 31 generations (gen31) of adaptation. For the common garden experiment at generation 0 (CGE-0), equal numbers (172 individuals) of 93 round-robin cross were pooled (a total of 16,000 individuals) on standard high-carbohydrate diet, and the eclosed adults were used to set up 10 replicates (each roughly 1,600 individuals). To phenotype the evolving replicates at generations 7 (CGE-7) and 31 (CGE-31), around 1000 individuals were collected from each replicate, and used to set up 3 sub-replicates. At each time point (generations 0, 7, and 31) the populations were maintained in a common garden environment for two generations on high-protein (1:1 P:C) diet at low density (400 eggs per bottle) before phenotyping to minimize the transgenerational effects. Eclosed individuals after two generations of maintenance in a common garden experiment were allowed to mate for 24 hours. In the following 3 days, females and males were separated while anesthetized with CO2. After 2 days of recovery from CO2, 6-days-old flies were flash frozen in liquid nitrogen and stored at -80°C. These samples were used for RNA sequencing and lipid content quantification.</p></sec><sec id="S16"><title>Fecundity assay and statistical analysis</title><p id="P40">Freshly eclosed individuals after 2 generations of maintenance in common garden were collected to measure female fecundity. In CGE-0, we measured fecundity in 10 replicates of the founder population (each with 3 sub-replicates), thus a total of 30 sub-replicates. In CGE-7 and CGE-31, fecundity was measured in 3 sub-replicates for each of the 6 evolved populations, a total of 18 sub-replicates. For each sub-replicate, roughly 100 freshly eclosed individuals were transferred to an embryo collection cage (Cat. #59–101, Genesee Scientific, San Diego, California) with a Petri-dish containing black media. The Petri-dish was changed twice a day for a week, photographed and the number of eggs were counted following the protocol in (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R47">47</xref>). Fecundity was measured for 7 days which spans the age of individuals during the maintenance of the populations in the evolution experiment. Females and males in each sub-replicate were counted, dried at 60°C for 24 hours, and weighed. Fecundity was measured as the total number of eggs laid over seven days per female. Weight was measured as the average dry mass (mg) per fly.</p><p id="P41">To assess the significance of changes in <italic>fecundity</italic> between the founder and evolved populations we used a linear mixed model using R package lme4 (version = 1.1.35.5) with <italic>generation</italic> as a fixed categorical effect with three levels (0, 7, and 31). We included <italic>replicate</italic> as random intercept with six levels (replicates 1 to 6) and uncorrelated, dummy coded centered <italic>generation</italic> as random slope to account for the hierarchical covariance structure in our data. <italic>Weight</italic> was used as a fixed continuous effect. <disp-formula id="FD1"><mml:math id="M1"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>~</mml:mo><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>‖</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>ε</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="P42">We also tested the divergence of <italic>fecundity</italic> among the 6 evolved replicates at each generation by fitting a linear model with <italic>replicate</italic> used as a fixed effect (with 6 levels). <italic>Weight</italic> was used as a fixed continuous effect. We fitted separate models for generation 7 and 31. We used the option REML = FALSE to request maximum likelihood estimation, which provides more accurate estimates for the fixed effects when comparing models. <disp-formula id="FD2"><mml:math id="M2"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>~</mml:mo><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>ε</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="P43"><italic>fecundity</italic> was log<sub>10</sub>-transformed to meet the assumptions of normality of residuals, and heterogeneity of variance. To test for the significance, we performed pairwise post-hoc tests using function <italic>emmeans</italic> from package <italic>emmeans</italic> with option <italic>pairwise</italic>, and corrected the <italic>p</italic> values applying the Tukey’s honest significant difference (HSD).</p><p id="P44">We also tested for the significance of changes in <italic>weight</italic> between the founder and evolved populations using a linear mixed-effects model with option REML = FALSE. We included <italic>generation</italic> as a fixed categorical effect with three levels (0, 7, and 31), and <italic>sex</italic> as a fixed categorical effect with two levels (female, male), along with their interaction. To make the variance homogeneous, we aggregated sub-replicate data by computing the mean weight for each replicate, sex, and generation combination. We included r<italic>eplicate</italic> as a random intercept with six levels (replicates 1 to 6). We used the to request maximum likelihood estimation, which provides more accurate estimates for the fixed effects when comparing models. <disp-formula id="FD3"><mml:math id="M3"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>W</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>~</mml:mo><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>∣</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>ε</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="P45">To test the divergence of <italic>weight</italic> among the replicates at each generation we fitted a mixed-effects model with <italic>replicate</italic> as a fixed effect with six levels (replicates 1 to 6). We fitted separate models for generations 7 and 31, and for each sex independently because the full model did not meet the assumption of homogeneity of variance. <italic>weight</italic> was log<sub>10</sub>-transformed. <disp-formula id="FD4"><mml:math id="M4"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>W</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>~</mml:mo><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>ε</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="P46">To test for the significant phenotypic changes in <italic>weight</italic>, pairwise post-hoc tests was performed as described above. <italic>P</italic>-values across all contrasts were corrected using FDR (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R48">48</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S17"><title>Lipid content assay and statistical analysis</title><p id="P47">We measured the amount of triglyceride (TAG) as the main constituent of body fat using coupled colorimetric assay as described in (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref>). Lipid content was measured in 8-10 sub-replicates for each sex of the founder population in CGE-0. For the evolved populations, lipid content was measured in 3 sub-replicates of each replicate for each sex in CGE-7 and CGE-31. For each sub-replicate, a total of six to nine 6-days-old flies were weighed and homogenized in 500μl PBST (1% Triton X-100) using an electric mortar (VWR®). The homogenates were incubated for 10 minutes at 70°C to inactivate enzymes, then centrifuged at 350 rpm for 3 minutes at 4°C. The supernatant was frozen at -80°C until quantification. We used a glycerol standard (Sigma G7793) with the following concentrations (1.2, 1, 0.8, 0.6, 0.4, 0.2, 0.1, 0 mg/mL) as reference. A total of 50 μL of supernatant and standard was transferred to a well in a 96-well plate. Samples were measured in duplicates. The initial absorbance was measured at 540 nm with the EnSpire 2300 Microplate Reader (PerkinElmer). Then, 200 μL of Triglyceride Working Reagent (TR22421 Thermo Fisher) was added to each well. The mixture was incubated at 37°C for 30 minutes with gentle agitation. The final absorbance was measured at 540 nm. All measurements were blank-corrected. The difference between the initial and final absorbance was attributed to the change in absorbance resulting from the conversion of triglyceride. Standard curves were made by fitting an inverse polynomial regression line, and were used to estimate the concentration of TAG. The technical replicates of each sample were used to calculate the coefficient of variation (CV) where <italic>S1</italic> and <italic>S2</italic> are the concentrations of technical replicates 1 and 2, and <italic>m</italic> is the mean. The concentration of TAG in samples with CV &gt; 10% were repeated. The estimated amount of TAG for each sample was the average of its two technical replicates. <disp-formula id="FD5"><mml:math id="M5"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo>|</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>|</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mo>|</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>|</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="P48">The lipid content was expressed as μg TAG equivalents per fly. We tested for the significance of changes in lipid content between the founder and evolved populations using a linear mixed-effects model with option REML = FALSE. We included <italic>generation</italic> as a fixed categorical effect with three levels (0, 7, and 31), and <italic>sex</italic> as a fixed categorical effect with two levels (female, male), along with their interaction. We used <italic>weight</italic> (wet mg per fly) as a fixed continuous effect. We aggregated sub-replicate data similar to above. <italic>TAG</italic> was log<sub>10</sub>-transformed. <italic>Replicate</italic> was included as a random intercept with six levels (replicates 1 to 6). The significance of phenotypic changes in TAG, and correction of <italic>p</italic>-values were done as described above.<disp-formula id="FD6"><mml:math id="M6"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>~</mml:mo><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mo>*</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>∣</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>ε</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p></sec></sec><sec id="S18"><title>Transcriptome analysis</title><sec id="S19"><title>RNA extraction and sequencing</title><p id="P49">We extracted total RNA from 5 sub-replicates of the founder population (CGE-0), 18 sub-replicates (3 sub-replicates for each replicates) in CGE-7 and 18 sub-replicates in CGE-31. For each sample, RNA was extracted from fifty 6-days-old males using TRIzol™ Reagent (Invitrogen) following the manufacturer protocol, and the reagent volume was adjusted to the sample. The extracted RNA was frozen at -80°C. RNA libraries were constructed using NEB poly-A enrichment multiplexed with dual indices. All samples were sequenced on the same lane on Illumina NovaSeq S4 PE150 XP platform.</p></sec><sec id="S20"><title>RNA-Seq data processing</title><p id="P50">The paired-end 150bp reads were mapped to <italic>D.simulans</italic> reference genome (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R49">49</xref>) using GSNAP (version = 2023.03.24) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R50">50</xref>) with parameters -A SAM -k 15 -N 1 -m 0.08. Read quality was checked for 3’ bias using RSeQC (Version 5.0.1) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R51">51</xref>), the gene body coverage was similar in all samples. The number of reads aligned to the exons was counted using <italic>featureCounts</italic> function of <italic>subread</italic> (version = 2.0.3) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R52">52</xref>) with parameters: -T 8 -s 0 -p --countReadPairs -B -t exon -g gene_id -Q 10 -C. The mapping statistics generated using SAMtools (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R53">53</xref>) (version = 1.16.1), and the statistics from <italic>subread</italic> mapping are presented in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD8">Table S8</xref>-<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD9">S9</xref>, respectively.</p></sec><sec id="S21"><title>Differential gene expression analysis</title><p id="P51">Gene expression data were normalized by library size using the <italic>cpm</italic> function in <italic>edgeR</italic> package (version 4.2.2) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R54">54</xref>), and presented as counts per million (CPM). Genes with low expression were filtered out, keeping only those with at least one CPM in all samples. We used the <italic>voomWithDreamWeights</italic> function in the <italic>variancePartition</italic> package (version 1.23.3) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R55">55</xref>) to compute log2-transformed CPM and estimate weights. We modeled the effect of evolution on gene expression, by fitting a linear mixed model (‘overall-model’) for each gene using <italic>dream</italic> function in <italic>variancePartition.</italic> We used log2 gene expression (<italic>Y</italic>) as the response variable, <italic>generation</italic> (0, 7 and 31) as a fixed categorical effect, and <italic>ε</italic> was the random error. Each replicate was phenotyped multiple times (at generation 7 in CGE-7 and at generation 31 in CGE-31), and a total of 3 sub-replicates were measured for each replicate. To account for this hierarchical covariance structure, we used an uncorrelated random intercept, random slope model. Random slopes were dummy coded and centered. <disp-formula id="FD7"><mml:math id="M7"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>‖</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>ε</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="P52">We used the <italic>eBayes</italic> function in the <italic>variancePartition</italic> package on the output of the <italic>dream</italic> function to compute moderated t-statistics and reduce the number of false positives. We performed differential gene expression analysis using three contrasts: a) generation 7 (CGE-7) vs. generation 0 (CGE-0), b) generation 31 (CGE-31) vs. generation 0 (CGE-0), and c) generation 31 (CGE-31) vs. generation 7 (CGE-7). The significance level was set at 5% after multiple testing correction using FDR (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R48">48</xref>) across all three contrasts. The magnitude of the gene expression change was expressed as the log2 fold change (log<sub>2</sub>FC).</p><p id="P53">Additionally, we assessed the replicate-specific gene expression response for each replicate separately (‘replicate-specific models’). We used log<sub>2</sub> gene expression (<italic>Y)</italic> as the response variable, and <italic>generation</italic> as a categorical fixed effect with 3 levels (0, 7, and 31). <disp-formula id="FD8"><mml:math id="M8"><mml:mrow><mml:munder accentunder="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">_</mml:mo></mml:munder><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>ε</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="P54">Similar to the ‘overall-model’ we performed differential gene expression analysis using three contrasts. Multiple testing corrections were performed across three contrasts and all 6 replicates. This ensured that the multiple testing correction to be as stringent as in the ‘overall-model’, i.e., with a similar number of tests. There was a high overlap in terms of the identified DEGs by the overall model and the replicate-specific models (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD11">Fig. S20A</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S22"><title>Patterns of co-expression in differentially expressed genes</title><p id="P55">The DEGs were classified into five groups based on the significance and direction of change in expression as determined by the differential gene expression analysis model. <list list-type="simple" id="L1"><list-item><label>1)</label><p id="P56">The ‘plateau’ group contained genes that their expressions significantly changed in both evolved time points, CGE-7 and CGE-31, compared to the founder population, CGE-0 (<italic>p</italic> value &lt; 0.05), but no significant change was observed between two evolved time points, CGE-7 and CGE-31 (<italic>p</italic> value &gt; 0.05).</p></list-item><list-item><label>2)</label><p id="P57">Genes in the ‘monotonic’ group, similar to the ‘plateau’ genes showed a significant change in expression at both evolved time points, CGE-7 and CGE-31, compared to the founder population, CGE-0. But unlike the ‘plateau’ genes, the expression between CGE-7 and CGE-31 was significant. The direction of change in the expression of these genes (either decreasing or increasing) was consistent across all time intervals.</p></list-item><list-item><label>3)</label><p id="P58">Genes in the ‘complete-reverse’ group had significant expression changes in CGE-7 compared to CGE-0. After CGE-7, the expression level reverted to the level observed in CGE-0.</p></list-item><list-item><label>4)</label><p id="P59">The gene expression patterns in the ‘incomplete-reverse’ group were similar to the ‘complete-reverse’ group. However, the expression changes between the last time point (CGE-31) and the founder population (CGE-0) were significant (<italic>p</italic>-value &lt; 0.05).</p></list-item><list-item><label>5)</label><p id="P60">Genes in the ‘late-response’ group had significant expression changes in the last time point (CGE-31) compared to the founder population (CGE-0). However, the expression of these genes was not significant in the first time point (CGE-7) compared to the founder population (CGE-0). Similar to the ‘monotonic’ group, the direction of gene expression changes was consistent across all time intervals.</p></list-item></list></p><p id="P61">To ensure that the patterns of co-expression were not driven by genes with small changes in expression, we classified only the DEG with absolute expression change higher than 0.32 into groups using the above criteria. Additionally, we performed a similar classification of DEGs for the temporal male transcriptomic data in a truncation selection experiment in <italic>Drosophila</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">20</xref>). We first modelled the gene expression across 14 time points, then performed contrasts using time intervals that best aligned with our experiment: generation 0 to 7 (fully matching our early evolution phase), from generation 7 to 13 (the latest available time point) as well as the contrast between generations 7 and 13. The classification of DEGs into groups with conserved patterns of co-expression was done using the above criteria.</p></sec><sec id="S23"><title>Gene ontology, pathway, and tissue enrichment analyses</title><p id="P62">We used the topGO package (<italic>version = 2.56.0</italic>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R56">56</xref>) to perform gene ontology (GO) enrichment analysis. We ran a weighted Fisher’s exact test for each gene set using the <italic>Weighted01</italic> algorithm. We performed tissue enrichment using the expression data for 15 tissues in males available in the <italic>FlyAtlas2</italic> dataset (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R57">57</xref>). We first determined the tissue-specific genes by comparing the tissue gene expression levels with that of the whole-body, and genes with more than 2-fold expression in a certain tissue were classified as tissue-specific. Subsequently, we performed Fisher’s exact test for each tissue and gene set. Pathway enrichment was conducted with <italic>clusterProfiler</italic> package (version= 4.10.0) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R58">58</xref>) using the Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes and Genomes database (KEGG) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R59">59</xref>). The background lists for all enrichment tests consisted of all expressed genes (10,197 genes). <italic>P</italic>-values were corrected using FDR (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R48">48</xref>) across all contrasts in tissue and pathways enrichment. We did not correct <italic>p</italic>-values from GO enrichment as suggested by the developers of topGO (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R56">56</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S24"><title>Magnitude of phenotypic evolution (Darwin numerator)</title><p id="P63">We computed the magnitude of phenotypic changes in Darwin, which expresses the evolutionary change as a factor of the base of natural logarithm (<italic>e</italic>) per million years. The time intervals between our phenotypic assays are not equal (7 versus 24 generations), therefore, following (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref>) we calculate Darwin numerator (the phenotypic change between different timepoints in natural-logarithm scale). We present the absolute Darwin numerator as the magnitude, not the direction, of phenotypic change is relevant. We computed Darwin numerator using the following formula (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref>) where <italic>y2</italic> and <italic>y1</italic> are the mean values of the log-transformed trait measured at different generations. <disp-formula id="FD9"><mml:math id="M9"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>ln</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">¯</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>ln</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">¯</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="P64">We quantified Darwin numerator for two time intervals: 1) between generation 0 and 7, and 2) between generation 0 and 31. To compute Darwin numerator for fecundity, weight and lipid content, we used the mean phenotype across six evolved replicates where the phenotype of each replicate is the average of 3 sub-replicates. The phenotype of the founder population is the average of 8-10 sub-replicates. For gene expression, Darwin numerator was computed for each gene separately. The gene expression in each evolved replicate was summarized as the mean expression level (CPM) across 3 sub-replicates. The expression of each gene at each time point is the mean expression level across six evolved replicates. Gene expression in the founder population is the average of gene expression in 5 sub-replicates. Note that all phenotypes were log-transformed before calculating the means.</p></sec><sec id="S25"><title>Parallelism in patterns of gene expression</title><p id="P65">We quantified the similarity of DEGs among the replicates, i.e. parallelism, using Jaccard index (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">23</xref>). We identified the DEGs independently in each replicate in generations 7 and 31 (CGE-7 and CGE-31) compared to the founder population (CGE-0). The Jaccard index was calculated using the following formula, where A and B are any two replicates: <disp-formula id="FD10"><mml:math id="M10"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>J</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>∩</mml:mo><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>∪</mml:mo><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="P66">At each time point, all pairwise comparisons were performed between six evolved replicates. A two-sided Wilcoxon rank-sum test was used to assess the difference between generations 7 and 31. Additionally, we quantified the similarity between the replicates based on the correlation in their transcriptomic response. We computed Pearson’s correlation coefficients of the expression response (log<sub>2</sub>FC) using the full transcriptome after filtering lowly expressed genes for each replicate dataset (the numbers of genes after filtering ranged from 10397 genes to 10476 genes).</p><p id="P67">To ensure that the high parallelism between replicates was not due to the high number of DEGs, we generated 1000 sets each consisting of six replicates using delete-D jackknifing. In each set, the number of DEGs for each replicate matched the number of DEGs identified in ‘replicate-specific models’, which ranged from 3647 to 4282 genes, but was randomly drawn (without replacement) from the total expressed genes after filtering out low expressed genes (n = 10197 genes). In each set, the pairwise Jaccard index was computed between six evolved replicates. We compared the empirical mean Jaccard Index with this null distribution.</p></sec><sec id="S26"><title>Pleiotropy degree of differentially expressed genes</title><p id="P68">We quantified the degree of pleiotropy using two independent indices: network connectivity and tissue specificity. Genes with a higher number of connections in regulatory networks affect the expression of many gene, and are more pleiotropic (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">29</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">30</xref>). In a gene regulatory network, the pleiotropic degree of a gene is determined by the number of genes that are affected by the focal gene. Thus, gene connectivity, i.e. the sum of all connections for each gene in a gene regulatory network, can be used as a proxy of pleiotropy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41">41</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42">42</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R44">44</xref>). We computed the number of connections for each gene using the reconstructed gene regulatory network in <italic>D.melanogaster</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R60">60</xref>). Moreover, pleiotropic genes are expressed in more tissues as they are involved in multiple functions in different tissues (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27">27</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R61">61</xref>). Tissue specificity (tau) is a proxy of pleiotropy which measures the homogeneity of expression for a given gene across different tissues. We measured tissue specificity (tau) as described in (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R61">61</xref>) using tissue-specific gene expression dataset in FlyAtlas2 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R57">57</xref>). We used male expression data from 15 tissues and excluded genes with zero expression across all tissues. <disp-formula id="FD11"><mml:math id="M11"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:msub><mml:mi>∑</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mi>max</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="P69"><italic>τ</italic> (Tau) is the coefficient of tissue specificity for a set of tissues (<italic>N</italic>), <italic>FPKMi</italic> (Fragments Per Kilobase of transcript per Million mapped reads) is the normalized expression value of a gene in tissue <italic>i</italic>, <italic>FPKMmax</italic> is the maximum expression value of the gene across the assessed tissues, and <italic>N</italic> is the number of assessed tissues. Tau ranges from 0 (uniform expression across tissues) to 1 (expression specific to one tissue). 1-Tau shows the degree of pleiotropy.</p><p id="P70">We measured pleiotropy using both indices for all DEGs and the five co-expression pattern groups. We also computed the Kendall’s tau rank correlation between the absolute expression change (log<sub>2</sub>FC) and pleiotropy for each transcriptomic group and generation. Furthermore, we tested whether the degree of pleiotropy is associated with the number of replicates in which a given gene is differentially expressed, i.e. the level of parallelism. We only included the DEGs that were identified in 2 replicates and had the same direction of expression change across the replicates. The significance of the degree of pleiotropy between different groups was tested using the Wilcoxon rank sum test, and <italic>p</italic>-values were corrected using FDR (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R48">48</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S27"><title>Data analysis and visualization</title><p id="P71">All data analysis, statistical tests, and visualization were performed in R Statistical Software (v4.3.0, R Core Team).</p></sec></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="SM"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1"><label>Supplemental Table 1</label><media xlink:href="EMS206472-supplement-Supplemental_Table_1.xlsx" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.spreadsheetml.sheet" id="d83aAcEbB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD2"><label>Supplemental Table 2</label><media xlink:href="EMS206472-supplement-Supplemental_Table_2.xlsx" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.spreadsheetml.sheet" id="d83aAcEcB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD3"><label>Supplemental Table 3</label><media xlink:href="EMS206472-supplement-Supplemental_Table_3.xlsx" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.spreadsheetml.sheet" id="d83aAcEdB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD4"><label>Supplemental Table 4</label><media xlink:href="EMS206472-supplement-Supplemental_Table_4.xlsx" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.spreadsheetml.sheet" id="d83aAcEeB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD5"><label>Supplemental Table 5</label><media xlink:href="EMS206472-supplement-Supplemental_Table_5.xlsx" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.spreadsheetml.sheet" id="d83aAcEfB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD6"><label>Supplemental Table 6</label><media xlink:href="EMS206472-supplement-Supplemental_Table_6.xlsx" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.spreadsheetml.sheet" id="d83aAcEgB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD7"><label>Supplemental Table 7</label><media xlink:href="EMS206472-supplement-Supplemental_Table_7.xlsx" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.spreadsheetml.sheet" id="d83aAcEhB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD8"><label>Supplemental Table 8</label><media xlink:href="EMS206472-supplement-Supplemental_Table_8.xlsx" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.spreadsheetml.sheet" id="d83aAcEiB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD9"><label>Supplemental Table 9</label><media xlink:href="EMS206472-supplement-Supplemental_Table_9.xlsx" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.spreadsheetml.sheet" id="d83aAcEjB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD10"><label>Supplemental Table 10</label><media xlink:href="EMS206472-supplement-Supplemental_Table_10.xlsx" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.spreadsheetml.sheet" id="d83aAcEkB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD11"><label>Supplementary Materials</label><media xlink:href="EMS206472-supplement-Supplementary_Materials.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" id="d83aAcElB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack id="S28"><title>Acknowledgement</title><p>We thank Paula Marconi and Magdalena Reitbauer for their help in maintaining the experimental populations, and Davide Salati for his help in the lipid measurements. We are grateful to Alexander Fedosov for his immense help in making many custom-made tools needed to maintain the large populations. We thank Claus Vogl and Andreas Futschik for their constructive suggestions, and all members of the Institute of Population Genetics for helpful discussion. RNA library preparation and sequencing were performed by the Next Generation Sequencing Facility at Vienna BioCenter Core Facilities (VBCF), member of the Vienna BioCenter (VBC), Austria. This research was funded by the Austrian Science Fund (FWF) to N. B. (P32672 and SFB091) and by the Max Planck Society. The funders had no role in the study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</p></ack><sec id="S29" sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p id="P72">The raw RNA-Seq reads will be available from the European Nucleotide Archive under project PRJEB83201 (accession numbers in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD10">Table S10</xref>) upon publication. Phenotypic data (fecundity, weight, lipid content and RNA count table) will be released following publication. All scripts are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/ClaudiaRamL/BigCages_high_protein">https://github.com/ClaudiaRamL/BigCages_high_protein</ext-link>.</p></sec><fn-group><fn id="FN1" fn-type="conflict"><p id="P73"><bold>Competing interests</bold></p><p id="P74">The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><ref id="R1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arnold</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Introduction</chapter-title><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Arnold</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group><source>Evolutionary Quantitative Genetics</source><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name><year>2023</year><comment>0</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mackay</surname><given-names>TFC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The genetic architecture of quantitative traits: lessons from Drosophila</article-title><source>Curr Opin Genet Dev</source><year>2004</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>253</fpage><lpage>257</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15172667</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Simons</surname><given-names>YB</given-names></name><name><surname>Bullaughey</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hudson</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name><surname>Sella</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A population genetic interpretation of GWAS findings for human quantitative traits</article-title><source>PLoS Biol</source><year>2018</year><volume>16</volume><elocation-id>e2002985</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5871013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29547617</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.2002985</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hayward</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name><name><surname>Sella</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Polygenic adaptation after a sudden change in environment</article-title><source>eLife</source><year>2022</year><volume>11</volume><elocation-id>e66697</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9683794</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36155653</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.66697</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jain</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Stephan</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rapid Adaptation of a Polygenic Trait After a Sudden Environmental Shift</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>2017</year><volume>206</volume><fpage>389</fpage><lpage>406</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5419483</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28341654</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1534/genetics.116.196972</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barghi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Schlötterer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Distinct Patterns of Selective Sweep and Polygenic Adaptation in Evolve and Resequence Studies</article-title><source>Genome Biol Evol</source><year>2020</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>890</fpage><lpage>904</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7313669</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32282913</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/gbe/evaa073</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Franssen</surname><given-names>SU</given-names></name><name><surname>Kofler</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Schlötterer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Uncovering the genetic signature of quantitative trait evolution with replicated time series data</article-title><source>Heredity</source><year>2017</year><volume>118</volume><fpage>42</fpage><lpage>51</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5176121</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27848948</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/hdy.2016.98</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stetter</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Thornton</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ross-Ibarra</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic architecture and selective sweeps after polygenic adaptation to distant trait optima</article-title><source>PLOS Genet</source><year>2018</year><volume>14</volume><elocation-id>e1007794</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6277123</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30452452</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1007794</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thornton</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Polygenic Adaptation to an Environmental Shift: Temporal Dynamics of Variation Under Gaussian Stabilizing Selection and Additive Effects on a Single Trait</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>2019</year><volume>213</volume><fpage>1513</fpage><lpage>1530</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6893385</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31653678</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1534/genetics.119.302662</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kawecki</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The Genomic Architecture of Adaptation to Larval Malnutrition Points to a Trade-off with Adult Starvation Resistance in Drosophila</article-title><source>Mol Biol Evol</source><year>2021</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>2732</fpage><lpage>2749</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8233504</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33677563</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/molbev/msab061</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barghi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genetic redundancy fuels polygenic adaptation in Drosophila</article-title><source>PLOSBiol</source><year>2019</year><volume>17</volume><elocation-id>e3000128</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6375663</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30716062</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.3000128</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mallard</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Nolte</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Tobler</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Kapun</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Schlötterer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A simple genetic basis of adaptation to a novel thermal environment results in complex metabolic rewiring in Drosophila</article-title><source>Genome Biol</source><year>2018</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>119</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6100727</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30122150</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13059-018-1503-4</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Graves</surname><given-names>JL</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genomics of Parallel Experimental Evolution in Drosophila</article-title><source>Mol Biol Evol</source><year>2017</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>831</fpage><lpage>842</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5400383</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28087779</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/molbev/msw282</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Finucane</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Partitioning heritability by functional annotation using genome-wide association summary statistics</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><year>2015</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>1228</fpage><lpage>1235</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4626285</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26414678</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng.3404</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maurano</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Systematic Localization of Common Disease-Associated Variation in Regulatory DNA</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2012</year><volume>337</volume><fpage>1190</fpage><lpage>1195</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3771521</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22955828</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1222794</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Flatt</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Aguilaniu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reproduction, Fat Metabolism, and Life Span: What Is the Connection?</article-title><source>Cell Metab</source><year>2013</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>10</fpage><lpage>19</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3567776</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23312280</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cmet.2012.12.003</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hendry</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Farrugia</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kinnison</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Human influences on rates of phenotypic change in wild animal populations</article-title><source>Mol Ecol</source><year>2008</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>20</fpage><lpage>29</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18173498</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hsu</surname><given-names>S-K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Rapid sex-specific adaptation to high temperature in Drosophila</article-title><source>eLife</source><year>2020</year><volume>9</volume><elocation-id>e53237</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7034977</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32083552</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.53237</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rudman</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Direct observation of adaptive tracking on ecological time scales in Drosophila</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2022</year><volume>375</volume><elocation-id>eabj7484</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10684103</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35298245</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.abj7484</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Souto-Maior</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Serrano Negron</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name><name><surname>Harbison</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nonlinear expression patterns and multiple shifts in gene network interactions underlie robust phenotypic change in Drosophila melanogaster selected for night sleep duration</article-title><source>PLOS Comput Biol</source><year>2023</year><volume>19</volume><elocation-id>e1011389</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10443883</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37561813</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1011389</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yeaman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Local Adaptation by Alleles of Small Effect</article-title><source>Am Nat</source><year>2015</year><volume>186</volume><fpage>S74</fpage><lpage>S89</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26656219</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>W-Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Otte</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Schlötterer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evolution of Metabolome and Transcriptome Supports a Hierarchical Organization of Adaptive Traits</article-title><source>Genome Biol Evol</source><year>2023</year><volume>15</volume><elocation-id>evad098</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10246829</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37232360</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/gbe/evad098</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jaccard</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><source>Nouvelles recherches sur la distribution florale</source><publisher-name>Rouge</publisher-name><year>1908</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Orr</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Population Genetics of Adaptation: The Distribution of Factors Fixed During Adaptive Evolution</article-title><source>Evolution</source><year>1998</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>935</fpage><lpage>949</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28565213</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Pleiotropic scaling of gene effects and the ‘cost of complexity.’</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2008</year><volume>452</volume><fpage>470</fpage><lpage>472</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18368117</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>B-Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genomic patterns of pleiotropy and the evolution of complexity</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci</source><year>2010</year><volume>107</volume><fpage>18034</fpage><lpage>18039</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2964231</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20876104</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1004666107</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mank</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hultin Rosenberg</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Zwahlen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ellegren</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pleiotropic Constraint Hampers the Resolution of Sexual Antagonism in Vertebrate Gene Expression</article-title><source>Am Nat</source><year>2008</year><volume>171</volume><fpage>35</fpage><lpage>43</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18171149</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A global overview of pleiotropy and genetic architecture in complex traits</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><year>2019</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>1339</fpage><lpage>1348</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31427789</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mähler</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Gene co-expression network connectivity is an important determinant of selective constraint</article-title><source>PLOS Genet</source><year>2017</year><volume>13</volume><elocation-id>e1006402</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5407845</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28406900</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1006402</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name><name><surname>Pavlicev</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheverud</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The road to modularity</article-title><source>Nat Rev Genet</source><year>2007</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>921</fpage><lpage>931</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18007649</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Orr</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Adaptation and the cost of complexity</article-title><source>Evol Int J Org Evol</source><year>2000</year><volume>54</volume><fpage>13</fpage><lpage>20</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10937178</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><source>The Genetical Theory of Natural Selection</source><publisher-name>Clarendon Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Oxford, UK</publisher-loc><year>1930</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1461012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10747041</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/genetics/154.4.1419</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lande</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Natural Selection and Random Genetic Drift in Phenotypic Evolution</article-title><source>Evolution</source><year>1976</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>314</fpage><lpage>334</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28563044</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Flatt</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Life-History Evolution and the Genetics of Fitness Components in Drosophila melanogaster</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>2020</year><volume>214</volume><fpage>3</fpage><lpage>48</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6944413</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31907300</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1534/genetics.119.300160</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>R’Kha</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Moreteau</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Coyne</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>David</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evolution of a lesser fitness trait: egg production in the specialist <italic>Drosophila sechellia</italic></article-title><source>Genet Res</source><year>1997</year><volume>69</volume><fpage>17</fpage><lpage>23</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9164172</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bolnick</surname><given-names>DI</given-names></name><name><surname>Barrett</surname><given-names>RDH</given-names></name><name><surname>Oke</surname><given-names>KB</given-names></name><name><surname>Rennison</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Stuart</surname><given-names>YE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>(Non)Parallel Evolution</article-title><source>Annu Rev Ecol Evol Syst</source><year>2018</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>303</fpage><lpage>330</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kutch</surname><given-names>IC</given-names></name><name><surname>McHugh</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Taggard</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Burke</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Crossing design shapes patterns of genetic variation in synthetic recombinant populations of Saccharomyces cerevisiae</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2021</year><volume>11</volume><elocation-id>19551</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8486856</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34599243</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-021-99026-0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hämälä</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Gorton</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Moeller</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Tiffin</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pleiotropy facilitates local adaptation to distant optima in common ragweed (Ambrosia artemisiifolia)</article-title><source>PLOS Genet</source><year>2020</year><volume>16</volume><elocation-id>e1008707</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7135370</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32210431</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1008707</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>W-Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Hsu</surname><given-names>S-K</given-names></name><name><surname>Futschik</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Schlötterer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pleiotropy increases parallel selection signatures during adaptation from standing genetic variation</article-title><source>eLife</source><year>2025</year><volume>13</volume><elocation-id>RP102321</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11996171</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40227842</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.102321</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bontonou</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Evolution of chemosensory tissues and cells across ecologically diverse Drosophilids</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2024</year><volume>15</volume><elocation-id>1047</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10844241</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38316749</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-023-44558-4</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R41"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Papakostas</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Gene pleiotropy constrains gene expression changes in fish adapted to different thermal conditions</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2014</year><volume>5</volume><elocation-id>4071</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4059932</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24892934</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncomms5071</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R42"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thorhölludottir</surname><given-names>DAV</given-names></name><name><surname>Nolte</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Schlötterer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Temperature-driven gene expression evolution in natural and laboratory populations highlights the crucial role of correlated fitness effects for polygenic adaptation</article-title><source>Evol Int J Org Evol</source><year>2023</year><volume>77</volume><fpage>2081</fpage><lpage>2089</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37455661</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R43"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Whiting</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The genetic architecture of repeated local adaptation to climate in distantly related plants</article-title><source>Nat Ecol Evol</source><year>2024</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>1933</fpage><lpage>1947</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11461274</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39187610</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41559-024-02514-5</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R44"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rennison</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Peichel</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pleiotropy facilitates parallel adaptation in sticklebacks</article-title><source>Mol Ecol</source><year>2022</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>1476</fpage><lpage>1486</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9306781</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34997980</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/mec.16335</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R45"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nocchi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Whiting</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Yeaman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Repeated global adaptation across plant species</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci</source><year>2024</year><volume>121</volume><elocation-id>e2406832121</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11670234</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39705310</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.2406832121</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R46"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Signor</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>New</surname><given-names>FN</given-names></name><name><surname>Nuzhdin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A Large Panel of Drosophila simulans Reveals an Abundance of Common Variants</article-title><source>Genome Biol Evol</source><year>2018</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>189</fpage><lpage>206</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5767965</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29228179</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/gbe/evx262</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R47"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nouhaud</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Mallard</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Poupardin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Barghi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Schlotterer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>High-throughput fecundity measurements in Drosophila</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2018</year><volume>8</volume><elocation-id>4469</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5849729</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29535355</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-018-22777-w</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R48"><label>48</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Benjamini</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Hochberg</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Controlling the False Discovery Rate: A Practical and Powerful Approach to Multiple Testing</article-title><source>J R Stat Soc Ser B Methodol</source><year>1995</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>289</fpage><lpage>300</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R49"><label>49</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Palmieri</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Nolte</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Schlötterer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genome assembly and annotation of a Drosophila simulans strain from Madagascar</article-title><source>Mol Ecol Resour</source><year>2015</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>372</fpage><lpage>381</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4344813</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24961367</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1755-0998.12297</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R50"><label>50</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><name><surname>Nacu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fast and SNP-tolerant detection of complex variants and splicing in short reads</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2010</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>873</fpage><lpage>881</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2844994</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20147302</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btq057</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R51"><label>51</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>RSeQC: quality control of RNA-seq experiments</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2012</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>2184</fpage><lpage>2185</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22743226</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R52"><label>52</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Smyth</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Subread aligner: fast, accurate and scalable read mapping by seed-and-vote</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2013</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>e108</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3664803</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23558742</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkt214</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R53"><label>53</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The Sequence Alignment/Map format and SAMtools</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2009</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>2078</fpage><lpage>2079</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2723002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19505943</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btp352</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R54"><label>54</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>McCarthy</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Smyth</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>edgeR: a Bioconductor package for differential expression analysis of digital gene expression data</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2010</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>139</fpage><lpage>140</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2796818</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19910308</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btp616</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R55"><label>55</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hoffman</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name><name><surname>Roussos</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dream: powerful differential expression analysis for repeated measures designs</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2021</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>192</fpage><lpage>201</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8055218</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32730587</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btaa687</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R56"><label>56</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alexa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rahnenführer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lengauer</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Improved scoring of functional groups from gene expression data by decorrelating GO graph structure</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2006</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>1600</fpage><lpage>1607</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16606683</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R57"><label>57</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krause</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Overend</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Dow</surname><given-names>JAT</given-names></name><name><surname>Leader</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>FlyAtlas 2 in 2022: enhancements to the Drosophila melanogaster expression atlas</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2022</year><volume>50</volume><fpage>D1010</fpage><lpage>D1015</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8728208</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34718735</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkab971</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R58"><label>58</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L-G</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>Q-Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>clusterProfiler: an R Package for Comparing Biological Themes Among Gene Clusters</article-title><source>OMICS J Integr Biol</source><year>2012</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>284</fpage><lpage>287</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3339379</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22455463</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/omi.2011.0118</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R59"><label>59</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kanehisa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Goto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>KEGG: Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes and Genomes</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2000</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>27</fpage><lpage>30</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC102409</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10592173</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/28.1.27</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R60"><label>60</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marbach</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Predictive regulatory models in Drosophila melanogaster by integrative inference of transcriptional networks</article-title><source>Genome Res</source><year>2012</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>1334</fpage><lpage>1349</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3396374</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22456606</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gr.127191.111</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R61"><label>61</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yanai</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genome-wide midrange transcription profiles reveal expression level relationships in human tissue specification</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2005</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>650</fpage><lpage>659</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15388519</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><title>Adaptive response of high-order phenotypes, fecundity (A) and lipid content (B,C).</title><p>A) Females from the evolved populations showed significantly higher fecundity at generations 7 and 31 compared to the founder population. Fecundity plateaued after generation 7, with no significant difference between generations 7 and 31. Fecundity is presented as the average number of eggs laid by a female during 7 days. B,C) In males, the amount of TAG was significantly less than in the founder population after 31 generations but not at generation 7. The lipid content in females from the evolved populations was not significantly different from the founder population. Asterisks indicate significance levels: <italic>p</italic>-value &lt; 0.01 (**), <italic>p</italic>-value &lt;0.001 (***), and <italic>p</italic>-value &lt; 0.0001 (****). Bars depict the predicted means of the linear mixed model, and error bars show the 95% confidence intervals of the least-square means.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS206472-f001"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><title>Highly correlated transcriptomic responses after 7 and 31 generations of adaptation.</title><p>There was a high correlation in the transcriptomic response of the evolved populations at generation 7 and 31 (Pearson correlation coefficient of log<sub>2</sub>FC = 0.96). Transcriptomic response is expressed as the log2 fold-change (log<sub>2</sub>FC) between the founder and evolved populations at generation 7 (x axis) and generation 31 (y axis). ‘Shared’ group: identified differentially expressed genes (DEGs) at both generations 7 and 31, ‘complete-reverse’ group: DEGs that are identified only at generation 7, and ‘late-response’ group: DEGs that are identified only at generation 31.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS206472-f002"/></fig><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><title>Evolutionary dynamics of differentially expressed genes (DEGs) with conserved co-expression patterns.</title><p>The pie chart which illustrates the proportion of DEGs in each group highlights that the expression of the majority of genes (65%) have reached a plateau. Principal Component Analysis (PCA) shows that the expression of the ‘plateau’ group has stabilized at generations 7 as PC1 and PC2 cannot distinguish between the evolved populations at generations 7 and 31. PCA depicts the directional continuous change in the expression of ‘monotonic’ and ‘late-response’ groups throughout time. However, the magnitude of expression changes at generation 7 is larger in the ‘monotonic’ group than the ‘late-response’ one. For ‘complete-reverse’ and ‘incomplete-reverse’ groups, the direction of expression change reverts to that of the founder population. However, the magnitude of expression change from generation 7 to 31 is higher in the ‘complete-reverse’ group. PCA was conducted on the scaled log2 per million (log2CPM) values of the DEGs in each group separately. The number of DEGs in each group is indicated in parentheses. Gen0, Gen7, and Gen31 correspond to gene expression at generations 0, 7, and 31, respectively. Each point represents a sub-replicate sample.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS206472-f003"/></fig><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><title>Rapid changes in fitness and gene expression after the environmental shift is followed by stasis.</title><p>A) Magnitude of the phenotypic change for high-order phenotypes across evolution experiments in <italic>Drosophila.</italic> ‘Outdoor cages’:<italic>D. melanogaster</italic>, population size = 100,000, exposed to a fluctuating environment, and phenotyped at three time points spanning a total of ~10 generations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref>). Darwin numerators correspond to intervals of 3, 6, and 10 generations. ‘LNS - high protein’: the current study, <italic>D. simulans</italic>, population size = 100,000, adaptation on a high-protein diet for 31 generations. ‘LNS hot I’: <italic>D. simulans</italic>, population size = 1250, evolved in a new hot temperature regime for &gt;100 generations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref>). ‘LNS hot II’: <italic>D. simulans</italic>, population size = 1000, evolved in a new hot temperature regime for 64 generations. ‘LNS cold’: <italic>D. simulans</italic>, population size = 1000, evolved in a new cold temperature regime for 39 generations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref>). In ‘LNS - high protein’, phenotypic changes between generations 0 and 7 are outlined in black. B) Magnitude of gene expression changes in <italic>Drosophila</italic> evolution experiments. ‘LNS Hot I’: the same population as in A, transcriptomic data from (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref>), ‘AS - Short Sleep Time’ : <italic>D. melanogaster</italic>, population size = 25, truncation selection on sleep duration for 13 generations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">20</xref>). C) The magnitude of gene expression change in groups with conserved co-expression patterns.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS206472-f004"/></fig><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><title>High similarity among the evolved replicate populations and the plateau of gene expression parallelism.</title><p>A) The number of DEGs across replicates at generations 7 and 31 using replicate-specific analysis shows that the majority of identified DEGs are shared across six replicates. The x axis shows the number of replicates where a gene was identified as differentially expressed. B) Two metrics of similarity in the transcriptomic response: 1) Jaccard index (JI, left panel) shows the pairwise proportion of DEGs (JI = 0; no overlap, JI= 1; complete sharing). There is a high level of parallelism at both generations (mean JI = 0.66) with no significant difference between the two time points (Wilcoxson rank sum test, two-tailed, <italic>p</italic>-value = 0.56). 2) Pairwise Pearson’s correlation coefficients (Right panel) of gene expression response (log<sub>2</sub>FC) in evolved replicates at generations 7 (Gen 7) and generation 31 (Gen31).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS206472-f005"/></fig><fig id="F6" position="float"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><title>Low pleiotropic genes facilitate adaptation and drive parallel changes among replicate populations.</title><p>A) Pleiotropy levels (tissue-specificity) of differentially expressed genes (DEGs) and non-differentially expressed genes (Non-DEGs) detected at generations 7 and/or 31 with available tissue specificity data (6,080 DEGs, and 3,682 non-DEGs). B) Pleiotropy levels of the DEGs groups with conserved patterns of co-expression. Two-tailed Wilcoxon rank-sum tests were conducted for two groups in (A) and all pairwise comparisons in (B). (*) <italic>p</italic>-value &lt; 0.05, (**) <italic>p</italic> -value &lt; 0.01, (***) <italic>p</italic>-value &lt;0.001 and (****) <italic>p</italic>-value &lt;0.0001. C) Pleiotropy levels (tissue-specificity) of DEGs across different numbers of replicates (e.g., group 2: DEGs shared by 2 replicates) show that genes with the highest level of parallelism (group 6) are significantly less pleiotropic than other groups (***, <italic>p</italic>-value &lt;0.001).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS206472-f006"/></fig></floats-group></article>