<!DOCTYPE article
 PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" article-type="preprint"><?all-math-mml yes?><?use-mml?><?origin ukpmcpa?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">bioRxiv</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>bioRxiv : the preprint server for biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2692-8205</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">EMS206455</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2025.06.09.658583</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="archive">PPR1035288</article-id><article-version-alternatives><article-version article-version-type="status">preprint</article-version><article-version article-version-type="number">1</article-version></article-version-alternatives><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Balance between autophagy and apoptosis determines anoikis resistance: a mathematical model on cell fate</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Maiti</surname><given-names>Sayoni</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chedere</surname><given-names>Adithya</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jolly</surname><given-names>Mohit Kumar</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chandra</surname><given-names>Nagasuma</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rangarajan</surname><given-names>Annapoorni</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CR1">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Interdisciplinary Programme in Mathematical Sciences, IISc Mathematics Initiative, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/04dese585</institution-id><institution>Indian Institute of Science</institution></institution-wrap>, <city>Bengaluru</city>, <country country="IN">India</country></aff><aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Department of Biochemistry, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/04dese585</institution-id><institution>Indian Institute of Science</institution></institution-wrap>, <city>Bengaluru</city>, <country country="IN">India</country></aff><aff id="A3"><label>3</label>Department of Bioengineering, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/04dese585</institution-id><institution>Indian Institute of Science</institution></institution-wrap>, <city>Bengaluru</city>, <country country="IN">India</country></aff><aff id="A4"><label>4</label>Department of Developmental Biology and Genetics, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/04dese585</institution-id><institution>Indian Institute of Science</institution></institution-wrap>, <city>Bengaluru</city>, <country country="IN">India</country></aff><author-notes><corresp id="CR1">
<label>*</label>Name and address for correspondence: Prof. Annapoorni Rangarajan, Department of Developmental Biology and Genetics, Indian Institute of Science, Bengaluru, Karnataka, India <email>anu@iisc.ac.in</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted"><day>14</day><month>06</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="preprint"><day>12</day><month>06</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><permissions><ali:free_to_read/><license><ali:license_ref>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is licensed under a <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">CC BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p id="P1">Although several cancer cells are shed into the circulation, most die due to the stresses they encounter. Detachment from the underlying extracellular matrix is one major stress; cell death due to matrix detachment is known as anoikis. Few cancer cells overcome this stress, become anoikis-resistant, and survive to seed metastasis. Autophagy, a cell survival mechanism during stressful conditions that promotes cellular homeostasis by recycling cellular components, is activated upon matrix detachment. On the other hand, apoptosis is a cellular mechanism that is responsible for programmed cell death which is also activated upon matrix detachment. It is unclear how matrix-deprived cancer cells maintain a balance between autophagy and apoptosis to decide the cell fate: whether the cell dies due to anoikis or acquires anoikis-resistance and survives to seed metastasis.</p><p id="P2">Though multiple pathways contribute to cell fate decisions, we have shown experimentally that autophagy and apoptosis are influenced by Akt-AMPK axis and AMPK-ERK axis in matrix-deprived cancer cells. Since Akt, AMPK and ERK are in turn linked to each other it is essential to understand how these proteins simultaneously affect the cell signaling and survival/death outcomes of matrix-deprived cancer cells. To study the cumulative effect of Akt-AMPK-ERK activities on survival/death decisions and to understand the fine balance between apoptosis and autophagy that facilitates the survival/death of matrix-deprived cancer cells, we formulated a deterministic ordinary differential equation (ODE)-based protein interaction model of anoikis resistance. Model stability analysis and 3D-nullcline analysis depicted that the system has a unique steady state in matrix-attached and matrix-deprived condition. Parameter sensitivity analysis depicted that the model is highly robust, and the model variables are sensitive to only a few model parameters. By simulating differential activity of pAkt, pAMPK and pERK, the model predicted a heterogeneity in pERK levels: high/low levels pERK along with high pAMPK enable survival as long as levels of pAkt are maintained low. Additionally, the model predicted a heterogeneity in pAMPK: high/low levels of pAMPK along with low pERK determines the shift from survival to death when levels of pAkt are high. Such high levels of pAkt are obtained at critically low levels of pERK. Molecular perturbation revealed a hierarchy among proteins while deciding the cell fate: pAkt dominates over pAMPK which further dominates over pERK and intermediate to high levels of pAkt were sufficient for apoptosis to surpass autophagy in matrix-detached cells. The model also predicted that Akt impacts apoptosis more than autophagy and classified the cell fate decision into survival and death zones in matrix-deprived condition. Overall, this work provided multiple insights on the molecular interplay among key kinases Akt, AMPK and ERK and their effects on apoptosis and autophagy. This model also depicted that autophagosome formation is rather robust as compared to apoptosis which is more sensitive to molecular perturbations. Hence, apoptosis emerged as a deciding factor that influences the decision of cell fate of a matrix-deprived cancer cell.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Metastasis</kwd><kwd>anoikis resistance</kwd><kwd>AMPK</kwd><kwd>Akt</kwd><kwd>ERK</kwd><kwd>autophagy</kwd><kwd>apoptosis</kwd><kwd>mathematical modeling</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="S1" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p id="P3">Metastasis is one of the primary causes of cancer-related mortality in most forms of solid tumors. It is a multistep biological process by which cancer cells detach from the primary site, intravasate into the vasculature, survive in the circulation, extravasate at a secondary site and develop into a secondary tumor (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">Chaffer and Weinberg, 2011</xref>). While all of the above steps are crucial to seed metastasis, the ability of the epithelial cancer cell to survive in an anchorage-independent manner is a critical step. As a barrier to developing metastases, cancer cells usually undergo apoptosis due to detachment from their extracellular matrix (ECM) by a process coined as “anoikis” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">Frisch and Francis,1994</xref>). Thus, tumor cells that acquire malignant potential have developed mechanisms to resist anoikis and thereby survive after detachment from their primary site and seed metastasis by a mechanism known as anoikis resistance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R49">Simpson et al., 2008</xref>).</p><p id="P4">Cancer cells acquire the resistance to anoikis by altering several signaling and metabolic pathways (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">Buchheit et al., 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37">Mason at al., 2017</xref>). A few signaling pathways known to regulate the cellular stress induced by matrix deprivation is along the Akt-AMPK-ERK axis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">Saha et al., 2018</xref>). Protein kinase B or Akt is another serine-threonine protein kinase that has emerged as a crucial regulator of widely divergent cellular processes including apoptosis, proliferation, differentiation, and metabolism (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40">Nicholson and Anderson, 2002</xref>). Although Akt has been extensively studied in solid tumors, its role in matrix-detached or migrating cancer cells is rather controversial. Some reports suggest that Akt activation is one of the most common mechanisms to achieve anoikis resistance in cancer cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43">Paoli et al., 2013</xref>). However, work from our lab showed that there is decrease in Akt activity in matrix-deprived cancer cells in multiple cell lines (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">Saha et al., 2018</xref>). AMP-activated protein kinase (AMPK) is a serine-threonine protein kinase that is a central regulator of cellular energy homeostasis and is known to get activated upon multiple bioenergetic stresses, such as, hypoxia, glucose deprivation, and matrix deprivation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">Bungard et al., 2010</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39">Ng et al., 2012</xref>). The RAS/RAF/MEK/ERK (Extracellular signal Regulated Kinase) pathway is a highly conserved signaling pathway which connects extracellular signals from cell surface receptors to machinery that regulates multiple critical physiological processes, including growth, proliferation, differentiation, migration, and apoptosis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31">Lavoie et al., 2020</xref>). ERK is shown to get activated in matrix-deprived state as compared to the matrix-attached state (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">Kumar et al., BioRxiv, 2019</xref>).</p><p id="P5">In addition to the intricate interplay of signaling pathways, anoikis resistance is also influenced by the balance between cell survival and cell death mechanisms which decides the fate of the cell. Numerous literatures have suggested that cell fate can be studied as a balance between autophagy and apoptosis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33">Liu et al., 2017</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R55">Tavassoly et al., 2015</xref>). Autophagy is the process by which cells degrade and recycle proteins and organelles to maintain intracellular homeostasis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34">Liu et al., 2023</xref>) and is also activated upon matrix detachment (Debnath, 2008; Fung et al., 2008). Generally, autophagy plays a protective role in cells, but disruption of autophagy mechanisms or excessive autophagic flux usually leads to cell death (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34">Liu et al., 2023</xref>). On the other hand, apoptosis is a cellular mechanism that is responsible for programmed cell death and is also activated upon matrix detachment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">Grossmann, J., 2002</xref>).</p><p id="P6">Prior work from our laboratory has shown that there is increase in the levels of active AMPK, ERK and decrease in the levels of active Akt upon matrix deprivation as compared to the matrix-attached state (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">Saha et al., 2018</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">Kumar et al., BioRxiv, 2019</xref>). We have also shown that there exists a double-negative feedback loop between AMPK and Akt in both matrix-attached and matrix-deprived condition (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">Saha et al., 2018</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">Chedere et al., 2021</xref>). Interestingly, though both pAMPK and pERK are found to be high in matrix-deprived condition, we have shown that upon AMPK inhibition by compound C, there is increase in ERK activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">Kumar et al., BioRxiv, 2019</xref>), and upon ERK inhibition by PD98059 there is increase in AMPK activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">Kumar et al., BioRxiv, 2019</xref>), suggesting a double-negative feedback loop between AMPK and ERK as well. Further, AMPK phosphorylates and activates PEA15, which prevents the activation of ERK (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">Hindupur et al., 2014</xref>). ERK has been shown to phosphorylate and inhibit LKB1, an upstream activator of AMPK, and thereby blocking the activation of AMPK by LKB1 in BRAF(V600E)-driven melanoma (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R58">Zheng et al., 2009</xref>). These indicate the existence of a double-negative feedback loop between AMPK and ERK in matrix-deprived condition. Though the Akt-ERK axis has not been explored enough in the matrix-detached state, literature shows that treating matrix-attached lung cancer cells with inhibitors of ERK signaling increased Akt phosphorylation while inhibition of Akt signaling increased ERK phosphorylation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R52">Stulpinas et al., 2023</xref>). Literature also shows that MEK inhibitor caused the induction in Akt activity in HER2-positive breast cancer (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">Chen et al., 2017</xref>), while ERK inhibition resulted in sustained Akt phosphorylation under the stress of low glucose in HEK 293 cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R48">Shin et al., 2015</xref>), and phosphorylation of Raf by Akt led to inhibition of ERK in MCF7 cell line (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38">Moelling et al., 2002</xref>). The above evidence indicates that there may exist a double-negative feedback between Akt and ERK as well.</p><p id="P7">Upon matrix deprivation, there is initiation of autophagy, but interestingly, the completion of autophagy is halted, and there is increase in apoptosis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">Kumar et al., BioRxiv, 2019</xref>). In addition to the interesting crosstalks that exist among Akt, AMPK and ERK in matrix-attached or matrix-detached condition, each of these three proteins influence cell fate pathways like autophagy and apoptosis. We have observed that hyperactivation of Akt enhanced the levels of active caspase-3 and reduced the number of anchorage independent colonies in matrix-deprived condition (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">Saha et al., 2018</xref>). This indicates that Akt impairs cell survival and enhances apoptosis of matrix-deprived cells. Secondly, we have observed that AMPK inhibition enhanced the levels of active caspase-3 and reduced the number of anchorage-independent colonies in matrix-deprived condition (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">Saha et al., 2018</xref>). This indicates that AMPK promotes cell survival and halts apoptosis of matrix-deprived cells. Thirdly, we have shown that ERK inhibition reduces the levels of active casepase-3 and increases autophagy completion in matrix-detached cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">Kumar et al., BioRxiv, 2019</xref>). This indicates that ERK halts autophagy completion and facilitates apoptosis in matrix-deprived condition. Although these data have independently highlighted Akt-AMPK and AMPK-Erk cross talks in regulating apoptosis and autophagy, yet little is known about how the interplay among these three kinases – Akt, AMPK and ERK – regulates the cell fate mechanisms like apoptosis and autophagy, and how does the fine balance between these mechanisms contributes towards the anoikis resistance of matrix-deprived breast cancer cells.</p><p id="P8">This study focuses on deciphering how cancer cells decide their fate (autophagy or apoptosis) under matrix deprivation using mathematical modelling. We integrated existing knowledge on anoikis resistance into a rigorous analytical framework and formulated an ordinary differential equation (ODE)-based mathematical model on cell fate pathways (autophagy and apoptosis) influenced by Akt, AMPK and ERK. Our dynamical model is built using existing experimental data of signaling pathways (Akt, AMPK and ERK) and cell fate pathways (autophagy and apoptosis) in metastatic breast cancer cells (MDA-MB-231) subjected to matrix deprivation (summarized in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table 1</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">Saha et al., 2018</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">Kumar et al., BioRxiv, 2019</xref>). Molecular perturbation of key proteins depicted that though low levels of pERK support cell survival, but this may happen so until levels of pAkt are maintained low. At extreme low levels of pERK, there is a possibility of high levels of pAkt which may dominate over AMPK in matrix-deprived state and favor anoikis. Overall, this work provided multiple insights on the molecular interplay among key kinases Akt, AMPK and ERK and their effects on cell-fate decision of apoptosis and autophagy. This model also depicted that autophagy is rather robust whereas apoptosis is more sensitive to molecular perturbations. Hence, apoptosis emerged as a deciding factor that influences the decision of cell fate of a matrix-deprived cancer cell.</p></sec><sec id="S2" sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec id="S3"><title>Extraction of experimental data</title><p id="P9"><italic>In vitro</italic> experimental data retrieved from previous work of our laboratory (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">Saha et al., 2018</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">Kumar et al., BioRxiv, 2019</xref>) as well as published literature (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R52">Stulpinas et al., 2023</xref>) were used for model calibration and validation. All the data used for model calibration and validation are summarized in the <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary table 1</xref>. In brief, the data used for model calibration comprise of the effect of matrix deprivation on pAkt, pAMPK, pERK, autophagy and apoptosis, across multiple timepoints. The data used for model validation consist of the effect of Akt hyperactivation and AMPK inhibition on apoptosis and autophagy. Additionally, the data also consists of the effect of PHLPP2 knockdown on pAkt, pAMPK (in the presence or absence of Akt inhibition), apoptosis and autophagy (was also used for validation).</p></sec><sec id="S4"><title>Formulation of anoikis resistance mathematical model</title><p id="P10">All the variables of the anoikis resistance model are listed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary table 2</xref>. The generic deterministic equations representing the temporal dynamics of pAkt, pAMPK, pERK, apoptosis and autophagy are given by: <disp-formula id="FD1"><mml:math id="M1"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula> where <italic>a<sub>x</sub> and d<sub>x</sub></italic> represent the basal activation and deactivation rates of the component <italic>x</italic> and <italic>f<sub>1</sub> and f<sub>2</sub></italic> are two functions representing the regulation of <italic>x</italic>’s activation and deactivation due to crosstalk between <italic>x</italic> and other components. The ordinary differential equations (ODEs) were formulated based on kinetic rate laws and mass balance of signaling proteins. Hill functions were used to capture important feedback and crosstalks in the network. Details on the model equations are elaborated in the <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Information section</xref> under ‘<bold>Model equations’</bold>. Dynamic solutions of these ODEs were obtained using ODE15s solver in MATLAB R2023a software. The initial conditions of the model and the steady state values of matrix-attached and matrix-deprived condition are listed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary table 3</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="S5"><title>Parameter estimation</title><p id="P11">The parameters of this mathematical model were either retrieved from literature or estimated sequentially through trial and error by fitting the model within the range defined by experimental data (as shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary table 1A</xref>). Since all the experimental data were obtained by western blotting, it was challenging to retrieve the data at regularly-spaced time intervals. Hence, most of the experimental data used for this study belong to early time points like 10 mins or 1 h or 2 h and later time points like 8 h or 24 h. Since uniformly spaced time points are not available, we performing a qualitative model fitting to the experimental data. To determine the baseline parameter set, we performed a grid search (within a specific range) for parameters associated with hill functions. Hill functions capture the interactions between Akt, AMPK, ERK and their impact on autophagy and apoptosis. These parameters included V (fold change of hill function; 1 - 100), k (threshold of hill function; 0 - 10) and n (hill coefficient; 2 - 8). Additionally, five other parameters namely, k<sub>a</sub>Cas<sub>Basal</sub> (basal rate of activation of caspases), k<sub>a</sub>Cas (Rate of activation of caspases), <inline-formula><mml:math id="M2"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>k</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>f</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Pg</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Basal</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (Basal rate of formation of phagophore), k<sub>fpg</sub>(Rate of formation of phagophore) and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M3"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>k</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>f</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Ag</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Basal</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (Basal rate of formation of autophagosome) were modified from values available in the literature (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33">Liu et al., 2017</xref>). All the parameters are tabulated in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary table 4</xref>.</p><p id="P12">Model calibration was done by estimating the above parameters to obtain fold change values of pAkt, pAMPK, pERK, autophagy and apoptosis for different conditions (attached vs suspension and treatment vs. control) within the range of experimental data as summarized in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary table 1A</xref>.</p><p id="P13">The calibrated model was further validated using independent set of experimental data that was not used previously for calibration (as summarized in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary table 1B</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S6"><title>Temporal dynamics of the model</title><p id="P14">To identify the steady states of the above calibrated and validated model, the model was simulated for 1440 min (24 h) as well as for longer durations (20,000 h). The timepoint of 24 h was chosen because most of the experimental data were available for 24 h timepoint. To understand the dependence of these steady states on the initial conditions, 1000 random initial conditions of pAkt, pAMPK and pERK were sampled from a uniform distribution of range 1-10 nM and were plotted against the steady states values.</p></sec><sec id="S7"><title>3D-Nullcline analysis</title><p id="P15">A nullcline is a curve on which the derivative of one variable is set to zero. The intersection of nullclines depicts the steady states of the system. To confirm the steady states of the system, 3D-nullclines for pAkt, pAMPK and pERK were obtained by plotting <inline-formula><mml:math id="M4"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M5"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>, in a three-dimensional space with axes pAkt (X-axis), pAMPK (Y-axis) and pERK (Z-axis). Since each variable depends on two other variable, each curve is a two-dimensional surface in three-dimensional space. For example, to plot the nullcline of pAkt, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M6"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>dpAkt</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>dt</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></inline-formula> was set to zero, and pAkt was written in term of pAMPK and pERK <inline-formula><mml:math id="M7"><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>pAkt</mml:mtext><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>k</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>a</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo><mml:mtext>tAkt</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>k</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>a</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mtext>Akt</mml:mtext><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mtext>k</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>d</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mtext>Akt</mml:mtext><mml:mo>*</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Hf</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∧</mml:mo><mml:mtext>MPK</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>*</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Hf</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>ERK</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula>. Then, for all possible values of pAMPK and pERK (ranging from 0 to 10), values of pAkt were computed using MATLAB. The resultant 2D surface was plotted in red for matrix-attached condition and for matrix-deprived condition. Likewise, the nullclines for pAMPK and pERK were also plotted separately.</p></sec><sec id="S8"><title>Stability analysis</title><p id="P16">A standard method to study the stability of steady states is linear stability analysis which is done by computing the Jacobian of differential equations and finding the corresponding eigenvalues. However, for a system of complex coupled-ODEs like in this anoikis resistance model, it is challenging to perform a linear stability analysis. Hence, to study the stability of the steady states of this system, steady state perturbation analysis and phase portraits were plotted.</p><p id="P17"><italic>Steady state perturbation analysis</italic> was performed by perturbing the steady state value (decreasing by 50% or increasing by 50%), and the temporal dynamics for pAkt, pAMPK and pERK in both matrix-attached and matrix-deprived state were plotted against time.</p><p id="P18"><italic>Phase portraits</italic> consist of vector fields at all points on the phase planes. The vector field at a particular point is computed by evaluating the sign of the derivative of all the variables which are denoted as individual vectors (plotted along the axes of the phase planes). The resultant of all the vectors at that point shows the direction in which the system may evolve if the system began from that point.</p></sec><sec id="S9"><title>Flux map analysis</title><p id="P19">To visualize the relative operational strengths of the feedback and crosstalks under matrix-attached and matrix-deprived conditions, the absolute values of the corresponding Hill functions were evaluated and plotted in the flux maps.</p></sec><sec id="S10"><title>Parameter sensitivity analysis</title><p id="P20">To assess how small perturbation in individual model parameter affect the model variables, parameter sensitivity analysis was done. The sensitivity of a steady-state output signal S to changes in the parameter p can be determined by the following formula: <disp-formula id="FD2"><mml:math id="M8"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>S</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>p</mml:mtext><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mo>Δ</mml:mo><mml:mtext>p</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mtext>S</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>p</mml:mtext><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>S</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>p</mml:mtext><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>*</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="P21">S(p<sub>0</sub>) corresponds to the steady state concentration of the signal S obtained using the initial parameter value p<sub>0</sub>. The parameter of interest p is decreased by 10% (Δ<italic>p</italic> = −0.1 * <italic>p</italic><sub>0</sub>), and the new steady state concentration <italic>S</italic>(<italic>p</italic><sub>0</sub> + Δ<italic>p</italic>) is obtained.</p></sec><sec id="S11"><title>Differential activity of proteins</title><p id="P22">To study the effect of differential activity of Akt-AMPK-ERK on each other and autophagy/apoptosis, the differential equation of each of the proteins was set to zero and the levels of these proteins were varied from 0 to 10 nM. The effects of the differential levels of these proteins were studied on the model outputs.</p></sec><sec id="S12"><title>Node and feedback perturbation</title><p id="P23">To study the effect of single versus double node perturbation, each molecular player (Akt-AMPK-ERK) was set at three different levels (low-intermediate-high) and their effects were studied on the model outputs. Subsequently, the feedback strengths ranging between 0 – 1 were also varied and their effects were studied on the model outputs.</p></sec><sec id="S13"><title>Linear discriminant analysis (LDA)</title><p id="P24">To study how Akt-AMPK-ERK influence cell fate decisions, LDA was performed. This is a supervised dimensionality reduction technique that uses class labels to find the most discriminative directions in the data. LDA seeks to maximize the separation between classes while minimizing within-class variance.</p></sec><sec id="S14"><title>Experimental design</title><sec id="S15"><title>Cell culture</title><p id="P25">Human breast cancer cell line MDA-MB-231 (ATCC) was cultured in DMEM (Dulbecco's Modified Eagle Medium; Sigma-Aldrich) supplemented with 10% FBS (fetal bovine serum; Gibco) containing penicillin (HiMedia) and streptomycin (HiMedia), at 37°C and 5% CO2. For matrix-detached (suspension) cultures of 24 hours, cancer cells were seeded on dishes coated with 2% noble agar (Sigma-Aldrich) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R57">Warrier et al., 2023</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S16"><title>Pharmacological compounds</title><p id="P26">Pharmacological compound used in cell culture was MEK/ERK inhibitor, PD98059 (Cat No. 513000; 10 μmol/L; referred to as PD in figures) from Merck India. Dimethyl sulfoxide (DMSO) was used as vehicle control for the pharmacological compound. For experiments carried out in matrix-deprived (suspension) condition, pharmacological compound was added during initial seeding. No prior treatment was given.</p></sec><sec id="S17"><title>Imm unoblotting</title><p id="P27">For immunoblotting, 5 x 10<sup>5</sup> cells were seeded in 35 mm dishes coated with noble agar and exposed to matrix deprivation for 24 h. Whole-cell lysates of suspension cells were prepared using RIPA lysis buffer as described before (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">Hindupur et al., 2014</xref>). Suspension cells were collected into a microcentrifuge tubes, spun down to remove media and then lysed using the lysis buffer. Protein concentration was estimated using Bradford method and equal quantity of protein (30 – 50 μg) per lane was resolved by SDS-PAGE after boiling with sample buffer for 2 minutes at 95 °C. Proteins were transferred to PVDF membrane and probed with appropriate antibodies. The membrane was incubated overnight with primary antibody at 4 °C followed by TBST washes and incubated for 2 h with HRP-conjugated secondary antibodies at room temperature. Chemiluminescence (using ECL substrate from Bio-Rad) was used to visualize proteins bands. a-tubulin served as loading control for each run. Representative immunoblots show data consistent with minimally three independent experiments. Densitometric analyses of Western blots were performed using ImageJ software. Relative protein levels were quantified by normalizing to loading control. Primary antibodies used in the study were against pERK1/2, tERK, pAkt<sup>S473</sup> (Cell Signaling Technology) and a-tubulin (CP06; Merck). HRP-conjugated anti-mouse and anti-rabbit antibodies were obtained from Jackson ImmunoResearch Laboratories.</p></sec><sec id="S18"><title>Autophagy assay</title><p id="P28">Autophagy was measured by autophagy assay kit (MAK138; Sigma Aldrich) according to the manufacturer’s instructions. Briefly, 1.5 × 10<sup>5</sup> MDA-MB-231 cells were seeded in a 24-well plate in attached and suspended condition. Following 24 h of suspension, cells were stained with 0.4 μL of autophagosome detection reagent in 200 μL of stain buffer and incubated for 30 minutes at 37°C and 5% CO2. Cells incubated with stain buffer only were used as negative control. Cells that were exposed to serum-free media for 24 h to induce autophagy and incubated with autophagosome detection reagent were used as positive control. Cells were washed thrice using wash buffer, resuspended in 30 μL of phosphate buffer saline (PBS). Both attached and suspended cells were trypsinized before resuspending in PBS for imaging. For detection, cells were placed on a glass slide and covered with cover slip and analyzed using Epifluorescence microscopy. Green (500 – 560 nm) fluorescence emission was measured after illumination with ultra-violet (360 nm) excitation light. Data were analyzed using ImageJ software.</p></sec><sec id="S19"><title>Apoptosis assay</title><p id="P29">Apoptosis was measured using dead cell apoptosis kit with Annexin V Alexa Fluor 488 and propidium iodide (V13245; Invitrogen) according to the manufacturer’s instructions. Briefly, 1.5 x 10<sup>5</sup> MDA-MB- 231 cells were seeded in a 12-well plate in attached and suspended condition. Following 24 h of suspension, cells were harvested and washed twice with cold phosphate buffer saline (PBS) and then resuspended in 100 μL of 1X annexin-binding buffer. Following this, 5 μL of Annexin V and 1 uL of 100 μg/mL PI working solution was added to each 100 μL of cell suspension and cells were incubated at room temperature for 15 minutes in the dark. After the incubation period, 400 μL of 1X annexin-binding buffer was added and the samples were gently mixed and kept in ice. Samples were analyzed by flowcytometry. The percentage of live cells was detected by Annexin V(-)/PI(-), necrotic cells were detected by Annexin V(-)/PI(+), early apoptotic cells were detected by Annexin V(+)/PI(-) and late apoptotic cells were detected by Annexin V(+)/PI(+).</p></sec><sec id="S20"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="P30">Statistical analyses were performed using MATLAB R2023a software using Student’s t test. All data are presented as mean±SEM, where *, P &lt; 0.05; **, P &lt; 0.01; *** P &lt; 0.001.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="S21" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="S22"><title>Matrix deprivation induces autophagy and apoptosis in breast cancer cells</title><p id="P31">Detachment from the matrix triggers cell death by apoptosis, termed as anoikis. To counter cell death, matrix detachement also triggers autophagy, a stress response that promotes cell survival. To begin to understand how matrix-deprived cancer cells regulate the balance between autophagy and apoptosis to overcome the stress of matrix deprivation, we first investigated the status of autophagy and apoptosis in MDA-MB-231 metastatic breast cancer cells subjected to matrix deprivation for 24 h. <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary figure 1</xref> shows the images of MDA-MB-231 cells grown in matrix-attached and matrix-deprived condition for 24 h. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1A-B</xref> depicts the status of autophagy in matrix-deprived cancer cells as compared to the matrix-attached cancer cells. An autophagy assay was performed by incubating the cells with autophagosome detection reagent (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="S2">Methods</xref>). The data showed enhanced levels of autophagosomes (~88%) in the matrix-deprived cancer cells as compared to the matrix-attached cancer cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1A-B</xref>). By microarray-based expression profiling of genes, we have previously shown that autophagy genes are upregulated in matrix-deprived condition as compared to matrix-attached state (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">Saha et al., 2018</xref>). Additionally, we have also shown the increased expression of proteins responsible for autophagy initiation and autophagosome formation (LC3II and p62) in matrix-deprived cells as compared matrix-attached state (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">Kumar et al.,2019</xref>, bioRxiv). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1C</xref> depicts the status of apoptosis in matrix-deprived cancer cells as compared to the matrix-attached cancer cells. The apoptosis assay was performed by incubating the cells with AnnexinV/PI reagent (see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="S2">Methods</xref>). Annexins are a family of calcium-dependent phospholipid-binding proteins that preferentially bind phosphatidylserine (PS). Under normal physiological conditions, PS is predominantly located in the inner leaflet of the plasma membrane. Upon initiation of apoptosis, PS loses its asymmetric distribution across the phospholipid bilayer and is translocated to the extracellular membrane leaflet marking cells as targets of phagocytosis. Once on the outer surface of the membrane, PS can be detected by fluorescently labelled Annexin V in a calcium-dependent manner. Propidium iodide (PI) is nucleic acid binding dye. PI is impermeant to live cells and early apoptotic cells, but stains dead cells with red fluorescence, binding tightly to the nucleic acids in the cell (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">Koç et al., 2018</xref>). After staining a cell population with Annexin V and PI, the percentage of live cells were scored as Annexin V(-)/PI(-), necrotic cells were detected by Annexin V(-)/PI(+), early apoptotic cells were detected by Annexin V(+)/PI(-) and late apoptotic cells were detected by Annexin V(+)/PI(+). Firstly, it is interesting to note that majority of the matrix-deprived cells (~73%) make up the live population. Similarly, majority of the matrix-attached cells (~82%) also contribute to the live population. Approximately, 12.9% of the matrix-deprived cells made up the early apoptotic population and compared to only 6.3% of matrix-attached cells which belonged to this population. Interestingly, 12.9% of matrix-deprived cells made up the late apoptotic population and compared to only 8.9% of matrix-attached cells which belonged to this population. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1D</xref> depicts the quantification of the proportion of cells in the late apoptotic state from three indepndent experiments. The data show that there is increased population of dead/late apoptotic cells (1.45 times) in matrix-deprived cancer cells as compared to matrix-attached cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1D</xref>).</p><p id="P32">Together, the above results depict that there is enhanced levels of autophagy and apoptosis in matrix-deprived cancer cells as compared to their adherent counterpart. This intrigued us to question how is the balance between autophagy and apoptosis decided in matrix-deprived cancer cells to overcome the stress due to matrix deprivation and enable survival. To answer this question, we utilized mathematical modeling techniques to formulate a mathematical model which could capture the above biology in additional to crucial signaling events that are altered in these conditions.</p></sec><sec id="S23"><title>Construction and calibration of anoikis-resistance mathematical model</title><p id="P33">Multiple pathways including AMPK/ACC, calcium/ROS signaling, integrin signaling, MAPK/ERK, HIF1, PEA15, NFκB/Wnt, Akt/mTOR/S6K1, anabolism/catabolsim and autophagy/apoptosis regulate anoikis and are perturbed upon matrix deprivation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">Buchheit et al., 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R53">Sundararaman et al., 2016</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">Saha et al., 2018</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R57">Warrier et al., 2023</xref>) as summarized in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2Ai</xref>. Though the above signaling events are highly interlinked, there exits a sequence in which the cue of matrix deprivation is transferred from one level to another. Upon matrix deprivation, the growth factor and integrin signaling are perturbed which effect RAS/RAF/MEK pathways. Additionally, there is a spike in cytosolic calcium and ROS signaling that activates AMPK via LKB1 and CaMKKβ. Akt-AMPK-ERK are unknown to influence eachother and regulate anoikis. Further downstream are mTOR/S6K1, PEA15, NFκB and HIF1 which regulate metabolism and autophagy/apoptosis. Previously, we built a mathematical model that captured the attachment-detachment signaling and linked the effects of AMPK-Akt-mTOR-S6K1 to metabolism (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35">Maiti et al., 2024</xref>). In this work, we focus on Akt-AMPK-ERK and their effect on autophagy and apoptosis. To reduce the complexity of the above system, we chose a few proteins or secondary messengers to formulate a mathematical model with minimum number of variables needed to study anoikis resistance. To create a mathematical model that captures the sequence of events during matrix deprivation (starting from the cue of detachment to the cell fate of survial/death), we coarse-grained the extended system (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2A(i)</xref>) into a minimum network consisting of Akt, AMPK and ERK signaling nodes coupled to cell fate pathways like autophagy and apoptosis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2Aii</xref>) based on experimental data summarized in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary table 1</xref>. This is named the ‘anoikis resistance mathematical model’, which is a deterministic model wherein, protein-protein interactions are described by ordinary differential equations and outputs report temporally variable protein concentration. The model consists of eight variables: Matrix, cytosolic calcium (Ccal), phospho-Akt (pAkt), phospho-AMPK pAMPK, phospho-ERK (pERK), phagophore, autophagosome, active-caspase (aCaspase) which capture the dynamics of attachment-detachment signaling. Phagophore and autophagosome are variables associated with autophagy and aCaspase is associated with apoptosis. All the variables are listed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary table 2</xref>, initial conditions on all the variables are listed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary table 3</xref> and all the parameters are listed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary table 4</xref>. All the equations and their brief descriptions are also presented in the <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Information</xref> section.</p><p id="P34">The following assumptions have been made while building the model: <list list-type="simple" id="L1"><list-item><label>1)</label><p id="P35">A double-negative feedback loop between Akt and ERK in matrix-deprived state.</p></list-item><list-item><label>2)</label><p id="P36">The total levels of Akt, AMPK, ERK and proCaspase were considered to be 10 nM.</p></list-item><list-item><label>3)</label><p id="P37">Since autophagosome are formed from phagophores and phagophore are dynamic structures, the amount of phagophore is written in the form of an ODE instead of a constant value.</p></list-item><list-item><label>4)</label><p id="P38">Apoptosis is studied by the levels of aCaspase. Once effector caspases are activated, the cell is programed to die. Hence, in the equation for aCaspase, only the activation of caspase has been included. There are no terms included for the reduction in the levels of aCaspase. Therefore, the levels of aCaspase keep increasing with time, while all other variables attain steady state.</p></list-item><list-item><label>5)</label><p id="P39">Since multiple players are involved in Akt-AMPK-ERK signaling pathways and how they influence autophagy and apoptosis, all their interactions are captured as hill functions.</p></list-item></list></p><p id="P40">The first assumption on the double-negative feedback loop between Akt and ERK in the matrix-deprived deprived state has been experimentally tested as shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary figure 2</xref>. Results show increase in the levels of pAkt upon ERK inhibition in matrix-deprived condition. Investigating the reverse (effect of Akt inhibition on the levels of pERK) is challenging to perform in matrix-deprived condition owing to the extremely low levels of pAkt in the matrix-deprived state. Hence, the reverse feedback was assumed based on the experimental data available for matrix-attached condition (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R52">Stulpinas et al., 2023</xref>).</p><p id="P41">The input to the anoikis resistance model is the presence or absence of extracellular matrix or simply ‘Matrix’. For the matrix-attached state, the value of Matrix is assigned as 1, which denotes the presense of matrix attachment. For the matrix-detached state, the value of Matrix is assigned as 0, which denotes the absence of matrix attachment. The key model players are Akt, AMPK and ERK. In the matrix-attached state, growth factor and integrin (attachment-mediated) signaling activates Akt. Active Akt inhibits AMPK and ERK. Whereas, in the matrix-deprived state, AMPK is activated via CAMKKβ due to the spike in cytosolic calcium (Ccal). Matrix detachment also leads to ERK activation. Detachment-triggered AMPK inhibits Akt and ERK. Active ERK also inhibits AMPK and Akt. Hence, multiple double-negative feedback loop exists among AMPK, Akt and ERK as depicted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1Aii</xref>.</p><p id="P42">In addition to the interaction of AMPK, Akt and ERK among themselves, these proteins also influence autophagy and apoptosis. AMPK activation promotes autophagy whereas AMPK inhibition enhanced caspase-3 activity and reduced anchorage independent colonies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">Saha et al., 2018</xref>). Hence, AMPK promotes survival mechanisms like autophagy and inhibits apoptosis. Though Akt levels are low in matrix-deprived state, hyperactivation of Akt enhanced caspase-3 activity and reduced anchorage independent colonies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">Saha et al., 2018</xref>). Hence, Akt inhibits autophagy but promotes apoptosis in matrix-deprived cancer cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">Saha et al., 2018</xref>). ERK inhibition reduced apoptosis and enhanced autophagy completion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">Kumar et al., BioRxiv, 2019</xref>). Therefore, ERK promotes apoptosis and inhibits autophagy. The experimental data depicting the above points are shown in the <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary table 1</xref>.</p><p id="P43">Though excess autophagy can lead to cell death, in this model we use the formation of autophagosome as a surrogate for autophagy induction (as used previously shown (Liu et al., 2019)) and portray autophagy as a mechaism of cell survival. The formation of autophagosome indicates that the cell is in survival mode. The activation of caspase-3 is used as a surrogate for apoptosis or cell death. In this model, we define survival as autophagy outweighing apoptosis. This scenario also exemplifies anoikis resistance. Alternately, we define cell death as apoptosis outweighing autophagy. This scenario exemplifies anoikis. The above description is pictorially depicted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2Aii</xref>.</p><p id="P44">Model calibration was done to fit the mathematical model to the experimental data. This calibration was done by retrieving some model parameters from the literature and estimating the remaining parameters to get the best fit of the model to the experimental data. All the experimental data used for model calibration are depicted in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary figure 3 and Supplementary figure 4</xref> and tabulated in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary table 1A</xref>. The results of model calibration are depicted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2B</xref>. The results show the dynamics of pAkt (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2Bi</xref>), pAMPK (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2Bii</xref>) and pERK (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2Biii</xref>) consistent with experimental observations under matrix deprivation. The model also captured the increase in autophagy (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2Biv</xref>), and apoptosis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2Bv</xref>) upon matrix deprivation. Additionally, model parameters were tweaked to capture a couple of experimental data from activation/inhibition studies. Model captured the increase in pAMPK upon Akt inhibition in the matrix-attached state (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary Figure. 5A</xref>), the decrease in pAkt upon enhancing the levels of pAMPK in the matrix-attached state (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary Figure. 5B</xref>), the increase in the levels of pAkt upon ERK inhibition (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary Figure. 5C</xref>) and increase in the levels of pERK upon Akt inhibition (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary Figure. 5D</xref>). The model also captured the increase in pAkt upon AMPK inhibition (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary Figure. 5E</xref>) in the matrix-deprived state.</p></sec><sec id="S24"><title>Mathematical analyses of anoikis resistance mathematical model</title><p id="P45">Following the model calibration, we performed multiple analyses on the model to evaluate the steady state of the system and to study the stability of these steady states.</p><p id="P46">To evaluate the steady states of the system, the model was simulated for 24 h and beyond. The temporal dynamics of the variables for 1440 min (24 h) along with the steady state values attained in matrix-attached and matrix-deprived conditions are depicted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3A</xref>. Since the key model players comprise of pAkt, pAMPK and pERK, further analyses were done on the three model players. When model was simulated for longer duration, the same steady state values were obtained for pAkt, pAMPK and pERK (data not shown).</p><p id="P47">To study the effect of initial conditions on the final steady state values of these model players, the initial conditions were randomly-sampled, and the model was simulated in both the matrix-attached and matrix-deprived conditions. Results show that irrespective of the value of initial condition of pAkt, pAMPK or pERK, the steady state values of these proteins were 4.78, 2.03 and 2.40 respectively in the matrix-attached state (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3Bi</xref>) and the steady state values of these proteins were 2.44, 8.26 and 4.82 respectively, in the matrix-deprived state (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3Bii</xref>), when simulated for a total time duration of 1440 min (24 h). The above analysis was also repeated for longer duration and similar results were obtained (data not shown). These results depicted that the model is robust and captures the biology irrespective of any initial conditions.</p><p id="P48">To confirm the steady states of the system, 3D-nullclines for pAkt, pAMPK and pERK were obtained by plotting <inline-formula><mml:math id="M9"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M10"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>, (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary figure 7</xref>) in a three-dimensional space with axes pAkt (X-axis), pAMPK (Y-axis) and pERK (Z-axis). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3Ci</xref> shows the intersection of pAkt, pAMPK and pERK 3D-nullclines plotted simultaneously for the matrix-attached state. The single intersection point reveals the unique steady state value [pAkt: 5.44, pAMPK: 1.71, pERK: 2.25] of the system in matrix-attached state. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3Cii</xref> shows the intersection of pAkt, pAMPK and pERK 3D-nullclines plotted simultaneously for the matrix-deprived state. The single intersection point reveals the unique steady state value [pAkt: 2.45, pAMPK: 8.27, pERK: 4.82] of the system in matrix-deprived state. Hence, this analysis confirms that the system has a single monostable steady state for matrix-attached and matrix-deprived state.</p><p id="P49">To study the stability of the steady states, steady state perturbation analysis was performed. This analysis helps to understand whether any perturbation caused at the steady state of the system affects the final steady state of the system. When the initial condition of pAkt was either decreased or increased by 50% for matrix-attached state (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary Figure. 8A</xref>) or matrix-deprived state (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary Figure. 8D</xref>), the temporal dynamics depicted that the system restored to original steady state values within 540 minutes. The same trend was obtained when pAMPK (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary Figure. 8B; Supplementary Figure. 8E</xref>) and pERK (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary Figure. 8C; Supplementary Figure. 8F</xref>) were perturbed in the same way. These results indicated that the model steady states are stable and were neither affected by changes in initial conditions nor by any perturbation to the steady state values.</p><p id="P50">Another gold standard technique to study the stability of steady states is by plotting phase portraits. <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary figure 9A</xref> depicts the phase portraits of the pAMPK 3D-nullcline in the matrix-attached state. We observe that all the vector fields point towards the steady state values of the system of matrix-attached state [pAkt: 5.44, pAMPK: 1.71, pERK: 2.25]. Likewise, the phase portraits of pAkt and pERK for matrix-attached state are shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary figure 9B</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary figure 9C</xref>. The phase portraits of pAMPK, pAkt and pERK for matrix-deprived state are shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary figure 9D, Supplementary figure 9E and Supplementary figure 9F</xref>, respectively. We observe that all the vector fields point towards the steady state values of the system of matrix-detached state value [pAkt: 2.45, pAMPK: 8.27, pERK: 4.82]. Hence, the above results depict that the system indeed has a unique steady state for matrix-attached and matrix-deprived condition.</p></sec><sec id="S25"><title>Model validation</title><p id="P51">Following rigorous mathematical analyses of the calibrated model, model validation was performed by comparing simulation results against experimental data not used for model fitting previously. In the previous sections we observed that the model captured the relative change in the levels of pAkt, pAMPK and pERK while shiting from the matrix-attached to the matrix-deprived condition. This relative change is mainly because of plausible strength of the feedbacks in the network. To find out the relative strength of the feedbacks in the matrix-attached and matrix-deprived condition, we plotted a flux map. The numbers in blue pertain to the matrix-attached condition while the numbers in red pertain to the matrix-detached state. As the feedbacks and crosstalks are written in terms of Hill functions, the numbers vary between the range of 0 and 1. These hill functions are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4A</xref>. A value closer to 0 represents mild/low strength of activation or inhibition, while a value closer to 1 represents a strong/high strength of activation or inhibition. A value closer to 0.5 depicts neutral effect.</p><p id="P52">In the matrix-attached state, integrin and growth factor signaling cause the activation of Akt. Flux map analysis in the matrix-attached state depicted that active Akt inhibited AMPK and ERK with a high strength of 0.86 and 0.82 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4A</xref>; blue values) respectively. However, in the matrix-deprived state, detachment from matrix activates ERK and spike in cytosolic calcium activates AMPK via CAMKKβ. Flux map analysis in the matrix-detached state depicted that active AMPK inhibited Akt and ERK with a high strength of 0.97 and 0.81 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4A</xref>; red values) respectively. Active ERK also inhibited AMPK and Akt with high strength of 0.85 and 0.85 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4A</xref>; red values). Since active Akt levels are low in matrix-deprived state, the strength of inhibition of AMPK and ERK by Akt was also low 0.35 and 0.37 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4A</xref>; red values), respectively. These results indicated that the strength of the feedbacks were biological relevant. Thes cnk jsh</p><p id="P53">Literature shows that hyperactivation of Akt in matrix-deprived state is detrimental to the cells. It promoted anoikis by enhancing apoptosis by increased caspase-3 activity and reduced the number of anchorage independent colonies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">Saha et al., 2018</xref>). Using the model, Akt hyperactivation was simulated in the matrix-deprived state (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4Bi</xref>) and an increase in apoptosis was observed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4Bii</xref>). Though anchorage independent colonies do not directly correspond to the levels of autophagy in the cell, but both anchorage independent colonies and autophagy indicate the extent of cell survival. The model does not show any significant difference in the levels of autophagy upon hyperactivation of Akt in matrix-deprived state (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4Bii</xref>). Similary, literature also shows that AMPK inhibition induces apoptosis via caspase-3 activation and reduces the number of anchorage independent colonies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">Saha et al., 2018</xref>). Our model also predicted the increase in apoptosis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4Cii</xref>) upon AMPK inhibition (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4Ci</xref>) as compared to the untreated control in the matrix-deprived state. The model did not show any significant difference in the levels of autophagy (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4Cii</xref>) upon AMPK inhibition in matrix-deprived state.</p><p id="P54">Another validation was done using experimental data on the effect of PHLPP2 knockdown (KD) on AMPK and Akt in matrix-deprived condition. PHLPP2 is a phosphatase that mediates the inhibitory effect of AMPK on Akt (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">Saha et al., 2018</xref>). PHLPP2 KD removes this inhibitory effect. Experimentally, it was shown that PHLPP2 KD leads to decreased AMPK activity in matrix-deprived condition via Akt activation (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary figure 5A</xref>). Hence, it was additionally shown that upon Akt inhibition in the PHLPP2 KD cells, there was a decrease in pAkt levels and an increase in pAMPK levels (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary figure 5B</xref>). PHLPP2 KD can be simulated in silico by delinking the inhibitory effect of AMPK on Akt. In matrix-deprived condition, the strength of the inhibitory effect of AMPK on Akt was calculated to be 0.97 (details elaborated in flux map analysis), hence delinking was performed by assigning a value of 0.01 to the respective hill function. Upon simulating the PHLPP2 KD in silico (by delinking), the model predicted the increase in pAkt (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4Di</xref>) and decrease in pAMPK (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4Di</xref>). Upon inducing different degrees of Akt inhibition, in addition to in silico PHLPP2 KD in the matrix-deprived condition, the model predicted the decrease in pAkt (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4Dii</xref>) and increase in pAMPK (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4Div</xref>). Experimentally we have also observed that PHLPP2 KD impairs autophagy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">Saha et al., 2018</xref>) and enhances apoptosis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">Saha et al., 2018</xref>). Upon simulating the effects of PHLPP2 KD on autophagy and apoptosis, the model predicted the increase in apoptosis upon PHLPP2 KD (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary Figure 3E</xref>); however, not much difference is noticed on autophagy ((<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4Diii</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S26"><title>Identification of key parameters that impact the system behaviour</title><p id="P55">Parameter sensitivity analysis is done to understand the sensitivity of the model variables to local variations in individual parameters around the baseline values. Most parameters have negligible effect on key model variables, with sensitivity values close to zero (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>). Each parameter is decreased by 10% and hence any change in the model variables above 10% or less than -10% is considered highly sensitive and any change from 8% to 10% or -8% to -10% is considered to be sensitive and any value in between -8% to 8% is not sensitive. Interestingly, we notice a context-dependent (matrix-attached or matrix-deprived) difference in the sensitivity analysis.</p><p id="P56">In the matrix-attached state (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5A</xref>), the variables (pAkt, pAMPK and pERK) are highly sensitive to kCcal (Threshold of CAMKKβ activation by Ccal). pAkt, pAMPK are sensitive to nCcal (Hill coefficient associated to Ccal). Apart from these, pAkt is sensitive to k1A (threshold of Akt inhibition by pAMPK). pAMPK is sensitive to ka_AMPK (rate of activation of AMPK), kd_AMPK (rate of deactivation of pAMPK), V2A (fold change of AMPK inhibition by pAkt) and V2B (fold change of AMPK inhibition by pERK). pERK is sensitive to ka_ERK (rate of activation of ERK), kd_ERK (rate of deactivation of pERK), and V3B (fold change of ERK inhibition by pAkt). The above results indicated that the model variables are sensitive to parameters linked to Ccal. This variable is directly linked to the input (Matrix) of the system. pAMPK and pERK are influenced by their respective rates of activation and deactivation but pAkt is not. The variables are also sensitive to parameters associated to the crosstalks between proteins.</p><p id="P57">In the matrix-deprived state (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5B</xref>), pAkt is highly sensitive to kd_Akt (rate of deactivation of pAkt), V1A (fold change of Akt inhibition by pAMPK) and V1B (fold change of Akt inhibition by pERK) and sensitive to ka_Akt (rate of activation of Akt). pERK is sensitive to k3B (threshold of ERK inhibition by pAkt) and ka_Akt (rate of activation of Akt). These results indicated that only pAkt and pERK are sensistive to certain parameters. pAMPK appears to be rather resilient to slight changes in parameters in the matrix-deprived state.</p></sec><sec id="S27"><title>How do Akt-AMPK-ERK and their interplay influence the cell fate of matrix-deprived cancer cells?</title><p id="P58">Using the developed anoikis resistance mathematical model, we attempted to understand how do Akt-AMPK-ERK and their interplay impact cell fate decision pathways like apoptosis and autophagy in matrix-deprived condition. In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>, the levels of aCaspase (black line) are used as a surrogate for apoptosis and levels of autophagosome (dark green line) are used as a surrogate for autophagy. When apoptosis outweighs autophagy, we define this as the state of anoikis in matrix-deprived cancer cells or in simple terms: cell death. When autophagy outweighs apoptosis, we define this as the state of anoikis resistance or in simple terms: cell survival. The crossover of the black and dark green lines depicts the shift from anoikis to anoikis resistance or vice versa.</p><p id="P59">The previous analyses revealed that the steady state values of pAkt, pAMPK, and pERK in the matrix-deprived state are 2.44 nM, 8.26 nM and 4.81 nM, respectively. In this experiment, one protein is perturbed at a time (the differential equation of that protein is set to zero, and the initial condition of that protein is varied from 0 to 10 nM). Any value below its steady state value is interpreted as different levels of knockdown of that protein. Any value above the steady state value is interpreted as different degrees of overexpression of that protein. In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>, we note the following key points: <list list-type="order" id="L2"><list-item><p id="P60">The balance between apoptosis and autophagy across different concentration of the perturbed protein.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P61">The concentration of the perturbed protein at the point of the cross over</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P62">The effect of the perturbed protein on the two other proteins</p></list-item><list-item><p id="P63">The levels of the other proteins at the point of the crossover. The levels are divided into three regions: 0-3 nM refers to low levels, 3-7 nM refers to intermediate levels, 7-10 nM refers to high levels.</p></list-item></list></p><p id="P64">This experiment is done specifically for the matrix-deprived condition, and each point on the graph in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref> is the steady state value at 1440 minutes (or 24 h). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6A</xref> depicts the levels of aCaspase (left Y-axis) and autophagosomes (right Y-axis) when pAkt is varied from 0 to 10 nM (X-axis). The steady state value of pAkt (2.4 nM) in the matrix-deprived state is marked by the red-dashed vertical line. The model predicted that from 0 - 3.8 nM of pAkt, autophagy outweighs apoptosis and hence the system is resistant to anoikis. However, the shift from anoikis resistance to anoikis happens at 3.8 nM (grey-dashed vertical line) of pAkt. This also corroborates the experimental data that hyperactivation of Akt induces anoikis in matrix-deprived cancer cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">Saha et al., 2018</xref>). Beyond this point, apoptosis outweighs autophagy and hence the system succumbs to anoikis. This balance between apoptosis and autophagy is tightly regulated by the effect of different levels of pAkt on pAMPK and pERK. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6B</xref> depicts the levels of pAMPK (left Y-axis) and pERK (right Y-axis) when pAkt is varied from 0 to 10 nM. The levels of pAMPK and pERK at the crossover (where pAkt is 3.8 nM) is 7.3 nM and 3.5 nM, respectively. Hence, perturbation of pAkt reveals that the region of anoikis resistance is marked by intermediate to high levels of pAkt, high levels of pAMPK and intermediate levels of pERK.</p><p id="P65">Following the perturbation of pAkt, the system was reset and pAMPK was perturbed in the same way as above. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6C</xref> depicts the levels of aCaspase (left Y-axis) and autophagosomes (right Y-axis) when pAMPK is varied from 0 to 10 nM (X-axis). The steady state value of pAMPK (8.2 nM) in the matrix-deprived state is marked by the green-dashed vertical line. The model predicted that from 10 – 3.4 nM of pAMPK, autophagy outweighs apoptosis and the system is resistant to anoikis. However, when the levels of pAMPK reduces below 3.4 nM, apoptosis outweighs autophagy and the system succumbs to anoikis. This also corroborates the experimental data that inhibition of pAMPK favors anoikis in matrix-deprived cancer cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">Saha et al., 2018</xref>). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6D</xref> depicts the levels of pAkt (left Y-axis) and pERK (right Y-axis) when pAMPK is varied from 0 to 10 nM. The levels of pAkt and pERK at the crossover (where pAMPK is 3.4 nM) is 2.9 nM and 4.4 nM, respectively. Hence, perturbation of pAMPK reveals that the region of anoikis resistance is marked by intermediate to low levels of pAMPK, high to intermediate levels of pAkt and intermediate levels of pERK.</p><p id="P66">Following the perturbation of pAMPK, the system was reset and pERK was perturbed in the same way as above. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6E</xref> depicts the levels of aCaspase (left Y-axis) and autophagosomes (right Y-axis) when pERK is varied from 0 to 10 nM (X-axis). The steady state value of pERK (4.8 nM) in the matrix-deprived state is marked by the blue-dashed vertical line. The model predicted that from 10 – 1.8 nM of pERK, autophagy outweighs apoptosis and the system is resistant to anoikis. This result is partly corroborated by previous work from our lab, where we have shown that low pERK and high pAMPK levels enable survival (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">Kumar et al., 2019</xref>, bioRxiv). However, when the levels of pERK reduces below 1.8 nM, apoptosis outweighs autophagy and the system succumbs to anoikis. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6F</xref> depicts the levels of pAkt (left Y-axis) and pAMPK (right Y-axis) when pERK is varied from 0 to 10 nM (X-axis). The levels of pAkt and pAMPK at the crossover (where pERK is 1.8 nM) is 3.8 nM and 8.2 nM, respectively. Therefore, the above results taken together portrays that a heterogeneity in pERK levels: high/low levels pERK along with high pAMPK enable survival as long as levels of pAkt are maintained low. Additionally, the model predicted a heterogeneity in pAMPK: high/low levels of pAMPK along with low pERK determines the shift from survival to death when levels of pAkt are high. Such high levels of pAkt are obtained at critically low levels of pERK.</p></sec><sec id="S28"><title>Is there any hierarchy among Akt-AMPK-ERK that may influence the cell fate decision?</title><p id="P67">The previous section elucidated the effects of Akt-AMPK-ERK on the cell fate decision when each of them are perturbed one at a time. Since each protein affects the other two proteins, we queried whether there is any specific combination of perturbation of Akt-AMPK-ERK which would depict effective crossover of apoptosis over autophagy and give further insights on the region of anoikis resistance. For this experiment, the differential equation of each protein was set to zero and the temporal dynamics of apoptosis (levels of aCaspase) and autophagy (levels of autophagosome) were plotted along with low (2 nM), intermediate (5 nM) and high (8 nM) levels of each protein. The temporal dynamics of two unperturbed proteins are also shown along with the pertubed protein. This experiment is done for a time span of 1440 minutes (or 24 h) in matrix-deprived condition.</p><p id="P68">Along the lines of the previous experiment, the model predicts that apoptosis (black line) surpasses autophagy (dark-green line) for intermediate and high levels of pAkt (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary 10A</xref>) and low levels of pAMPK (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary 10B</xref>). Interestingly, none of the perturbations (low/intermediate/high) of ERK depict a crossover of apoptosis over autophagy (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary 10C</xref>; right panel) until 1440 minutes (or 24 h). This is because for all levels of pERK, levels of pAkt and pAMPK are maintained low and high (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary 10Cc</xref>), respectively.</p><p id="P69">The above results motivated us to enquire if pERK is perturbed along with pAkt or pAMPK, does it enable a crossover of apoptosis over autophagy. For this, the differential equation of two proteins were set to zero and the temporal dynamics of apoptosis (levels of aCaspase) and autophagy (levels of autophagosome) were plotted at low (2 nM), intermediate (5 nM) and high (8 nM) levels of those two proteins. To our surprise, when pERK was perturbed along with pAkt, the model predicted that apoptosis surpased autophagy for intermediate and high levels of the dual protein perturbation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7A</xref>, right panel). Simultaneously, we observed a gradual decrease in the levels of pAMPK (green line in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7A</xref>, left panel) with increase in the levels of pAkt and pERK. When pERK was perturbed along with pAMPK, apoptosis surpased autophagy for low levels of the dual protein perturbation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7B</xref>, right panel). Additionally, we observed a gradual decrease in the levels of pAkt (red line in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7B</xref>, left panel) with increase in the levels of pAMPK and pERK. It is interesting to note that, when pERK is either perturbed along with pAkt or pAMPK (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7A and Figure 7B</xref>), the crossover pattern resembles that of individual perturbation of pAkt (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary 10A</xref>) or pAMPK (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary 10B</xref>). These results indicate that pAkt and pAMPK dominates over pERK while influencing cell fate decisions.</p><p id="P70">The above results further made us curious to question the existance of any hierarchy among pAkt and pAMPK. When dual perturbations of pAkt and pAMPK were simulated, the model predicted crossover of apoptosis over autophagy only for intermediate and high levels of dual perturbations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7C</xref>, right panel). It is interesting to note that low levels of dual perturbations of pAkt and pAMPK no longer depicted the crossover, as observed previously when pAMPK was perturbed individually (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary 10B</xref>, right panel). Additionally, we also observed the gradual decrease of pERK (blue line in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7C</xref>, left panel) with the increase in dual perturbation of pAkt and pAMPK. This indicated that pAkt dominates over pAMPK while influencing cell fate decisions.</p><p id="P71">Hence, the above results illustrate that there exists a hierarchy among Akt-AMPK-ERK and pAkt dominates over pAMPK, which further dominates over pERK while influencing cell fate decision pathways like apoptosis and autophagy.</p></sec><sec id="S29"><title>What combination of Akt-AMPK-ERK favours pro-apoptotic signals over pro-survival signals?</title><p id="P72">Intrigued by the findings on single and double perturbations of Akt-AMPK-ERK and their imapct on cell fate pathways, we were curious to know when all three proteins were perturbed at the same time, what combinations of Akt-AMPK-ERK favored apoptosis over autophagy and hence the system would succumb to anoikis. Understanding this will enable us to idnetify key nodes that can be targeted for therapy.</p><p id="P73">For this experiment, we sampled five different concentrations (1 nM, 3 nM, 5 nM, 7 nM and 10 nM) of three proteins: pAkt, pAMPK and pERK. This resulted in 5<sup>3</sup> or 125 different combinations of proteins. For each of these 125 combinations of proteins, the levels of aCaspase and autophagosome were computed and the ratio of aCaspase and autophagosome was evaluated. When the ratio was less than 1 (aCaspase &lt; autophagosome), those combinations of proteins were marked to belong to the prosurvival zone. When the ratio was more than 1 (aCaspase &gt; autophagosome), those combinations of proteins were marked to belong to the pro-apoptotic zone. This experiment was done exclusively for the matrix-deprived state.</p><p id="P74">Among the 125 combinations of pAkt, pAMPK and pERK, we selected eight extreme combinations for simplicity. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figure 8A</xref> depicts the eight vertices of the 3D figure denote pAkt<sup>Low</sup>pAMPK<sup>Low</sup>pERK<sup>Low</sup> ([1,1,1]; <bold>a</bold>), pAkt<sup>Low</sup>pAMPK<sup>High</sup>pERK<sup>Low</sup> ([1,10,1]; <bold>b</bold>), pAkt<sup>Low</sup>pAMPK<sup>High</sup>pERK<sup>High</sup> ([1,10,10]; <bold>c</bold>), pAkt<sup>Low</sup>pAMPK<sup>Low</sup>pERK<sup>High</sup> ([1,1,10]; <bold>d</bold>), pAkt<sup>High</sup>pAMPK<sup>Low</sup>pERK<sup>Low</sup> ([10,1,1]; <bold>e</bold>), pAkt<sup>High</sup>pAMPK<sup>High</sup>pERK<sup>Low</sup> ([10,10,1]; <bold>f</bold>), pAkt<sup>High</sup>pAMPK<sup>High</sup>pERK<sup>High</sup> ([10,10,10]; <bold>g</bold>), and pAkt<sup>High</sup>pAMPK<sup>Low</sup>pERK<sup>High</sup> ([10,1,10]; <bold>h</bold>). In order to understand, what combinations of pAkt, pAMPK and pERK contribute towards pro-survival or pro-apoptotic cell fate decisions, we plotted the corresponding cell fate decisions in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figure 8B</xref>. We observe that for pAkt<sup>Low</sup>pAMPK<sup>Low</sup>pERK<sup>Low</sup>, pAkt<sup>Low</sup>pAMPK<sup>High</sup>pERK<sup>Low</sup>, pAkt<sup>Low</sup>pAMPK<sup>High</sup>pERK<sup>High</sup>, and pAkt<sup>Low</sup>pAMPK<sup>Low</sup>pERK<sup>High</sup>, the model predicted pro-survival phenotype. However, for pAkt<sup>High</sup>pAMPK<sup>Low</sup>pERK<sup>Low</sup>, pAkt<sup>High</sup>pAMPK<sup>High</sup>pERK<sup>Low</sup>, pAkt<sup>High</sup>pAMPK<sup>High</sup>pERK<sup>High</sup>, and pAkt<sup>High</sup>pAMPK<sup>Low</sup>pERK<sup>High</sup> the model predicted pro-apoptotic phenotype. In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figure 8B</xref>, the 2D plane in blue (known as the ‘decision boundary’) is the plane where ratio of aCaspase and autophagszome is 1. This plane seperates the three-dimensional space into two zones: the zone with all green dots that depict all those combinations of Akt-AMPK-ERK that contribute to pro-survival signals (where the ratio of aCaspase and autophagszome is less than 1) and the zone with red dots that depict all those combinations of Akt-AMPK-ERK that contribute to pro-apoptotic signals (where the ratio of aCaspase and autophagszome is more than 1). It is interesting to note that this decision boundary splits the 3D space into two zones based on the levels pAkt. It depicted that both low/high levels of pAMPK and pERK contributed to pro-survival signals until pAkt levels are maintained below 4 nM. Above 4 nM of pAkt, all combinations of pAMPK and pERK resulted in pro-apoptotic signals. This experiment, corroborating with our previous results, confirmed that the status of pAkt emerged as a deciding factor – increase in pAkt shifts the system from pro-survival to pro-apoptotic state.</p></sec><sec id="S30"><title>The interplay between Akt-AMPK-ERK impacts apoptosis more than autophagy</title><p id="P75">In the previous section, we found that pAkt emerged as a deciding factor among the three proteins which majorly imapcts the cell fate decision. However, it is not clearly understood what balance of apoptosis and autophagy dictates this decision. Towards understanding this, we computed the levels of aCaspase and autophagosome and plotted them for each of the above eight combinations of proteins. This experiment was also done for the matrix-deprived state and the steady state value for 1440 minutes (or 24 h) were plotted.</p><p id="P76"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figure 8C</xref> depicts the levels of aCaspase and autophagosome for all the eight combinations of pAkt, pAMPK and pERK. The labels on the X-axis show the combination of these proteins. The Y-axis shows the levels of aCaspase (red) and autophagosome (green). Following the combinations sequencially in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figure 8C</xref>, we observed that when the levels of all three proteins was low, levels of autophagosome dominated over levels of aCaspase. When pERK levels were maintained high in addition to low pAkt and pAMPK, a slight increase in levels of aCaspase was noticed, but levels of autophagosome still surpassed levels of aCaspase. When levels of pAMPK were maintained high in addition to low levels of pAkt and pERK, it was interesting to note that there was a decline in the levels aCaspase as compared to the previous two combination, but levels of autophagosome remained unchanged. When levels of pAkt were maintained high, in addition to low levels of pAMPK and pERK, the levels of aCaspase surpassed levels of autophagosome. When both pAkt and pAMPK were maintained high along with low pERK, there was a reduction in aCasapse and increase in levels of autophagosome as compared to the previous case, but apoptosis still dominated over autophagy. When pAkt and pERK were maintained high along with low pAMPK, levels of aCaspase was greater than levels of autophagosome. When pAMPK and pERK was maintained high along with low pAkt, levels of autophagosome was more than aCaspase. When all three levels of proteins were maintained high, levels of aCaspase was more than autophagosome. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figure 8D</xref> depicts the ratio of aCaspase and autophagosome for all eight combinations of proteins. The above results depict that the fluctuations in the levels of aCaspase are more than the changes in the levels of autophaghagosome. This also shows that autophagy is rather robust as compared to apoptosis which is more sensitive to molecular perturbations.</p><p id="P77">Our system consists of three key variables (Akt, AMPK and ERK) and each of them affect each other and their combined effect influences cell fate. This enhances the complexity of the above analyses. To minimize the complexity, we attempted methods of dimensionality reduction. Linear discriminant analysis (LDA) and principal component analysis (PCA) are ways of dimensionality reduction. We chose to perform a LDA on cell fate. As compared to PCA which is unsupervised and it does not consider the class difference of survival or death, linear discriminant analysis is supervised, and it preserves the class difference. LDA helps to reduce the dimensionality of three different variables (Akt, AMPK, ERK) by computing a weighted linear combination of all three and then evaluate its effect on cell fate. LDA maximizes between-class variance while minimizing within class variance. LDA analysis depicts that the combination of proteins that indicates towards most apoptotic cells (farthest away and above the decision boundary) comprise of high levels of pAkt, low levels of pAMPK and all concentrations of pERK. Alternately, the combination of proteins that indicates towards most apoptotic cells (farthest away and lower the decision boundary) comprise of lowest levels of pAkt, highest levels of pAMPK and all concentrations of pERK (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figure 8E</xref>). These results corroborate the previous outcomes and ascertain the superiority of Akt on cell fate decisions.</p></sec><sec id="S31"><title>How does the feedback between Akt-AMPK-ERK impact cell fate decisions?</title><p id="P78">The previous sections indicate several molecular signatures that favors anoikis. These proteins interact with each other indirectly. There is either a kinase or a phoshatase involved in each case. We hypothesized that perturbing the levels of these kinases and phosphatases may also contribute towards anoikis. Literature shows that PHLPP2 is involved in the negative feedback from AMPK to Akt and PP2Cα is involved in the negative feedback from Akt to AMPK (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">Saha et al., 2018</xref>). PEA15 and TFEB may be involved in the inhibitory feedback from AMPK to ERK and vive versa (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">Hindupur et al., 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">Kumar et al., BioRxiv, 2019</xref>). Molecular players that are involved in the Akt/ERK crosstalk is not yet known. These intermediate players affect the strength of the feedbacks. In order to study the effect of intermediate players on cell fate decisions, the strength of the feedbacks were altered and their effect on cell fate decisions were studied.</p><p id="P79">Each of these feedbacks are Hill functions and hence they vary from 0 to 1. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figure 9Ai</xref> shows that the original strength of the feedback from AMPK to Akt is 0.97 (as written in the bracket). The model is simulated by varying the strength of this feedback from 0.1 to 0.9 at an interval of 0.1, and the dynamics of pAkt, pAMPK, pERK and cell fate were plotted. Since the original strength of this feedback is 0.97, a value of 0.1 indicated least strength of this feedback which is synonymous to most effective knockdown of the intermediate player responsible for that feedback. Varying the strength of this feedback translates to different degrees of knockdown of the intemediate player. By varying the strength of this feedback from 0.1 to 0.9 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figure 9Ai</xref>), the model predicted the dynamics the pAkt (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figure 9Aii</xref>), pAMPK (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figure 9Aiii</xref>), pERK (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figure 9Aiv</xref>) and cell fate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figure 9Av</xref>). When the feedback was varied from low strength to high strength, the model predicted that the levels of pAkt ranged from 8 nM to 3 nM (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figure 9Aii</xref>), levels of pAMPK ranged from 7 nM to 8 nM (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figure 9Aiii</xref>), levels of pERK ranged from 2.5 nM to 4.5 nM (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figure 9Aiv</xref>). The most effective crossover between the levels of aCaspase and autophagosome happened at the lowest strength of this feedback (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figure 9Av</xref>). Altering the strength of this feedback primarily affects pAkt. However, the model also shows that different levels of pAkt impacts pAMPK and pERK. This also causes a gradient of cell fate, the most effective one being that of the lowest strength. The same effect was observed when the negative feedback from pERK to pAkt is delinked (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Figure 9B</xref>). However, for no other feedback perturbation (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary figure 11A-D</xref>), the crossover between apoptosis and autophagy was seen. Hence, the above results depict that in addition to perturbing Akt, the feedbacks affecting Akt can also be targeted to influence cell fate decisions.</p></sec></sec><sec id="S32" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p id="P80">Many cancer cells detach from the extracellular matrix (ECM); however most die due to anoikis and other stresses, while some adapt and survive, initiating metastasis. Cancer cells acquire resistance to anoikis by altering several signaling pathways. Understanding these altered pathways that contribute to the cell fate decisions of survival or death is crucial towards combating metastasis. Apoptosis is responsible for cell death, while autophagy generally plays a protective role in cells, albeit excessive autophagic flux or disrupted autophagy leads to cell death. Though some studies have investigated cell fate decisions as a balance between apoptosis and autophagy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33">Liu et al., 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R55">Tavassoly et al., 2015</xref>), this has not been explored extensively in the context of matrix-deprived cancer cells. This study investigates the interplay among Akt, AMPK, and ERK signaling pathways in regulating cell fate, specifically apoptosis and autophagy, in breast cancer cells deprived of extracellular matrix. It explores how these pathways, which can either promote cell death (apoptosis) or survival (autophagy), influence the balance between these processes and ultimately affect the resistance of cells to anoikis (matrix-dependent cell death).</p><p id="P81">We began the study by evaluating the status of autophagy and apoptosis in matrix-deprived breast cancer cells as compared to the matrix-attached state. When subjected to suspension for 24 h, we observed that in MDA-MB-231 metastatic breast cancer cells, the extent of autophagy was greater than apoptosis, suggesting, cell survival dominated cell death. These results intrigued us to ask how is the balance between autophagy and apoptosis regulated in matrix-deprived cancer cells which enables their survival and subsequent metastasis. Towards understanding this, we formulated an anoikis resistance mathematical model capturing the effects of matrix deprivation on apoptosis and autophagy via Akt-AMPK-ERK interplay – 3 key players that couple cell signaling perturbations to cell-fate decisions.</p><p id="P82">Following model calibration, validation and several mathematical analyses, the model was used to understand what levels of pAkt, pAMPK and pERK can bifurcate the cell fate into survival vs death. Concurrent with previous experimental data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">Saha et al., 2018</xref>), the model predicted that intermediate to high levels of pAkt and low levels of pAMPK trigger cell death. Interestingly, the model predicted a heterogeneity in pERK levels: high/low levels pERK along with high pAMPK enable survival as long as levels of pAkt are maintained low. This result is also partly corroborated by previous work from our lab, where we have shown that low pERK and high pAMPK levels enable survival (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">Kumar et al., 2019</xref>, bioRxiv). Additionally, the model predicted a heterogeneity in pAMPK: high/low levels of pAMPK along with low pERK determines the shift from survival to death when levels of pAkt are high. Such high levels of pAkt are obtained at critically low levels of pERK. Additionally, we have also shown previously that hyperactivation of Akt is detrimental to matrix-deprived breast cancer cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">Saha et al., 2018</xref>). Similarly, Akt hyperactivation has been also shown to induce cell death in chronic lymphocytic leukemia (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">Ecker et al., 2021</xref>). Pondering upon these results, we hypothesize that there may exist a threshold of low pERK below which activation of Akt dominates over AMPK to shift the balance in favour of cell death. Low levels of pERK may contribute to cell survival until pAkt is maintained low and pAMPK is high. It may be beyond the scope of experimental techniques to quantify this threshold of low pERK which may contribute towards the activation of Akt and hence the switch from cell survival to cell death. However, this theoretical study indicates towards the possibility of critically low levels of pERK, which leads to high pAkt and favor cell death. The data reveals that matrix-detached cancer cells exhibit complex signaling interactions, where the balance of these interactions dictates cell fate, while cellular heterogeneity arising from these cross-talks might potentially complicate cancer treatment.</p><p id="P83">Following the above findings, we were curious to know whether the zones of cell fate varied based on a single protein perturbed at a time or more than one protein perturbed simultaneously. This query banked on the fact that the cell fate decisions does not depend only on the perturbed protein but also depends on the effect that the perturbed protein has on the other proteins. Previously, we observed that when the levels of pERK were maintained low, intermediate or high, none of the perturbation depicted the crossover between aCaspase and autophagosome, thereby supporting cell survival (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary figure 10C</xref>). However, when pERK was perturbed either with pAkt or pAMPK, we observed the cell fate patterns (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7A-B</xref>) similar to independent perturbations of pAkt and pAMPK (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supplementary figure 10A-B</xref>). This indicated towards the existence of a hierarchy among Akt-AMPK-ERK while deciding the cell fate. Our results from the dual perturbation studies indicated that pAkt dominated over pAMPK which further dominated over pERK while contributing to cell fate decisions. When all the three proteins are pertubed at the same time, we acquired a three-dimensional space defining the cell fate. In this case too, we found that Akt split this three-dimensional space into two zones of pro-survival and pro-apoptotic (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figure 8A-B</xref>). Additionally, feedback perturbation study also revealed that removing inhibitory feedbacks from AMPK to Akt and ERK to Akt, enables prediction of cell death (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figure 8A-B</xref>). Thus, in this study, Akt emerged as the deciding factor in influencing cell fate pathways like apoptosis and autophagy in matrix-deprived cancer cells. These results suggest the possibility of narrowing down to key molecular targets to attack matrix-deprived cancer cells.</p><p id="P84">Lastly, by shifting our focus on apoptosis and autophagy, we wanted to understand which among these two pathways contributed majorly to their crossover leading to cell death: is it reduced autophagy, enhanced apoptosis or both simultaneously. By sampling eight extreme combinations of pAkt, pAMPK and pERK we noticed that apoptosis (aCaspase) is imapcted more than autophagy (autophagosome). This indicates that autophagy is a robust mechanism and may not fluctutate much due to molecular pertubation. It may serve as a block to cell death. However, apoptosis is more sensitive to molecular perturbations and is majorly impacted by pAkt in matrix-deprived condition (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figure 8C-D</xref>). In keepinf with this, a prior report also showed that Akt sensitizes cells to oxidative apoptosis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42">Nogueira et al., 2008</xref>). These data show that Akt-AMPK-ERK influence cell fate decision pathways like apoptosis and autophagy in a very regulated manner. Akt impacts apoptosis more than autophagy and classifies the cell fate decision into pro-survival and pro-apoptotic zones in the matrix-deprived state.</p><p id="P85">Though there are several interesting insights in this work, there are a few limitations too. To evaluate the status of autophagy and apoptosis in matrix-deprived breast cancer cell, autophagy and apoptosis assays were performed in independent sets of MDA-MB-231 cells exposed to matrix deprivation as compared to the attached condition. However, it will be interesting to design an experiment to investigate the status of autophagy and apoptosis in the same population of matrix-deprived cancer cells. Further, in this study we did not consider the effect of aCaspases or autophagosomes on pAkt, pAMPK and pERK. Here, only the proteins influence the cell fate markers. Additionally, we did not look into the crosstalk between autophagy and apoptosis as described previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">Eisenberg et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">Bata and Cosford, 2021</xref>). Here, we described the balance between autophagy and apoptosis as a cell fate for cell survival or cell death. Additionally, both time and status of matrix are independent variables, and the proteins and cell fate markers depend on the time and status of matrix. However, the transition from attached state to matrix-deprived state is also a time-dependent phenomena. It will be interesting to introduce matrix as a time dependent variable and then check the effect of matrix on the system. Lastly, due to the availability of experimental data at limited timepoints, parameter estimation was performed manually and the model fitting to experimental data was done qualitatively. It will be very helpful to design future experiments which would be conducive for mathematical modeling work and hence aid in the understanding a biological phenomenon jointly.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="SM"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1"><label>Supplementary Information</label><media xlink:href="EMS206455-supplement-Supplementary_Information.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" id="d71aAcEbB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD2"><label>Supplementary Figures</label><media xlink:href="EMS206455-supplement-Supplementary_Figures.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" id="d71aAcEcB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack id="S33"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We acknowledge Diptanshu Banerjee for helping with experiments. S.M. acknowledges the Prime Minister Research Fellowship (PMRF). Funds from Wellcome Trust DBT India Alliance Senior Research Fellowship (500112-Z-09-Z to AR) and funds from the DBT-IISc partnership programme of the Department of Biotechnology, Govt of India, for experimental data used in this manuscript are acknowledged. Infrastructural support from the UGC and DST-FIST to the Department of DBG is also acknowledged.</p></ack><fn-group><fn id="FN1" fn-type="con"><p id="P86"><bold>Author contributions</bold></p><p id="P87">S.M., and A.R. conceptualized and designed the study. S.M. performed all the experiments, constructed the model in MATLAB, performed all the computer simulations, assembled and analyzed the data and scripted the original draft of the manuscript. A.C. supervised the model building and all the mathematical analyses for model construction. S.M., A.C, M.K.J, N.C., and A.R. were involved in interpreting the results and critical discussion. A.R., M.K.J, N.C. edited and revised the manuscript.</p></fn><fn id="FN2" fn-type="conflict"><p id="P88"><bold>Declaration of interests</bold></p><p id="P89">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><ref id="R1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aoki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kunida</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yasuda</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsuda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Processive phosphorylation of ERK MAP kinase in mammalian cells</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</source><year>2011</year><volume>108</volume><issue>31</issue><fpage>12675</fpage><lpage>12680</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3150946</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21768338</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1104030108</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bata</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Cosford</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cell survival and cell death at the intersection of autophagy and apoptosis: Implications for current and future cancer therapeutics</article-title><source>ACS pharmacology &amp; translational science</source><year>2021</year><volume>4</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1728</fpage><lpage>1746</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8669714</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34927007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acsptsci.1c00130</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bartlett</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bartlette</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group><source>Chapter 2: first order differential equations</source><year>2012</year><comment>Retrieved on November, 23</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Buchheit</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Weigel</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Schafer</surname><given-names>ZT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cancer cell survival during detachment from the ECM: multiple barriers to tumour progression</article-title><source>Nature Reviews Cancer</source><year>2014</year><volume>14</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>632</fpage><lpage>641</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25098270</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bungard</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Fuerth</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>PY</given-names></name><name><surname>Faubert</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Maas</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name><name><surname>Viollet</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Carling</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Signaling kinase AMPK activates stress-promoted transcription via histone H2B phosphorylation</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2010</year><volume>329</volume><issue>5996</issue><fpage>1201</fpage><lpage>1205</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3922052</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20647423</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1191241</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Detachment-Based Equilibrium of Anoikic Cell Death and Autophagic Cell Survival Through Adaptor Protein p66Shc</article-title><source>The Anatomical Record</source><year>2016</year><volume>299</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>325</fpage><lpage>333</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26643258</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chaffer</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Weinberg</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A perspective on cancer cell metastasis</article-title><source>science</source><year>2011</year><volume>331</volume><issue>6024</issue><fpage>1559</fpage><lpage>1564</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21436443</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chedere</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hari</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rangarajan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Jolly</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multi-stability and consequent phenotypic plasticity in ampk-akt double negative feedback loop in cancer cells</article-title><source>Journal of clinical medicine</source><year>2021</year><volume>10</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>472</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7865639</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33530625</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/jcm10030472</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Hsia</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name><name><surname>Yeh</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name><name><surname>Tu</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MEK inhibitors induce Akt activation and drug resistance by suppressing negative feedback ERK-mediated HER 2 phosphorylation at Thr701</article-title><source>Molecular oncology</source><year>2017</year><volume>11</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>1273</fpage><lpage>1287</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5579385</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28632938</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/1878-0261.12102</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ecker</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Stumpf</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Brandmeier</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Neumayer</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Pfeuffer</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Engleitner</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ringshausen</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Jücker</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wanninger</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zenz</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Targeted PI3K/AKT-hyperactivation induces cell death in chronic lymphocytic leukemia</article-title><source>Nature Communications</source><year>2021</year><volume>12</volume><issue>1</issue><elocation-id>3526</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8192787</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34112805</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-021-23752-2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grossmann</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular mechanisms of “detachment-induced apoptosis—Anoikis”</article-title><source>Apoptosis</source><year>2002</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>247</fpage><lpage>260</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hindupur</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Balaji</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Saxena</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pandey</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sravan</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name><name><surname>Heda</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name><name><surname>Mukherjee</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Dey</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Rangarajan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of a novel AMPK-PEA15 axis in the anoikis-resistant growth of mammary cells</article-title><source>Breast Cancer Research</source><year>2014</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>16</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4303232</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25096718</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13058-014-0420-z</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hinz</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Jücker</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Distinct functions of AKT isoforms in breast cancer: a comprehensive review</article-title><source>Cell Communication and Signaling</source><year>2019</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>29</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6873690</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31752925</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12964-019-0450-3</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Napolitano</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Ballabio</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>TFEB at a glance</article-title><source>J Cell Sci</source><year>2016</year><month>Jul</month><day>1</day><volume>129</volume><issue>13</issue><fpage>2475</fpage><lpage>81</lpage><comment>Epub 2016 Jun 1</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4958300</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27252382</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/jcs.146365</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saha</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bukhari</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Balaji</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hindupur</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Rangarajan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>AMPK–Akt double-negative feedback loop in breast cancer cells regulates their adaptation to matrix deprivation</article-title><source>Cancer research</source><year>2018</year><volume>78</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1497</fpage><lpage>1510</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6033311</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29339542</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-17-2090</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Settembre</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Di Malta</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Polito</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name><name><surname>Garcia Arencibia</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Vetrini</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Erdin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Erdin</surname><given-names>SU</given-names></name><name><surname>Huynh</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Medina</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Colella</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Sardiello</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>TFEB links autophagy to lysosomal biogenesis</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2011</year><month>Jun</month><day>17</day><volume>332</volume><issue>6036</issue><fpage>1429</fpage><lpage>33</lpage><comment>Epub 2011 May 26</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3638014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21617040</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1204592</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Timofeev</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Giron</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Lawo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Pichler</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Noeparast</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>ERK pathway agonism for cancer therapy: evidence, insights, and a target discovery framework</article-title><source>NPJ Precision Oncology</source><year>2024</year><volume>8</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>70</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10940698</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38485987</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41698-024-00554-5</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Ouyang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of anoikis-related subgroups and prognosis model in liver hepatocellular carcinoma</article-title><source>International journal of molecular sciences</source><year>2023</year><volume>24</volume><issue>3</issue><elocation-id>2862</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9918018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36769187</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms24032862</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Debnath</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gammoh</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Autophagy and autophagy-related pathways in cancer</article-title><source>Nature reviews Molecular cell biology</source><year>2023</year><volume>24</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>560</fpage><lpage>575</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9980873</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36864290</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41580-023-00585-z</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Degtyarev</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>De Mazière</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Orr</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name><name><surname>Tien</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name><surname>Prior</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name><name><surname>van Dijk</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Akt inhibition promotes autophagy and sensitizes PTEN-null tumors to lysosomotropic agents</article-title><source>The Journal of cell biology</source><year>2008</year><volume>183</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>101</fpage><lpage>116</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2557046</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18838554</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.200801099</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eisenberg-Lerner</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bialik</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>HU</given-names></name><name><surname>Kimchi</surname><given-names>AJCD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Life and death partners: apoptosis, autophagy and the cross-talk between them</article-title><source>Cell Death &amp; Differentiation</source><year>2009</year><volume>16</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>966</fpage><lpage>975</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19325568</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fornari</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Pin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Yates</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Mettetal</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Importance of stability analysis when using nonlinear Semimechanistic models to describe drug-induced Hematotoxicity</article-title><source>CPT: pharmacometrics &amp; systems pharmacology</source><year>2020</year><volume>9</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>498</fpage><lpage>508</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7499189</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32453487</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/psp4.12514</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Frisch</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Francis</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Disruption of epithelial cell-matrix interactions induces apoptosis</article-title><source>The Journal of cell biology</source><year>1994</year><volume>124</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>619</fpage><lpage>626</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2119917</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8106557</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.124.4.619</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gump</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Thorburn</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Autophagy and apoptosis: what is the connection?</article-title><source>Trends in cell biology</source><year>2011</year><volume>21</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>387</fpage><lpage>392</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3539742</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21561772</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tcb.2011.03.007</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hindupur</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Balaji</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Saxena</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pandey</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sravan</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name><name><surname>Heda</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name><name><surname>Mukherjee</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Dey</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Rangarajan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of a novel AMPK-PEA15 axis in the anoikis-resistant growth of mammary cells</article-title><source>Breast Cancer Research</source><year>2014</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>16</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Holczer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hajdú</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Lőrincz</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Szarka</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bánhegyi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Kapuy</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fine-tuning of AMPK–ULK1–mTORC1 regulatory triangle is crucial for autophagy oscillation</article-title><source>Scientific Reports</source><year>2020</year><volume>10</volume><issue>1</issue><elocation-id>17803</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7576158</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33082544</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-020-75030-8</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Reggiori</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular regulation of autophagosome formation</article-title><source>Biochemical Society Transactions</source><year>2022</year><volume>50</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>55</fpage><lpage>69</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9022990</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35076688</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1042/BST20210819</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ichimura</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumanomidou</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Sou</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name><name><surname>Mizushima</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ezaki</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ueno</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kominami</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamane</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Komatsu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structural basis for sorting mechanism of p62 in selective autophagy</article-title><source>Journal of Biological Chemistry</source><year>2008</year><volume>283</volume><issue>33</issue><fpage>22847</fpage><lpage>22857</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18524774</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koç</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Çelik-Uzuner</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Uzuner</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Çakmak</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The detailed comparison of cell death detected by annexin V-PI counterstain using fluorescence microscope, flow cytometry and automated cell counter in mammalian and microalgae cells</article-title><source>Journal of fluorescence</source><year>2018</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>1393</fpage><lpage>1404</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30343360</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hari</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Jolly</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Rangarajan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Feedback loops involving ERK, AMPK and TFEB generate non-genetic heterogeneity that allows cells to evade anoikis</article-title><source>bioRxiv</source><year>2019</year><elocation-id>736546</elocation-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lavoie</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Gagnon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Therrien</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>ERK signalling: a master regulator of cell behaviour, life and fate</article-title><source>Nature reviews Molecular cell biology</source><year>2020</year><volume>21</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>607</fpage><lpage>632</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32576977</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lippai</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lőw</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of the selective adaptor p62 and ubiquitin-like proteins in autophagy</article-title><source>BioMed research international</source><year>2014</year><volume>2014</volume><issue>1</issue><elocation-id>832704</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4075091</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25013806</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2014/832704</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Oltvai</surname><given-names>ZN</given-names></name><name><surname>Bayir</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Silverman</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Pak</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Perlmutter</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Bahar</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quantitative assessment of cell fate decision between autophagy and apoptosis</article-title><source>Scientific reports</source><year>2017</year><volume>7</volume><issue>1</issue><elocation-id>17605</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5730598</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29242632</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-017-18001-w</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Autophagy: Regulator of cell death</article-title><source>Cell death &amp; disease</source><year>2023</year><volume>14</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>648</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10551038</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37794028</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41419-023-06154-8</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maiti</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rangarajan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kareenhalli</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Experimentally-driven mathematical model to understand the effects of matrix deprivation in breast cancer metastasis</article-title><source>npj Systems Biology and Applications</source><year>2024</year><volume>10</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>132</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11557960</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39532909</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41540-024-00443-4</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marrone</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name><name><surname>Sepulchre</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ventura</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pseudo-nullclines enable the analysis and prediction of signaling model dynamics</article-title><source>Frontiers in Cell and Developmental Biology</source><year>2023</year><volume>11</volume><elocation-id>1209589</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10568075</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37842096</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fcell.2023.1209589</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R37"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mason</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hagel</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name><surname>Hawk</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Schafer</surname><given-names>ZT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Metabolism during ECM detachment: achilles heel of cancer cells?</article-title><source>Trends in cancer</source><year>2017</year><volume>3</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>475</fpage><lpage>481</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28718402</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R38"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moelling</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Schad</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Bosse</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Zimmermann</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Schweneker</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regulation of Raf-Akt cross-talk</article-title><source>Journal of Biological Chemistry</source><year>2002</year><volume>277</volume><issue>34</issue><fpage>31099</fpage><lpage>31106</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12048182</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R39"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name><surname>Leprivier</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Chow</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Laderoute</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name><surname>Davicioni</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Triche</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Sorensen</surname><given-names>PHB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The AMPK stress response pathway mediates anoikis resistance through inhibition of mTOR and suppression of protein synthesis</article-title><source>Cell Death &amp; Differentiation</source><year>2012</year><volume>19</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>501</fpage><lpage>510</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3278733</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21941369</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/cdd.2011.119</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R40"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nicholson</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>NG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The protein kinase B/Akt signalling pathway in human malignancy</article-title><source>Cellular signalling</source><year>2002</year><volume>14</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>381</fpage><lpage>395</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11882383</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R41"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nikoletopoulou</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Markaki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Palikaras</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Tavernarakis</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Crosstalk between apoptosis, necrosis and autophagy</article-title><source>Biochimica et Biophysica Acta (BBA)-Molecular Cell Research</source><year>2013</year><volume>1833</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>3448</fpage><lpage>3459</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23770045</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R42"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nogueira</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>PZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Tonic</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Unterman</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hay</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Akt determines replicative senescence and oxidative or oncogenic premature senescence and sensitizes cells to oxidative apoptosis</article-title><source>Cancer cell</source><year>2008</year><volume>14</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>458</fpage><lpage>470</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3038665</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19061837</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ccr.2008.11.003</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R43"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Paoli</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Giannoni</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Chiarugi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anoikis molecular pathways and its role in cancer progression</article-title><source>Biochimica et Biophysica Acta (BBA)-Molecular Cell Research</source><year>2013</year><volume>1833</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>3481</fpage><lpage>3498</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23830918</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R44"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ryter</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name><surname>Mizumura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The impact of autophagy on cell death modalities</article-title><source>International journal of cell biology</source><year>2014</year><volume>2014</volume><issue>1</issue><elocation-id>502676</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3932252</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24639873</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2014/502676</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R45"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saha</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><source>Role of AMP-Activated Protein Kinase in Cancer Cell Survival under Matrix-Deprived Conditions</source><year>2018</year><publisher-name>Doctoral dissertation</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="R46"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saha</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bukhari</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Balaji</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hindupur</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Rangarajan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>AMPK–Akt double-negative feedback loop in breast cancer cells regulates their adaptation to matrix deprivation</article-title><source>Cancer research</source><year>2018</year><volume>78</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1497</fpage><lpage>1510</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R47"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Settembre</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Di Malta</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Polito</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name><name><surname>Arencibia</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Vetrini</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Erdin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Erdin</surname><given-names>SU</given-names></name><name><surname>Huynh</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Medina</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Colella</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Sardiello</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>TFEB links autophagy to lysosomal biogenesis</article-title><source>science</source><year>2011</year><volume>332</volume><issue>6036</issue><fpage>1429</fpage><lpage>1433</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R48"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Buel</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolgamott</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Plas</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Asara</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Blenis</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoon</surname><given-names>SO</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>ERK2 mediates metabolic stress response to regulate cell fate</article-title><source>Molecular cell</source><year>2015</year><volume>59</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>382</fpage><lpage>398</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4530034</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26190261</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molcel.2015.06.020</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R49"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Simpson</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Anyiwe</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Schimmer</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anoikis resistance and tumor metastasis</article-title><source>Cancer letters</source><year>2008</year><volume>272</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>177</fpage><lpage>185</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18579285</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R50"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sobie</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bistability in biochemical signaling models</article-title><source>Science signaling</source><year>2011</year><volume>4</volume><issue>192</issue><elocation-id>tr10</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4118931</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21954291</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/scisignal.2001964</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R51"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stolz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ernst</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Dikic</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cargo recognition and trafficking in selective autophagy</article-title><source>Nature cell biology</source><year>2014</year><volume>16</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>495</fpage><lpage>501</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24875736</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R52"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stulpinas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sereika</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Vitkeviciene</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Imbrasaite</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Krestnikova</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalvelyte</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Crosstalk between protein kinases AKT and ERK1/2 in human lung tumor-derived cell models</article-title><source>Frontiers in Oncology</source><year>2023</year><volume>12</volume><elocation-id>1045521</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9848735</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36686779</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fonc.2022.1045521</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R53"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sundararaman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Amirtham</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Rangarajan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Calcium-oxidant signaling network regulates AMP-activated protein kinase (AMPK) activation upon matrix deprivation</article-title><source>Journal of Biological Chemistry</source><year>2016</year><volume>291</volume><issue>28</issue><fpage>14410</fpage><lpage>14429</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4938166</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27226623</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M116.731257</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R54"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Todd</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanner</surname><given-names>KG</given-names></name><name><surname>Denu</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Extracellular regulated kinases (ERK) 1 and ERK2 are authentic substrates for the dual-specificity protein-tyrosine phosphatase VHR: a novel role in downregulating the ERK pathway</article-title><source>Journal of Biological Chemistry</source><year>1999</year><volume>274</volume><issue>19</issue><fpage>13271</fpage><lpage>13280</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10224087</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R55"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tavassoly</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Parmar</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Shajahan-Haq</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name><name><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Baumann</surname><given-names>WT</given-names></name><name><surname>Tyson</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dynamic modeling of the interaction between autophagy and apoptosis in mammalian cells</article-title><source>CPT: pharmacometrics &amp; systems pharmacology</source><year>2015</year><volume>4</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>263</fpage><lpage>272</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4429580</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26225250</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/psp4.29</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R56"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>An</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhagat</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Reichelt</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Levine</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Akt-mediated regulation of autophagy and tumorigenesis through Beclin 1 phosphorylation</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2012</year><volume>338</volume><issue>6109</issue><fpage>956</fpage><lpage>959</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3507442</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23112296</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1225967</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R57"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Warrier</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Srinivasan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Chedere</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rangarajan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inhibition of protein translation under matrix-deprivation stress in breast cancer cells</article-title><source>Frontiers in Medicine</source><year>2023</year><volume>10</volume><elocation-id>1124514</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10324034</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37425300</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmed.2023.1124514</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R58"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeong</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Asara</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>YY</given-names></name><name><surname>Granter</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Chin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Cantley</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Oncogenic B-RAF negatively regulates the tumor suppressor LKB1 to promote melanoma cell proliferation</article-title><source>Molecular cell</source><year>2009</year><volume>33</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>237</fpage><lpage>247</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2715556</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19187764</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molcel.2008.12.026</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R59"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Development of a prognostic model to predict BLCA based on anoikis-related gene signature: preliminary findings</article-title><source>BMC urology</source><year>2023</year><volume>23</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>199</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10694890</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38049825</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12894-023-01382-8</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Matrix deprivation promotes autophagy and apoptosis.</title><p>MDA-MB-231 cells were cultured in matrix-attached (att) and matrix-deprived (sus) condition for 24 h. Thereafter, cells were harvested for autophagy assay and apoptosis assay. <bold>(A)</bold> Representative epifluorescence microscopy images of autophagosome distribution in MDA-MB-231 cells exposed to matrix-attached and matrix-deprived conditions. <bold>(B)</bold> Graphs represent relative fluorescence intensity measurements for equal number of cells across matrix-attached and matrix-deprived conditions. <bold>(C)</bold> Representative flow cytometry dot plots of apoptosis. The lower left quadrant shows percentage of live cells [Annexin V(-)/PI(-)], upper left quadrant shows percentage of necrotic cells [Annexin V(-)/PI(+)], lower right quadrant shows percentage of early apoptotic cells [Annexin V(+)/PI(-)] and upper right quadrant shows percentage of late apoptotic cells [Annexin V(+)/PI(+)]. <bold>(D)</bold> Graphs represent the quantification of the proportion of cells in the late apoptosis state. Error bars represent SEM, n=3. Scale bars: 100 μM. *P &lt; 0.05; **P &lt; 0.01; *** P &lt; 0.001 ; ns: not significant.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS206455-f001"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Anoikis resistance mathematical model.</title><p><bold>(A) Model construction. i</bold> Multiple pathways that regulate anoikis and are perturbed upon matrix deprivation. <bold>ii</bold> The anoikis resistance mathematical model depicting the model input: matrix, model players: Akt, AMPK and ERK, and model outputs: apoptosis and autophagy.</p><p><bold>(B) Model calibration.</bold> The calibration set consists of temporal dynamics of simulated concentration of following protein species in MDA-MB-231 cell line for 24 h period following matrix deprivation: <bold>i</bold> pAkt, <bold>ii</bold> pAMPK, <bold>iii</bold> pERK, <bold>iv</bold> Autophagy, and <bold>v</bold> Apoptosis. The above calibration data is summarized in the table. The red shared area depicts the range of experimental data. The black solid line depicts the temporal dynamics predicted by the model. The black arrow indicates the time point of induction of matrix deprivation. X axis depicts time in minutes, where, first 60 minutes is the matrix-attached state and remaining is the matrix-deprived state. Y axis depicts the fold change normalized to matrix-attached condition.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS206455-f002"/></fig><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Mathematical analysis of anoikis resistance model.</title><p><bold>(A)</bold> Temporal dynamics of model variables in <bold>(i)</bold> matrix attached and <bold>(ii)</bold> matrix-deprived state. X axis depicts time in minutes. Y axis depicts the concentration of pAkt, pAMPK and pERK in nM or levels of apoptosis and autophagy. <bold>(B)</bold> Effect of randomly-sampled initial conditions on steady states of pAkt, AMPK and pERK in <bold>(i)</bold> matrix attached and <bold>(ii)</bold> matrix-deprived state. For each matrix-attached and matrix-deprived state, the panel of the left shows 1000 random initial states which were sampled from a uniform distribution of range 1-10 nM and the panel on the right shows the final steady state values at 1440 min, with the mean value depicted on the graph. X axis depicts the three model players (pAkt, pAMPK and pERK). Y axis depicts the concentration of these protein in nM. (C) 3D-nullcline analysis for (i) matrix attached and (ii) matrix-deprived state. The red surface shows pAkt nullcline (d/dt(pAkt) = 0; X axis). The green surface shows pAMPK nullcline (d/dt(pAMPK) = 0;) The blue surface shows pERK nullcline (d/dt(pERK) = 0). The intersection point of three nullclines depict the stable steady state value of the (i) matrix-attached state [5.44, 1.71, 2.25] and (ii) matrix-deprived state [2.45, 8.27, 4.82].</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS206455-f003"/></fig><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Model validation.</title><p><bold>(A)</bold> Flux map in matrix-attached (blue) and matrix-deprived (red) condition. Numbers along the feedbacks indicate their magnitude in terms of the corresponding hill function values (mentioned on the left), which lie between 0 and 1. The matrix-attached state is marked by high levels of pAkt and low levels of pAMPK and pERK. The matrix-deprived state is marked by low levels of pAkt and high levels pAMPK and pERK. <bold>(B)</bold> The effect of hyperactivation of Akt on apoptosis and autophagy. <bold>(C)</bold> The effect of inhibition of AMPK on apoptosis and autophagy. <bold>(D)</bold> The effect of knockdown of PHLPP2 on pAkt and pAMPK in the absence and presence of Akt inhibition and apoptosis and autophagy. X axis depicts time in minutes. Y axis depicts concentration (nM) or levels of apoptosis and autophagy.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS206455-f004"/></fig><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>Parameter sensitivity analysis.</title><p>The effect of small perturbation of all model parameters on pAkt, pAMPK and pERK in (A) matrix-attached state and (B) matrix-deprived state. Effect above 10% is shown in deep red color and less than -10% is shown in deep green color and is considered highly sensitive. Effect from from 8% to 10% is shown in light red color or -8% to -10% is shown in light green color and is considered to be sensitive and any value in between -8% to 8% is shown in white and is not sensitive.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS206455-f005"/></fig><fig id="F6" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title>Effect of Akt-AMPK-ERK interplay on cell fate of matrix-deprived cancer cells.</title><p><bold>(A)</bold> The effect of differential activity Akt on apoptosis (black line) and autophagy (dark-green line). The red-dotted line depicts the concentration of pAkt at steady state and grey-dotted line depicts the concentration of pAkt at the cross over of apoptosis and autophagy. <bold>(B)</bold> The effect of differential activity Akt on pAMPK (light-green line) and pERK (blue line). <bold>(C)</bold> The effect of differential activity pAMPK on apoptosis (black line) and autophagy (dark-green line). The green-dotted line depicts the concentration of pAMPK at steady state and grey-dotted line depicts the concentration of pAMPK at the cross over of apoptosis and autophagy. <bold>(D)</bold> The effect of differential activity AMPK on pAkt (red line) and pERK (blue line). <bold>(E)</bold> The effect of differential activity pERK on apoptosis (black line) and autophagy (dark-green line). The blue-dotted line depicts the concentration of pERK at steady state and grey-dotted line depicts the concentration of pERK at the cross over of apoptosis and autophagy. <bold>(F)</bold> The effect of differential activity pERK on pAkt (red line) and pAMPK (light-green line). X axis depicts concentration of proteins (pAkt, pAMPK, pERK). For the left panel, the left Y axis depicts the levels of apoptosis, and the right Y axis depicts the levels of autophagy. For the right panel, both Y axes depict the concentration of proteins.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS206455-f006"/></fig><fig id="F7" position="float"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><title>Effect of dual protein perturbation on apoptosis and autophagy.</title><p>The left panel shows proteins which are maintained in low (2 nM), intermediate (5 nM) and high (8 nM) levels and the right panel shows their effect on apoptosis (aCaspase; black line) and autophagy (autophagosome; dark-green line) for <bold>(A)</bold> pAkt and pERK perturbation, <bold>(B)</bold> pAMPK and pERK perturbation, and <bold>(C)</bold> pAkt and pAMPK perturbation. X axis shows time in minutes. Y axis shows concentration in nM.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS206455-f007"/></fig><fig id="F8" position="float"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><title>Akt impacts apoptosis more than autophagy and classifies the cell fate decision into pro-survival and pro-apoptotic zones in the matrix-deprived state.</title><p><bold>(A)</bold> A three-dimensional space with 125 different combinations of Akt (X axis), AMPK (Y axis) and ERK (Z axis). The coordinates [1,1,1] shows the lowest concentration of Akt, AMPK and ERK (colored deep blue) and [10,10,10] shows the highest concentration (colored deep red). The intermediate concentrations, 3 nM, 5 nM and 7 nM, are depicted by intermediate color ranges. The heat map color bar shows a normalized value between 0 and 1. The normalization was done in the following manner: the point [1,1,1] has a combined value of 3, which normalizes to (3-3)/(30-3) = 0, resulting in deep blue color. The point [10,10,10] has a combined value of 30, which normalizes to (30-3)/(30-3) = 1, resulting in deep red. All other points fall somewhere in between on the scale. For example, [5,5,5] has a combined value of 15, normalizing to (15-3)/30-3) = 12/27 ~ 0.44, resulting in greenish-cyan color. <bold>(B)</bold> For each of these 125 combinations of proteins, the levels of aCaspase and autophagosome were computed and the ratio of aCaspase and autophagosome was evaluated. When the ratio was less than 1 (aCaspase &lt; autophagosome), those combinations of proteins were marked to belong to the pro-survival zone (marked with green dots). When the ratio was more than 1 (aCaspase &gt; autophagosome), those combinations of proteins were marked to belong to the pro-apoptotic zone (marked with red dots). The two-dimensional surface (blue) is called the decision boundary and it marks the plane where the ratio is equal to 1. <bold>(C)</bold> Effects of different concentrations of pAkt, pAMPK and pERK (along the X axis) on aCaspase (red) and autophagosome (green) (along the Y axis). <bold>(D)</bold> Effects of different concentrations of pAkt, pAMPK and pERK (along the X axis) on the ratio of aCaspase/autophagosome (green) (along the Y axis). Ratio below 1 marks the pro-survial zone (green) and ratio above 1 marks the pro-apoptotic zone (red). <bold>(E)</bold> Linear discriminant analysis of 125 combinations of pAkt, pAMPK and pERK and the resultant cell fate outcome. Each circle represents one combination, with colors indicating pro-survival zone (green, ratio &lt; 1) and pro-apoptotic zone (red, ratio &gt; 1). X-axis (LDA Component 1) shows the discriminant score representing the optimal linear combination of pAkt, pAMPK, and pERK that maximally separates cell fate classes. Higher values indicate combinations more favorable to cell survival; lower values indicate combinations more favorable to apoptosis. Y-axis (Ratio - 1, Distance from Decision Boundary) shows distance from the cell fate decision threshold, calculated as the aCaspase/Autophagosome ratio minus 1. Positive values (above dashed line) indicate apoptotic dominance (aCaspase &gt; Autophagosome); negative values (below dashed line) indicate survival dominance (Autophagosome &gt; aCaspase). The horizontal dashed line at y = 0 represents the decision boundary which shows the critical threshold where aCaspase and Autophagosome levels are equal (ratio = 1), separating survival and apoptotic cell fate domains.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS206455-f008"/></fig><fig id="F9" position="float"><label>Figure 9</label><caption><title>The effect of feedback perturbation on pAkt, pAMPK, pERK and cell fate.</title><p><bold>(A</bold>) Delinking the feedback from AMPK to Akt <bold>(B)</bold> Delinking the feedback from ERK to Akt.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS206455-f009"/></fig></floats-group></article>