<!DOCTYPE article
 PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" article-type="preprint"><?all-math-mml yes?><?use-mml?><?origin ukpmcpa?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">bioRxiv</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>bioRxiv : the preprint server for biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2692-8205</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">EMS207439</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2025.07.18.665573</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="archive">PPR1053137</article-id><article-version-alternatives><article-version article-version-type="status">preprint</article-version><article-version article-version-type="number">1</article-version></article-version-alternatives><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Astrocytes connect specific brain regions through plastic gap junctional networks</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>Melissa L</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CR1">#</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Selles</surname><given-names>Maria Clara</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cammer</surname><given-names>Michael</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gildea</surname><given-names>Holly K</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sall</surname><given-names>Joseph</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chiurri</surname><given-names>Katelyn E</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Saab</surname><given-names>Aiman S</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Liddelow</surname><given-names>Shane A</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">5</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A6">6</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CR1">#</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chao</surname><given-names>Moses V</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">5</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A8">8</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A9">9</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CR1">#</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN1">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Institute for Translational Neuroscience, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/0190ak572</institution-id><institution>NYU</institution></institution-wrap> Grossman School of Medicine, <city>New York</city>, <state>NY</state><country country="US">USA</country></aff><aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Microscopy Laboratory, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/0190ak572</institution-id><institution>NYU</institution></institution-wrap> Grossman School of Medicine, <city>New York</city>, <state>NY</state><country country="US">USA</country></aff><aff id="A3"><label>3</label>Institute of Pharmacology and Toxicology, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/02crff812</institution-id><institution>University of Zurich</institution></institution-wrap>, <city>Zurich</city>, <country country="CH">Switzerland&gt;</country></aff><aff id="A4"><label>4</label>Neuroscience Center Zurich, University and <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">05a28rw58</institution-id><institution>ETH Zurich</institution></institution-wrap>, <city>Zurich</city>, <country country="CH">Switzerland&gt;</country></aff><aff id="A5"><label>5</label>Department of Neuroscience, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/0190ak572</institution-id><institution>NYU</institution></institution-wrap> Grossman School of Medicine, <city>New York</city>, <state>NY</state><country country="US">USA</country></aff><aff id="A6"><label>6</label>Department of Ophthalmology, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/0190ak572</institution-id><institution>NYU</institution></institution-wrap> Langone Health, <city>New York</city>, <state>NY</state><country country="US">USA</country></aff><aff id="A7"><label>7</label>Parekh Center for Interdisciplinary Neurology, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/0190ak572</institution-id><institution>NYU</institution></institution-wrap> Grossman School of Medicine, <city>New York</city>, <state>NY</state><country country="US">USA</country></aff><aff id="A8"><label>8</label>Department of Psychiatry, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/0190ak572</institution-id><institution>NYU</institution></institution-wrap> Langone Health, <city>New York</city>, <state>NY</state><country country="US">USA</country></aff><aff id="A9"><label>9</label>Department of Cell Biology, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/0190ak572</institution-id><institution>NYU</institution></institution-wrap> Grossman School of Medicine, <city>New York</city>, <state>NY</state><country country="US">USA</country></aff><author-notes><corresp id="CR1">
<label>#</label>Corresponding authors: <email>melissa.cooper@nyulangone.org</email>, <email>shane.liddelow@nyulangone.org</email>, <email>moses.chao@nyulangone.org</email>
</corresp><fn id="FN1"><label>*</label><p id="P1">Jointly supervised this work</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted"><day>23</day><month>07</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="preprint"><day>22</day><month>07</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><permissions><ali:free_to_read/><license><ali:license_ref>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is licensed under a <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">CC BY-NC 4.0 International license</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p id="P2">Traditionally, neuronal axons have been considered the primary mediators of functional connectivity among brain regions. However, the role of astrocyte-mediated communication has been largely underappreciated. While astrocytes communicate with one another through gap junctions, the extent and specificity of this communication remain poorly understood. Astrocyte gap junctions are necessary for memory formation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">2</xref></sup>, synaptic plasticity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">3</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref></sup>, coordination of neuronal signaling<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref></sup>, and closing the visual and motor critical periods<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">8</xref></sup>. These findings indicate that this form of communication is essential for proper central nervous system development and function. Despite their significance, studying astrocyte gap junctional networks has been challenging. Current methods like slice electrophysiology disrupt network connectivity and introduce artifacts due to tissue damage. To overcome these limitations, we developed a vector-based approach that labels molecules as they are fluxed by astrocyte gap junctions in awake, behaving animals. We then used whole-brain tissue clearing<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref></sup> to image these intact, three-dimensional astrocyte networks. We show that multiple astrocyte networks traverse the mouse brain. These networks selectively connect specific regions, rather than diffusing indiscriminately, and vary in size and organization. We observe local networks are confined to single brain regions and long-range networks robustly interconnecting multiple regions across hemispheres, often exhibiting patterns distinct from known neuronal networks. Further, we demonstrate that astrocyte networks undergo structural reorganization in adult brain following sensory deprivation. These discoveries reveal a previously unrecognized mode of communication between distant brain regions, mediated by plastic networks of gap junction-coupled astrocytes.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec id="S1" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p id="P3">Astrocyte intercellular communication is critical to proper central nervous system (CNS) function. This communication occurs through gap junctions, membrane channels connecting the cytoplasm of neighboring cells that enable them to redistribute resources and share biochemical signals. Studies using astrocyte gap junction knockout mice have shown their necessity for memory formation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">2</xref></sup>, synaptic plasticity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">3</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref></sup>, coordination of neuronal signaling<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref></sup>, and closing the visual and motor critical periods<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">8</xref></sup>. In disease, networks of gap junction linked astrocytes redistribute metabolic resources across the CNS to protect degenerating neurons<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref></sup>. Despite these insights, our understanding of the spatial architecture and functional topology of astrocyte networks remains limited. Existing methods, such as dye diffusion in acute slices or reporter activation in injury models, are inherently constrained to local environments and often disrupt native connectivity. As a result, it remains unknown whether astrocytes form a continuous brain-wide syncytium or operate through discrete, region-specific subnetworks. It is also unclear whether their anatomical connectivity aligns with neuronal networks or establishes an independent framework for long-range, non-neuronal signaling.</p></sec><sec id="S2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="S3"><title>Astrocyte gap-junctional network tracing</title><p id="P4">To address this knowledge gap, we developed a vector-based approach to express a fusion protein comprised of connexin 43 (Cx43), the main gap junction protein used by astrocytes, and TurboID, a rapid and promiscuous biotinylating enzyme<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref></sup>, under the shortened <italic>Gfap</italic> promoter<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref></sup> (AAV5-GfaABC1D-Cx43:TID:HA; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1a</xref>). When this fusion protein incorporates into a connexon as any one of its 6 constituent connexins (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1b</xref>), molecules that flux through the infected astrocyte’s gap junctions are rapidly tagged with small, inert biotin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1c</xref>). This enables us to detect the infected astrocyte population (via the HA tag on the fusion protein), the in-network astrocytes (through staining biotinylated moieties with streptavidin), and cells that are not in-network with the infected population (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1d</xref>). Because the mouse CNS has minimal-to-no native biotin<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref></sup>, streptavidin staining provides little background. Further, each biotin can only bind a single streptavidin, eliminating variability introduced through antibody multiplexing and making images more quantitative.</p><p id="P5">To validate the construct, we first infected cultures of primary immunopanned serum-free rat astrocytes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1e</xref>; purity confirmation in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplemental Figure 1a</xref>). When ~10% of cells expressed Cx43-TID, over 80% of cells in the plate were identifiably in-network (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1e</xref>; quantification and controls in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplemental Figure 2</xref>). Streptavidin staining beyond the infected astrocyte population was confirmed to be gap junction-dependent in primary astrocyte cultures from inducible astrocyte gap junction knockout mice (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplemental Figures 1, 3</xref>).</p><p id="P6">To confirm that TurboID resides within the gap junction vestibule, where it would be proximal to molecules staged for gap junction flux<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref></sup>, we used a combination of expansion microscopy<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">20</xref></sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1f</xref>) and superresolution imaging (Zeiss Elyra 7 SIM2). This approach allowed us to visualize the fusion protein incorporated within a gap junction in expanded primary cultured rat astrocytes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">21</xref></sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1g</xref>). It also enabled us to measure the distance between the Cx43 vestibule and the HA tag on the N terminus of TurboID (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1h,i</xref>). The 20.73 Å median distance indicates that the HA tag lies immediately outside of the ~15 Å gap junction vestibule<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref></sup>. While the 3D structure of TurboID has not been solved, the labeling radius of biotin ligases throughout the TurboID family of enzymes has been estimated at ~10-30 nm (100-300 Å)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">23</xref></sup>, well within all measured intrafluorophoric distances.</p><p id="P7">Following our in vitro validation of the fusion protein’s structure and function, we moved to in vivo experiments (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1j</xref>). For each in vivo experiment, mice were unilaterally injected with AAV5-GfaABC1D-Cx43:TID:HA (henceforth referred to as ‘astrocyte network tracer’) in a single defined brain region. Three weeks later, biotin was administered via drinking water for one week. On day 28, mice were perfused and brains carefully dissected. Brains were then delipidated, stained, cleared, and imaged using light sheet microscopy. In cleared brains, infected cells expressed Cx43-TID-HA in a punctate pattern on the cell membrane, characteristic of gap junctions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1k</xref>). Streptavidin staining revealed an adjacent in-network, uninfected cell (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1l</xref>); while this cell was negative for Cx43-TID-HA, it contained biotinylated molecules that had passed through the infected astrocyte’s gap junctions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1m</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S4"><title>Astrocyte networks vary regionally</title><p id="P8">To visualize in vivo astrocyte networks, assess their reproducibility across mice, and examine regional differences in connectivity, we injected male, 3-month-old C57BL/6 mice in one of 3 brain regions: motor cortex (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>, top row), hypothalamus (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>, middle row), or prefrontal cortex (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>, bottom row). Dorsal, sagittal, and oblique views of the light sheet datasets illustrate distinct network morphologies across regions and reveal the specificity of astrocytic connectivity. Infected cells displayed the canonical stellate morphology of astrocytes as well as the expected punctate HA-tag staining pattern (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplemental Figure 4</xref>). We found consistent patterns of regional connectivity among animals injected in the same area (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplemental Figures 5, 6, 7</xref>), suggesting that astrocyte networks are conserved across mice.</p><p id="P9">Virtual coronal sections of these brains, mapped<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref></sup> to the Allen Brain Atlas, further illustrate the specificity and complexity of astrocyte networks (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>). Regions with robust connectivity are often directly adjacent to areas that lack any detectable connections. Within a single astrocyte network, different brain regions can display distinct patterns of network-linked cells (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplemental Figure 8</xref>). While some regions remain largely unilaterally connected (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplemental Figure 8b,e</xref>), others show robust bilateral connectivity (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplemental Figure 8c</xref>). In rare instances, specific neuronal populations contain biotinylated molecules. When present, this labeling typically occurs at the terminus of an intercon-nected chain of astrocytes and is restricted to neurons within a localized area (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplemental Figure 8k</xref>). Most cells (and in many networks, all cells) that contain biotinylated molecules exhibit the characteristic stellate morphology of astrocytes.</p><p id="P10">Astrocyte networks can link multiple astrocyte subtypes. In bilateral networks, chains of interconnected astrocytes spanning white matter tracts such as corpus collosum are clearly visible (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplemental Figure 9</xref>). Rather than filling the entire corpus callosum, these chains of astrocytes appear to follow specific neuronal axons. Networks can also include both parenchymal astrocytes and glia limitans superficialis astrocytes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">25</xref></sup> located at the brain’s surface (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplemental Figure 10</xref>). These two astrocytic populations contact one another, although the glia limitans superficialis astrocytes are not necessarily directly coupled to one another.</p></sec><sec id="S5"><title>Gap junctions link distant astrocytes</title><p id="P11">To examine whether non-gap junctional mechanisms could account for biotinylated molecules beyond the initially infected cells, we used tamoxifen-inducible, astrocyte-specific Cx30 and Cx43 double knockouts (<italic>Slc1a3</italic>(GLAST)<sup>CreERT2+/</sup><italic>Gja1</italic>(Cx43)<sup>fl/fl</sup><italic>Gjb6</italic>(Cx30)<sup>fl/fl</sup>, referred to herein as cKO)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref></sup>. Knockout of Cx43 alone is insufficient, as astrocytes also express connexin 30 (Cx30), albeit at lower levels<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref></sup>. We designed our vector to biotinylate molecules fluxed by Cx43 because it is the most permissive connexin<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">26</xref></sup>. However, we knocked out both Cx43 and Cx30 in this cKO to control for the possibility that a subset of small molecules might still pass through Cx30 in the absence of Cx43.</p><p id="P12">We first used immunohistochemistry (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplemental Figure 3</xref>) and qPCR (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplemental Figure 1</xref>) to confirm reduction of connexin expression in cKO mouse astrocytes. One week after tamoxifen gavage, immunoreactivity for Cx43 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4a,c,e</xref>) and Cx30 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4b,d,f</xref>) was diminished in cKO mice (right column) relative to littermate controls (left column). As expected for Cx43, a small degree of immunoreactivity was retained around vasculature in cKO mice (vasculature marked in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4c-f</xref> using Lycopersicon Esculentum (Tomato) lectin (TL), red), reflecting pericyte localization. Pericytes express Cx43<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27">27</xref></sup> and are not Cre+ in this model. The persistence of connexins expression adjacent to vasculature, but not elsewhere, confirms that our gap junction knockout was specific to astrocytes. We quantified this by determining fluorescence intensity relative to the distance from the nearest blood vessel in two-dimensional sections. Immunoreactivity in cKO brains (n = 3 per group) was significantly reduced compared to littermate controls at all locations except for ~3μm from vessel walls, where pericytes reside (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4i</xref>).</p><p id="P13">We infected 4 cKO and 4 control mice per condition in either hippocampus (HPC), prefrontal cortex (PFC), or barrel cortex (BC). Astrocyte networks originating in each region were significantly smaller in cKO mice compared to controls (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4j</xref>). Network volume within each brain region was consistent among animals in the same condition, even among networks of different sizes, such as the relatively small barrel cortex astrocyte network. This internal consistency parallels that observed in C57BL/6 mice injected in the motor cortex, prefrontal cortex, and hypothalamus (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplemental Figures 5, 6, 7</xref>). Following knockout, network volume in each brain region was restricted to the infected astrocytes, which had Cx43 reintroduced via the astrocyte network tracer. These cells could form a network with one another, but not with neighboring uninfected astrocytes lacking Cx43 and Cx30.</p><p id="P14">We next examined whether pericyte-expressed Cx43 or other vasculature-related mechanisms could compensate for the loss of astrocyte gap junctions and support the distribution of biotinylated molecules in this system. After infection with the astrocyte network tracer and one week of biotin-supplemented water, mice were perfused with TL. Brains were subsequently stained and cleared. We found no evidenc that streptavidin signal followed vasculature in cKO brains (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4k</xref>), indicating that vasculature-related mechanisms did not compensate for the loss of astrocyte gap junctions.</p></sec><sec id="S6"><title>Astrocyte networks are plastic</title><p id="P15">The barrel cortex is a pliable and accessible forebrain region commonly used to investigate neuroplasticity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">28</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">30</xref></sup>. To test whether astrocyte networks, like neurons, exhibit structural plasticity, whiskers on 4-week-old mice were unilaterally trimmed for 28 days (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5a</xref>). This manipulation is known to induce robust structural remodeling in neurons<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">28</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32">32</xref></sup>. At day 28, a viral mixture containing the astrocyte network tracer and a CaMKIIα-driven mCherry (to label excitatory neurons) was injected into the barrel cortex corresponding to the trimmed whiskers (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5b</xref>). Whiskers were trimmed for an additional 4 weeks, with biotin administered via drinking water during the final week.</p><p id="P16">We quantified network size in both trimmed and naïve conditions by calculating the ratio of streptavidin-positive to HA-positive cells in a cohort with reduced injection volumes to improve measurement precision (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5c</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplemental Figure 11</xref>). Mice with unilaterally trimmed whiskers had significantly smaller astrocyte networks in corresponding barrel cortex (p = 0.002; naïve 3.54 ± 0.39 vs trim 2.16 ± 0.22), indicating that astrocyte networks are indeed structurally plastic.</p></sec><sec id="S7"><title>Astrocyte and neuronal networks differ</title><p id="P17">We next increased the injection volume to assess commonalities and differences among long-range astrocytic networks and neuronal projections. While astrocyte streptavidin signal occasionally overlapped with neuronal projections, this was not uniformly the case. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5d</xref> shows a three-dimensional rendering of astrocyte networks and neuronal projections in naïve barrel cortex. While local connections and some long-range projections were shared among astrocytes and neurons, many neuronal projections lacked corresponding astrocyte connectivity. This divergence became more pronounced following whisker trim. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5g</xref>, the astrocyte network contracted markedly, particularly in prefrontal cortex. Virtual horizontal (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5e,h</xref>) and coronal (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5f,i</xref>) sections of these brains reveal the extent of this effect. In the naïve brain, barrel cortex astrocyte networks project to prefrontal cortex and show limited contralateral signal, both of which are largely absent following whisker trim. In contrast, midbrain connectivity remained relatively stable. These findings demonstrate that long-range astrocyte networks are structurally plastic, and that their architecture can diverge significantly from the neuronal connectome.</p></sec></sec><sec id="S8" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p id="P18">Here, we demonstrate that multiple astrocyte networks traverse the mouse brain, each selectively connecting and omitting brain regions rather than diffusing indiscriminately (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>). These networks vary in size and organization, with some local networks limited to a single brain region and other long-range networks robustly interconnecting multiple regions across hemispheres. Interconnected astrocytes display region-specific patterns of connectivity within the same network (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>). In some regions, such as prefrontal cortex in the motor cortex-derived astrocyte network, nearly all astrocytes contain biotinylated molecules. In other regions, only subsets of astrocytes are linked, sometimes in linear chains, other times in honeycomb-like patterns that exclude scattered astrocytes. The morphology of networks in different regions may provide clues about their local functions. In brain regions that are fully interconnected, we hypothesize that the network buffers ions across as many astrocytes as possible. In regions with honeycomb-like patterns, we propose that multiple interleaved astrocyte networks may occupy distinct functional niches for the same neuronal population.</p><p id="P19">Astrocyte networks can directly link brain regions that are not connected by neurons, suggesting that previously unassociated brain regions communicate with one another through gap junction-coupled astrocytes. What physiological role might such an overlapping multicellular network serve in the brain? The answer to this question is likely multifaceted and beyond the scope of this study. However, it is tantalizing to hypothesize that under physiological conditions, these networks facilitate redistribution of metabolic and antioxidant support from regions of low neuronal activity to those with high demand. Glutathione and phosphocreatine could mediate such support, respectively serving antioxidant and energetic buffering roles and both small enough to diffuse through Cx43 gap junctions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33">33</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35">35</xref></sup>. In contrast, during pathology, astrocyte networks may help dissipate locally accumulated metabolic byproducts or pathogenic molecules by redistributing them across the network for degradation or clearance from the CNS<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36">36</xref></sup>.</p><p id="P20">Some networks also exhibit streptavidin labeling in small, specific populations of neurons. Connexin 36, the canonical neuronal connexin<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37">37</xref></sup>, is a delta-type connexin and therefore incompatible for heterodimerization with the alpha-type Cx43 or beta-type Cx30 expressed by astrocytes – explaining why neuronal streptavidin staining is so rare. A notable exception is motor neurons, which have been reported to express Cx43 during development or in response to injury<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38">38</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40">40</xref></sup>. Although we don’t induce a significant injury and study only adult mice, we observed streptavidin-positive motor neurons projecting through the spinal cord following astrocyte network tracer injection into the motor cortex (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplemental Figure 8k,n</xref>). This observation suggests that connexin-mediated astrocyte-neuron communication in motor neurons may be more prevalent than previously appreciated.</p><p id="P21">The reason for astrocyte-to-neuron molecular transfer is unclear, but there are several potential explanations. Neurotransmitters have been shown to flux gap junctions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41">41</xref></sup>, raising the possibility that astrocyte networks resupply neurons with neurotransmitters, allowing them to conserve energy. This may be particularly important for neurons with long, energetically-intensive projections. In addition, highly active neuronal populations may also receive antioxidants such as glutathione (~307 Da) from astrocytes to mitigate oxidative stress without incurring the metabolic cost of de novo antioxidant production. Future work should use mass spectrometry to identify the specific biotinylated molecules transferred through astrocyte networks, which will help us understand the functional roles of astrocyte networks across conditions.</p><p id="P22">Crucially for future experimentation, astrocyte networks link both hemispheres, including at least the contralateral counterpart of the infected region. This raises critical considerations: internally controlled experiments must be interpreted cautiously, as astrocyte connectivity may undermine the assumption of regional independence. If a so-called control region is functionally linked to an experimental region by astrocyte networks, it is unlikely to remain biologically naïve.</p><p id="P23">This bilateral connectivity may also explain the contralateral astrocytic responses to unilateral stressors. For example, ischemic stroke in somatosensory cortex causes astrocytic responses in the contralateral hemisphere following ipsilateral limb stimulation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42">42</xref></sup>. Similarly, a unilateral model of glaucoma elicits astrocytic responses in both the contralateral retina and the contralateral hemisphere of the brain<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43">43</xref></sup>. Importantly, these contralateral responses are not restricted to a single sensory system, suggesting that astrocyte-mediated interhemispheric communication may represent a broader feature of neurodegenerative progression.</p><p id="P24">We additionally find that astrocyte networks are plastic. Barrel cortex astrocyte networks shrink in response to whisker trim (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>). To mirror the canonical timeline of neuronal remodeling, we trimmed whiskers for a month before astrocyte infection<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">29</xref></sup>. However, both astrocyte gap junctions and the fine processes that house them can remodel on much shorter timescales. The half-life of Cx43 is estimated to be between 1.5-5 hours<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R44">44</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R45">45</xref></sup>, and astrocyte process remodeling occurs over similarly rapid intervals<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R46">46</xref></sup>. Our whisker barrel experiments indicate that astrocyte networks can reconfigure in a stable manner, but it is also likely that rapid remodeling occurs on a smaller scale during more acute perturbations. Future studies should explore whether acute energetic stress triggers dynamic reorganization of astrocyte networks to meet varied metabolic demands across the CNS.</p><p id="P25">While our approach visualizes astrocyte networks through a binary lens (connected or not via viral labeling), it is important to recognize that a diverse array of molecules may flux through these networks, and their distribution is unlikely to be uniform. Local and long-distance astrocyte networks may serve distinct physiological roles, even within the same interconnected chain of cells. Uncovering the specific dynamics of different fluxed molecules and how these dynamics are shaped by the molecular identity and subtypes of each astrocyte will be a complex task. However, such studies may ultimately reveal a rich array of functional niches that astrocyte networks occupy across the brain.</p><p id="P26">Here, we define the specificity and spatial extent of astrocyte networks across brain regions, demonstrate how they differ from neuronal networks, and reveal their ability to remodel. These findings establish a foundation for future exploration of how astrocyte network structure and function are shaped by injury, disease, development, aging, and experience-dependent processes such as learning and memory.</p></sec><sec id="S9" sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec id="S10"><title>Animals</title><p id="P27">Animal procedures were performed in accordance with National Institutes of Health guidelines with the approval of NYU Grossman School of Medicine’s Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee (IACUC). All animals were housed at 22-25 °C with 50-60% humidity. Animals had access to food and water ad libitum and were housed on a 12 hour light/dark cycle. Experiments in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figures 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref> were on male, 12-week-old C57BL/6J mice. For experiments in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>, the Saab laboratory crossbred mice<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref></sup> expressing the tamoxifen-sensitive Cre recombinase Cre-ERT2 under the control of the murine <italic>Slc1a3</italic> (GLAST) promoter<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R47">47</xref></sup> with mice carrying floxed Gjb6 (<italic>Cx30</italic><sup>fl/fl</sup>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R48">48</xref></sup> and floxed Gja1 (<italic>Cx43</italic><sup>fl/fl</sup>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R49">49</xref></sup>. Mice hemizygous for <italic>Slc1a3</italic><sup>Cre-ERT2</sup> were bred to noncarriers to generate <italic>Slc1a3</italic><sup>Cre-ERT2+/</sup><italic>Gja1</italic><sup>fl/fl</sup><italic>Gjb6</italic><sup>fl/fl</sup> experimental mice and <italic>Gja1</italic><sup>fl/fl</sup><italic>Gjb6</italic><sup>fl/fl</sup> littermate controls for in vivo experiments; in vivo experiments on this genotype were balanced for sex. When primary mouse astrocytes were isolated, <italic>Slc1a3</italic><sup>Cre-ERT2</sup> was kept homozygous to obtain a culture in which all astrocytes could be induced via 4-hydroxytamoxifen. All mice were on a C57BL/6 background. The primer sequences used for genotyping were: for <italic>Cx30</italic> flox; 5’-TTCCCTATGCTGGTAGAGTGCTTGT-3’ and 5’-GCAGTAACTTATTGAAACCCTTCACCT-3’; for <italic>Cx43</italic> flox: 5’-GGGATACAGACCCTTGGACTCC-3’ and 5’-TCACCCCAAGCTGACTCAACCG-3’; and for GLAST-CreERT2, 5’-GAGGCACTTGGCTAGGCTCTGAGGA-3’ and 5’-GAGGAGATCCTGACCGATCAGTTGG-3’ and 5’-GGTGTACGGTCAGTAAATTGGACAT-3’. The Saab lab previously analyzed Cre reporter function<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref></sup> by crossing with ROSA26-floxed-STOP-GCaMP6s (Ai96; JAX: 024106).</p><p id="P28">Following shipment, mice were rederived by NYU Grossman School of Medicine’s Rodent Genetic Engineering Laboratory.</p></sec><sec id="S11"><title>Tamoxifen treatment</title><p id="P29">Tamoxifen treatment was performed as previously described11. For 3 consecutive days, both <italic>Slc1a3</italic><sup>Cre-ERT2+/</sup><italic>Gja-1</italic><sup>fl/fl</sup><italic>Gjb6</italic><sup>fl/fl</sup> experimental and littermate control mice received daily (between 3 and 5 p.m.) gavage of a tamoxifen solution (20 mg/mL dissolved in corn oil). Solution was prepared 2 hours prior to administration, during which it was shaken at 37 °C in the dark. Any further experimental manipulations were performed at least 7 days following the last dose of tamoxifen.</p></sec><sec id="S12"><title>Primary rat astrocyte cultures</title><p id="P30">Isolation of primary rat astrocytes by immunopanning was performed as previously described<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">21</xref></sup>. Briefly, cortices of postnatal day (P) 6/7 Sprague Dawley rats (Charles River) were blunt dissected, meninges removed, and enzymatically dissociated at 37 °C / 10% CO<sub>2</sub> via papain (Worthington Biochemical LS003126). Tissue was then triturated using a 5mL serological pipette to generate a single cell suspension, resuspended in Dulbecco’s Phosphate Buffered Saline (PBS; VWR SH30264.FS) with bovine serum albumin (BSA, Sigma Aldrich A4161) and DNAse (Worthington Biochemical LS002007), and filtered using a 20 μm nitex filter. The suspension was negatively panned for non-specific secondary antibody binding, endothelial cells (BSL-1, Vector Labs L-1100), microglia (CD45, BD Pharmingen 553076), oligodendrocyte lineage cells (O4 hybridoma, generated in house), and positively panned for astrocytes (ITGB5, Thermo Scientific 14-0497-82). Astrocytes were removed from the positive panning plate using TrypLE (Thermo Scientific 12-605-010) and plated at 10K per well in an 8 well chamber slide pre-coated with poly-l-lysine (Ibidi 80804). Astrocytes were cultured in serum-free medium containing 50% neurobasal, 50% DMEM, 100 U/mL penicillin, 100 μg/mL streptomycin, 1 mM sodium pyruvate, 292 μg/ mL L-glutamine, 1× SATO, 5 μg/mL N-acetylcysteine, and 5 ng/ mL HBEGF (Sigma-Aldrich E4643-50UG). After 7 days, AAV was added to the media change, resulting in an effective titer of 105. Cells were incubated for a further 7 days, with biotin (effective concentration 250 μM) added to the media 2 days prior to fixation.</p></sec><sec id="S13"><title>Expansion microscopy</title><p id="P31">Expansion microscopy was performed based on published protocols. Primary astrocytes were quickly washed in phosphate buffered saline (PBS), then fixed in 4% PFA in PBS at RT for 15 min. After three 5-min washes in PBS, they were permeabilized for 15 minutes in PBS with 0.5% triton X-100, then blocked for 1 hour in 5% BSA and 0.2% Tween-20 in PBS while shaking at RT. They were then incubated in primary antibody solution overnight at 4°C (3% BSA, 0.2% Tween-20 in PBS containing: Mouse monoclonal anti HA-tag (Cell Signaling 2367) directly conjugated to ATTO488-NHS (ATTO-TEC AD 488-31), Rabbit polyclonal anti-Cx43 (Cell Signaling 3512) directly conjugated to ATTO565-NHS (AT-TO-TEC AD 565-31), and ATTO643-Streptavidin (ATTO-TEC AD 643-61)). Dye conjugation was performed according to the manufacturer’s protocol. Antibodies were added for an effective concentration of 2 μM for anti-Cx43, 10 μM for anti-HA, and streptavidin (stock concentration 2ug/ml) was added at 1:1000. Cells were then washed 3 x 5 min in PBS and incubated for 10 min in 300nM DAPI in PBS, then imaged on a spinning disk confocal (CrestOptics X-LIGHT V3 Confocal on Nikon Ti2) with a 60x N.A. 1.4 oil lens to later establish an expansion coefficient. 250 μL Acryloyl-X, SE (Invitrogen A20770) was then added for an overnight incubation at RT. Cells were washed twice for 15 min in PBS, then incubated in 300 μL Gelation Solution per well (For 2 mL: 542 μL 4 M Na Acrylate (VWR S03880), 1mL PROTOGEL (Fisher 50-899-90119), 200 μL 10x PBS, 198 μL H<sub>2</sub>O (MQ), 30 μL 10% ammonium persulfate (Thermo Scientific 17874), 30 μL Tetramethylethylenediamine (TEMED, Thermo Scientific 17919)) for 1 hour at 37 °C. 300 μL digestion buffer was added to each well and gels were carefully outlined with a needle to facilitate detachment; once gels detached, they were each transferred to one well of a 12-well plate for the remainder of the 4 hour incubation at 37 °C (volume per gel/well of 12-well plate: 1550 μL Tris-acetate-EDTA (TAE) buffer, 100μL 10% Triton X-100 in PBS, 320μL 5M NaCl with 26 μL Proteinase K (Thermo Scientific EO0491) added immediately before use). Gels were then each transferred to 15 cm petri dishes filled with RT H2O (MQ) and incubated for 30 minutes at RT. H<sub>2</sub>O (MQ) was then replaced and gels left overnight at RT to expand. Gels were stored at 4 °C until imaging.</p></sec><sec id="S14"><title>Single-molecule imaging and localization</title><p id="P32">Gels were mounted into 35 mm dishes with #1.5 coverslip bottoms (Ibidi 81158) with SlowFade Glass soft-set antifade mountant (RI 1.52; Invitrogen S36917) immediately before imaging. For lattice-SIM imaging, we used a ZEISS Elyra 7 with an Alpha Plan Apochromat 63x/1.46 oil TIRF (total internal reflection fluorescence microscopy) objective. Dual PCO.Edge 4.2 sCMOS cameras collected data (1280 x 1280 pixels) with a Dual Camera Beam Splitter (SBS LP 560) utilized for channel separation on Zen Black 3.0 SR software corresponding to 15 phases of a 27.5 μm grating period for both 488 and 561 channels. SIM2 (structured illumination microscopy) 3D Leap processing was run with the following parameters: Input SNR: Low, Iterations: 25, Regularization Weight: 0.01; Processing sampling and output sampling: 2. At least 10,000 frames with a 30ms acquisition time were collected from each sample for each wavelength channel and processed via the Localization Microscopy processing function in 3D. All single- and multi-emitter events were fitted as single emitter events.</p></sec><sec id="S15"><title>Primary mouse astrocyte cultures</title><p id="P33">Mouse astrocytes were obtained from <italic>Slc1a3</italic><sup>Cre-ERT2+/+</sup> x <italic>Gja1</italic><sup>fl/fl</sup><italic>Gjb6</italic><sup>fl/fl</sup> (note the homozygous Cre, opposed to hemizygous for in vivo experiments where mice could be genotyped). Cortices of P3 mice were blunt dissected, meninges removed, and enzymatically dissociated at 37 °C / 10% CO<sub>2</sub> via papain (Worthington Biochemical LS003126). Tissue was then triturated using a 5 mL serological pipette to generate a single cell suspension, resuspended in Dulbecco’s PBS (VWR SH30264.FS) with bovine serum albumin (BSA, Sigma Aldrich A4161) and DNAse (Worthington Biochemical LS002007), and filtered using a 20 μm nitex filter. The suspension was negatively panned for non-specific secondary antibody binding, microglia (CD45, BD Pharmingen 553076), oligodendrocyte lineage cells (O4 hybridoma<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R50">50</xref></sup>, generated in house), L1 (Millipore Rat anti-L1, MAB5272), and positively panned for astrocytes (HepaCAM51; Human HepaCAM antibody MAB4108, R&amp;D Systems). Astrocytes were removed from the positive panning plate using TrypLE (Thermo Scientific 12-605-010) and plated at 10K per well in an 8 well chamber slide pre-coated with poly-l-lysine (Ibidi 80804). Astrocytes were cultured in serum-free medium containing 50% neurobasal, 50% DMEM, 100 U/mL penicillin, 100 μg / mL streptomycin, 1 mM sodium pyruvate, 292 μg/ mL L-glutamine, 1× SATO, 5 μg/mL N-acetylcysteine, and 5 ng/ mL HBEGF (Sigma-Aldrich E4643-50UG). On day 6, 4-hydroxytamoxifen (Sigma-Aldrich SML1666) was added at 1:5000 (or concentration appropriate for gradient experiments); ethanol:isopropanol (95:5) was added to control wells at the same concentration. On day 7, AAV was added to the media change, resulting in an effective titer of 1.5 x 104. Cells were incubated for a further 7 days, with biotin (effective concentration 250 μM) added to the media 2 days prior to fixation. Cells were washed 2 x in PBS, then fixed in 4% PFA in PBS for 15 minutes prior to immunocytochemistry.</p></sec><sec id="S16"><title>Immunocytochemistry</title><p id="P34">Fixed cells were washed 2 x in PBS/azide, then blocked for 2 hours in 5% normal donkey serum (NDS) with 0.1% Tween-20 in PBS/azide. They were then incubated overnight at 4°C with shaking in 3% NDS, 0.1% Triton X-100 in PBS/azide with corresponding primary antibodies (Rabbit polyclonal Anti-HA: Cell Signaling 3724 at 1:500; Goat polyclonal Anti-GFAP (Glial Fibrillary Acidic Protein): Abcam ab53554 at 1:500). Cells were washed 3 x 5 min in PBS/azide, then incubated for 2 hours at RT with shaking in 1% NDS, 0.1% Triton X-100 in PBS/azide with the corresponding secondary antibodies (Donkey anti-Goat conjugated to Alexa Flu- or 488: Invitrogen A-110055 at 1:500; Donkey anti-Rabbit conjugated to Alexa Fluor 555: Invitrogen A-31572 at 1:500) and streptavidin conjugated to AlexaFluor647 (ThermoFisher S32357 at 1:500). Cells were washed 3 x 5 min in PBS/azide, then imaged (2048 x 2048) on a Zeiss 880 laser scanning confocal microscope using a 20x N.A. 0.8 plan apochromat air objective.</p></sec><sec id="S17"><title>Western Blotting</title><p id="P35">Cells were lysed in ice-cold 1x RIPA buffer (diluted in ddH2O from 10x, Cell Signaling #9806) with 1 mM PMSF (Cell Signaling #8553) and HaltTM Protease &amp; Phosphatase Single-Use Inhibitor Cocktail (Thermo Scientific #78440). Samples were sonicated and lysate was separated from insoluble material by centrifugation at 20,000 g. 1.5 mm 10% acrylamide gels (Running gel: 4 mL PROTOGEL (Fisher 50-899-90119), 3 mL 1.5 M Tris pH 8.8 + SDS, 5 mL ddH2O, 120 μL 10% ammonium persulfate (Thermo Scientific 17874), and 12 μL Tetramethylethylenediamine (TEMED, Thermo Scientific 17919); Stacking gel: 780 μL PROTOGEL (Fisher 50-899-90119), 1.5 mL 0.5 M Tris pH 6.8 + SDS, 3.75 mL ddH2O, 60 μL 10% ammonium persulfate (Thermo Scientific 17874), and 18 μL Tetramethylethylenediamine (TEMED, Thermo Scientific 17919)). Gels were loaded with 10 μg protein per well and run at 120 V; transfers onto PVDF membranes (Immoblion-FL, IPFL00010; pore size 0.45 μm) occurred overnight at 4°C at 20 V with stirring. Following a 1 hour block (LI-COR Intercept® PBS Blocking Buffer (LI-COR 927-70001)), blots were incubated with rabbit anti-Cx43 (1:1000; Cell Signaling #3512) and mouse anti-Actin (1:1000; abcam ab8226) antibodies in LI-COR Intercept® PBS Blocking Buffer (LI-COR 927-70001) with 0.1% Tween-20 (Sigma #P9416) for 4 hours, then washed 4 x 5 min with PBST. They were then incubated for 1 hour in LI-COR Intercept® PBS Blocking Buffer (LI-COR 927-70001) containing 0.1% Tween20 and 0.1% SDS with donkey anti-mouse IRDye 680LT (1:20,000; LI-COR P/N 926-68072) and donkey anti-rabbit IRDye 800CW (1:20,000; LI-COR P/N 926-32213). Following 3 x 5 min PBST washes and 1 x 5 min PBS wash, blots were imaged on a ChemiDoc MP (BIO-RAD). Band peaks were quantified in FIJI (ImageJ) using the Gels function.</p></sec><sec id="S18"><title>qPCR</title><p id="P36">RNA was obtained from cultures using Qiagen’s RNeasy Micro Kit (74004) and converted to cDNA via Qiagen’s QuantiTect Reverse Transcription Kit (205311) per manufacturer instructions. Real-time PCR was performed using SYBR™ Green Universal Master Mix (ThermoFisher 4309155) on a StepOne Plus Real-Time PCR System (Applied Biosystems) using the following primers: Gja1 (F: TCATTGGGGGAAAGGCGTGA, R: CATGTCTGGGCACCTCTCTTTCA), <italic>Aldh1l1</italic> (F: TCCCGTCTTTGACCTTGGGT, R: CGCCACCGAGGGAACTTAAA), <italic>Slc1a3</italic> (F: CCCCTTACAAAATCAGAAAAGTTGT, R: CCCATCTTGGGCTCTTCTCC), <italic>Sox10</italic>: (F: GAAGAAGGCTCCCCCATGTC, R: TTGGGTGGCAGGTATTGGTC), <italic>Mog</italic> (F: GCAGGTCTCTGTAGGCCTTG, R: CCCTCAGGAAGTGAGGATCAAA), <italic>Aif1</italic> (F: CTGGGCAAGAGATCTGCCAT, R: ACCAGTTGGCCTCTTGTGTT), <italic>Cd14</italic> (F: ACTGAAGCCTTTCTCGGAGC, R: TGAAAGCGCTGGACCAATCT), <italic>Tubb3</italic> (F: ACCATGGACAGTGTTCGGTC, R: ACACTCTTTCCGCACGACAT), <italic>Syp</italic> (F: CGGCTACCAGCCTGACTATG, R: CTGGGCTTCACTGACCAGAC).</p></sec><sec id="S19"><title>Perfusion and tissue preparation</title><p id="P37">Mice were always perfused between 2 and 5 PM to control for circadian effects. Mice were heavily anesthetized with an overdose of pentobarbital (Euthasol: 390 mg Pentobarbital / 50 mg Phenytoin/mL at 2 uL/g) and transcardially perfused with PBS containing 10 mg/L Heparin (Sigma Aldrich, Heparin sodium salt from porcine intestinal mucosa, H3393) until the liver and right ventricle were clear of blood. Perfusion solution was then switched to 4% PFA in PBS; all solutions were administered at RT at 70% cardiac perfusion pressure. Brains were immediately dissected taking care to leave the surface fully intact and post-fixed in 4% PFA in PBS overnight to stabilize protein tertiary structures. Fixed samples were washed in PBS with 0.01% sodium azide 3 times for 1 hour, then stored in PBS/azide at 4 °C.</p><p id="P38">When Lycopersicon Esculentum lectin (Tomato lectin, TL) was used to image vasculature, 100 μg of TL conjugated to DyLight 649 diluted in 100 μL PBS was injected directly into the left ventricle of the heart prior to perfusion. After circulating via the beating heart for 1 minute, transcardial perfusion resumed as above.</p></sec><sec id="S20"><title>Slice Immunohistochemistry</title><p id="P39">Hemibrains were delipidated (see Clearing), rehydrated through the same methanol gradient to B1n, then washed 3 x in PBS/azide. They were then sectioned sagittally at 200 μm on a vibrating microtome (Leica VT1000 S). Floating sections were blocked for 2 hours in 5% normal donkey serum (NDS) with 0.1% Tween-20 in PBS/azide, then incubated overnight at 4 °C with shaking in 3% NDS, 0.1% Triton X-100 in PBS/azide with corresponding primary antibodies (Rabbit polyclonal Anti-Connexin 43: Cell Signaling 3512 at 1:500; Rabbit polyclonal Anti-Connexin 30: Invitrogen 71-2200 at 1:250; Goat polyclonal Anti-GFAP (Glial Fibrillary Acidic Protein): Abcam ab53554 at 1:500). Sections were washed 5 x 10 min in PBS/azide, then incubated overnight at 4 °C with shaking in 1% NDS, 0.1% Triton X-100 in PBS/azide with the corresponding secondary antibodies (Donkey anti-Goat conjugated to Alexa Fluor 488: Invitrogen A-110055 at 1:500; Donkey anti-Rabbit conjugated to Alexa Fluor 555: Invitrogen A-31572 at 1:500). Sections were washed 5 x 10 min in PBS/azide and mounted in ProLong Diamond Antifade Mountant with DAPI (Invitrogen P36962) to obtain a close refractive index match to the delipidated sections.</p></sec><sec id="S21"><title>Confocal Imaging</title><p id="P40">Sections were imaged on a Zeiss 800 confocal microscope; montages were obtained using a 20x plan apochromat N.A. 0.75 air objective at 512 x 512 per image and high-resolution inset images were obtained using a 63x plan apochromat N.A. 1.4 oil objective at 2048 x 2048 resolution. Z-stacks were obtained at a step size of 8.2 μm (20x) or 4.4 μm (63x). All directly compared sections were obtained at the same magnification and were imaged using the same settings. Maximum Z-projections were rendered using FIJI (ImageJ 1.54f).</p></sec><sec id="S22"><title>Connexin and vasculature relative localization analysis</title><p id="P41">Confocal images were analyzed in FIJI/ImageJ (Version 1.54m). Three confocal micrographs for each of three mice per condition were analyzed using ImageJ’s ‘Plot Profile’ function for three equally spaced line segments perpendicular to imaged vasculature. Line segments were placed so they began on the edge of a vessel, completely transected it, and then passed through the remainder of the micrograph. Profile values for each line were averaged to represent one micrograph. Graph is presented as distance from the far end of each blood vessel with the average in-vessel portion of all images demarcated.</p></sec><sec id="S23"><title>Intracerebral Viral Injections</title><p id="P42">Surgeries were performed under aseptic conditions in accordance with NYU Grossman School of Medicine’s institutional biosafety guidelines. A glass micropipette was pulled to a tip diameter of approximately 20 microns, filled with mineral oil, and attached to a Nanoject III microinjector (Drummond Scientific, 3-000-207). The micropipette was then backfilled with 1ul of Adeno-associated Virus (AAV) at a titer of 1010 genomic units per microliter. Mice were anaesthetized with 0.7-2.5% isoflurane (adjusted on the basis of scored reflexes and breathing rate during surgery), placed into a stereotaxic apparatus (Kopf), and a single craniotomy performed over the experimental brain region (coordinates below), the micropipette was inserted, and 200 nL of virus was injected (40 cycles, 5 second delay between cycles, 5 nL injected per cycle and 5nL/s). 10 minutes following injection the micropipette was withdrawn and the wound sutured closed. Buprenorphine (0.1 mg/kg) was subcutaneously administered immediately following surgery and twice daily for the following 72 hours. We used the following stereotaxic coordinates (in mm: AP, anteroposterior; ML, mediolateral; DV, dorsoventral): Motor Cortex (AP -2.6; ML 1.3; DV -0.8), Hippocampus (AP -2.0; ML 1.5; DV -1.5), Paraventricular Nucleus (AP 0.12; ML -0.71, DV -4.8), Prefrontal Cortex (AP 0.35; ML 1.9; DV -2.5), Barrel Cortex (AP -1.5; ML 3.5; DV -0.7). The astrocyte network tracer (AAV5-GfaABC1D-Cx43:TID:HA) was constructed and packaged by VectorBuilder. The AAV9-CaMKIIa-mCherry was obtained from Addgene as a gift from Karl Deisseroth (Addgene viral prep #114469-AAV9). All vectors were injected at a titer of 1 x 211.</p></sec><sec id="S24"><title>Biotin administration</title><p id="P43">Biotin (Sigma Aldrich, B4639) stocks were diluted to 100 mM in DMSO, aliquoted for single-use, and stored frozen at -20 °C. 21 days following intracerebral injections, biotin stock was diluted in distilled water to 160 μM (400 μL of 100 mM stock per 250 mL of distilled water) and provided ad libitum for 7 days, after which mice were perfused (always between 2 and 5 p.m. to control for circadian effects).</p></sec><sec id="S25"><title>Whisker trimming</title><p id="P44">Every other day from P28 through P84, mice were lightly anaesthetized with 0.7-1.5% isoflurane (adjusted on the basis of scored reflexes and breathing rate). All whiskers one side of the face were trimmed with scissors. On P56, whisker trim coincided with intracerebral viral injections (see above). For P77-P84, mice received biotin-supplemented drinking water (see above); perfusion occurred on P84 (see above).</p></sec><sec id="S26"><title>Clearing</title><p id="P45">The clearing protocol uses similar principles to the iDISCO<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref></sup> or AdipoClear<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref></sup> protocol with several adjustments specific to brain tissue and astrocyte morphological maintenance. To delipidate, fixed samples were washed in B1N buffer (H2O / 0.1% Triton X-100 / 0.3 M glycine / 0.01% sodium azide, pH 7) for 1 hour, followed by 1 hour washes each in 20%, 40%, 60%, and 80% methanol in B1N. Samples were fully dehydrated in 100% methanol (MeOH) for three 1 hour washes, then delipdated in 2:1 dichloromethane (DCM; Sigma-Aldrich SHBR8133) overnight. Delipidation resumed the following day in three 1 hour washes in 100% DCM. Samples were then washed in 100% MeOH for 1 hour twice. Residual fluorescence was quenched through an overnight incubation in 80% MeOH / 5% H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> / 15% H<sub>2</sub>O at 4 °C. Brains were then rehydrated via 1 hour incubations in each 60%, 40%, and 20% methanol in B1N. Samples were then washed in B1N overnight.</p><p id="P46">Samples were permeabilized in PTxwH buffer (PBS / 0.1% Triton X-100 / 0.05% Tween-20 / 2 μg/mL heparin / 0.02% sodium azide) with an added 45 g/L glycine and 50 mL/L dimethyl sulfoxide (DMSO) two times for 1 hour each. Then, samples were washed three times in PTxwH for 1 hour.</p><p id="P47">Samples were incubated in primary antibody (HA-tag, Cell Signaling mAb #3724, 1:2000) and conjugated streptavidin (Alexa Fluor 647 Streptavidin, ThermoFisher S32357, 1:800) for 1 week at 37 °C with rotation. After primary incubation, samples were washed in PTxwH with 8 solution changes over a period of 3 days. Samples were then incubated in secondary antibody (donkey anti-rabbit conjugated to AlexaFluor Plus 555, ThermoFisher A32794) and conjugated streptavidin (1:800) for 1 week at 37 °C with rotation. As after secondary incubation, samples were washed in PTxwH with 8 solution changes over a period of 3 days.</p><p id="P48">For tissue clearing, samples were dehydrated in a 20%, 40%, 60%, 80%, 100%, 100%, 100% methanol/H2O series for 45 minutes each. Following dehydration, samples were washed in 2:1 DCM:methanol overnight followed by three 1 hour washes in 100% DCM. Samples were cleared overnight in dibenzyl ether (DBE, Sigma-Aldrich) and stored at room temperature in the dark in amber glass vials until imaging.</p></sec><sec id="S27"><title>Light sheet imaging</title><p id="P49">Whole, cleared brains were imaged on a light sheet microscope (Zeiss Z1) equipped with a 5x EC plan neofluar N.A. 0.16 objective lens and 20x Clr plan neofluar N.A. 1.0 objective lens. Images were collected with two 1920 x 1920 pixels sCMOS cameras and acquired using Zen Black software (Zeiss). Samples were staged in a custom imaging chamber (Translucence Biosystems) filled with DBE and illuminated from both sides by the laser light sheet (5x light sheet thickness:13.08 μm, step size 4.5 μm; 20x light sheet thickness: 4.35 μm, step size 0.61 μm).</p></sec><sec id="S28"><title>Light sheet image analysis</title><p id="P50">For cKO experiments, Imaris (Version 9.9) was used to generate surfaces around positive signal (calculated via thresholding) in HA and Streptavidin channels. The total volume of Streptavidin signal divided by the total volume of HA signal was used to generate a Relative Network Volume representing each brain. For whisker trim experiments, individual astrocytes were counted in FIJI (ImageJ version 1.54b) following background thresholding. The number of streptavidin positive astrocytes was divided by the number of HA positive astrocytes to generate a Network Size value representing each brain.</p></sec><sec id="S29"><title>Statistical analysis and reproducibility</title><p id="P51">Data are presented as mean ± standard deviation. Mice were assigned at random to groups. Experiments were not performed in a blinded fashion. Statistical significance for each experiment was determined as detailed in the respective figure legend. In figure legends, n = the biologically independent number of animals per group. Statistical analyses were performed in Prism 10 software (GraphPad). No data points were excluded.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="SM"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1"><label>Supplementary Materials</label><media xlink:href="EMS207439-supplement-Supplementary_Materials.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" id="d7aAcEbB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack id="S30"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank the Microscopy Core at New York University (NYU) Langone Medical Center for experimental and technical support. We thank Giorgia Bertoli for her advice on expansion microscopy and the course directors of the Kavli iDISCO course at Rockefeller University for their expertise in tissue clearing. We thank the NYU Langone Medical Center Genotyping Core and Mouse Genetic Engineering Core for their assistance with colony rederivation and genetic maintenance. We thank Eleni Katafygiotou, Brianna Somoza Balza, Jesus Morales Santos, and Adwoa Amponsah for their assistance with tissue clearing and Jessica Minder for her cloning and surgical expertise. We thank Simon Peron for his advice on working with whisker barrel cortex. We thank Paul Glimcher, Stephen Davis Jr, and Xavier Castellanos for their proofreading assistance. Thanks go to the Lean Levy Fellowship in Neuroscience (M.L.C.), the PEW Charitable Trusts Postdoctoral Fellowship (M.C.S.), the Simons Foundation SURFiN Fellowship (K.E.C./M.V.C.), the Swiss National Science Foundation (320030-232028, A.S.S.) and the NIH [K00 AG068343 (H.K.G.), 5U19 NS107616 (M.V.C.), T32 MH019524 (M.L.C.), and R01 EY033353 (S.A.L.)]. NYU shared resources are partially supported by the Cancer Center Support Grant P30CA016087 at the Laura and Isaac Perlmutter Cancer Center. Thanks additionally go to the Belfer Neurodegeneration Consortium of MD Anderson (S.A.L.), the Carol and Gene Ludwig Family Foundation (S.A.L.), and the Cure Alzheimer’s Fund (S.A.L.).</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="con" id="FN2"><p id="P52"><bold><italic>Author Contributions</italic></bold></p><p id="P53">M.L.C. designed research; S.A.L. and M.V.C. supervised the work; M.L.C., M.C.S., M.C., H.K.G., J.S., and K.E.C. performed research; M.L.C. and A.S.S. contributed new reagents/analytic tools; M.L.C. analyzed and visualized the data; M.L.C. wrote the paper; M.L.C., M.C.S., M.C., H.K.G., K.E.C., A.S.S., S.A.L., and M.V.C. edited the paper; M.L.C., M.C.S., H.K.G., S.A.L., and M.V.C. acquired funding.</p></fn><fn fn-type="conflict" id="FN3"><p id="P54"><bold><italic>Declarations of Interests</italic></bold></p><p id="P55">S.A.L. is an academic founder and sits on the SAB of AstronauTx Ltd. and is a SAB member of the BioAccess Fund. S.A.L. declares ownership interests in AstronauTx Ltd., and SynaptiCure Inc. All ofther authors declare no conflicts.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><ref id="R1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hösli</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Binini</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferrari</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name><name><surname>Thieren</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Looser</surname><given-names>ZJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Decoupling astrocytes in adult mice impairs synaptic plasticity and spatial learning</article-title><source>Cell Rep</source><year>2022</year><volume>38</volume><issue>10</issue><elocation-id>110484</elocation-id><comment>2022</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35263595</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Frisch</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Theis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>De Souza</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Dere</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Söhl</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Mice with astrocyte-directed inactivation of connexin43 exhibit increased exploratory behaviour, impaired motor capacities, and changes in brain acetylcholine levels</article-title><source>Eur J Neurosci</source><year>2003</year><volume>18</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>2313</fpage><lpage>2318</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14622192</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Murphy-Royal</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Boyce</surname><given-names>AKJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Diaz-Castro</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Institoris</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Stress gates an astrocytic energy reservoir to impair synaptic plasticity</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2020</year><volume>11</volume><issue>1</issue><elocation-id>3064</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-020-15778-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7181611</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32332733</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pannasch</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Vargová</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Reingruber</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ezan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Holcman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Astroglial networks scale synaptic activity and plasticity</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2011</year><volume>108</volume><issue>20</issue><fpage>8467</fpage><lpage>8472</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1016650108</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3100942</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21536893</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pannasch</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Freche</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Dallérac</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghézali</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Escartin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Connexin 30 sets synaptic strength by controlling astroglial synapse invasion</article-title><source>Nat Neurosci</source><year>2014</year><volume>17</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>549</fpage><lpage>558</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24584052</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chever</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Dossi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Pannasch</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Derangeon</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rouach</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Astroglial networks promote neuronal coordination</article-title><source>Sci Signal</source><year>2016</year><volume>9</volume><issue>410</issue><fpage>ra6</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26758214</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ribot</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Breton</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Calvo</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name><name><surname>Moulard</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ezan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Astrocytes close the mouse critical period for visual plasticity</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2021</year><volume>373</volume><issue>6550</issue><fpage>77</fpage><lpage>81</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34210880</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ackerman</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Perez-Catalan</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name><surname>Freeman</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Doe</surname><given-names>CQ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Astrocytes close a motor circuit critical period</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2021</year><volume>592</volume><issue>7854</issue><fpage>414</fpage><lpage>420</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41586-021-03441-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9901311</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33828296</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Crane</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Adipo-Clear: A Tissue Clearing Method for Three-Dimensional Imaging of Adipose Tissue</article-title><source>J Vis Exp</source><year>2018</year><volume>137</volume><elocation-id>58271</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3791/58271</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6126572</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30102289</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Renier</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Yany</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ariel</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>iDISCO: a simple, rapid method to immunolabel large tissue samples for volume imaging</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2014</year><volume>159</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>896</fpage><lpage>910</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25417164</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Pasini</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lambert</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name><name><surname>D’Alessandro</surname><given-names>KB</given-names></name><name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Redistribution of metabolic resources through astrocyte networks mitigates neurodegenerative stress</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2020</year><volume>117</volume><issue>31</issue><fpage>18810</fpage><lpage>18821</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.2009425117</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7414143</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32690710</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rouach</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Koulakoff</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Abudara</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Willecke</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Giaume</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Astroglial metabolic networks sustain hippocampal synaptic transmission</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2008</year><volume>322</volume><issue>5907</issue><fpage>1551</fpage><lpage>1555</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19056987</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Branon</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name><name><surname>Bosch</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanchez</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Udeshi</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name><name><surname>Svinkina</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Efficient proximity labeling in living cells and organisms with TurboID</article-title><source>Nat Biotechnol</source><year>2018</year><volume>36</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>880</fpage><lpage>887</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nbt.4201</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6126969</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30125270</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rayaprolu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bitarafan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Santiago</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name><name><surname>Betarbet</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Sunna</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cell type-specific biotin labeling in vivo resolves regional neuronal and astrocyte proteomic differences in mouse brain</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2022</year><volume>13</volume><issue>1</issue><elocation-id>2927</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-022-30623-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9132937</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35614064</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Takano</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Wallace</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Baldwin</surname><given-names>KT</given-names></name><name><surname>Purkey</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Uezu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Chemico-genetic discovery of astrocytic control of inhibition in vivo</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2020</year><volume>588</volume><issue>7837</issue><fpage>296</fpage><lpage>302</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41586-020-2926-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8011649</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33177716</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Haustein</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Sofroniew</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name><name><surname>Khakh</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Imaging intracellular Ca(2)(+) signals in striatal astrocytes from adult mice using genetically-encoded calcium indicators</article-title><source>J Vis Exp</source><year>2014</year><volume>93</volume><elocation-id>e51972</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3791/51972</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4354287</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25490346</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nagai</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bellafard</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Qu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Olliier</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Specific and behaviorally consequential astrocyte G(q) GPCR signaling attenuation in vivo with ibetaARK</article-title><source>Neuron</source><year>2021</year><volume>109</volume><issue>14</issue><fpage>2256</fpage><lpage>2274</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2021.05.023</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8418870</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34139149</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shigetomi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Bushong</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Haustein</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Tong</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Jackson-Weaver</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Imaging calcium micro-domains within entire astrocyte territories and endfeet with GCaMPs expressed using adeno-associated viruses</article-title><source>J Gen Physiol</source><year>2013</year><volume>141</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>633</fpage><lpage>647</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1085/jgp.201210949</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3639581</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23589582</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>H-J</given-names></name><name><surname>Cha</surname><given-names>H-J</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeong</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S-N</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>C-W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Conformational changes in the human Cx43/GJA1 gap junction channel visualized using cryo-EM</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2023</year><volume>14</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>931</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-023-36593-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9938869</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36805660</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Damstra</surname><given-names>HGJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohar</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Eddison</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Akhmanova</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kapitein</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Ten-fold robust expansion microscopy</article-title><source>Bio Protoc</source><year>2023</year><volume>13</volume><issue>12</issue><elocation-id>e4698</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21769/BioProtoc.4698</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10308184</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37397797</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Foo</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Purification of rat and mouse astrocytes by immunopanning</article-title><source>Cold Spring Harb Protoc</source><year>2013</year><volume>2013</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>421</fpage><lpage>432</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23637363</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mair</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bergmann</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Advances in enzyme-mediated proximity labeling and its potential for plant research</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>2022</year><volume>188</volume><fpage>756</fpage><lpage>768</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/plphys/kiab479</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8825456</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34662401</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name><name><surname>Branon</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name><name><surname>Udeshi</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name><name><surname>Myers</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Carr</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Proximity labeling in mammalian cells with TurboID and split-TurboID</article-title><source>Nat Protoc</source><year>2020</year><volume>15</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>3971</fpage><lpage>3999</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33139955</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chiaruttini</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Castoldi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Requie</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Camarena-Delgado</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Del Bianco</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>ABBA+BraiAn, an integrated suite for whole-brain mapping, reveals brain-wide differences in immediate-early genes induction upon learning</article-title><source>Cell Rep</source><year>2025</year><volume>44</volume><issue>7</issue><elocation-id>115876</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40553651</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hasel</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Marchildon</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Rufen-Blanchette</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Defining the molecular identity and morphology of glia limitans superficialis astrocytes in mouse and human</article-title><source>Cell Rep</source><year>2025</year><volume>44</volume><issue>3</issue><elocation-id>115344</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.celrep.2025.115344</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12160017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39982817</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weber</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><name><surname>Spaeth</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name><surname>Nitsche</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Nicholson</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The permeability of gap junction channels to probes of different size is dependent on connexin composition and permeant-pore affinities</article-title><source>Biophys J</source><year>2004</year><volume>87</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>958</fpage><lpage>973</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1529/biophysj.103.036350</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1304503</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15298902</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alarcon-Martinez</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Villafranca-Baughman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Quintero</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kacerovsky</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Dotigny</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Interpericyte tunnelling nanotubes regulate neurovascular coupling</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2020</year><volume>585</volume><issue>7823</issue><fpage>91</fpage><lpage>95</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32788726</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Renier</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Dominici</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Erzurumlu</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kratochwill</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name><name><surname>Rijli</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A mutant with bilateral whisker to barrel inputs unveils somatosensory mapping rules in the cerebral cortex</article-title><source>Elife</source><year>2017</year><volume>6</volume><elocation-id>e23494</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.23494</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5404921</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28350297</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Margolis</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lütcke</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Schulz</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Haiss</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Weber</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Reorganization of cortical population activity imaged throughout long-term sensory deprivation</article-title><source>Nat Neurosci</source><year>2012</year><volume>15</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>1539</fpage><lpage>1546</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23086335</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Carvell</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name><name><surname>Kodger</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Simons</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sensory loss by selected whisker removal produces immediate disinhibition in the somatosensory cortex of behaving rats</article-title><source>J Neurosci</source><year>1999</year><volume>19</volume><issue>20</issue><fpage>9117</fpage><lpage>9125</lpage><comment>1999</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.19-20-09117.1999</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6782760</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10516329</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Renier</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name><name><surname>Kirst</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Azevedo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Mapping of brain activity by automated volume analysis of immediate early genes</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2016</year><volume>165</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>1789</fpage><lpage>1802</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2016.05.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4912438</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27238021</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sellien</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ebner</surname><given-names>FF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rapid plasticity follows whisker pairing in barrel cortex of the awake rat</article-title><source>Exp Brain Res</source><year>2007</year><volume>177</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>14</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16924487</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saccheri</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Pozzi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Avogadri</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Barozzi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Faretta</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Bacteria-induced gap junctions in tumors favor antigen cross-presentation and antitumor immunity</article-title><source>Sci Transl Med</source><year>2010</year><volume>2</volume><issue>44</issue><elocation-id>44ra57</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20702856</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Emerging issues of connexin channels: biophysics fills the gap</article-title><source>Q Rev Biophys</source><year>2001</year><volume>34</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>325</fpage><lpage>472</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11838236</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Valiunas</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>IS</given-names></name><name><surname>Brink</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Defining the factors that affect solute permeation of gap junction channels</article-title><source>Biochim Biophys Acta Biomembr</source><year>2018</year><volume>1860</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>96</fpage><lpage>101</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbamem.2017.07.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5705451</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28690048</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Sleep drives metabolite clearance from the adult brain</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2013</year><volume>342</volume><issue>6156</issue><fpage>373</fpage><lpage>377</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1241224</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3880190</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24136970</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S-N</given-names></name><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>H-J</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeong</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ryu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>H-J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cryo-EM structures of human Cx36/GJD2 neuronal gap junction channel</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2023</year><volume>14</volume><issue>1</issue><elocation-id>1347</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-023-37040-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10008584</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36906653</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Connexin43 in neonatal excitatory neurons is important for short-term motor learning</article-title><source>Brain Res</source><year>2019</year><volume>1720</volume><elocation-id>146287</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31194949</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Balice-Gordon</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gap junctional communication among developing and injured motor neurons</article-title><source>Brain Res Brain Res Rev</source><year>2000</year><volume>32</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>242</fpage><lpage>249</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10751674</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Pereda</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pinter</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Balice-Gordon</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nerve injury induces gap junctional coupling among axotomized adult motor neurons</article-title><source>J Neurosci</source><year>2000</year><volume>20</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>674</fpage><lpage>684</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.20-02-00674.2000</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6772393</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10632597</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R41"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cheung</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Bataveljic</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Visser</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Moulard</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Physiological synaptic activity and recognition memory require astroglial glutamine</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2022</year><volume>13</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>753</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-022-28331-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8826940</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35136061</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R42"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Takatsuru</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Eto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaneko</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Masuda</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Shimokawa</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Critical role of the astrocyte for functional remodeling in contralateral hemisphere of somatosensory cortex after stroke</article-title><source>J Neurosci</source><year>2013</year><volume>33</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>4683</fpage><lpage>4692</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.2657-12.2013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6619011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23486942</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R43"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Gildea</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name><name><surname>Selles</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Katafygiotou</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Liddelow</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Astrocytes in the mouse brain respond bilaterally to unilateral retinal neurodegeneration</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2025</year><volume>122</volume><issue>11</issue><elocation-id>e241824912</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.2418249122</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11929491</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40063795</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R44"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beardslee</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Laing</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Beyer</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name><name><surname>Saffitz</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rapid turnover of connexin43 in the adult rat heart</article-title><source>Circ Res</source><year>1998</year><volume>83</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>629</fpage><lpage>635</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9742058</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R45"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Laing</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Beyer</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The gap junction protein connexin43 is degraded via the ubiquitin proteasome pathway</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1995</year><volume>270</volume><issue>44</issue><fpage>26399</fpage><lpage>26403</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7592854</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R46"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lawal</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Ulloa Severino</surname><given-names>FP</given-names></name><name><surname>Eroglu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of astrocyte structural plasticity in regulating neural circuit function and behavior</article-title><source>Glia</source><year>2022</year><volume>70</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>1467</fpage><lpage>1483</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/glia.24191</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9233050</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35535566</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R47"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mori</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Buffo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wurst</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Kühn</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Inducible gene deletion in astroglia and radial glia--a valuable tool for functional and lineage analysis</article-title><source>Glia</source><year>2006</year><volume>54</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>21</fpage><lpage>34</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16652340</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R48"><label>48</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boulay</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>del Castillo</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Giraudet</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamard</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Giaume</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Hearing is normal without connexin30</article-title><source>J Neurosci</source><year>2013</year><volume>33</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>430</fpage><lpage>434</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.4240-12.2013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6704917</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23303923</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R49"><label>49</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Theis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Jauch</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhuo</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Speidel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Wallraff</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Accelerated hippocampal spreading depression and enhanced locomotory activity in mice with astrocyte-directed inactivation of connexin43</article-title><source>J Neurosci</source><year>2003</year><volume>23</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>766</fpage><lpage>776</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.23-03-00766.2003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6741919</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12574405</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R50"><label>50</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bansal</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Pfeiffer</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reversible inhibition of oligodendrocyte progenitor differentiation by a monoclonal antibody against surface galactolipids</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>1989</year><volume>86</volume><issue>16</issue><fpage>6181</fpage><lpage>6185</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.86.16.6181</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC297801</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2668957</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R51"><label>51</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Sloan</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name><surname>Caneda</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Plaza</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Purification and characterization of progenitor and mature human astrocytes reveals transcriptional and functional differences with mouse</article-title><source>Neuron</source><year>2016</year><volume>89</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>37</fpage><lpage>53</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2015.11.013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4707064</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26687838</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Visualizing astrocyte gap junctional communication using the astrocyte network tracer.</title><p><bold>a</bold>. Diagram of the astrocyte network tracer construct. <bold>b</bold>. Cx43 connexons contain 6 connexins, only one of which needs to be the fusion protein for TurboID to reside on the gap junction. <bold>c</bold>. Infected astrocytes biotinylate molecules that flux through Cx43 gap junctions into adjacent, uninfected cells. <bold>d</bold>. This volume-fills in-network astrocytes with biotinylated molecules such that infected (HA+, streptavidin+), in-network (HA-, streptavidin+), and out-of-network (HA-, streptavidin-) cells can be visualized. <bold>e</bold>. Infection of primary immunopanned rat astrocytes (GFAP, green) resulted in Cx43-TID-HA expression (cyan) in 10% of cells, forming a biotin-labeled network containing 80% of cells (streptavidin, magenta) (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplemental Figures 1, 2</xref>). f. Primary rat astrocytes were expanded 8.7x to visualize individual Cx43 gap junctions (grey) and incorporated fusion protein (HA, cyan). <bold>g</bold>. Superresolution microscopy on expanded astrocytes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">20</xref></sup> enabled single-molecule imaging of the fusion protein incorporated into astrocyte gap junctions expressed in immunopanned primary rat astrocytes. Polyclonal Cx43 antibodies conjugated directly to fluorophores reveal gap junction structure (grey) and the HA tag (cyan) shows TurboID within the gap junction vestibule. <bold>h</bold>. Single-molecule localization microscopy (SMLM) of HA (cyan) and Cx43 (magenta). <bold>i</bold>. Quantification of the intrafluorophoric distance from HA to the nearest Cx43. Median (20.73 Å) indicated with the solid blue line; dotted lines denote the 25th (18.09 Å) and 75th (25.74 Å) percentiles. <bold>j</bold>. In vivo experimental timeline. 3 weeks following viral injection, mice received biotin-supplemented drinking water for 1 week, after which they were perfused. Brains were then delipidated, stained with streptavidin to reveal biotinylated molecules, cleared, and imaged via light sheet microscopy. <bold>k</bold>. Light sheet micrograph of HA-tag (cyan) shows gap junctions containing fusion protein in an infected cell within a cleared brain. l. Streptavidin (magenta) labeling of biotinylated molecules. <bold>m</bold>. Merged image showing a two-cell example of an infected (left) and an uninfected in-network (right) cell.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS207439-f001"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Multiple astrocyte networks varying in size and organization traverse the mouse brain.</title><p>Three-dimensional renderings of light sheet-imaged brains infected in motor cortex (top row), hypothalamus (middle row), or prefrontal cortex (bottom row). Each image is presented in two views: the first shows the infected region (HA-tag, cyan) inside of the autofluorescence capture (grey) for context; the second shows the same infected region within the streptavidin-stained astrocyte network originating from that brain region (magenta). Dorsal (left column), sagittal (middle column), and oblique (right column) views of the same light sheet datasets show network morphology at different angles.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS207439-f002"/></fig><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Astrocyte networks link specific brain regions.</title><p>Virtual coronal sections of light sheet imaged brains infected in motor cortex (left column), hypothalamus (middle column), or prefrontal cortex (right column). Sections from each brain are arranged from rostral to caudal (top to bottom images) and were selected as representative examples of robust astrocyte network connections. Brain regions are outlined using an overlay of the Allen Brain Atlas (fitted via the FIJI ABBA plugin<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref></sup>; 3D mouse Allen Brain Atlas, mouse.brain-map.org and atlas.brain-map.org).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS207439-f003"/></fig><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Non-gap-junctional mechanisms do not compensate for astrocyte gap junctional knockout.</title><p><bold>a</bold>. Sagittal section of <italic>Cx43</italic><sup>fl/fl</sup><italic>Cx30</italic><sup>fl/fl</sup> mouse brain, littermate to <bold>b</bold>. <italic>Slc1a1</italic>(GLAST)<sup>Cre-ERT2</sup><italic>Gja1</italic><sup>fl/fl</sup><italic>Gjb6</italic><sup>fl/fl</sup> (cKO) mouse. Both mice were given tamoxifen, inducing robust Cx ablation in cKO mice; sections are stained for Cx43. <bold>c-f</bold>. Higher resolution images of hippocampi stained for GFAP (green, astrocytes), tomato lectin (red, vasculature), and either Cx43 or Cx30 (white) in control (c, d) or conditional knockout (e, f) mice. <bold>g</bold>. Control mouse injected in hippocampus expresses the astrocyte network tracer in CA2 (HA tag, cyan) and exhibits bilateral streptavidin labeling across hippocampus and hypothalamic regions. <bold>h</bold>. In conditional knockout mice, streptavidin labeling is restricted to infected astrocytes where Cx43 is reintroduced via the astrocyte network tracer. <bold>i</bold>. Quantification of Cx43 levels across vasculature and parenchyma. In cKO mice, Cx43 immunoreactivity is significantly diminished in all locations except at the periphery of blood vessels, where pericytes reside (paired two-sided t-tests across 180 locations relative to vasculature with Bonferroni correction; p &lt; 0.001 in all significant locations; n = 3 mice per condition with 3 micrographs averaged to generate values for each mouse). <bold>j</bold>. Quantification of astrocyte network volume normalized to the volume of infected astrocytes. When astrocytes are infected in either hippocampus, prefrontal cortex (PFC), or barrel cortex, conditional knockout mouse networks are significantly reduced from those in control mice (unpaired two-sided t-tests; p &lt; 0.001 in all regions; n = 4 mice per region per condition). <bold>k</bold>. cKO mice induced via tamoxifen gavage were injected with astrocyte network tracer per the experimental timeline in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1j</xref>. Tomato Lectin was injected during perfusion to stain vasculature. Micrographs show the streptavidin-labeled astrocyte network (magenta) and vasculature (red). The network does not appear to follow or expand along blood vessels following astrocyte network loss.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS207439-f004"/></fig><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>Astrocyte networks are plastic and differ from neuronal networks.</title><p><bold>a</bold>. Experimental timeline. <bold>b</bold>. Diagram of the constructs in the viral mixture. <bold>c</bold>. Following whisker trim, the number of streptavidin-positive cells relative to the number of HA-positive cells was significantly reduced in corresponding barrel cortex relative to naïve animals (n = 4 naïve, n = 3 trim) Statistical significance (p value indicated on graph) determined via unpaired Welch’s t-test (α = 0.05). Values are mean ± standard deviation. <bold>d</bold>. Three-dimensional rendering of a naïve mouse infected with both constructs in a single injection Streptavidin (magenta) shows astrocyte connectivity originating from the same region in which infected neurons (yellow, mCherry) reside. <bold>e</bold>,<bold>f</bold>. Horizontal (<bold>e</bold>) and coronal (<bold>f</bold>) virtual sections provide a detailed view of connectivity among specific regions. <bold>g-i</bold>. Corresponding images in a brain from a mouse with unilaterally trimmed whiskers corresponding to infected barrel cortex.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS207439-f005"/></fig></floats-group></article>