<!DOCTYPE article
 PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" article-type="preprint"><?all-math-mml yes?><?use-mml?><?origin ukpmcpa?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">bioRxiv</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>bioRxiv : the preprint server for biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2692-8205</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">EMS207377</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2025.07.17.664155</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="archive">PPR1052176</article-id><article-version-alternatives><article-version article-version-type="status">preprint</article-version><article-version article-version-type="number">1</article-version></article-version-alternatives><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Deciphering the evolutionary origin of the enantioselectivity of short-chain dehydrogenases from plants toward 1-borneol</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zuson</surname><given-names>Jasmin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Helmer</surname><given-names>Carl P.O.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Geronimo</surname><given-names>Bruno Di</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chánique</surname><given-names>Andrea M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kavciaková</surname><given-names>Katarina</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Teijeiro-Juiz</surname><given-names>Rosa</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Brickel</surname><given-names>Sebastian</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Drienovská</surname><given-names>Ivana</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kracher</surname><given-names>Daniel</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A6">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3190-1173</contrib-id><name><surname>Kamerlin</surname><given-names>Shina Caroline Lynn</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A7">7</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CR1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7928-4488</contrib-id><name><surname>Loll</surname><given-names>Bernhard</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CR1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-2853-3525</contrib-id><name><surname>Kourist</surname><given-names>Robert</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A6">6</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CR1">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Institute of Molecular Biotechnology, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/00d7xrm67</institution-id><institution>Graz University of Technology</institution></institution-wrap>, <addr-line>Petersgasse 14</addr-line>, <city>Graz</city><postal-code>8010</postal-code>, <country country="AT">Austria</country></aff><aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Institute of Chemistry and Biochemistry, Laboratory of Structural Biochemistry, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/046ak2485</institution-id><institution>Freie Universität Berlin</institution></institution-wrap>, <addr-line>Takustraße 6</addr-line>, <postal-code>14195</postal-code><city>Berlin</city>, <country country="DE">Germany</country></aff><aff id="A3"><label>3</label>School of Chemistry and Biochemistry and of Chemical and Biomolecular Engineering, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/01zkghx44</institution-id><institution>Georgia Institute of Technology</institution></institution-wrap>, <addr-line>901 Atlantic Drive NW, Atlanta</addr-line>, <city>Georgia</city><postal-code>30332-0400</postal-code>, <country country="US">United State</country></aff><aff id="A4"><label>4</label>Department of Chemistry - BMC, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/048a87296</institution-id><institution>Uppsala University</institution></institution-wrap>, <addr-line>BMC Box 576</addr-line>, <postal-code>S-751 23</postal-code><city>Uppsala</city>, <country country="SE">Sweden</country></aff><aff id="A5"><label>5</label>UVA Amsterdam, Department of Chemistry and Pharmaceutical Sciences, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/008xxew50</institution-id><institution>Vrije Universiteit Amsterdam</institution></institution-wrap>, <addr-line>De Boelelaan 1108</addr-line>, <postal-code>1081 HZ</postal-code><city>Amsterdam</city>, <country country="NL">The Netherlands</country></aff><aff id="A6"><label>6</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/02jfbm483</institution-id><institution>BioTechMed-Graz</institution></institution-wrap>, <addr-line>Mozartgasse 12</addr-line>, <postal-code>8010</postal-code><city>Graz</city>, <country country="AT">Austria</country></aff><aff id="A7"><label>7</label>Department of Chemistry, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/012a77v79</institution-id><institution>Lund University</institution></institution-wrap>, <addr-line>Box 124</addr-line>, <postal-code>22100</postal-code><city>Lund</city>, <country country="SE">Sweden</country></aff><author-notes><corresp id="CR1">Corresponding authors: Robert Kourist, Institute of Molecular Biotechnology, Graz University of Technology, Petersgasse 14, Graz 8010, Austria, <email>skamerlin3@gatech.edu</email>; Shina Caroline Lynn Kamerlin, School of Chemistry and Biochemistry, Georgia Institute of Technology, Atlanta, Georgia, USA, <email>loll@chemie.fu-berlin.de</email>; Bernhard Loll, Institute of Chemistry and Biochemistry, Laboratory of Structural Biochemistry, Freie Universität Berlin, Takustr. 6, 14195 Berlin, Germany, <email>kourist@tugraz.at</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted"><day>22</day><month>07</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="preprint"><day>18</day><month>07</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><permissions><ali:free_to_read/><license><ali:license_ref>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is licensed under a <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0 International license</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p id="P1">Enzyme engineering has produced numerous methods to optimize enzymes for biotechnological processes; however, less is known about how natural evolution creates new functionalities. We investigate the evolutionary emergence of enantioselectivity in plant borneol dehydrogenases (BDHs), which feature hydrophobic active-sites and are enantioselective towards dibornane-type monoterpenols. Ancestral sequence reconstruction provided a trajectory from the oldest unselective BDH ancestor N30 (E=12) toward the youngest selective ancestor N32, involving 19 mutations: 18 mutations are peripheral, one (I111L) occurs in the active-site. The mutation L111I in the hydrophobic pocket increased the selectivity of N30, while the back-mutation I111L decreased the selectivity of N32. Additional peripheral mutations (V136L/G169A/V183I) were required for high selectivity. Crystal structures suggested that protein dynamics, rather than structural changes shape these catalytic properties. Molecular simulations with funnel-metadynamics revealed a correlation between the active-site’s solvent-accessible surface area (SASA) and selectivity. This potential evolutionary pathway shapes enantioselectivity, and guides future enzyme engineering campaigns.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec id="S1" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p id="P2">Stereoselectivity enables the striking enantiomerical purity of Nature’s molecules.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref></sup> The often high enantioselectivity of enzymes towards natural and unnatural substrates is a reason for their broad application in chemical and pharmaceutical industries.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">2</xref></sup> Despite this importance, the evolutionary pathways leading to the formation of stereoselectivity in enzymes remain largely unknown. Enzyme engineering often aims to improve enzymes for the conversion of unnatural substrates, but these engineering campaigns rarely follow the principles observed in natural evolutionary trajectories leading to stereoselectivity. For practical reasons, rational design and saturation mutagenesis focus mostly on the active-site, while the periphery is largely ignored. In contrast, gene randomization methods, such as error-prone PCR, overrepresent peripheral amino acids.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">3</xref></sup> Deep mutational scanning (DMS) might offer insights on structure-function relationships, but, to our knowledge, has not yet been applied to investigate the stereoselectivity of enzymes.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">4</xref></sup></p><p id="P3">Borneol-type dehydrogenases (BDHs) encompass both highly selective and unselective enzymes towards their natural, chiral substrate 1-borneol. This makes them an interesting model for the study of the natural emergence of stereoselectivity. BDHs are produced during the maturation of the plant and catalyze the enzymatic production of camphor in oil glands on the leaf surface.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref></sup> Most known bornyl-diphosphate synthases produce (+)-bornyl-pyrophosphate, which is then hydrolysed to (+)-1-borneol.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref></sup> Bornyl-diphosphate synthases leading to the (–)-stereoisomer are rare, with only one enzyme described from the plant Sambong.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref></sup> Stereoselective 1-borneol oxidation does not offer any obvious evolutionary advantages in most plants. This is reflected by the very low stereoselectivity of most characterized enzymes.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">8</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref></sup> In the 1980s, Croteau <italic>et al.</italic> reported a stereoselective dehydrogenase from the <italic>Salvia</italic> genus where the essential oil contains (–)-1-borneol and (+)-camphor.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref></sup> The presence of (–)-1-borneol in the essential oil is an indicator for the high (+)-selectivity of its BDH. By mining the genomes of <italic>S. officinalis</italic> and <italic>S. rosmarinus,</italic> we identified several highly stereoselective short-chain dehydrogenases (SDRs) and determined their structures.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref></sup> BDH have been applied for the kinetic resolution of 1-borneol and 1-isoborneol, which can be derived as racemate from α-pinene, allowing the synthesis of optically pure ingredients of therapeutics, cosmetics, and fragrances from an inexpensive bio-based starting material (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref></sup></p><p id="P4">The structure of <italic>Sr</italic>BDH1 (PDB: 6ZYZ)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref></sup> shows that the substrate-binding pocket is very hydrophobic. The 1-borneol molecule is very compact and has few rotational degrees of freedom. Only the alcohol function of the hydrophobic substrate can engage in hydrogen bonds with the active-site amino acids. To initiate oxidation, the OH-group forms a hydrogen bond with the hydroxyl-tyrosinate ion, and the α-CH must be positioned close to the nicotinamide</p><p id="P5">cofactor.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">20</xref></sup> These two interactions determine productive binding poses. Therefore, discrimination between the two enantiomers must be accomplished by their interactions with the residues lining the hydrophobic active-site pocket. The composition of the hydrophobic pockets of the unselective and selective BDH is very similar. Several point mutations in the first shell of the active-site of the highly selective <italic>Sr</italic>BDH1 did not reduce the high selectivity towards (+)-1-borneol.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref></sup> This poses a significant challenge to understanding the molecular basis underlying the remarkable selectivity of these enzymes.</p><p id="P6">Hydrophobic pockets are often crucial elements of enzyme catalysis. For example, unfavourable interactions of a carboxylic group of substituted malonic acids in a hydrophobic pocket of bacterial arylmalonate decarboxylase induce carboxylate cleavage.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">21</xref></sup> Increasing the hydrophobicity of the surface residues by iterative saturation mutagenesis significantly enhanced activity.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">22</xref></sup> Placing a Cys-His-Glu catalytic triad in a hydrophobic lumen of a <italic>de novo</italic> generated catalytic scaffold allowed the creation of an artificial hydrolase.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">23</xref></sup> Baker and Green created a tuneable hydrophobic pocket within a designed heme-binding protein that catalyzed cyclopropanation reactions.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref></sup> Hydrophobic pockets are also crucial for the stereoselectivity of enzymes. For instance, the different accommodation of isomers in hydrophobic pockets is decisive for the stereoselectivity of α/β-fold hydrolases, and saturation mutagenesis of amino acids in the hydrophobic surface increased stereoselectivity.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">25</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">29</xref></sup> In these examples, improvements of the enzymes were achieved by combinatorial methods. These have in common that precise predictions on the outcome of amino acid substitutions within hydrophobic pockets are difficult with the currently available knowledge and methodology. A comparison of unselective and selective extant enzymes may reveal clues to the difference in selectivity. In horizontal approaches, extant enzymes are directly compared with each other to identify potential target residues.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">30</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31">31</xref></sup> While this method compares individual residues, it neglects any context-dependent changes that the enzymes have accumulated during their evolutionary history. Without context, transplantation of potential selectivity-determining residues is likely to have detrimental effects on activity. In contrast, vertical approaches use ancestral sequence reconstruction (ASR) to create evolutionary information, which was gradualy lost over time.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">30</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31">31</xref></sup> Narayan <italic>et al</italic>. resurrected flavin-dependent monooxygenases and demonstrated that exchanging a small number of active-site residues could switch the stereochemical outcome of oxidative dearomatization.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">30</xref></sup> Similarly, a study on imine reductases revealed the residues involved in stereoselectivity, allowing for inversion of the reaction.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32">32</xref></sup> A campaign on vanillyl alcohol oxidases successfully identified key residues for broadening the substrate scope of these enzymes.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33">33</xref></sup> A study on spiroviolene synthases created ancestral variants that exhibited higher stability and solubility, enabling the crystallization of an ancestor.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34">34</xref></sup> The ancestral proteins further pointed to specific amino acid substitutions, allowing for fine-tuning of the substrate specificity in the extant enzyme.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34">34</xref></sup> Furthermore, evolutionary information can guide through fitness landscapes.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35">35</xref></sup></p><p id="P7">Comparison of the last unselective ancestor with more recent, selective ancestors may reveal evolutionary ‘switches’, i.e. residues and mutations involved in the emergence of stereoselectivity in the BDH enzyme family. Herein, we use ancestral sequence reconstruction, structural analysis, site-directed mutagenesis and computational simulations to demonstrate how epistatic effects determine the evolutionary emergence of stereoselectivity in enzyme catalysis.</p></sec><sec id="S2" sec-type="results | discussion"><title>Results and discussion</title><sec id="S3"><title>Ancestral sequence reconstruction of BDHs</title><p id="P8">The sequences of ten known plant BDHs were used as queries for a search against the 1KP database<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36">36</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37">37</xref></sup> that identified 100 sequences originating from 59 plant genera (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2A</xref>). The stereoselective <italic>Salvia rosmarinus</italic> BDH1 (SrBDH1) and the unselective <italic>Artemisia annua</italic> BDH2 (AaBDH2) are located in different clades and are, as such, evolutionarily distant. Sequence alignments of the extant enzymes show that the catalytic residues (SxxxxxxxxxxxxYxxxK) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 1</xref>) and the cofactor binding motif (TGxxx[AG]xG) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 1</xref>) are conserved.</p><p id="P9">97 ancestral protein sequences (enumerated N1-N97) were computed, and twelve ancestral proteins from different sections of the tree (N4, N5, N6, N7, N13, N23, N30, N32, N39, N48, N49, and N74) were selected. All ancestral variants could be produced as soluble proteins in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table S1</xref>). Similar to several extant BDH,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref></sup> N13, N23, and N48 precipitated during His-tag affinity purification, which prevented their further characterization.</p></sec><sec id="S4"><title>Determination of the enantioselectivity of ancestral proteins</title><p id="P10">The ancestors closest to the common ancestor (N4, N5, N6) displayed the highest activity in the oxidation of (–)-1-borneol, the slower-reacting enantiomer for all characterized BDH (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 2</xref>). N32, the ancestral protein closest to <italic>Sr</italic>BDH1, was specific for the oxidation of (+)-1-borneol and did not convert (–)-1-borneol. The evolutionary trajectory from N6 to <italic>Sr</italic>BDH1 includes N30 and N32. We assume that the evolutionary ‘switch’, i.e. the mutations responsible for the high selectivity of N32 and <italic>Sr</italic>BDH1, lie within the sequence space between N6 and N32. Therefore, ancestors N6, N30, and N32 were chosen for further characterization.</p><p id="P11">We determined the Michaelis-Menten kinetics of the three ancestors towards the faster-converted (+)-1-borneol, which was complicated by the low solubility of the substrate in aqueous solution<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38">38</xref></sup> and required extrapolation of data obtained below the <italic>K</italic><sub>M</sub>-value. Addition of 20% DMSO enhanced the solubility of borneol from 4.8 to 9.0 mM, while retaining around 40% of the overall enzymatic activity (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 3</xref>). Ancestor N6 exhibited substrate inhibition with (+)-1-borneol (<italic>K</italic><sub>i(+)-bor</sub> [mM] = 2.5). Surprisingly, the <italic>K</italic><sub>M</sub>-values for the ancestors N30 (<italic>K</italic><sub>M</sub> = 20.27±7.21 mM) and N32 (<italic>K</italic><sub>M</sub> = 17.36±5.40 mM) were ten-fold higher than those of the wild-type <italic>Sr</italic>BDH1 (<italic>K<sub>M</sub></italic> = 2.02±0.18 mM)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref></sup>, while the <italic>K</italic><sub>M</sub> of N6 (<italic>K</italic><sub>M</sub> = 0.01 ±0.01 mM) was below that of the wild-type (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 4</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table S2</xref>).</p><p id="P12">The strong substrate inhibition of ancestor N6 rendered measurement of the E-value from enantiomeric excess and conversion unsuitable.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39">39</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40">40</xref></sup> Furthermore, the low solubility of 1-borneol prevented measuring catalytic efficiencies for the determination of the E-value. The Quick-E method developed by Kazlauskas <italic>et al</italic>. provided a suitable method to include the competition of both enantiomers.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40">40</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41">41</xref></sup> In this approach, the activity of an enantiopure substrate is measured against a non-chiral surrogate competitor and is correlated to the reaction of the opposing enantiomer. This setup mimics the natural competition between two enantiomers. Oxidation of the slower-converted enantiomer (–)-1-borneol with and without surrogate substrate (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 5</xref>) confirmed that the competition with the surrogate substrate decreased the activity towards (–)-1-borneol, thus mimicking a racemic reaction. Determination of E<sub>comp</sub>-values (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>) showed that under competition, ancestors N6 and N30 have low selectivity towards the 1-borneol enantiomers. N30 lost the substrate inhibition observed in N6, and N32 is the first ancestor to be specific for (+)-1-borneol. While having similar total activity toward (+)-1-borneol compared to the N30, no activity toward (–)-1-borneol was detectable. N32 is highly selective under competitive conditions (E&gt;200), highlighting the transition from N30 to N32 as the critical evolutionary step towards enantioselectivity.</p></sec><sec id="S5"><title>Structure determination of ancestral proteins</title><p id="P13">BDHs can exhibit two distinct conformations.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42">42</xref></sup> Upon substrate binding, the enzyme transforms from an ‘open’ to a ‘closed’ conformation by the movement of the αFG-helix and loop toward the active-site (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42">42</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R45">45</xref></sup></p><p id="P14">To account for these conformational dynamics, we attempted to obtain crystal structures of the ancestors N6, N30, N32 and N39 but were only able to collect high-resolution diffraction data of the tetrameric N32 and N39. N32 is arranged as a tetramer in the unit cell (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table S3-4</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 6-7</xref>). As there is a single N39 protomer in the asymmetric unit, the tetrameric arrangement unit was calculated based on crystal symmetry. Both structures superimpose with an RMSD of 1.19 Å (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table S5</xref>). The overall structure of N32 resembles the structures of <italic>Sr</italic>BDH1 as well as <italic>So</italic>BDH2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>). Co-crystallization and soaking experiments of the protein crystals with either (+)-1-borneol or (–)-camphor did not lead to structures bound to these compounds.</p><p id="P15">As no high-resolution crystal structure of N6 was obtained, AlphaFold3<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R46">46</xref></sup> was used to generate a model, which showed a mean pLDDT of 89.39 with the lowest scores located at the termini (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 7</xref>). Despite an overall high similarity with <italic>Sr</italic>BDH1, differences can be observed in the loop-αFG motif of chain A, whereas chains B-D have a closed conformation, which aligns with AlphaFold3 models. Aligning the model of N6 to the crystal structure of <italic>Sr</italic>BDH1 yields an RMSD of 0.308 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table S5</xref>). Since the open confirmation appears to be an artefact unique to chain A of PDB: 6ZYZ, the generated models of non-crystallized variants were used for structural analysis.</p></sec><sec id="S6"><title>Analysis of evolutionary pathways between ancestors</title><p id="P16">The first shell of the enzyme was defined as the residues within a 6 Å radius of the nicotinamide moiety of the cofactor, while residues outside were considered as secondary shell. In N6, the first shell hosts 16 residues, in N30 15 residues, in N32 17 residues and in <italic>Sr</italic>BDH1 14 residues. N6 and N30 differ by 38 amino acids (three in the first shell), while N30 and N32 differ by 19 amino acids (only one in the first shell). A full combinatorial approach, would result in a sequence space that is too large for a comprehensive kinetic analysis.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R47">47</xref></sup> Motivated by prior studies indicating that interactions with second-shell residues can affect enzyme selectivity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref></sup> we incorporated second-shell variants into our investigation.</p><p id="P17">To probe the three residues differing in the first shell of N6 and N30, we incorporated the first shell of N30 into N6, creating four variants (N6_V167A; N6_A211G; N6_A213V; N6_V167A/A211G/A213V). Point mutations of N6 did not relieve the substrate inhibition. Oxidation of (+)-1-borneol by N6_V167A and N6_A211G was lower at concentrations below and above the <italic>K</italic><sub>i</sub> of N6 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref>). In contrast, the substitution A213V lowered the substrate inhibition of N6. Combining the residues in N6_V167A/A211G/A213V lead to an activity similar to that of N6, neutralizing any negative or positive effects. The inhibition was still present when the complete set of first shell mutations of the non-inhibited N30 was introduced to N6, indicating that it is heavily influenced by peripheral residues, independent of or synergistic to the first shell residues.</p><p id="P18">While selectivity increases slightly between ancestor N6 (E<sub>comp</sub> = 10) and ancestor N30 (E<sub>comp</sub> = 12), the major gain of selectivity is achieved in the mutational transition from N30 to N32 (E<sub>comp</sub> &gt; 200). The loss of the ability to oxidize (–)-1-borneol in the transition between ancestors N30 and N32 highlights key mutations. Interestingly, the transition between N30 and N32 involves a single mutation L111I in the first shell. To test its significance as a potential evolutionary switch, a bidirectional exchange of the first shell residues was performed by site-directed mutagenesis (N32_I111L, N30_L111I). Mutants were purified, rates and enantioselectivity were determined.</p><p id="P19">N30_L111I (E<sub>comp</sub> = 21) had a two-fold higher selectivity, while the backmutation of Ile to Leu in N32 induced activity in this ancestor towards (–)-1-borneol. N32_I111L is converting both enantiomers (E<sub>comp</sub> = 27), whereas N32 did not show any activity towards (–)-1-borneol. We note that this mutation in the hydrophobic pocket is crucial for the specificity of N32, underlining that residue 111 is a switch in the evolutionary emergence of selectivity in the BDH.</p><p id="P20">The underlying ASR data suggest different ancestral protein sequences based on the marginal or joint ancestral sequence reconstruction. In the consensus sequence, the position in question (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 8</xref>, position 158; position 111 in N30/N32) is highly variable, with 11 amino acids present in the multiple sequence alignment (MSA). The most abundant amino acid is Ser, followed by Ile, Val, Pro, and Ala. In the marginal reconstruction, for N30 Val (posterior probability (PP)=0.54), Ile (PP=0.38), or Leu (PP=0.06) are suggested, while N32 hosts an Ile at this position. In the joint reconstruction, which was chosen for this study, the inferred positions are N30 Leu111 and N32 Ile111.</p><p id="P21">As the extant <italic>Sr</italic>BDH1 contains a Val in the analogous position 97,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref></sup> all three proposed mutations are covered by the set of ancestors obtained from joint reconstruction. While this residue proved key to the enantioselectivity, the enantiospecificity (i.e. completely suppressed conversion of the slower-reacting enantiomer) appeared to depend on additional interactions within the remaining 18 secondary shell residues. Additional peripheral substitutions were required to achieve reversal of selectivity. In addition to the ancestral mutant, <italic>Sr</italic>BDH1_V97L was designed to investigate the effects of exchanging the position equivalent to position 111 in N30 on the enantioselective extant enzyme. <italic>Sr</italic>BDH1_V97L showed similar activity toward (+)-1-borneol as N30_L111I but did not convert (–)-1-borneol, confirming the importance of additional peripheral mutations (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>).</p><p id="P22">Rational mutational approaches were chosen to uncover epistatic effects of position 111 with further peripheral amino acids in N32. The variant N30_L111I was chosen as base for the introduction of further co-mutations, to construct an enantiospecific variant. For this, the remaining 18 amino acids between N30 and N32 were targeted. Targeted mutations were based on structure-function relations in SDRs (N30_L111I/M213I/A214G)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R44">44</xref></sup>, the Grantham’s distance matrix N32/N30 (N30_L111I/S232V)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R48">48</xref></sup>, mutational hotspots (N30_L111I/A222V/E223A/S227A/S232V), evolutionary coupling analysis (N30_L111I/S166A/V167S/G169A)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R49">49</xref></sup>, and conserved residues (N30_L111I/V136L/G169A/V183I). Mutations in N30_L111I/M213I/A214G are located in the vicinity of the loop region between the βF-sheet and αG helix of N30_L1111. Residue S232 shows the highest Grantham’s distance, which is located in the αG helix. The αG helix is a hotspot of mutations, comprising four substitutions of N30_L111I/A222V/E223A/S227A/S232V within a distance of ten amino acids. Evolutionary coupling analysis highlighted three residues that possibly co-evolved with position 111 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 9</xref>), mirrored in N30_L111I/S166A/V167S/G169A. N30_L111I/V136L/S139G/V183I targets three mutations which reside in antiparallel arranged α-helices close to the active-site. N30_L111I/L47W/E74K/V79I/E107A/E153Q/Y197H includes all remaining mutations between the two BDH ancestors. These mutations display the largest distance to the active-site of the enzyme. Residues which are conserved between N32 and <italic>Sr</italic>BDH1 are introduced in N30_L111I/V136L/G169A/V183I. Since the most unusual amino acid substitution according to Grantham’s distance (N30_L111I/S232V) is also present in N30_L111I/A222V/E223A/S227A/S232V, N30_L111I/S232V was not investigated further.</p><p id="P23">Variants N30_L111I/M213I/A214G to N30_L111I/V136L/S139G/V183I displayed an increased activity toward (–)-1-borneol and equal or higher activity toward the preferred enantiomer (+)-1-borneol compared to N30. N30_L111I/L47W/E74K/V79I/E107A/E153Q/Y197H and N30_L111I/V136L/G169A/V183I, displayed similar conversion to (+)-1-borneol like N30_L111I, however no conversion of (–)-1-borneol was detectable. N30_L111I/S166A/V167S/G169A further stands out, as displaying the closest (+)-1-borneol conversion to the wildtype, while other variants show rather low activities (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>).</p><p id="P24">The peripheral mutations in N30_L111I/L47W/E74K/V79I/E107A/E153Q/Y197H are mainly located in loop regions or termini of the α-helices pointing away from the active-site (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 10 A</xref>). In N30_L111I/V136L/G169A/V183I, two mutations (Leu136 and Ile183) are located on opposing sites in the αE- and αG-helices with a distance of 9.8 Å and 10.7 Å to the α-carbon of the catalytic Tyr, while Ala169 is located in the loop region between αGH close to residue 111 in a distance of 11.0 Å (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 10 B</xref>). Evolutionary coupled residue Ala169 does not influence selectivity in N30_L111I/S166A/V167S/G169A. However, the combination with other conserved residues in N30_L111I/V136L/G169A/V183I shows positive epistatic effects towards increased selectivity.</p></sec><sec id="S7"><title>Simulation of the selectivity by molecular mechanics</title><p id="P25">Following our inability to co-crystallize or soak the substrate despite numerous attempts, molecular modelling elucidated the binding of 1-borneol to <italic>Sr</italic>BDH1. Initially, we modelled the binding mode of the 1-borneol substrate using docking techniques on the open conformation of <italic>Sr</italic>BDH1, using PDB: 6ZYZ<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref></sup>, chain A. Docking poses for both enantiomers were selected based on the lowest catalytic distances, <italic>d<sub>1</sub></italic> and <italic>d<sub>2</sub></italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref>). <italic>d<sub>1</sub></italic> shows the distance between the catalytic Tyr and the oxygen of the substrate. <italic>d<sub>2</sub></italic> shows the nicotinic acid moiety of the cofactor and the α-CH.</p><p id="P26">The reactive conformations interact mainly with Val97, Pro100, Ile147, Ala148, Tyr154, Phe190, Tyr253 and Phe260 from the opposite chain (PDB: 6ZYZ<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref></sup> numbering). Within the SDR superfamily, the triad Ser-Tyr-Lys SYK or extended tetrad Asn-Ser-Tyr-Lys facilitates catalysis.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43">43</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R44">44</xref></sup> Thereby, Tyr acts as an acid/base catalyst, whose p<italic>Ka</italic> is lowered by the neighbouring Lys and positively charged nicotinamide cofactor.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43">43</xref></sup> Lys is furthermore involved in the cofactor binding in the active-site, while Ser stabilizes and polarizes the substrate.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43">43</xref></sup> In some SDRs, the highly conserved Asn residue is involved in a proton relay mechanism from the bulk solvent to the Tyr.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43">43</xref></sup> The oxygen atoms of 1-borneol and the catalytic Tyr’s phenolic oxygen distances are 5.5 and 5.6 Å, and the oxidizable positions are at 3.9 Å (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref>). Our results underline that position 111 (ancestor numbering) is a selectivity switch, although additional peripheral mutations were necessary to completely suppress activity towards (–)-1-borneol. In case of the ancestral N30 and N32 variants, as well as variants N32_I111L, N30_L1111 and N30_L111I/V136L/G169A/V183I, the presence of either Leu or Ile at position 111 blocks the interaction and closeness within catalytic Tyr and NAD<sup>+</sup>, resulting in a maximum increasing of 3.8 Å for <italic>d<sub>1</sub></italic> and 2.2 Å for <italic>d<sub>2</sub></italic> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>).</p><p id="P27">This position is located directly downstream of the NNAG motif, another highly conserved motif in SDRs stabilizing the central β-sheet of the Rossman-fold.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43">43</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R44">44</xref></sup> Previous studies on SDRs, including hydroxysteroid dehydrogenases<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43">43</xref></sup>, actinorhodin polyketide ketoreductase<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R50">50</xref></sup>, and farnesol dehydrogenases<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R51">51</xref></sup> suggested that in the hydrophobic pocket of SDRs a water relay mechanism involves the Asp of the NNAG motif. The NNAG motif bridges the bulk water to the catalytic Lys in the hydrophobic pocket. Local water molecules relay a proton over the NNAG motif to stabilize the positive charge of the catalytic Lys. It was stated that small residues in the proximity of Asp facilitate easier proton transfer than bulky ones due to their higher rotational degrees of freedom.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43">43</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R44">44</xref></sup> Extending this hypothesis, the substitutions of the local residue 111 to Ile/Leu/Val are likely to influence the proton transfer, probably impacting the conversion of the two stereoisomers. However, the docking scores presented in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table S6</xref> do not reveal significant differences between the enantiomers; therefore, the enantioselectivity of BDHs cannot be discriminated based on these results alone. Consequently, conventional Molecular Dynamics (MD) simulations were conducted to further assess substrate accessibility of the enzymes.</p><p id="P28">We performed 3 x 500 ns MD simulations on each system following minimization and with both borneol enantiomeric molecules replicated for each chain. Our results indicate significant instability for both enantiomers in the wild-type system, with RMSD values exceeding 2 Å (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 11-12</xref>), suggesting that 1-borneol is not stabilized inside the cavity. We monitored distances <italic>d<sub>1</sub></italic> and <italic>d<sub>2</sub></italic> across three simulations and employed kernel density estimation (KDE) to generate distinct surfaces for each chain (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 13-14</xref>). These surfaces represent the most frequently observed configurations of the two distances during the simulations. None of the most populated points fall within the reactive zone with <italic>d<sub>1</sub></italic> and <italic>d<sub>2</sub></italic> distances under 5 Å. Instead, all data points, across all four chains of <italic>Sr</italic>BDH1, are in regions corresponding to distances between 7 to 10 Å, significantly distant from the reactive zone. Visual inspection of the simulations shows how 1-borneol is moving inside the cavity with apparently no stable binding, making it challenging to assess specific interactions. These findings are not surprising, as the substrate remains highly mobile and rapidly shifts, also observed in simulations of the ancestral and mutant enzymes. All monitored RMSD values exceeded 2 Å (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 15-24</xref>), and the KDE plots did not fall within the defined reactive area (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 25-39</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S8"><title>Funnel-MD simulations</title><p id="P29">Given the low-affinity 1-borneol values for <italic>Sr</italic>BDH1, we applied Funnel-MD simulations using exclusively upper limit walls to retain the 1-borneol molecules within the active-site defined by the funnel. No bias potential was applied since 1-borneol binding is not stable. This method ensures that the molecules remain available for interaction analyses despite the inherent dynamics of the simulation environment, mimicking a more biologically relevant scenario where transient interactions dictate functional outcomes. These findings suggest a more selective environment, enhancing our ability to predict the narrow substrate scope. Monitored distances for the <italic>Sr</italic>BDH1-(+)-1-borneol complexes present 2 out of 3 replicas inside the reactive state (most populated <italic>d<sub>1</sub></italic> and <italic>d<sub>2</sub></italic> lower than 5 Å) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 40</xref>). The visual inspection of the simulations also reveals the closure of the αFG-helix through the active-site, providing a plausible transitory state of this reactive complex (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 40-B</xref>). In <italic>Sr</italic>BDH1-(-)-1-borneol complexes, any of the experimental replicas reached this reactive state (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8</xref>). Unselective ancestor N6 displayed the highest frequency of active density points in the reactive conformation for (+)-1-borneol across three replicas and for (–)-1-borneol in two replicas (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 35</xref>). In case of ancestor N32, selectivity for (+)-1-borneol can be observed as well in the density plots since all peaks at <italic>d<sub>1</sub></italic> remain close 5 Å and <italic>d<sub>2</sub></italic> close to 5 Å or lower, whereas for (–)-1-borneol <italic>d<sub>2</sub></italic> density peaks are close to 8 Å or above far away from the reactive state (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 36</xref>). Unselective N32_I111L with its low activity, shows diffuse kernel density estimate (KDE) plots (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 37</xref>) where only a few areas approach the reactive state, and none of the minima for both enantiomers reach the defined reactive area. We can approach the low stereoselectivity on the KDE plots, rendering two replicas for both enantiomers in the reactive state (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 38</xref>). Only in N30_L111I/V136L/G169A/V183I the funnel restriction approach does not enable us to distinctly verify 1-borneol selectivity, as evidenced by KDE plots that display reactive states for both enantiomers (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 39</xref>).</p><p id="P30">The solvent-accessible surface area (SASA) of both the substrate and the enzyme pocket significantly affect the enzymatic reaction by substrate orientation.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R52">52</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R53">53</xref></sup> Violin plots of SASA values for both substrate and enzyme pocket reveal significant variability between systems and replicas. Enantioselectivity correlated with lower SASA values. In the wild-type (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 41</xref>), pocket SASA values are 439 Å<sup>2</sup> for (+)-1-borneol and 533 Å<sup>2</sup> for (–)-1-borneol, while substrate SASA values are 69 Å<sup>2</sup> and 81 Å<sup>2</sup>. These data demonstrate that residues within the active-site tend to enclose the substrate, while the substrate becomes less exposed to the solvent. This trend is also evident in ancestor N6 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 42</xref>), where pocket SASA values are similar, with 573 Å<sup>2</sup> for (+)-1-borneol and 594 Å<sup>2</sup> for (–)-1-borneol, yet substrate exposure is lower for (–)-1-borneol with 54 Å<sup>2</sup> compared to 70 Å<sup>2</sup> for (+)-1-borneol. Selective N32 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 43</xref>) shows even lower values for this substrate at 423 Å<sup>2</sup> compared to 600 Å<sup>2</sup> for (–)-1-borneol, with respective substrate exposures of 70 Å<sup>2</sup> and 84 Å<sup>2</sup>. Unselective N32_I111L (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 44</xref>) shows a reduced SASA pocket value by 171 Å<sup>2</sup> compared between (+)-1-borneol and (–)-1-borneol. The unselective variant N30_L111I cannot be clearly determined from these data since both pocket SASAs are similar, and the substrate SASA is lower for (–)-1-borneol (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 45</xref>). Lastly, variant N30_L111I/V136L/G169A/V183I demonstrates higher selectivity for (+)-1-borneol, as evidenced by its significantly lower pocket SASA (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 46</xref>).</p><p id="P31">Finally, MM-ISMSA<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R54">54</xref></sup> was employed to perform per-residue energy decomposition, offering a qualitative view of key residues contributing to 1-borneol binding and enantioselectivity (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 47-51</xref>). In <italic>Sr</italic>BDH1, residues are primarily hydrophobic and aromatic: Val97, Ala147, Ile154, Phe190, Leu193, Tyr194, Phe207, Met211 and Phe260 from the counterpart chain from the 3 replicas, with position Ile154 being the most energetic one and Cys148 forming a hydrogen bond (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 52</xref>). We observed that Leu 193 and Phe207 are notably influential for (+)-1-borneol, while Phe260 is particularly significant for (–)-1-borneol. N6 residues highlighted are catalytic Tyr166, Leu161 and Ala155 for both enantiomers (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 47</xref>). For N32, Ile154 was observed for (+)-1-borneol only (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 48</xref>). For N32_I111L, positions Leu91 and Pro94 are highlighted for both enantiomers (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 49</xref>). For N30_L111I, Met191 is among the positions highlighted and close to both enantiomers and might affect selectivity (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 50</xref>). For the N30_L111I/V136L/G169A/V183I variant, position Leu149 exhibits the highest binding energy for both enantiomers, which is corroborated by the KDE plot analysis (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 51</xref>). While these computational results help locate interactions with the hydrophobic pocket, these findings should be interpreted cautiously.</p><p id="P32">BDHs represent a rare case where related enzymes with high and low stereoselectivity against a natural substrate exist. The fact that plants of the genus <italic>Salvia</italic> contain (–)-1-borneol in their essential oils, and that several dehydrogenases isolated from them have outstanding stereoselectivity towards (+)-1-borneol, is a very strong indication that their stereoselectivity serves the purpose to oxidize (+)-1-borneol while leaving (–)-1-borneol largely unreacted. The availability of selective and unselective extant enzymes allowed us to study natural mutations leading to stereoselectivity in their natural context. The comparison of the structures of the last unselective and first selective ancestors indicated a point mutation in the hydrophobic pocket of the enzyme as an evolutionary switch towards stereoselectivity. Interestingly, the key amino acid substitution leading to full stereospecificity occurred at a position adjacent to the highly conserved NNAG motif, which is involved in a water relay mechanism stabilising the positive charge on the catalytic Lys during catalysis. Having an Ile in this position disfavours conversion of (–)-1-borneol, which was shown by the decrease of its conversion in ancestor N30, and the activating effect of Leu on N32. Active-site positions are underrepresented in random mutagenesis. Therefore, it was striking to find that the evolutionary switch of the stereoselectivity of BDHs towards 1-borneol is situated in the active-site and very close to the catalytic amino acids and the cofactor. While this switch increased the selectivity significantly, three peripheral substitutions, within a distance of 9.8 to 11.0 Å to the catalytic Tyr residue, created a variant specific for the (–)-enantiomer. The extant <italic>Sr</italic>BDH1 contains the same amino acids Ala169, Leu136 and Ile183 in these peripheral positions.</p><p id="P33">Funnel-restricted molecular dynamic simulations allowed us to explore the conformational dynamics that underpin borneol enantioselectivity in <italic>Sr</italic>BDH1, its ancestors and variants thereof. We took advantage of MD simulations to address the inherent challenges in the co-crystallisation of the substrate within <italic>Sr</italic>BDH1. Although conventional MD simulations face limitations, primarily due to insufficient timescales and potential inaccuracies in force fields, our funnel-restricted approach allowed us to capture the process of substrate binding. We observed that the selectivity towards (+)-1-borneol is influenced by specific interactions at critical residues like positions Val97, Pro100, Ala155, Leu193, Phe207 and Phe260 playing pivotal roles in modulating enzyme affinity and specificity. Analysis of two catalytic distances allowed us to describe the active or ground state conformations. Simulations indicate that substrate selectivity is connected to lower SASA values, and that the substitution of Leu for Ile strongly influences the SASA. This outlines a possible mechanism by which modulation of the hydrophobic pocket achieves the selectivity change.</p><p id="P34">All of these identified substitutions leading to higher selectivity would be very challenging to predict with our current knowledge on enzyme mechanisms determined by hydrophobic pockets and the available methods for the simulation of interactions in these catalytic motifs. Narayan <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">30</xref></sup> showed that simply transplanting point mutations between extant enzymes removes amino acids from their natural context, which might interfere with their role in selectivity. While it is not certain that the mutations identified by us represent the true historic trajectory leading to the high stereoselectivity of the <italic>Sr</italic>BDHs, all point mutations leading from the common, unselective ancestor N6 of <italic>Sr</italic>BDH1 and to <italic>Aa</italic>BDH2, are amino acid substitutions that occurred in this enzyme family. The amino acid substitutions reported here thus represent a plausible evolutionary pathway to stereoselectivity. In conclusion, our findings highlight how epistatic interactions involving peripheral residues explain the evolutionary development of stereoselectivity, providing valuable insights into the complex interplay between enzyme structure and substrate binding. We believe that this example of the natural emergence of this important catalytic feature will guide future protein engineering endeavors to improve enzyme selectivity.</p></sec></sec><sec id="S9" sec-type="materials | methods"><title>Materials and Methods</title><p id="P35">All chemicals were purchased from Sigma Aldrich (Vienna, Austria) or Roth (Karlsruhe, Germany) and used without further purification unless otherwise stated.</p><sec id="S10"><title>Plasmids and point mutations</title><p id="P36">Codon-optimized synthetic gene fragments were either cloned into pET15b or pET28a(+)or purchased in pET28a(+) from GenScript (US) or Twist Bioscience (US) with sequences containing an N-terminal polyhistidine tag. Primers for quick-change mutagenesis were generated by the NEBaseChanger tool (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://nebasechanger.neb.com/">https://nebasechanger.neb.com/</ext-link>). Primer synthesis was facilitated by IDT (US). The reactions were performed according to the Q5® site-directed mutagenesis Kit from NEB (US), whereas chemo-competent <italic>E. coli</italic> TOP10 were used for transformation. Annealing temperatures were adjusted according to the respective primers. The PCR products were treated with 1 μl of DpnI (NEB, US), at 37°C for 1 h followed by inactivation at 80°C for 20 min. After transformation cells were picked for plasmid extraction using the Wizard® <italic>Plus</italic> SV Minipreps DNA Purification System (Promega, US). Plasmid sequences were confirmed by Sanger sequencing (Microsynth, CH) and analyzed by the web tool Benchling (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://benchling.com/">https://benchling.com/</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec id="S11"><title>Alignment, Phylogenetic tree, ASR</title><p id="P37">Eleven independent BLAST searches were carried out against the 1KP database<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36">36</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37">37</xref></sup>, with BDH from <italic>Lavandula intermedia</italic> (AFV30207.1, <italic>Li</italic>BDH), alcohol dehydrogenase 2 from <italic>Artemisia annua</italic> (ADK56099.1 <italic>Aa</italic>ADH2), borneol dehydrogenase from <italic>Artemisia annua</italic> (ANJ65952.1, <italic>Aa</italic>BDH), borneol dehydrogenase from <italic>Pseudomonas sp.</italic> TCU-HL1 (WP_032492645.1, <italic>Ps</italic>BDH), borneol-type dehydrogenases 1 and 2 from <italic>Salvia officinalis</italic> (MT525100, <italic>So</italic>BDH1 and MT525099, <italic>So</italic>BDH2), borneol-type dehydrogenases 1 and 2 from <italic>Salvia rosmarinus</italic> (MT857224, <italic>Sr</italic>BDH1 and <italic>Sr</italic>BDH2) and borneol-type dehydrogenases 1 and 2 from <italic>Tanacetum parthenium</italic> (<italic>Tp</italic>BDH1 and <italic>Tp</italic>BDH2) as queries. Hits with an E-value lower than 10<sup>-5</sup> were selected, and sequence duplicates were deleted and then aligned using ClustalW<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36">36</xref></sup>. In pairs of sequences displaying a p-distance below 0.25, one sequence was randomly deleted. The remaining sequences were then realigned using ProbCons<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R55">55</xref></sup> and curated using Gblocks<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36">36</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37">37</xref></sup>. The phylogenetic tree was constructed using PhyML<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R56">56</xref></sup>, and the ancestral sequence reconstruction based on the evolutionary model Jones-Taylor-Thornton (<italic>JTT</italic>) was carried out by GRASP<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R57">57</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="S12"><title>Growth conditions, protein expression &amp; purification</title><p id="P38">Initially, <italic>E. coli</italic> Top10 cells were transformed with all BDH gene variants to propagate the plasmid prior to transformation of <italic>E. coli</italic> BL21 (DE3) for over-expression of the BDH enzyme variants.</p><p id="P39"><italic>E. coli</italic> strains were cultivated in Lennox lysogeny broth (LB-Lennox; 10 g/L tryptone, 5 g/L yeast extract, and 5 g/L NaCl) medium supplemented with a final concentration of 40 mg/ml kanamycin or 100 mg/ml ampicillin. LB-agar plates were prepared similarly with the addition of 15 g/L agar-agar. Precultures were prepared in 50 ml reaction tubes by the addition of material of the corresponding glycerol stock to 25 ml LB supplemented with respective antibiotics. Precultures were cultivated at 37°C, 130 rpm, overnight. Main cultures of 250 ml LB were grown in 1 L baffled flasks with the addition of 40 mg/ml kanamycin or 100 mg/ml ampicillin and inoculated to an OD<sub>600</sub> of 0.1. Main cultures were then grown at 37°C, 130 rpm until an OD<sub>600</sub> of 0.8-1.0 and induced by the addition of 1 M (1000x stock) isopropyl-β-D-thiogalactopyranosid.</p><p id="P40">Cells were harvested by centrifugation (Beckman Coulter, USA, Avanti JXN-26, JA-10 rotor) at 4,000 rpm at 4°C for 15 min. For purification, the harvested cells were resuspended in 20 mL of cell lysis buffer (100 mM KPi, 500 mM NaCl, 10% (v/v) glycerol, pH 8). The suspension was sonicated for 6 min (output control 7, duty cycle 60%) and then centrifuged at 13,200 rpm for 15 min at 4°C (Eppendorf Centrifuge 5415 R). The supernatants were recovered and filtered with 0.45 μm and 0.22 μm filters consecutively. Protein purification was carried out by His-tag affinity chromatography on 2 ml Ni-Sepharose 6 Fast Flow gravity columns (Cytiva, Sweden). Columns stored on 20% EtOH, were washed with 3 column volumes (CV) of dH<sub>2</sub>O. The column was then equilibrated by the addition of 2 × CV binding buffer (100 mM KPi, 500 mM NaCl, 10% (v/v) glycerol, 30 mM imidazole, pH 8) while shaking on ice for 15 min. Following the release of the binding buffer, the filtered cell-free extract was applied onto the column and incubated on ice under slight orbital shaking for 15 min. The flow-through was collected and unspecifically bound protein was eluted by the addition of 5 × CV binding buffer. The target protein was then eluted by the addition of 3 × CV elution buffer (100 mM KPi, 500 mM NaCl, 10% (v/v) glycerol, 500 mM imidazole, pH 8). The purified enzymes were then rebuffered by dialysis (Spectra/Por® 1, MWCO 6-8 kD, Carl Roth, Germany) with storage buffer (100 mM KPi, 500 mM NaCl, 10% glycerol, pH 8) for 4 h at 4°C under gentle orbital shaking. Afterwards, the enzymes were aliquoted and stored with a final concentration of 10% (v/v) glycerol at -20°C until further use.</p><p id="P41">Protein concentrations were determined spectrophotometrically at 562 nm in a 96-well format, following the Pierce™ BCA Protein Assay Kit protocol (Thermo Fisher Scientific, US). Measurements were performed in triplicates.</p><p id="P42">SDS-PAGE was conducted to analyze the purified fractions. The samples were mixed with NuPage Sample Reducing Agent (10x), NuPage LDS Sample Buffer (4x) (Thermo Fischer Scientific, US) and dH<sub>2</sub>O to a final concentration of 1 mg/ml.</p><p id="P43">To denature the protein, samples were heated at 90°C for 10 min. Precast SDS gels (NuPAGE 4-12% Bis-Tris Gel, Thermo Fisher Scientific, US) were inserted into the XCell SureLock Mini-Cell (Thermo Fisher Scientific, US), filled with 1x NuPAGE MES SDS running buffer, prepared from a 20× stock solution (Thermo Fisher Scientific, US). Five μl of the protein standard (PageRuler Prestained, Thermo Fisher Scientific, US) and 10 μl of the samples were loaded onto the gel. The gel was developed under a current of 200 V and 110 mA for 35 min with an electric current generator (PowerEase®500, Invitrogen, US). Afterwards, the gels were stained by submerging them in (de-) staining solution (4.9% (v/v) phosphoric acid, 6.5% (v/v) EtOH, 0.011% (w/v) Coomassie Blue G-250 and 1% (w/v) β-cyclodextrin) for 40 min at room temperature under slow shaking on a tabletop horizontal shaker. Further destaining was facilitated by washing with water at room temperature and continued shaking for 1 h.</p></sec><sec id="S13"><title>Determination of specific activity and inhibition</title><p id="P44">Determination of the oxidation rates of extant enzymes, ancestors and ancestor variants towards (+)-1-borneol, (–)-1-borneol or <italic>r</italic>-1-isoborneol was performed with purified enzymes. Reactions containing 0.2, 0.3 or 9 mM of the respective alcohol (dissolved in DMSO), 1 or 9 mM NAD<sup>+</sup>, 20% total DMSO in 0.1 M Tris-HCl (pH 9) were started by the addition of 2 μM purified enzyme (final concentration). The reactions were carried out at 25°C, 300 rpm. Over time, multiple samples were taken and stopped by 1:1 addition of 1 M NaOH. Substrate and product were extracted via a two-step extraction process with 1:2 MTBE, the organic layers were collected and dried over Na<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub> and product formation was quantified via gas chromatography. Experiments were carried out in triplicates.</p></sec><sec id="S14"><title>Determination of kinetic parameters</title><p id="P45">Kinetic parameters of N32, N30 and N6 were obtained by measuring initial velocities in the presence of varying concentrations of (+)-1-borneol (0.02 or 0.05–9 mM) at constant 9 mM of NAD<sup>+</sup> under the conditions given above. Kinetic parameters were obtained by fitting the obtained data to the Michaelis-Menten equation with SigmaPlot 14.0 (Systat Software). Experiments were carried out in quintuplicates.</p></sec><sec id="S15"><title>Determination of E-value</title><p id="P46">Determination of the selectivity expressed through the enantiomeric ratio (E-value) was carried out by following the principle of the Quick-E method developed by Kazlauskas <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41">41</xref></sup> with slight modifications. In the Quick-E method, initial rates of the enantiopure substrate are measured in competition with a reference compound via a kinetic spectroscopic measurement. In this adaptation of the assay, the competitive oxidation of a surrogate substrate mixed with the enantiopure alcohol occurs, and the reaction is analyzed by GC analysis. Determination of the reaction rates under competitive conditions is carried out under the same conditions as mentioned above, with the addition of equimolar amounts of either cyclohexanol or n-octanol.</p></sec><sec id="S16"><title>Quantitative GC analysis</title><p id="P47">Achiral GC analysis of 1-borneol and camphor was carried out on a Shimadzu GC-2030 GC-FID system equipped with a ZB-5 column (30 m length, 0.32 mm inner diameter, 0.25 μM film thickness, Shimadzu, JP). Samples were injected in split mode (9.1) with an injection temperature of 250°C and FID temperature of 320°C. The instrument was programmed to an initial oven temperature of 50°C. After 5 min of holding time, a linear increase of 40°C/min up to 300°C was set, followed by 5 min holding. N<sub>2</sub> was set to a constant flow of 30 ml/min. Achiral analysis of reactions containing an additional surrogate substrate was carried out with the same method, on a Shimadzu GC-2010 Plus GCMS-QP2010 SE system equipped with a ZB5-ms column (30 m length, 0.25 mm inner diameter, 0.25 μM film thickness, Shimadzu, JP) with helium as carrier gas. Carrier gas flow was set to a constant flow of 15 ml/min, while the ion source temperature was set to 250°C and the interface temperature to 320°C. Chiral analysis of r-1-isoborneol was carried out on a Shimadzu GC-2030 GC-FID system equipped with a Hydrodex βTBDM column (25 m length, 0.25 mm inner diameter, Macherey-Nagel, Germany). Samples were injected in split mode (100:1 or 50:1) at an injection temperature of 250°C and FID temperature of 320°C. The instrument was programmed to an initial oven temperature of 90°C. After 5 min of holding time, a linear increase of 2°C/min up to 150°C was set, followed by a linear increase of 45°C/min up to 200°C and (2 min holding). N<sub>2</sub> was set to a constant flow of 24 ml/min.</p></sec><sec id="S17"><title>Protein expression and purification for crystallization</title><p id="P48">Purification of N32 and N39 was conducted as mentioned before.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref></sup> <italic>E. coli</italic> BL21-RIL cells were transformed with a pET28a(+) vector containing either N32 or N39 fused to an N-terminal hexa-histidine-tag. Protein production was carried out in auto-induction media at 37°C for 4 h and subsequently cooled down to 16°C.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R58">58</xref></sup> Cells were grown overnight and harvested by centrifugation (10 min, 6,000 rpm at 4°C). The pellets were resuspended in buffer A (20 mM Tris/HCl pH 8.0, 500 mM NaCl). Cells were lysed by sonification at 4°C for 15 min after the addition of 0.5 mg/l DNase and the lysate was cleared by centrifugation (30 min, 21,500 rpm at 4°C). A Ni<sup>2+</sup>NTA column (1 CV = 1 ml, Macherey-Nagel) was equilibrated with buffer A and the lysed suspension of N32 or N39 was loaded on the column and washed with 15 CV of buffer A. The proteins of interest were eluted with buffer A supplemented with 300 mM imidazole. An additional size-exclusion chromatography (SEC) step was performed with a HighLoad Superdex S200 16/60 column (GE Healthcare), equilibrated with 20 mM Tris/HCl pH 8.0, 125 mM NaCl. Pooled protein fractions were concentrated with Amicon-Ultra-15 (Merck KGaA) to 29 mg/ml for N32 or 28 mg/ml for N39 as measured by the absorbance at 280 nm.</p></sec><sec id="S18"><title>Crystallization</title><p id="P49">Crystallization was conducted as mentioned before.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref></sup> Crystals of N32 were obtained by the sitting-drop vapor-diffusion method at 18°C with a reservoir solution composed of 0.1 M HEPES/NaOH pH 7.6, 0.2 M proline, 12% (w/v) PEG 3,350. Crystals were cryo-protected with 30 % (v/v) glycerol supplemented to the reservoir resolution and subsequently flash-cooled in liquid nitrogen. Crystals of N39 were obtained with a reservoir solution composed of 0.1 M HEPES/NaOH pH 7.4, 11% (w/v) PEG 3,000. Initially, inter-grown crystals were used to prepare a seed stock. With a cat whisker, seeds were transferred to a freshly prepared crystallization drop with the mentioned buffer composition and crystals were subsequently grown at 18°C. Prior to flash-freezing in liquid nitrogen, the fished crystals were transferred to a cryo-protectant solution composed of the reservoir solution supplemented with 25% (v/v) PEG 400.</p></sec><sec id="S19"><title>X-ray data collection, structure determination and refinement</title><p id="P50">Synchrotron diffraction data were collected at the beamline 14.2 of the MX Joint Berlin laboratory at BESSY (Berlin, Germany) and beamline P11 of PETRA III (Deutsches Elektronen Synchrotron, Hamburg, Germany) at 100 K. Diffraction data were processed with XDS (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Table S3</xref>).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R59">59</xref></sup> The structures were solved by molecular replacement using PHASER<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R60">60</xref></sup> with a search model comprising a single protomer of <italic>Sr</italic>BDH1 (PDB: 6ZZ0). The structure was refined by maximum-likelihood restrained refinement in PHENIX.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R61">61</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R62">62</xref></sup> Model building was performed with COOT.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R63">63</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R64">64</xref></sup> Model quality was evaluated with MolProbity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R65">65</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R66">66</xref></sup> and the JCSG validation server (JCSG Quality Control Check v3.1). Secondary structure elements were assigned with DSSP.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R67">67</xref></sup> Structure-based alignments were visualized by Alscript.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R68">68</xref></sup> Figures were prepared using PyMOL (Schrödinger Inc).</p></sec><sec id="S20"><title>SrBDHl models</title><p id="P51">Unliganded 3D models of the extant N32_I111L, N30, N30_L111I, N30_L111I/V136L/G169A/V183I, and ancestral N6 and N32 variants were built with the SWISS-MODEL webserver<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R69">69</xref></sup>, using as templates PDB: 6ZYZ<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref></sup> (chain A) for the open and closed conformations, respectively. In all systems, hydrogens were added, and the protonation states of titratable residues were adjusted to pH 7.0, using the H++ webserver<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R70">70</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R71">71</xref></sup>, while ensuring the catalytic Tyr remained deprotonated. Hydrogens for the oxidized state of the cofactor NAD<sup>+</sup> were added using the Open Babel<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R72">72</xref></sup> software. The complete tetramer was assembled by superimposing chain A with chains C, D, and D of the template structure, using PyMOL.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R73">73</xref></sup></p></sec><sec id="S21"><title>Docking calculations</title><p id="P52">Docking calculations were conducted using AutoDock VINA.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R74">74</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R75">75</xref></sup> PDBQT files for both 1-borneol enantiomers, as well as the receptor, were prepared using Open Babel<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R72">72</xref></sup> with Gasteiger charges assigned. The docking grid box was centered on the niacin moiety of NAD<sup>+</sup> at carbon position 4, with a 30x30x30 Å dimension. The top 20 poses were computed, and the optimal binding mode was determined by measuring the distance between 1-borneol oxygen and the catalytic phenolic oxygen of Tyr.</p></sec><sec id="S22"><title>Molecular Dynamic simulations</title><p id="P53">The initial structures were obtained from previous docking models, and 1-borneol poses were replicated across each chain. After that, protein residues were parameterized using the AMBER ff19SB<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R76">76</xref></sup> force field, while NAD<sup>+</sup>, 1-borneol substrates and the deprotonated Tyr were treated were calculated at the HF/6-31G(d) level of theory using restrained electrostatic potential (RESP)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R77">77</xref></sup> fitting with Antechamber (GAFF2<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R78">78</xref></sup>), based on gas-phase geometries optimized at the B3LYP/6-31G(d) level of theory using Gaussian 16.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R79">79</xref></sup> Once the systems were parametrized using the tleap module from AmberTools. We conducted an initial <italic>in vacuo</italic> minimization of our <italic>Sr</italic>BDH1 systems using molecular mechanics using sander module from Amber 24.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R80">80</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R81">81</xref></sup> This process allowed us to refine the system towards a conformation that closely approximates the reactive or ground state before 1-borneol is oxidized, aligning the structure to a represented reactive conformation.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R82">82</xref></sup> In the wild-type system (+)-1-borneol reduces its reactive distances, whereas for (–)-1-borneol, the distances are increased (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>). We performed the same approach for our selected ancestors and variants providing us with similar results. After that, all systems were embedded in a truncated octahedron water box, setting the stage for conventional molecular dynamics simulations.</p><p id="P54">MD simulations were conducted afterwards. Initially, all systems were energetically minimized to eliminate steric clashes. Each system was then centered in a cubic box containing between 21,000 and 23,000 TIP3P water molecules, depending on the system. Subsequent minimization occurred in three phases—first targeting all protons, followed by the solvent, and finally the entire system. The systems were gradually heated from 100K to 300K over 50 ps under an NVT ensemble using a Langevin thermostat with a gamma friction coefficient of 1.0 ps<sup>-1</sup>. During heating, harmonic constraints of 40 kcal/mol·Å<sup>-2</sup> were applied to all solute atoms. These constraints were systematically reduced to 10 kcal/mol·Å<sup>-2</sup> over four simulation stages at 300 K under NVT conditions. Transitioning to an NPT ensemble, we employed the Berendsen barostat at 300 K and completely removed the harmonic constraints. Each system underwent further simulation for a total of 1.5 μs across three independent 500 MD simulations. A cut-off of 10.0 Å was used for calculating van der Waals interactions, and long-range electrostatics were managed via the Particle-Mesh Ewald (PME) method. The SHAKE algorithm was employed to restrain the hydrogen atoms in water molecules. Analysis of the MD trajectories, including monitoring RMSD and distances <italic>d<sub>1</sub></italic> and d<sub>2</sub>, was conducted using the CPPTRAJ module from Amber Tools.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R81">81</xref></sup></p></sec><sec id="S23"><title>Funnel-MD simulations</title><p id="P55">Funnel-MD simulations were conducted starting from the equilibrated systems, as detailed in previous sections, without the addition of any biasing hills<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R84">84</xref></sup> and only one funnel at chain A with the upper-limit walls were applied. Funnel coordinates were generated following the tutorial by Dominykas Lukauskis on funnel maker (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/dlukauskis/funnel_maker/tree">https://github.com/dlukauskis/funnel_maker/tree</ext-link>).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R85">85</xref></sup> These simulations were performed during 3 replicas x 240ns each, and the analysis was conducted again with CPPTRAJ<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R83">83</xref></sup> module from Amber Tools.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R81">81</xref></sup> MM-ISMSA<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R54">54</xref></sup> analysis was performed on the output trajectory using a total of 1000 snapshots from the total 240 ns for each replica.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="SM"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1"><label>Supplementary information 1</label><media xlink:href="EMS207377-supplement-Supplementary_information_1.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" id="d14aAcDbB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD2"><label>Supplementary information 2</label><media xlink:href="EMS207377-supplement-Supplementary_information_2.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" id="d14aAcDcB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack id="S24"><title>Acknowledgment</title><p>This research was funded in part by the Austrian Science Fund (FWF) (Grant-dois: 10.55776/P34280, 10.55776/COE17). This project has received funding from the European Union’s Horizon Europe research and innovation programme under the Marie Sklodowska-Curie grant agreement No 101072686. We accessed beamlines of the BESSY II (Berliner Elektronenspeicherring-Gesellschaft für Synchrotronstrahlung II) storage ring (Berlin, Germany) via the Joint Berlin MX-Laboratory sponsored by the Helmholtz Zentrum Berlin für Materialien und Energie, the Freie Universität Berlin, the Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin, the Max-Delbrück Centrum and the Leibniz-Institut für Molekulare Pharmakologie. Parts of this research were carried out at PETRA III at DESY, a member of the Helmholtz Association (HGF). S. C. L. K. acknowledges support from Georgia Tech, the Vasser Wooley Foundation and the Georgia Research Alliance. We acknowledge National Academic Infrastructure for Supercomputing in Sweden (NAISS) for awarding this project access to the LUMI supercomputer, owned by the EuroHPC Joint Undertaking, hosted by CSC (Finland) and the LUMI consortium through grant agreement no. NAISS 2023/8-3 and NAISS 2024/8-16. This work used the Hive cluster, which is supported by the National Science Foundation under grant number 1828187. This research was supported in part through research cyberinfrastructure resources and services provided by the Partnership for an Advanced Computing Environment (PACE) at the Georgia Institute of Technology, Atlanta, Georgia, USA. C.P.O.H. was supported by a scholarship from the Hanns Seidel Foundation with funds from Federal Ministry of Education and Research Germany (BMBF), as well as by the Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft (Grant RTG 2473-1). D.K. acknowledges the BioTechMed-Graz Young Researcher Group programme. R. T.J. was supported by EU grant. R.T.J. was supported by European Union’s Horizon Europe research and innovation programme under the Marie Sklodowska-Curie grant agreement No 101072686.</p></ack><fn-group><fn id="FN1"><p id="P56"><bold>Notes</bold></p><p id="P57">The atomic coordinates have been deposited in the Protein Data Bank with the accession code 8R0C (N32) and 8R0D (N39). Diffraction raw images have been deposited at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://proteindiffraction.org/">proteindiffraction.org</ext-link>: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.18430/M38R0C">10.18430/M38R0C</ext-link> (N32) and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.18430/M38R0D">10.18430/M38R0D</ext-link> (N39).</p></fn><fn id="FN2" fn-type="con"><p id="P58"><bold>Contributions</bold></p><p id="P59">J.Z., K.K. and A.M.C. performed the experiments. C.P.O.H. and R.T-J. conducted crystal structure determination. B.D.G. performed MD simulations. S.B. conducted ancestral sequence reconstruction (ASR). R.K. conceptualized the project and the main ideas. All authors discussed results, contributed to the manuscript writing and provided critical comments.</p></fn><fn id="FN3" fn-type="conflict"><p id="P60"><bold>Competing interests</bold></p><p id="P61">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><ref id="R1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Enantioselectivity of <italic>Candida Rugosa</italic> Lipase Toward Carboxylic Acids: A Predictive Rule from Substrate Mapping and X-Ray Crystallography</article-title><source>Biocatalysis</source><year>1994</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>209</fpage><lpage>225</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Buller</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>From nature to industry: harnessing enzymes for biocatalysis</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2023</year><volume>382</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37995253</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kazlauskas</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bornscheuer</surname><given-names>UT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Finding better protein engineering strategies</article-title><source>Nat Chem Biol</source><year>2009</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>526</fpage><lpage>529</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19620988</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>An integrated technology for quantitative wide mutational scanning of human antibody Fab libraries</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2024</year><volume>15</volume><elocation-id>3974</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-024-48072-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11087541</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38730230</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Croteau</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Felton</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Karp</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Kjonaas</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Relationship of Camphor Biosynthesis to Leaf Development in Sage <italic>(Salvia officinalis)</italic></article-title><source>Plant Physiology</source><year>1981</year><volume>67</volume><fpage>820</fpage><lpage>824</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.67.4.820</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC425779</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16661761</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Whittington</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Bornyl diphosphate synthase: Structure and strategy for carbocation manipulation by a terpenoid cyclase</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</source><year>2002</year><volume>99</volume><fpage>15375</fpage><lpage>15380</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.232591099</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC137724</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12432096</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Identification of (–)-bornyl diphosphate synthase from <italic>Blumea balsamifera</italic> and its application for (–)-borneol biosynthesis in Saccharomyces cerevisiae</article-title><source>Synthetic and Systems Biotechnology</source><year>2022</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>490</fpage><lpage>497</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.synbio.2021.12.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8671873</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34977393</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Polichuk</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Reed</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Covello</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A Glandular Trichome-Specific Monoterpene Alcohol Dehydrogenase from <italic>Artemisia Annua</italic></article-title><source>Phytochemistry</source><year>2010</year><volume>71</volume><fpage>1264</fpage><lpage>1269</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20621795</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sarker</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name><name><surname>Galata</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Demissie</surname><given-names>ZA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahmoud</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>lecular cloning and functional characterization of borneol dehydrogenase from the glandular trichomes of <italic>Lavandula x intermedia</italic></article-title><source>Archives of Biochemistry and Biophysics</source><year>2012</year><volume>528</volume><fpage>163</fpage><lpage>170</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23058847</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Molecular cloning and functional identification of a high-efficiency (+)-borneol dehydrogenase from <italic>Cinnamomum camphora</italic> (L.) Presl</article-title><source>Plant Physiology and Biochemistry</source><year>2021</year><volume>158</volume><fpage>363</fpage><lpage>371</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33243711</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Molecular cloning and functional identification of a novel borneol dehydrogenase from <italic>Artemisia annua</italic> L</article-title><source>Industrial Crops and Products</source><year>2015</year><volume>77</volume><fpage>190</fpage><lpage>195</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Heterologous expression and characterization of a borneol dehydrogenase from <italic>Arabidopsis lyrate</italic> and its application for the enzymatic resolution of rac-camphor</article-title><source>Molecular Catalysis</source><year>2022</year><volume>530</volume><elocation-id>112572</elocation-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genome-wide identification and functional characterization of borneol dehydrogenases in <italic>Wurfbainia villosa</italic></article-title><source>Planta</source><year>2023</year><volume>258</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>16</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37608037</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Satyal</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Chemotypic Characterization and Biological Activity of <italic>Rosmarinus officinalis</italic></article-title><source>Foods</source><year>2017</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>15</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/foods6030020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5368539</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28273883</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Croteau</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee Hooper</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Felton</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biosynthesis of monoterpenes. Partial purification and characterization of a bicyclic monoterpenol dehydrogenase from sage <italic>(Salvia officinalis)</italic></article-title><source>Archives of Biochemistry and Biophysics</source><year>1978</year><volume>188</volume><fpage>182</fpage><lpage>193</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">677891</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Drienovská</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Molecular cloning and functional characterization of a two highly stereoselective borneol dehydrogenases from <italic>Salvia officinalis</italic> L</article-title><source>Phytochemistry</source><year>2020</year><volume>172</volume><elocation-id>112227</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31927319</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dimos</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>CryoEM analysis of small plant biocatalysts at sub-2 Å resolution</article-title><source>Acta Crystallographica Section D: Structural Biology</source><year>2022</year><volume>78</volume><fpage>113</fpage><lpage>123</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1107/S205979832101216X</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8725159</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34981767</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chánique</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A Structural View on the Stereospecificity of Plant Borneol Type Dehydrogenases</article-title><source>ChemCatChem</source><year>2021</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>2262</fpage><lpage>2277</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cctc.202100110</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8261865</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34262629</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Calderini</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Simple Plug In Synthetic Step for the Synthesis of (–) Camphor from Renewable Starting Materials</article-title><source>ChemBioChem</source><year>2021</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>2951</fpage><lpage>2956</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cbic.202100187</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8596451</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34033201</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kavanagh</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Jörnvall</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Persson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Oppermann</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Medium- and short-chain dehydrogenase/reductase gene and protein families: The SDR superfamily: functional and structural diversity within a family of metabolic and regulatory enzymes</article-title><source>Cell Mol Life Sci</source><year>2008</year><volume>65</volume><fpage>3895</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00018-008-8588-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2792337</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19011750</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Okrasa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Structure and Mechanism of an Unusual Malonate Decarboxylase and Related Racemases</article-title><source>Chemistry A European J</source><year>2008</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>6609</fpage><lpage>6613</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18576402</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Biler</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Crean</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Schweiger</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Kourist</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamerlin</surname><given-names>SCL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ground-State Destabilization by Active-Site Hydrophobicity Controls the Selectivity of a Cofactor-Free Decarboxylase</article-title><source>J Am Chem Soc</source><year>2020</year><volume>142</volume><fpage>20216</fpage><lpage>20231</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jacs.0c10701</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7735706</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33180505</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Burton</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomson</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Dawson</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name><name><surname>Brady</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Woolfson</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Installing hydrolytic activity into a completely de novo protein framework</article-title><source>Nature chemistry</source><year>2016</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>837</fpage><lpage>844</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27554410</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kalvet</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Design of Heme Enzymes with a Tunable Substrate Binding Pocket Adjacent to an Open Metal Coordination Site</article-title><source>J Am Chem Soc</source><year>2023</year><volume>145</volume><fpage>14307</fpage><lpage>14315</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jacs.3c02742</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10326885</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37341421</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sandström</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Engström</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Nyhlén</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kasrayan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bäckvall</surname><given-names>J-E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Directed evolution of <italic>Candida antarctica</italic> lipase A using an episomaly replicating yeast plasmid</article-title><source>Protein Engineering, Design &amp; Selection</source><year>2009</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>413</fpage><lpage>420</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19509064</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sandström</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Wikmark</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Engström</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Nyhlén</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bäckvall</surname><given-names>J-E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Combinatorial reshaping of the <italic>Candida antarctica</italic> lipase A substrate pocket for enantioselectivity using an extremely condensed library</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>2012</year><volume>109</volume><fpage>78</fpage><lpage>83</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1111537108</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3252943</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22178758</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bartsch</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kourist</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Bornscheuer</surname><given-names>UT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Complete Inversion of Enantioselectivity towards Acetylated Tertiary Alcohols by a Double Mutant of a <italic>Bacillus Subtilis</italic> Esterase</article-title><source>Angewandte Chemie (International Ed. in English)</source><year>2008</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>1508</fpage><lpage>1511</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18203225</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brundiek</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name><name><surname>Evitt</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kourist</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Bornscheuer</surname><given-names>UT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Creation of a lipase highly selective for trans fatty acids by protein engineering</article-title><source>Angewandte Chemie (International Ed. in English)</source><year>2011</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>412</fpage><lpage>414</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22113941</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jan Deniau</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Subileau</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dubreucq</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization and Reshaping of a Large and Hydrophobic Nucleophile Pocket in Lipases/Acyltransferases</article-title><source>ChemBioChem</source><year>2018</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>1839</fpage><lpage>1844</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29949676</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chiang</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Deciphering the evolution of flavin-dependent monooxygenase stereoselectivity using ancestral sequence reconstruction</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</source><year>2023</year><volume>120</volume><elocation-id>e2218248120</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.2218248120</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10104550</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37014851</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hochberg</surname><given-names>GKA</given-names></name><name><surname>Thornton</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reconstructing Ancient Proteins to Understand the Causes of Structure and Function</article-title><source>Annual Review of Biophysics</source><year>2017</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>247</fpage><lpage>269</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-biophys-070816-033631</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6141191</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28301769</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>XX</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Evolutionary insights into the stereoselectivity of imine reductases based on ancestral sequence reconstruction</article-title><source>Nature Communications</source><year>2024</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-024-54613-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11605051</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39609402</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eggerichs</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Vanillyl alcohol oxidase from <italic>Diplodia corticola:</italic> Residues Ala420 and Glu466 allow for efficient catalysis of syringyl derivatives</article-title><source>Journal of Biological Chemistry</source><year>2023</year><elocation-id>104898</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jbc.2023.104898</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10404669</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37295774</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schriever</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Engineering of Ancestors as a Tool to Elucidate Structure, Mechanism, and Specificity of Extant Terpene Cyclase</article-title><source>Journal of the American Chemical Society</source><year>2021</year><volume>143</volume><fpage>3794</fpage><lpage>3807</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jacs.0c10214</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8023661</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33496585</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vongsouthi</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Ancestral reconstruction of polyethylene terephthalate degrading cutinases reveals a rugged and unexplored sequence-fitness landscape</article-title><source>Sci Adv</source><year>2025</year><volume>11</volume><elocation-id>eads8318</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/sciadv.ads8318</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC12077509</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40367179</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leebens-Mack</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>One thousand plant transcriptomes and the phylogenomics of green plants</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2019</year><volume>574</volume><fpage>679</fpage><lpage>685</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41586-019-1693-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6872490</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31645766</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carpenter</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Access to RNA-sequencing data from 1,173 plant species: The 1000 Plant transcriptomes initiative (1KP)</article-title><source>GigaScience</source><year>2019</year><volume>8</volume><elocation-id>giz126</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/gigascience/giz126</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6808545</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31644802</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yalkowsky</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Samuel</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Jain</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><source>Handbook of aqueous solubility data</source><year>2010</year><fpage>1608</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Straathof</surname><given-names>AJJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Panke</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmid</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The production of fine chemicals by biotransformations</article-title><source>Current Opinion in Biotechnology</source><year>2002</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>548</fpage><lpage>556</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12482513</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title><italic>Quick E.</italic> A Fast Spectrophotometric Method To Measure the Enantioselectivity of Hydrolases</article-title><source>J A Recl Trav Chim Pays-Bas</source><year>1992</year><volume>104</volume><fpage>4560</fpage><lpage>4561</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R41"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Janes</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name><surname>Kazlauskas</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Quick</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A Fast Spectrophotometric Method to Measure the Enantioselectivity of Hydrolases</article-title><source>Journal of Organic Chemistry</source><year>1997</year><volume>62</volume><fpage>4560</fpage><lpage>4561</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R42"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Crystal Structures of the Binary and Ternary Complexes of 7 - Hydroxysteroid Dehydrogenase from <italic>Escherichia coli</italic></article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><year>1996</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>7715</fpage><lpage>7730</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8672472</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R43"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Filling</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Critical Residues for Structure and Catalysis in Short-chain Dehydrogenases/Reductases</article-title><source>Journal of Biological Chemistry</source><year>2002</year><volume>277</volume><fpage>25677</fpage><lpage>25684</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11976334</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R44"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oppermann</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Short-chain dehydrogenases/reductases (SDR): the 2002 update</article-title><source>Chemico-Biological Interactions</source><year>2003</year><volume>143-144</volume><fpage>247</fpage><lpage>253</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12604210</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R45"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><name><surname>Tetu</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name><surname>Harrop</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Paulsen</surname><given-names>IT</given-names></name><name><surname>Mabbutt</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structure of a short-chain dehydrogenase/reductase (SDR) within a genomic island from a clinical strain of Acinetobacter baumannii</article-title><source>Acta CrystF</source><year>2014</year><volume>70</volume><fpage>1318</fpage><lpage>1323</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1107/S2053230X14019785</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4188072</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25286932</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R46"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abramson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Accurate structure prediction of biomolecular interactions with AlphaFold 3</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2024</year><volume>630</volume><fpage>493</fpage><lpage>500</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41586-024-07487-w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11168924</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38718835</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R47"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lipsh-Sokolik</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Fleishman</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Addressing epistasis in the design of protein function</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</source><year>2024</year><volume>121</volume><elocation-id>e2314999121</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.2314999121</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11348311</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39133844</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R48"><label>48</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grantham</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Amino Acid Difference Formula to Help Explain Protein Evolution</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1974</year><volume>185</volume><fpage>862</fpage><lpage>864</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4843792</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R49"><label>49</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hopf</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The EVcouplings Python framework for coevolutionary sequence analysis</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2019</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>1582</fpage><lpage>1584</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/bty862</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6499242</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30304492</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R50"><label>50</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Korman</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name><name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Thanh</surname><given-names>NV</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structural analysis of actinorhodin polyketide ketoreductase: Cofactor binding and substrate specificity</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><year>2004</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>14529</fpage><lpage>14538</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/bi048133a</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2263080</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15544323</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R51"><label>51</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Crystal structure and molecular characterization of NADP+-farnesol dehydrogenase from cotton bollworm, <italic>Helicoverpa armigera</italic></article-title><source>Insect Biochemistry and Molecular Biology</source><year>2022</year><volume>147</volume><elocation-id>103812</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35820537</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R52"><label>52</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Geronimo</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Digging out the Molecular Connections between the Catalytic Mechanism of Human Lysosomal α-Mannosidase and Its Pathophysiology</article-title><source>J Chem Inf Model</source><year>2025</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.jcim.4c02229</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11898060</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39976451</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R53"><label>53</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Substrate Positioning Dynamics Involves a Non-Electrostatic Component to Mediate Catalysis</article-title><source>JPhys Chem Lett</source><year>2023</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>11480</fpage><lpage>11489</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.jpclett.3c02444</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11211065</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38085952</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R54"><label>54</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Klett</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>MM-ISMSA: An Ultrafast and Accurate Scoring Function for Protein-Protein Docking</article-title><source>J Chem Theory Comput</source><year>2012</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>3395</fpage><lpage>3408</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26605745</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R55"><label>55</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Do</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahabhashyam</surname><given-names>MSP</given-names></name><name><surname>Brudno</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Batzoglou</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>ProbCons: Probabilistic consistency-based multiple sequence alignment</article-title><source>Genome Res</source><year>2005</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>330</fpage><lpage>340</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gr.2821705</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC546535</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15687296</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R56"><label>56</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guindon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gascuel</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A Simple, Fast, and Accurate Algorithm to Estimate Large Phylogenies by Maximum Likelihood</article-title><source>Systematic Biology</source><year>2003</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>696</fpage><lpage>704</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14530136</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R57"><label>57</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Foley</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Engineering indel and substitution variants of diverse and ancient enzymes using Graphical Representation of Ancestral Sequence Predictions (GRASP)</article-title><year>2022</year><elocation-id>2019.12.30.891457</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1010633</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9632902</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36279274</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R58"><label>58</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Studier</surname><given-names>FW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Protein production by auto-induction in high-density shaking cultures</article-title><source>Protein Expression and Purification</source><year>2005</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>207</fpage><lpage>234</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1458504</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15915565</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R59"><label>59</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kabsch</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>XDS</article-title><source>Acta CrystallogrDBiol Crystallogr</source><year>2010</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>125</fpage><lpage>132</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1107/S0907444909047337</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2815665</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20124692</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R60"><label>60</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McCoy</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Phaser crystallographic software</article-title><source>JAppl Crystallogr</source><year>2007</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>658</fpage><lpage>674</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1107/S0021889807021206</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2483472</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19461840</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R61"><label>61</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liebschner</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Macromolecular structure determination using X-rays, neutrons and electrons: recent developments in Phenix</article-title><source>Acta Crystallogr D Struct Biol</source><year>2019</year><volume>75</volume><fpage>861</fpage><lpage>877</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1107/S2059798319011471</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6778852</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31588918</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R62"><label>62</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>PHENIX: a comprehensive Python-based system for macromolecular structure solution</article-title><source>Acta Crystallogr DBiol Crystallogr</source><year>2010</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>213</fpage><lpage>221</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1107/S0907444909052925</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2815670</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20124702</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R63"><label>63</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Emsley</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Lohkamp</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>WG</given-names></name><name><surname>Cowtan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Features and development of Coot</article-title><source>Acta CrystallogrDBiol Crystallogr</source><year>2010</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>486</fpage><lpage>501</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1107/S0907444910007493</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2852313</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20383002</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R64"><label>64</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Casañal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lohkamp</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Emsley</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Current developments in Coot for macromolecular model building of Electron Cryo-microscopy and Crystallographic Data</article-title><source>Protein Sci</source><year>2020</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>1069</fpage><lpage>1078</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/pro.3791</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7096722</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31730249</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R65"><label>65</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>MolProbity: More and better reference data for improved all atom structure validation</article-title><source>Protein Sci</source><year>2018</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>293</fpage><lpage>315</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/pro.3330</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5734394</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29067766</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R66"><label>66</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vb</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>MolProbity: all-atom structure validation for macromolecular crystallography</article-title><source>Acta crystallographica Section D, Biological crystallography</source><year>2010</year><volume>66</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1107/S0907444909042073</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2803126</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20057044</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R67"><label>67</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kabsch</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Sander</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dictionary of protein secondary structure: pattern recognition of hydrogen-bonded and geometrical features</article-title><source>Biopolymers</source><year>1983</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>2577</fpage><lpage>2637</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6667333</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R68"><label>68</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barton</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>ALSCRIPT: a tool to format multiple sequence alignments</article-title><source>Protein Eng</source><year>1993</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>37</fpage><lpage>40</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8433969</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R69"><label>69</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Waterhouse</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>SWISS-MODEL: Homology Modelling of Protein Structures and Complexes</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2018</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>296</fpage><lpage>303</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gky427</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6030848</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29788355</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R70"><label>70</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>H++: A Server for Estimating PKas and Adding Missing Hydrogens to Macromolecules</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2005</year><volume>33</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gki464</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1160225</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15980491</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R71"><label>71</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anandakrishnan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Aguilar</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Onufriev</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>H++ 3.0: Automating PK Prediction and the Preparation of Biomolecular Structures for Atomistic Molecular Modeling and Simulations</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2012</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>537</fpage><lpage>541</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gks375</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3394296</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22570416</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R72"><label>72</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>O’Boyle</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Open Babel: An Open Chemical Toolbox</article-title><source>J Cheminform</source><year>2011</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>33</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1758-2946-3-33</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3198950</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21982300</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R73"><label>73</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>DeLano</surname><given-names>LW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pymol: An Open-Source Molecular Graphics Tool</article-title><source>Newsletter On Protein Crystallography</source><year>2002</year><volume>40</volume></element-citation></ref><ref id="R74"><label>74</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eberhardt</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Santos-Martins</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Tillack</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><name><surname>Forli</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>AutoDock Vina 1.2.0: New Docking Methods, Expanded Force Field, and Python Bindings</article-title><source>J Chem Inf Model</source><year>2021</year><volume>61</volume><fpage>3891</fpage><lpage>3898</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.jcim.1c00203</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10683950</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34278794</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R75"><label>75</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Trott</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>AJAV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Improving the Speed and Accuracy of Docking with a New Scoring Function, Efficient Optimization, and Multithreading</article-title><source>J Comput Chem</source><year>2009</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jcc.21334</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3041641</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19499576</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R76"><label>76</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Ff19SB: Amino-Acid-Specific Protein Backbone Parameters Trained against Quantum Mechanics Energy Surfaces in Solution</article-title><source>J Chem Theory Comput</source><year>2020</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>528</fpage><lpage>552</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31714766</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R77"><label>77</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Woods</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Chappelle</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Restrained Electrostatic Potential Atomic Partial Charges for Condensed-Phase Simulations of Carbohydrates</article-title><source>Journal of Molecular Structure: THEOCHEM</source><year>2000</year><volume>527</volume><fpage>149</fpage><lpage>156</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0166-1280(00)00487-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4191892</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25309012</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R78"><label>78</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Man</surname><given-names>VH</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>T-S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A fast and high-quality charge model for the next generation general AMBER force field</article-title><source>The Journal of Chemical Physics</source><year>2020</year><volume>153</volume><fpage>153</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1063/5.0019056</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7728379</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32962378</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R79"><label>79</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Frisch</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>J V, and D J Gaussian</source><year>2009</year><volume>16</volume></element-citation></ref><ref id="R80"><label>80</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cheatham</surname><given-names>CTE</given-names></name><name><surname>Amber</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group><source>San Francisco</source><year>2024</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R81"><label>81</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Case</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>K. M. AmberTools J Chem Inf Model</source><year>2023</year><volume>63</volume><fpage>6183</fpage><lpage>6191</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.jcim.3c01153</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10598796</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37805934</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R82"><label>82</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Summa</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Levitt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Near-Native Structure Refinement Using in Vacuo Energy Minimization</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2007</year><volume>104</volume><fpage>3177</fpage><lpage>3182</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0611593104</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1802011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17360625</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R83"><label>83</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roe</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheatham</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>PTRAJ and CPPTRAJ: Software for Processing and Analysis of Molecular Dynamics Trajectory Data</article-title><source>J Chem Theory Comput</source><year>2013</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>3084</fpage><lpage>3095</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26583988</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R84"><label>84</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Limongelli</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonomi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Parrinello</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Funnel Metadynamics as Accurate Binding Free-Energy Method</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences 2013</source><volume>110</volume><fpage>6358</fpage><lpage>6363</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1303186110</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3631651</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23553839</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R85"><label>85</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hedges</surname><given-names>LO</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A Suite of Tutorials for the BioSimSpace Framework for Interoperable Biomolecular Simulation</article-title><source>Living J Comput Mol Sci</source><year>2023</year><volume>5</volume></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><title>Overview of the evolutionary trajectories.</title><p>(A) Enantioselective oxidation of 1-borneol by BDHs. (B). Simplification of the evolutionary trajectories leading to the enantioselective <italic>Sr</italic>BDH1. (C) The natural trajectory between N30 and N32. (D) 4 out of 19 mutations between N30 and N32 suffice to make N30 highly selective (E&gt;200). The amino acids in the active-site (yellow) and second shell (red) lead to enantioselectivity. (E) Mutation of the active-site residue (yellow) in the selective ancestor N32 leading to a loss in selectivity.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS207377-f001"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>(A) Phylogenetic tree of BDHs from plants. The circles on the tree leaves represent the extant enzymes. Extant BDHs with low enantioselectivity (E &lt; 10) are highlighted in orange, and selective BDHs (E&gt;200) in blue. Circles at nodes represent ancestral proteins. Dark-blue circles represent investigated ancestral proteins. (B) Inset illustrating the phylogenetic trajectory leading up to the stereoselective <italic>Sr</italic>BDH1. Ancestors N30 and N32 are highlighted in red. (C) Specific activity and enantioselectivity E<sub>comp</sub>-values determined for <italic>Sr</italic>BDH1 and ancestors N6, N30 and N32 by oxidation of (+/–)-1-borneol enantiomers in comparison to the competitive oxidation between (+/-)-1-borneol and the reference compound. <sup>[1]</sup> determined by GC; <sup>[2]</sup> determined as the ratio of specific activities of an enantiomer over the rate of a competing co-substrate divided by the rate of the other enantiomer over the competing co-substrate (Supplemental Equation S1); <sup>[3]</sup> n.c.: no conversion.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS207377-f002"/></fig><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>(A) Structural overview of <italic>Sr</italic>BDH1 based on PDB: 6ZYZ showing its tetrameric composition. (B) The active-site of <italic>Sr</italic>BDH1 with NAD<sup>+</sup> depicted in stick representation. The active-site pocket is highlighted by a red mesh. (C) Superimposition of the four chains from PDB: 6ZYZ, highlighting the αFG-helix and the preceding loop conformations among them.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS207377-f003"/></fig><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Active-site structure of N32, N39, <italic>So</italic>BDH1 and <italic>Sr</italic>BDH1. The residues lining the active-sites are color-coded as named below, while the catalytic residues are represented in orange for all four structures. Residues originating from the adjacent protomer of the tetramer (not shown) are underlined. (A) Architecture of the active-site of N32 (purple). Most of the residues lining the active-site are hydrophobic. Residues Ile 191 and Gly 192 were not resolved in the electron density. (B) Superposition of N39 (teal) over N32 (purple). Residues lining the active-site are mostly hydrophobic. Only chain A from N39 was resolved in the electronic density, therefore, residue N30 Leu111 was not resolved. Residues Ile192 and Gly193 were also not resolved in the electron density. (C) Representation of the active-site structure of <italic>So</italic>BDH1 (green), formed mainly by hydrophobic residues. The residues Leu206 and Ala207 were not resolved in the electron density. (D) Superposition of <italic>Sr</italic>BDH1 (blue) onto N32 (purple), N39 (teal) and SoBDH1 (green). Conclusively, the active-site is formed mainly by hydrophobic residues. Residues equivalent to Leu206 and Ala207 in <italic>So</italic>BDH2 were not resolved in the electron density.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS207377-f004"/></fig><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Oxidative rates for (+)-1-borneol given in [mU/mg] catalyzed by the purified mutant variants of N6. Reaction conditions: 2 μM enzyme, 20% DMSO, 25°C, 300 rpm, 1 or 9 mM NAD<sup>+</sup>, 0.2 or 9 mM (+)-1-borneol, 0.1 M Tris-HCl pH 9.0. Measurements were carried out in triplicates.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS207377-f005"/></fig><fig id="F6" position="float"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>Molecular docking results of the open <italic>Sr</italic>BDH1 structure (PDB: 6ZYZ) with (A) (+)-1-borneol (teal) and (B) (–)-1-borneol (brick) and <italic>in vacuo</italic> minimized structures (C) and (D) before <italic>in vacuo</italic> minimization. Chains A and B are represented in green and blue cartoon. Residues interacting with the substrate are represented as thick sticks. Dashed lines show the distances between the catalytic Tyr and the O of the substrate (blue) and the nicotinic acid moiety of the cofactor and the α-CH (red).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS207377-f006"/></fig><fig id="F7" position="float"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><p>(A) Surfaces distribution of the two monitored distances <italic>d<sub>1</sub></italic> and <italic>d<sub>2</sub></italic> across three simulation replicas in the system (+)-1-borneol bound to <italic>Sr</italic>BDH1 at chain A. (B) Most populated conformation for each replica, relevant amino acids are highlighted in stick representation. Dashed lines show the distances between the catalytic Tyr (phenolic oxygen) and the hydroxyl oxygen of the substrate (blue) and the nicotinic acid moiety of the cofactor and the α-CH (red).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS207377-f007"/></fig><fig id="F8" position="float"><label>Fig. 8</label><caption><p>(A) Surfaces distribution of the two monitored distances <italic>d<sub>1</sub></italic> and <italic>d<sub>2</sub></italic> across three simulation replicas in the system (–)-1-borneol bound to <italic>Sr</italic>BDH1 at chain A. (B) Most populated conformation for each replica, relevant amino acids are highlighted in stick. Dashed lines show the distances between the catalytic Tyr (phenolic oxygen) and the hydroxyl oxygen (blue) and the nicotinic acid moiety of the cofactor and the α-CH (red).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS207377-f008"/></fig><table-wrap id="T1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Specific activity and enantioselectivity E<sub>comp</sub>-values determined for BDH variants by oxidation of (+/-)-1-borneol enantiomers in comparison to the competitive oxidation between (+/-)-1-borneol and the reference compound.</p></caption><table frame="box" rules="all"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="2">Enzyme</th><th align="left" valign="top" colspan="2"><bold>Specific activity<sup>[<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFN1">1</xref>]</sup> [mU/mg]</bold></th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="2">E<sub>comp</sub><sup>[<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFN3">3</xref>]</sup></th></tr><tr><th align="left" valign="top">(+)-1-borneol</th><th align="left" valign="top">(–)-1-borneol</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top">N32_I111L</td><td align="left" valign="top">35.9 ± 1.8</td><td align="left" valign="top">2.9 ± 0.1</td><td align="left" valign="top">27</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">N30_L111I</td><td align="left" valign="top">14.2 ± 0.2</td><td align="left" valign="top">0.05 ± 0.01</td><td align="left" valign="top">21</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">N30_L111I/M213I/A214G</td><td align="left" valign="top">12.6 ± 0.9</td><td align="left" valign="top">0.4 ± 0.01</td><td align="left" valign="top">8.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">N30_L111I/A222V/E223A/S227A/S232V</td><td align="left" valign="top">62.4 ± 2.9</td><td align="left" valign="top">0.5 ± 0.06</td><td align="left" valign="top">128</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">N30_L111I/S 166A/V167S/G169A</td><td align="left" valign="top">271.3 ± 9.7</td><td align="left" valign="top">0.4 ± 0.2</td><td align="left" valign="top">31</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">N30_L111I/V136L/S139G/V183I</td><td align="left" valign="top">174.2 ± 9.7</td><td align="left" valign="top">0.4 ± 0.02</td><td align="left" valign="top">25</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">N30_L111I/L47W/E74K/V79I/E107A/E153Q/Y197H</td><td align="left" valign="top">9.1 ± 0.2</td><td align="left" valign="top">n.c.</td><td align="left" valign="top">&gt;200</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">N30_L111I/V136L/G169A/V183I</td><td align="left" valign="top">9.9 ± 1.7</td><td align="left" valign="top">n.c.</td><td align="left" valign="top">&gt;200</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">SÆDH1 V97I<sup>[<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFN5">5</xref>]</sup></td><td align="left" valign="top">10.7 ± 2.1</td><td align="left" valign="top">n.c.</td><td align="left" valign="top">&gt;200</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">N32_I111V</td><td align="left" valign="top">5.8 ± 0.7</td><td align="left" valign="top">n.c.</td><td align="left" valign="top">&gt;200</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">SÆDH1</td><td align="left" valign="top">296.9 ± 15.3</td><td align="left" valign="top">1.3 ± 0.09</td><td align="left" valign="top">&gt;200</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TFN1"><label>[1]</label><p id="P62">determined by gas chromatography</p></fn><fn id="TFN2"><label>[2]</label><p id="P63">determined as the ratio of specific activities of the enantiomers</p></fn><fn id="TFN3"><label>[3]</label><p id="P64">determined as the ratio of specific activities of an enantiomer over the rate of a competing co-substrate divided by the rate of the other enantiomer over the competing co-substrate (Supplemental Equation S1)</p></fn><fn id="TFN4"><label>[4]</label><p id="P65">n.c.: no conversion</p></fn><fn id="TFN5"><label>[5]</label><p id="P66">V97 in <italic>Sr</italic>BDH1 is equal to Ile 111 and Leu111 in N30 and N32.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Relevant catalytic distances obtained from docking calculations and docking scores using AutoDock Vina<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref></sup>.</p></caption><table frame="box" rules="all"><thead><tr><th align="center" valign="top">System</th><th align="center" valign="top">d borneol O1 – OH-Y154 (Å)</th><th align="center" valign="top">d borneol C5 – C4 NAD<sup>+</sup> (Å)</th><th align="center" valign="top">Vina Docking score</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top">wild-type (+)-1-borneol</td><td align="center" valign="top">5.5</td><td align="center" valign="top">3.9</td><td align="center" valign="top">-4.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">wild-type (–)-1-borneol</td><td align="center" valign="top">5.6</td><td align="center" valign="top">3.9</td><td align="center" valign="top">-5.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">N32 (+)-1-borneol</td><td align="center" valign="top">7.2</td><td align="center" valign="top">5.6</td><td align="center" valign="top">-3.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">N32 (–)-1-borneol</td><td align="center" valign="top">8.8</td><td align="center" valign="top">6.1</td><td align="center" valign="top">-4.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">N6 (+)-1-borneol</td><td align="center" valign="top">7.0</td><td align="center" valign="top">5.2</td><td align="center" valign="top">-3.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">N6 (–)-1-borneol</td><td align="center" valign="top">5.7</td><td align="center" valign="top">3.7</td><td align="center" valign="top">-3.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">N32_I111L (+)-1-borneol</td><td align="center" valign="top">9.1</td><td align="center" valign="top">6.1</td><td align="center" valign="top">-4.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">N32_I111L (–)-1-borneol</td><td align="center" valign="top">9.3</td><td align="center" valign="top">5.8</td><td align="center" valign="top">-3.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">N30_L111I (+)-1-borneol</td><td align="center" valign="top">7.3</td><td align="center" valign="top">5.2</td><td align="center" valign="top">-4.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">N30_L111I (–)-1-borneol</td><td align="center" valign="top">7.6</td><td align="center" valign="top">5.2</td><td align="center" valign="top">-4.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">N30_L111I/G169A/V 136L/V183I (+)-1-borneol</td><td align="center" valign="top">7.3</td><td align="center" valign="top">5.2</td><td align="center" valign="top">-4.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">N30_L111I/G169A/V 136L/V183I (–)-1-borneol</td><td align="center" valign="top">7.6</td><td align="center" valign="top">5.2</td><td align="center" valign="top">-4.3</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></floats-group></article>