<!DOCTYPE article
 PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" article-type="preprint"><?all-math-mml yes?><?use-mml?><?origin ukpmcpa?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">bioRxiv</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>bioRxiv : the preprint server for biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2692-8205</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">EMS201301</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2024.11.25.625153</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="archive">PPR945868</article-id><article-version-alternatives><article-version article-version-type="status">preprint</article-version><article-version article-version-type="number">1</article-version></article-version-alternatives><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The mechanical anisotropy of adipose tissues regulates ovarian cancer invasion</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gonzalez-Molina</surname><given-names>Jordi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CR1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nabili</surname><given-names>Parisa</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Marciano</surname><given-names>Daniele</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Abdelnabi</surname><given-names>Sara</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gultekin</surname><given-names>Okan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rasul</surname><given-names>Mohammed Fatih</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Yikun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nadal</surname><given-names>Clémence</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chrysanthou</surname><given-names>Alexandra</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Alkasalias</surname><given-names>Twana</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Salehi</surname><given-names>Sahar</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Balkwill</surname><given-names>Frances</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lehti</surname><given-names>Kaisa</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A6">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gautrot</surname><given-names>Julien E.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CR1">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Department of Microbiology, Tumor and Cell Biology, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/056d84691</institution-id><institution>Karolinska Institutet</institution></institution-wrap>, <addr-line>Solnavägen 9</addr-line>, <city>Solna</city><postal-code>17165</postal-code>, <country country="SE">Sweden</country></aff><aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Department of Women’s and Children’s Health, Division of Obstetrics and Gynecology, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/056d84691</institution-id><institution>Karolinska Institutet</institution></institution-wrap>, <addr-line>Solnavägen 9</addr-line>, <city>Solna</city>, <country country="SE">Sweden</country></aff><aff id="A3"><label>3</label>School of Engineering and Materials Science, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/026zzn846</institution-id><institution>Queen Mary University of London</institution></institution-wrap>, <addr-line>Mile End Road</addr-line>, <city>London</city><postal-code>E1 4NS</postal-code>, <country country="GB">United Kingdom</country></aff><aff id="A4"><label>4</label>Department of Pelvic Cancer, Theme Cancer, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/00m8d6786</institution-id><institution>Karolinska University Hospital</institution></institution-wrap>, <city>Stockholm</city>, <country country="SE">Sweden</country></aff><aff id="A5"><label>5</label>Barts Cancer Institute, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/026zzn846</institution-id><institution>Queen Mary University of London</institution></institution-wrap>, <addr-line>Charterhouse Square</addr-line>, <postal-code>EC1M6BQ</postal-code><city>London</city>, <country country="GB">UK</country></aff><aff id="A6"><label>6</label>Department of Biomedical Laboratory Science, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/05xg72x27</institution-id><institution>Norwegian University of Science and Technology</institution></institution-wrap>, <addr-line>Erling Skjalgssons gate 1</addr-line>, <city>Trondheim</city><postal-code>NO-7491</postal-code>, <country country="NO">Norway</country></aff><author-notes><corresp id="CR1">Correspondence: <email>jordigonzalezmolina@gmail.com</email> and <email>j.gautrot@qmul.ac.uk</email>.</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted"><day>28</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="preprint"><day>26</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><permissions><ali:free_to_read/><license><ali:license_ref>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is licensed under a <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">CC BY-NC 4.0 International license</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p id="P1">High-grade serous ovarian cancer, the most common and aggressive form of ovarian cancer, generally metastasises to visceral adipose tissues. In these tissues, the extracellular matrix through which ovarian cancer cells adhere and migrate is confined by the presence and preponderance of adipocytes. How cells migrate in this unique environment is not known, yet critical to understanding metastatic progression. To study these processes, we develop biomimetic organo-hydrogels that recreate structural and mechanical properties of human visceral adipose tissues. We show that ovarian cancer cells present invasive tropism towards organo-hydrogels, replicating the behaviour observed in native adipose tissues. This migration is facilitated by the mechanical anisotropy and microstructure of organo-hydrogels and adipose tissues, allowing the formation of cell force-induced migratory tracks, a process regulated by TGFβ in an MMP degradation-independent manner. These results highlight the contribution of adipocytes to tissue biophysical features as a key regulatory factor of ovarian cancer cell migration.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec id="S1" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p id="P2">Ovarian cancer is the deadliest gynaecological malignancy<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref></sup>. High-grade serous ovarian cancer (HGSC) is the most common and aggressive subtype of ovarian cancer, accounting for approximately 70% of all cases<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">2</xref></sup>. Ovarian cancer commonly disseminates transcoelomically by shedding cancer cells from the surface of the fallopian tube and/or ovary into the peritoneal cavity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">3</xref></sup>. After detachment, cells are carried by the ascitic fluid, attach to the mesothelial cell layer, and invade the adipose tissue of the omentum and the peritoneum. This tropism for adipose tissues, which has also been observed in the alternative haematogenous route of metastasis, is not fully understood<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref></sup>.</p><p id="P3">Cell migration within tissues is a fundamental process for the establishment and progression of metastases<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref></sup>. By using natural and engineered biomaterials, recent studies have revealed that the biochemical and biophysical properties of the ECM control cell migration and can dictate the migratory mode adopted by cells<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">8</xref></sup>. These regulatory mechanisms are particularly relevant to understand cancer cell invasion into ECM-rich tissues such as bone as well as the stroma of desmoplastic tumours and some sarcomas<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref></sup>. Conversely, adipose, muscle, and epithelial tissues display a high cellularity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref></sup>. Adipose tissues are largely composed of adipocytes, while the volume occupied by the ECM-containing interstitial space is minimal. However, upon ovarian cancer invasion, adipocytes shrink and are progressively replaced by an ECM-rich stroma<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref></sup>. The processes regulating ovarian cancer cell invasion into adipose tissues and the impact of the unique microstructural and biophysical properties of the adipose microenvironment remain ill-defined.</p><p id="P4">In this work, we develop an organo-hydrogel (OHG) model that captures the microstructure, mechanics and ECM biochemistry of adipose tissues. Using this model, we replicate the tropism of ovarian cancer cells observed in native adipose tissues, and demonstrate that the anisotropic mechanical properties and microstructure of adipose tissues play a significant role in this phenomenon. We uncover that ovarian cancer cell invasion is independent of matrix degradation but requires contractile cell-mediated forces to generate migratory tracks at the adipocyte-ECM interface. We demonstrate that the size of adipocyte-mimicking microdroplets and their density regulate the mode of cell migration and effective tissue invasion, capturing the close relationship linking the development of omental metastasis and tissue microstructural changes. This study uncovers the biophysical regulation of cancer cell migration in adipose tissues and presents an in vitro platform to study and model adipose tissue metastasis.</p></sec><sec id="S2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="S3"><label>1</label><title>Organo-hydrogels mimic the microstructure and mechanics of human adipose tissues</title><p id="P5">To recreate the microstructure of visceral adipose tissues, we designed organo-hydrogels (OHGs) comprising microdroplets mimicking the adipocyte phase, separated by an aqueous ECM-rich phase. The omental/peritoneal adipocyte-like emulsion was formulated using ~70 μm diameter oil microdroplets (silicone oil for inertness) stabilised by bovine serum albumin (BSA; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1a,b</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Extended data Fig 1a</xref>). To gel these microdroplets into OHGs, we selected collagen type I as the ECM phase because it is the main ECM component of adipose omental tissues (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Extended data Fig 1b</xref>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref></sup>. We compared the bulk mechanical properties of human peritoneal adipose and connective tissues with those of adipose tissue-mimicking OHGs and collagen matrices (with identical collagen concentrations in the aqueous phase). The storage moduli of OHGs and collagen gels were found to be similar and comparable to peritoneal connective tissues and within the range of peritoneal and omental adipose tissues (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1c</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Extended data Fig. 1c</xref>). Similarly, the stress-relaxation profile of OHGs closely matched those of peritoneal tissues, while collagen gels presented slower relaxation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1d</xref>). Analysis of local mechanical properties by force probe microscopy revealed marginally higher Young’s moduli of OHGs (1,300 ± 41 Pa (s.e.m.); range: 210-2,600) compared to peritoneal adipose tissues (1,100 ± 74 Pa (s.e.m.); range: 90-7,900; p = 0.0473; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Extended data Fig. 1d</xref>). Collectively, these data indicate that the structural and mechanical properties of OHGs closely resemble those of native peritoneal and omental adipose tissues.</p></sec><sec id="S4"><label>2</label><title>Tropism for invasion into adipose tissue is recapitulated in organo-hydrogels</title><p id="P6">To evaluate the invasive behaviour of ovarian cancer cells, we embedded pre-formed spheroids of 7 human ovarian cancer cell lines in collagen and OHGs. After 7 days, OVCAR8 and CAOV3 presented increased spheroid area, broke spherical symmetry and showed invasiveness into OHGs while OVCAR3, Kuramochi, and OVCAR4 were non-invasive (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1e,f</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Extended data Fig. 2a</xref>). Tyk-nu and Tyk-nu.CPR spheroids broke spherical symmetry and presented invasiveness in both collagen and OHGs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Extended data Fig. 2a,b</xref>). Collagen matrix pore size and density can alter 3D cell migration<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">8</xref></sup>. Collagen gels in bulk and in the aqueous phase of OHGs displayed equivalent collagen density and average pore size, indicating that the presence of the oil microdroplets in OHGs did not alter the collagen phase microstructure, but significantly affected the spheroid area and invasive phenotype of corresponding cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Extended Fig. 3a-c</xref>). To determine whether OHGs altered proliferation or apoptosis, we compared Ki67 and cleaved-caspase 3 expression in the distinct cell lines, respectively. Cleaved-caspase 3 expression was generally low, but Ki67 expression was enhanced in both CAOV3 and OVCAR8 cells, especially at the periphery of the spheroid (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1f</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Extended data Fig. 4</xref>). These results are in line with other reports showing that pro-invasive matrices promote cell proliferation in cancer spheroids<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref></sup>.</p><p id="P7">Ovarian cancer cell invasion of the adipose tissue occurs after attachment of cells present in the ascites fluid. To mimic this process, we established an organotypic invasion assay where cells were seeded on top of cell-free collagen gels or OHGs. In agreement with the spheroid model, OVCAR8 showed greater depth of invasion in OHGs than in collagen gels, where invasion was minimal (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1h,i</xref>). Next, we investigated the invasive behaviour of OVCAR8 cells <italic>ex vivo</italic> in human tissues by seeding OVCAR8 cells on top of adipocyte- or connective tissue-rich human peritoneal tissues. Recapitulating the behaviour in the hydrogel models, OVCAR8 depth of invasion was greater in adipose tissues than in connective tissues, where cells largely remained at the surface (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1j,k</xref>). In contrast, collagen gel-invading Tyk-nu cells were able to invade into the connective tissue (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Extended data Fig. 5a,b</xref>). Next, we investigated the behaviour of HGSC patient-derived malignant ascites cells. Malignant ascites cells often form heterogeneous cell aggregates of cancer (PAX8+) and stromal/mesothelial cells (PAX8-) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Extended data Fig. 5c</xref>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">3</xref></sup>. The organotypic invasion of both PAX8- and PAX8+ ascites cells was enhanced in OHGs compared to collagen gels (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Extended data Fig. 5d,e</xref>). Moreover, embedding of malignant cell aggregates indicated that cell invasion of CK7+ cells (expressed in cancer cells and mesothelial cells) and cell proliferation of both PAX8- and PAX8+ cells was enhanced in OHGs compared to collagen gels (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Extended data Fig. 5f,g</xref>). Altogether, these data indicate that the tropism shown by ovarian cancer cells for adipose tissues is recapitulated in OHGs without the presence of chemotactic gradients.</p></sec><sec id="S5"><label>3</label><title>ECM adhesion and TGFβ regulate ovarian cancer invasion in adipose microenvironments</title><p id="P8">Cancer cells invade into 3D microenvironments through single-cell or collective modes of migration, based on both ECM adhesion-dependent and -independent mechanisms<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref></sup>. To investigate the impact of ECM adhesion and signalling on ovarian cancer cell invasion, we embedded single OVCAR8 cells in collagen or OHGs for 48 h and investigated the phosphorylation of focal adhesion kinase (pFAK) and myosin light chain (pMLC). The expression of both phosphorylated proteins was found to be enhanced in OHGs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2a,b</xref>). Concurrently, nuclear localisation of yes-associated protein (YAP) was higher in OHGs. Although the surface of the oil microdroplets of OHGs did not present adhesion ligands, we observed that cells spread at the microdroplet-collagen interface (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2c</xref>). This led to alterations in nuclear morphology such as increased aspect ratio and reduced circularity in OHGs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2c</xref>). Similarly, we observed a greater nuclear aspect ratio and lower circularity in cells invading human peritoneal adipose tissue compared to cells at the tissue surface (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Extended data Fig. 6a,b</xref>). These observations suggest that the microstructure of adipose tissues and OHGs dictate cell confinement and spreading, and impose physical barriers to cell migration. To evaluate the impact of the altered ECM adhesion and signalling on invasion, we treated embedded OVCAR8 spheroids with integrin β1 blocking antibody or with FAK, myosin-II, Rho-associated protein kinase (ROCK), or YAP inhibitors. All inhibitions except that of YAP reduced cell invasion into OHGs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2e</xref>). Similarly, inhibition of FAK, which showed the strongest inhibition in OHGs, resulted in decreased invasion into human peritoneal adipose tissue (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2f,g</xref>). In addition, in HGSC ascites cells embedded in OHGs, inhibition of FAK diminished the proliferation of PAX8- and PAX8+ cells, although the response of PAX8+ cells in distinct donors was heterogeneous (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Extended data Fig. 6c</xref>). Finally, as confinement and nuclear deformations can cause DNA damage, in turn regulating migratory phenotypes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref></sup>, we compared the expression of the DNA damage marker <italic>γ</italic>H2AX in cells after culture within collagen gels and OHGs. Expression of <italic>γ</italic>H2AX was found to be low and comparable within both materials (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Extended data Fig. 6d,e</xref>). Thus, these data indicate that ECM-mediated adhesion, cytoskeletal contractility and downstream signalling are fundamental for cell invasion into OHGs and native adipose tissues, but that associated confinement is not conducive of DNA damage, as in other reported microstructured environments<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref></sup>.</p><p id="P9">To further understand the regulation of ovarian cancer invasiveness, we conducted a gene set enrichment analysis of differentially expressed genes between OHG-invading and non-invading cell lines (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">Extended data Fig. 7a,b</xref>). The most enriched gene sets in the downregulated genes were bone marrow stromal, cell morphogenesis, and cell-cell junction. Loss of cell-cell junctions typically occurs during epithelial-to-mesenchymal transition (EMT)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref></sup>. A key inducer of EMT is the transforming growth factor-β (TGFβ), which has been associated with ovarian cancer metastasis and omental invasion<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">21</xref></sup>. Thus, we investigated the impact of TGFβ signalling on OHG invasion. Inhibition of TGFβ signalling in OVCAR8 reduced spheroid invasion while treatment with TGFβ enhanced CAOV3 invasion in OHGs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2h-k</xref>). Similarly, inhibition of TGFβ reduced CK7+ spheroid size and the number of invading CK7+ single HGSC malignant ascites cells embedded in OHGs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">Extended data Fig. 7c-e</xref>). Moreover, inhibition of TGFβ signalling diminished organotypic invasion of PAX8- and PAX8+ ascites cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">Extended data Fig. 7f,g</xref>). Finally, TGFβ treatment induced OHG invasiveness in the initially non-invading Kuramochi cell line (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2l,m</xref>). These data indicate that TGFβ signalling is pivotal to the regulation of ovarian cancer cell invasion into adipose tissue-mimicking OHGs.</p><p id="P10">To better understand the role of the ECM phase of OHGs on cell invasion, we explored the use of norbornene-functionalised hyaluronic acid (NB-HA) as the ECM phase instead of collagen. This system allowed us to investigate whether the observed cell behaviours are collagen-dependent and provided a higher degree of control over ECM features such as adhesion ligand presentation, matrix degradability and mechanics. We formed OHGs by photo-crosslinking microdroplets with NB-HA and di-cysteine matrix metalloproteinase (MMP)-cleavable peptides (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3a</xref>). The storage modulus of NB-HA OHGs was slightly higher than that of collagen-based OHG but within the range of peritoneal and omental adipose tissues (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3b</xref>). Stress relaxation in NB-HA OHGs was reduced compared to collagen-based OHGs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3c</xref>). Despite these differences, OVCAR8 cells invaded NB-HA OHGs presenting the collagen-derived adhesion motif GFOGER and similarly presented cell spreading at the matrix-microdroplet interface, albeit to a reduced level compared to their migration in collagen-based OHGs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3d-g</xref>). During the development of omental metastases, the composition of the ECM evolves, with increasing presence of non-collagenous proteins such as fibronectin and osteopontin which contain the cell adhesion motif RGD<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref></sup>. Thus, we compared OVCAR8 invasion into OHGs containing GFOGER and RGD. Invasion into OHGs was comparable in both types of OHGs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3f-h</xref>). These results indicate that, although OVCAR8 invasion into OHGs is integrin-mediated, it is not restricted to collagenous ECM phases.</p></sec><sec id="S6"><label>4</label><title>Invasion is regulated by the mechanical anisotropy of adipose microenvironments</title><p id="P11">Invasion through dense matrices often requires the proteolytic degradation of the ECM<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref></sup>. However, as cell migration in OHGs was found to be associated with spreading at microdroplet-ECM and adipocyte-ECM interfaces (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2c</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Extended data Fig 6a</xref>), we hypothesized that the physico-chemistry of these interfaces, but not MMP activity, is critical to the migratory phenotype observed. First, we investigated the importance of ECM degradation on invasion into adipose tissues. The invasion of OVCAR8 spheroids embedded in collagen-based OHGs was not altered upon treatment with a pan-MMP inhibitor (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig 3i,j</xref>). Likewise, pan-MMP inhibition did not alter OVCAR8 invasion into human peritoneal adipose tissue explants or the organotypic invasion and the proportion of proliferating malignant ascites cells in OHGs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3k,l</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">Extended data Fig 8a-c</xref>). To further confirm that MMP activity and enzymatic degradation are not required for invasion, we embedded spheroids in NB-HA-based OHGs and compared the invasion of cells in systems crosslinked with an MMP-cleavable peptide or non-degradable polyethylene glycol-dithiol (PEGDT). Cell invasion and spheroid area was comparable in both MMP-cleavable and PEGDT-crosslinked OHGs, where cells migrated in direct contact with microdroplets (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3m</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">Extended data Fig 8d</xref>).</p><p id="P12">These data indicate that invasion in adipose tissues and OHGs is MMP-independent and could be enabled by migration at the adipocyte-ECM interface. This contrasts with cell migration through dense collagen matrices, typically dependent on local degradation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">23</xref></sup>. In agreement with these observations, single cells embedded in OHGs spread at the microdroplet-ECM interface, but not in equally dense collagen matrices, upon pan-MMP inhibition (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4a</xref>). Notably, the microdroplets and peritoneal adipocytes in contact with OVCAR8 cells presented deformed interfaces at contact points (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4b</xref>). This further suggests that cell migration at the adipocyte-ECM interface is adhesion-mediated, resulting in forces that can deform adipocyte/microdroplet interfaces. Indeed, blocking cell contractility by inhibiting ROCK abolished the invasion into OHGs and adipose tissue explants, reducing the nuclear deformation of cells at the invasive front (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig, 4c</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">Extended data Fig. 9a-c</xref>). Similarly, ROCK inhibition diminished organotypic OHG invasion of HGSC patient ascites cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">Extended data Fig. 9d,e</xref>).</p><p id="P13">Subsequently, we investigated whether microdroplet deformation, and the associated mechanical anisotropy of droplet-matrix interfaces, facilitate cell invasion. Liquid PDMS microdroplets forming OHGs were replaced by elastomer beads based on crosslinked Sylgard 184 PDMS cured with increasing crosslinker concentration (2-10 wt%) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4d</xref>). The mechanics of liquid-liquid interfaces is highly anisotropic<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref></sup>. Oil microdroplets display extremely low interfacial shear moduli in the absence of tensioactive stabilisers, but display comparatively high indentation moduli. This can be reversed upon the adsorption of protein assemblies such as albumin nanosheets, raising interfacial shear moduli above 60 mN/m (from 10<sup>-5</sup>-10<sup>-4</sup> N/m for bare interfaces), whilst indentation moduli are reduced 1.69-fold<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref></sup>. The introduction of crosslinked PDMS to form OHGs therefore aimed to reverse the mechanical anisotropy at organic-aqueous interfaces within these materials, with Sylgard 184 bead formulations with storage shear moduli of 20, 147 and 260 kPa (corresponding to 2, 5 and 10 wt% crosslinking, respectively; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F15">Extended data Fig. 10a,b</xref>). Circularity of elastomeric PDMS microbeads in contact with OVCAR8 cells was lower in soft compared to stiff PDMS microbeads (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F15">Extended data Fig. 10c,d</xref>). Concurrently, invasion of OVCAR8 cells was significantly reduced in OHGs with stiff PDMS microbeads (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4e,f</xref>). Therefore, these results indicate that cell-mediated deformation of microdroplets and adipocytes, enabled by the mechanical anisotropy of associated interfaces, facilitate cell invasion in adipose tissues and adipose-mimicking OHGs.</p><p id="P14">To investigate how cell adhesion at the microdroplet-ECM interface regulates invasion, we modified the HA-NB OHG system to include norbornene-BSA (BSA-NB) at the microdroplet surface, allowing functionalization of the droplet surface with cell adhesion peptides (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4g</xref>). Both OHGs generated with BSA and BSA-NB droplets, with HA-NB in the aqueous/gel phase, had comparable stiffness and stress-relaxation profiles and OVCAR8 spheroid invasive response was similar (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">Extended data Fig. 11a-d</xref>). We introduced RGD ligands either in the gel (NB-HA) phase and at the microdroplet surface of OHGs, or restricted to the microdroplet surface (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4h</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">Extended data Fig. 11e</xref>). Although cell invasion into microdroplet-restricted RGD OHGs was significantly reduced compared to global-RGD OHGs, cells were still able to spread and migrate through the corresponding networks of microdroplets (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4h</xref>). Next, we investigated whether the mechanics of the microdroplet interface, which was found to modulate cell adhesion at liquid-liquid interfaces<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">26</xref></sup>, regulates cell invasion in OHGs. We softened the stabilizing protein assemblies by introducing β-casein (resulting in interfaces displaying interfacial shear storage moduli of 11.2 ± 1.0 mN/m) and stiffened them by crosslinking with sulfosuccinimidyl 4-(N-maleimidomethyl)cyclohexane-1-carboxylate (sSMCC; 65.6 ± 13.7 mN/m), compared to BSA-only controls (35.7 ± 4.1 mN/m) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4i</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F17">Extended data Fig. 12a,b</xref>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27">27</xref></sup>. β-casein acts as a competitor for BSA adsorption, preventing the formation of the extensive protein nanosheet network that normally leads to the formation of interfaces with high interfacial shear moduli<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">28</xref></sup>. In contrast, the introduction of cyclohexyl residues via SMCC coupling enhances crosslinking of albumin nanosheets, increasing their interfacial shear moduli<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27">27</xref></sup>. When adhesive motifs were only localised at the surface of microdroplets, cell invasion into OHGs with stiff interfaces was enhanced compared to softer interfaces (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4j,k</xref>). However, altering interfacial mechanics of microdroplets forming OHGs presenting adhesion ligands also in the gel phase did not affect cell invasion (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F17">Extended data Fig. 12c,d</xref>). Altogether, these data indicate that the localisation of cell adhesion motifs, together with the nanoscale mechanical properties of adipocyte-mimicking microdroplet interfaces, modulate actomyosin-dependent cell invasion of adipose tissues.</p></sec><sec id="S7"><label>5</label><title>Microdroplet size regulates modes of cell invasion</title><p id="P15">In omental metastases, as the stromal compartment and ECM deposition increases, adipocyte diameter is reduced from approximately 70 to 25 μm<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref></sup>. Concurrently, the total volume occupied by adipocytes in the tissue diminishes progressively. Thus, we set out to determine whether microdroplet size and volume fraction in OHGs have an impact on cell invasion. We generated collagen-based OHGs with microdroplets of average diameters of ~140, 70, 25, and 15 μm, and 80, 60, 30, and 15% oil volume fractions, in which OVCAR8 spheroids were embedded (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5a</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F18">Extended data Fig. 13a</xref>). At 80% oleophilic volume fraction, the storage modulus of OHGs increased exponentially with reduced microdroplet size (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5b</xref>). The droplet size also affected the viscoelastic profile of OHGs, with slower stress-relaxation observed for OHGs formed with smaller microdroplets (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5c</xref>). At 80% emulsion volume fraction, the spheroid size and invasion was maximal in 70 and 25 μm microdroplet OHGs, while both larger and smaller microdroplets presented reduced invasion (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5d,e</xref>). Diminishing the total oil volume fraction decreased the spheroid area in 140 and 70 μm microdroplet OHGs. However, spheroid areas in 25 and 15 μm microdroplet OHGs was maximal at 60 and 30% oleophilic volume fractions, before decreasing again at 15% volume fraction. Overall, maximum invasiveness was achieved in biomimetic metastatic omentum OHGs, featuring 25 μm microdroplets, at 60 and 30% emulsion volume fractions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref></sup>. These data indicate that microdroplets size and volume fraction, and therefore the microstructure of adipose tissues, are key regulators of cancer cell migration. This suggests that reduced adipocyte size in conjunction with partial reduction of volume fraction facilitate cell invasion within adipose tissues during tumour invasion.</p><p id="P16">Next, we examined the mechanisms via which cancer cells sense microstructural features of the adipose microenvironment and regulate their invasion. Analysis of the invasive front in OHGs showed that cells migrate collectively in 70 μm but present single cell migration in 25 μm OHGs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5d</xref>). Moreover, in 25 μm OHGs, nuclear aspect ratios increased and circularity decreased compared to 70 μm OHGs, suggesting that cells experience greater confinement in these conditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F19">Extended data Fig. 14a,b</xref>). Indeed, the inter-microdroplet space is larger in 70 μm compared to 25 μm OHGs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5f</xref>). Thus, the physical barriers imposed by 25 μm droplet OHGs are more prominent and the proportion of cells in contact with droplets is higher (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5g</xref>). Cell confinement has been found to be sensed via mechanosensitive ion channels and the deformation of the nucleus, causing reduced nuclear envelope wrinkles<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">30</xref></sup>. Indeed, OVCAR8 cells in contact with both 70 and 25 μm microdroplets showed reduced nuclear envelope wrinkles compared to cells embedded in collagen (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5h</xref>). Concurrently, proliferation, YAP nuclear localisation, and pMLC expression was comparable while pFAK expression was slightly increased in 25 μm compared to 70 μm droplet OHGs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5i</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F19">Extended data Fig. 14c</xref>). These results suggest that cells spreading within OHGs formed of small and large (25 and 70 μm) droplets engage the adhesion machinery, but that nuclear deformation is significantly enhanced in the former OHGs, as a result of the reduced interdroplet distance.</p><p id="P17">To investigate whether cellular sensors of confinement are activated in OHGs and regulate cell invasion, we first analysed the impact of the mechanosensitive ion channels Piezo1 and TRPV4. Inhibition of Piezo1 did not affect the area of OVCAR8 spheroids embedded in 70 μm OHGs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F20">Extended data Fig. 15a</xref>). In contrast, inhibition of TRPV4 caused a reduction of the spheroid area in both 70 and 25 μm OHGs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F20">Extended data Fig. 15b</xref>). Analysis of spheroids under TRPV4 inhibition revealed that cell invasion into OHGs is not blocked but, as shown previously<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31">31</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32">32</xref></sup>, cell proliferation is reduced (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F20">Extended data Fig. 15c-e</xref>). Next, we investigated whether the cytosolic phospholipase A2 (cPLA2)-Arachidonic acid-InsP3Rs-myosin II signalling cascade, involved in nuclear sensing of confinement, regulates OVCAR8 invasion into OHGs<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">30</xref></sup>. Inhibition of the signalling cascade did not cause major effects on OVCAR8 invasion in either 70 or 25 μm OHGs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F21">Extended data Fig. 16a</xref>). Conversely, activation of the cascade with arachidonic acid reduced spheroid area and reduced spheroid invasion (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F21">Extended data Fig. 16b,c</xref>). Therefore, inhibition of previously described mechanosensors activated in confinement were not found to regulate OVCAR8 cell invasion into OHGs.</p><p id="P18">Finally, we investigated whether the observed differences in migration mode between 70 and 25 μm OHGs are caused by the increased ability of single migrating cells to navigate within confined microenvironments. Thus, we compared the impact of TGFβ treatment, which induces a mesenchymal phenotype, on normally collectively migrating CAOV3 cells in 70 μm and 25 μm droplet OHGs. The effect of TGFβ treatment on CAOV3 was greater in 25 μm than in 70 μm droplet OHGs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5j,k</xref>). Therefore, these data indicate that the biochemical microenvironment, through TGFβ-induced phenotypical changes in cancer cells, synergises with the biophysical alterations occurring in adipose tissues (i.e. reduced adipocyte size) to facilitate ovarian cancer cell invasion.</p></sec></sec><sec id="S8" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p id="P19">Biomimetic OHGs recapitulate the architecture and mechanical characteristics of native adipose tissue at the nano- to macro-scale, and enable the direct encapsulation of cells and spheroids, or the study of cell migration in invasion assays. OHGs recreated the invasive behaviour of ovarian cancer cells observed in peritoneal adipose tissues, which collagen gels could not replicate. Similarly, although previous hydrogel models have mimicked the mechanical and biochemical properties of the tissue ECM, the greater complexity of native tissues, including adipose tissues, can lead to discrepancies between in vitro and in vivo cell migration studies<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33">33</xref></sup>. Granular hydrogels and other porous hydrogels introduce structural features of tissues such as interstitial spaces and porosity, demonstrating that such characteristics can regulate cell invasion<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34">34</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37">37</xref></sup>. Similarly, the size and shape of the particles forming granular hydrogels can control cell invasion<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37">37</xref></sup>. Here, we demonstrate that by including both ECM-like and adipocyte-like phases in OHGs, ovarian cancer cell invasion can be induced without the requirement of pro-invasive adipose tissue-derived biochemical factors.</p><p id="P20">We find that cells do not require MMP activity to invade adipose tissues and OHGs. Instead, the establishment of adhesion and myosin-regulated migration tracks at the adipocyte-ECM interface, enables cell invasion (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5l</xref>). However, MMP expression is associated with poor overall survival in HGSC, possibly due to their function in breaching the mesothelial layer and basement membrane, and in regulating the subsequent fibrotic remodelling of the tissue<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38">38</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42">42</xref></sup>. We show that ECM adhesion at the adipocyte-ECM interface is fundamental for cell invasion. Integrin-mediated adhesion to collagen, FAK activity, and YAP are also involved in therapy resistance in ovarian cancer<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41">41</xref></sup>. Thus, various clinical trials targeting the ECM and related signalling in ovarian cancer are currently underway<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43">43</xref></sup>.</p><p id="P21">Cells migrating at the adipocyte/microdroplet-ECM interface are under confinement, especially in small droplet OHGs. Although we observed cellular hallmarks of confinement such as nuclear deformations and nuclear envelop stretching, cells did not present enhanced DNA damage and the inhibition of confinement-related pathways had a minimal effect on invasiveness<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">30</xref></sup>. This suggests that confinement does not reach the threshold to induce these effects, possibly facilitated by the mechanical anisotropy of adipocytes/microdroplets (high compliance radially, but displaying high interfacial shear moduli), leading to the opening of migration tracks. In addition, the induction of phenotypic plasticity and a mesenchymal phenotype<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R44">44</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R45">45</xref></sup>, as well as cancer-associated stromal cells<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R46">46</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R48">48</xref></sup>, may facilitate invasion into OHGs, particularly within smaller microdroplets, and adipose tissues.</p><p id="P22">In this study, we did not explore stromal-cancer cell communication, however, we envision OHGs will be fundamental to fully understand this process. Indeed, using patient-derived cells, we observed that PAX8- stromal cells present higher invasion and proliferation in OHGs than in microdroplet-free collagen gels, a phenomenon that may be fundamental to understand the evolution of omental and peritoneal metastases. Since adipose tissues are involved in multiple cancer types including gastric, breast, colon, pancreatic, renal cancers and leukaemia<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R49">49</xref></sup>, adipose tissue models such as OHGs will be central for decoding the complex regulation of ECM and cell communication in these tissues.</p></sec><sec id="S9" sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec id="S10"><title>Patient samples</title><p id="P23">Research samples including ascites fluid, omental and peritoneal tissues were obtained from the Karolinska University Hospital. The samples used in this study contain biobanked and fresh material from female HGSC patients who have been submitted to surgery at the Karolinska Institute Hospital, Sweden. The protocol of this study was approved by the Ethics Review Board of the Stockholm Region (DNR 2021-03768), and all methods were performed in accordance with relevant guidelines and regulations and in compliance with the principles outlined in the Declaration of Helsinki. All cases were reviewed centrally. Patients gave their written informed consent.</p></sec><sec id="S11"><title>Human cell line culture</title><p id="P24">The human cell lines were cultured at 37°C in 5% CO2. OVCAR3, OVCAR8, OVCAR4, KURAMOCHI and CAOV3 cells were grown in RPMI medium, while Tyk-nu and Tyk-nu.CPR were cultured in Minimum Essential Medium (MEM). All culture media were supplemented with 10% FBS (v/v) and 100 mg/ml penicillin/streptomycin. OVCAR8-mRFP and Tyk-nu-mRFP were generated by transfecting OVCAR8 and Tyk-nu cells with recombinant histone H2A-red fluorescent protein and subsequently sorting highly expressing cells by flow cytometry<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R50">50</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="S12"><title>Primary human cell culture</title><p id="P25">Patient ascites fluid was surgically drained from the peritoneal cavity and collected at the operating theatre of Karolinska University Hospital prior to ultra-radical hysterectomy of HGSOC tumours. The transportation and processing of the fluid is done in sterile conditions. Isolation of cells from ascites fluid was performed immediately after acquisition. After centrifugation at 800 g for 10 min, the supernatant was filtered using a 0.20-μm bottle filter (Thermo Scientific™ Nalgene™ Rapid-Flow™) to obtain cleared fluid used as supplement for cell culture media. If needed, red blood cells were lysed from the cell pellet by using Tris-buffered ammonium chloride solution (Tris-NH4Cl). Multicellular clusters were collected from the cell suspension using 45-μm strainer and re-suspended in 1:1 DMEM:F12 medium with 100 mg/ml penicillin/streptomycin and 10% clarified ascites. Cells were cultured at 37°C in 5% CO2 incubator.</p></sec><sec id="S13"><title>Human explant culture</title><p id="P26">Fresh macroscopically normal omental and peritoneal tissues were cut into 1-2 mm<sup>3</sup> pieces and placed into non-adherent U-bottom 96 well plates (Merck). A solution with 10,000 cells in 10 μl media was added and cells were allowed to attach to the tissues for 2 h at 37°C. Then, 150 μl DMEM:F12 media containing 10% (v/v) sterile-filtered HGSC patient ascites was added. Tissues were cultured for 7 days prior to overnight fixation with 4% paraformaldehyde.</p></sec><sec id="S14"><title>BSA functionalization</title><p id="P27">BSA-Norbornene (BSA-NB) was prepared using the following protocol. 10 g of BSA (15 mmol, Sigma-Aldrich) were dissolved in 100 ml of carbonate (NaHCO<sub>3</sub>/Na<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub>) buffer at pH 9. Then, 2 g of carbic anhydride (12.2 mmol, ThermoFisher Scientific) were slowly introduced into the reaction mixture, at room temperature. The resulting mixture was then heated whilst stirring at 40°C for 4 h. A pale-yellow solution was recovered, dialysed against deionised water for 4 days and freeze-dried. The functionalisation degree of the resulting BSA-NB was determined by <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref></sup>H NMR, by integration of the 2 alkene protons (8 6.0-6.3 ppm) of norbornene moieties, normalised by the aromatic protons of BSA (8 6.5-7.5 ppm).</p></sec><sec id="S15"><title>Oil emulsions</title><p id="P28">To generate adipocyte-mimicking droplets, emulsions of silicone oil (10 cP, Sigma) stabilized with BSA were prepared. First, 2 ml silicone oil was added into 10 ml of 0.1% or 10% BSA (w/v in PBS) solutions. To obtain microdroplets stabilized by protein assemblies with softer interfacial shear moduli, emulsions were prepared with 0.099% or 9.9% BSA, combined with 0.001% or 0.1% β-casein (Sigma), respectively. Solutions were then vortexed or homogenized, to generate the corresponding emulsions, varying the homogenization speed and time to control the size of resulting oil microdroplets. The emulsions were then centrifuged at 300 g for 5 min. After the remaining BSA solution was removed, the emulsions were washed three times with 10 ml PBS. The emulsions were centrifuged twice at 200 g for 2 min to remove excess PBS. To generate microdroplets stabilized by protein assemblies with higher interfacial shear storage moduli, BSA-formed emulsions were crosslinked with 2 mg ml<sup>-1</sup> sulfo-succinimidyl 4-(N-maleimidomethyl) cyclohexane-1-carboxylate (sulfo-SMCC, Thermofischer Scientific) for 1 h at RT and washed 3x with PBS.</p></sec><sec id="S16"><title>Preparation of PDMS Microdroplets</title><p id="P29">Polydimethylsiloxane (PDMS) emulsions containing bovine serum albumin (BSA) were prepared using Sylgard 184 silicone base and crosslinker in various proportions. To generate PDMS emulsions, 2 g of Sylgard 184 base were mixed with 0.04 g (2%), 0.1 g (5%), or 0.2 g (10%) PDMS crosslinker. Each mixture was gently stirred to ensure homogeneity. The tubes were then placed under vacuum, with the lids open, for 30 min to remove trapped air bubbles. Following degassing, bovine serum albumin (BSA) was dissolved in phosphate-buffered saline (PBS) to a concentration of 100 mg ml<sup>-1</sup>. A total of 8 ml of this BSA solution was added to each PDMS mixture. To form the emulsions, the samples were homogenized using a T25 Ultra Turrax Homogenizer at a speed of 12,000 rpm for 5 min, ensuring that the homogenizer probe fully immersed in the oil phase during the process. After homogenization, the samples were centrifuged at 300 rpm for 5 minutes to remove any air bubbles that formed during mixing.</p><p id="P30">The samples were then heated in an oil bath at 50°C for 4 h to cure the PDMS. After heating, each sample was vortexed to resuspend the emulsion droplets and subsequently centrifuged at 3,500 rpm for 5 minutes. Excess aqueous solution was carefully removed using a pipette. To sterilize the samples, 5 ml of a 5 mg ml<sup>-1</sup> sodium azide solution in PBS was added to each tube, and the samples were stored at 4°C overnight. The following day, the samples were vortexed and centrifuged again at 3,500 rpm for 5 minutes. The supernatant was discarded, and the emulsions were washed 3X by adding 5 mL of sterilized PBS. After the final wash, any remaining liquid was removed using a pipette, leaving behind the final PDMS emulsion product.</p></sec><sec id="S17"><title>Collagen-based hydrogels</title><p id="P31">To prepare collagen-only and collagen-based organohydrogels, a 2.25 mg ml<sup>-1</sup> solution of type I collagen (C7661, Sigma) was first prepared. This solution contained a 1:1 ratio of the collagen stock (4.5 mg ml<sup>-1</sup> in 0.4% (v/v) Acetic acid) and 2x minimum essential medium (MEM). The pH of the solution was then adjusted to pH 7 with cold 1M NaOH. For the organohydrogels, 20% volume of the prepared collagen was mixed with 80 % volume of the undiluted emulsion, giving a final aqueous phase concentration of collagen of 1.125 mg ml<sup>-1</sup>. To obtain an equal concentration of collagen (1.125 mg ml<sup>-1</sup>) for the collagen-only gels, the collagen solution was mixed 1:1 with cold PBS. For cell embedding, the prepared solutions were mixed with cells. Then, the solutions added into plates and placed in a humidified incubator at 37°C for 1 h. After incubation, media were added.</p></sec><sec id="S18"><title>HA-based Organohydrogels</title><p id="P32">To functionalise hyaluronic acid (HA) with norbornene, sodium hyaluronate (0.2 g, 0.527 mmol for each repeating unit) (Mw: 200,000 g mol<sup>-1</sup>) was dissolved in 20 mL of MES buffer (0.1M, pH 5.5). The solution was purged with nitrogen and then EDC-HCl (0.148g, 0.772 mmol) and NHS (0.089g, 0.772 mmol) were added in one portion and left to stir for 10 min. Subsequently, the pH of the solution was increased to approximately 8 using NaOH (2M). 5-norbornene-2-methylamine (0.1 mL, 0.812 mmol) was added by syringe to the reaction solution while stirring under nitrogen atmosphere and was left to stir overnight at room temperature. NaCl (0.75 g, 12.83 mmol) was then added to the reaction solution to neutralise the reaction product and form sodium hyaluronate derivates. The reaction solution was then precipitated into 10-fold excess cold (4 °C) acetone. The precipitate was dissolved in 20 mL of deionised water and dialysed against deionised water by changing the dialysate every 24 h for 5 days. Finally, the solution was frozen in liquid nitrogen and lyophilised to yield norbornene-functionalised hyaluronic acid (HA-nor). The degree of functionalisation of HA-nor derivates was determined via 1H NMR spectroscopy. 1H NMR shifts of attached norbornenes (D2O) are δ: 6.33 and 6.02 ppm (vinyl protons, endo), 6.26 and 6.23 ppm (vinyl protons, exo). To calculate the degree of substitution (DS), the integrations of these peaks were normalised to the peak of the methyl group of HA monomer at δ: 2.0 ppm.</p><p id="P33">To form HA-based organohydrogels, 80% vol emulsions were mixed with 20% vol 3.75 % (w/v, in PBS) HA-NB and cells or spheroids, and crosslinked with 1.3 mM PEG dithiol (Mw 1000 g mol<sup>-1</sup>; Sigma) 1.3 mM GCGPQGIAGQGCG (MMP-cleavable, Proteogenix, &gt;95% purity, TFA removed), 1 mM lithium phenyl-2,4,6-trimethylbenzoylphosphinate (LAP; Sigma) and ultraviolet (UV) light for 30 sec. For cell adhesion, 2 mM of CGGRGDSP<italic>K</italic>-FITC-G (RGD-FITC, Proteogenix, &gt;95% purity, TFA removed), GCGGRGDSPG (RGD, Proteogenix, &gt;95% purity, TFA removed), or trimerized (Ac)-GGYGGGPGGPPGPPGPPGPPGPPGFOGERGPPGPPGPPGPPGPPGPC-(Am) (GFOGER, Proteogenix, &gt;95% purity, TFA removed) were added to the solution or to BSA-NB emulsion, prior to UV light exposure. For localised peptide presentation (only at the surface of microdroplets), emulsions were washed 3X with PBS following photoirradiation in the presence of 1 mM RGD or RGD-FITC in PBS and were then mixed with the crosslinker, initiator and cells, in the absence of additional adhesion ligands.</p></sec><sec id="S19"><title>Antibodies</title><p id="P34">Primary antibodies: Ki67 mouse (1:400, 9449S, Cell Signaling Technology) and cleaved Caspase-3 rabbit (1:800, 9664, Cell Signaling Technology), Collagen-I (1:800, MA1-26771, Thermo Fisher Scientific), pFAK (1:200, phosphorylated (Y397) FAK, BD Biosciences), pMLC (1:400, phosphorylated (S20) myosin light chain, Abcam), YAP/TAZ (1:200, sc-101199, Santa Cruz Biotechnology), γH2A.X (1:200, phosphorylated (S139) gamma H2AX, Cell Signaling Technologies), LAP2 (1:400, PA5-52519, Thermo Fisher Scientific), PAX8 (1:400, 10336-1-AP, 1:400), CK7 (1:400, MA5-11986, Thermo Fisher Scientific). Secondary antibodies: Alexa Fluor Plus 488 anti-mouse IgG (1:1000, A-21202, Thermo Fisher), Alexa Fluor 350 anti-rabbit IgG (1:500, A10035, Thermo Fisher) and Alexa Fluor Plus 555 anti-rabbit IgG (1:1000, A32794, Thermo Fisher), Alexa Fluor 647 anti-rabbit IgG (1:500, A31573, Thermo Fisher Scientific), Alexa Fluor 647 anti-mouse IgG (1:500, A31571, Thermo Fisher Scientific).</p></sec><sec id="S20"><title>IF of hydrogels</title><p id="P35">Cells were fixed with 4% paraformaldehyde (PFA) for 1 h. For nuclear proteins (YAP/TAZ, Ki67, γH2A.X, and LAP2) cells were post-fixed for 1 min with a 1:1 solution of ice-cold acetone-methanol. Before incubation with primary antibodies, the cells were blocked in blocking buffer (15% FBS and 0.3% Triton-X in PBS) for 2 h at RT. Next, samples were incubated overnight at 4°C with primary antibodies diluted in blocking buffer. Subsequently, the samples were washed twice with PBS containing 0.45% Triton-X and stained with the corresponding fluorescence conjugated secondary antibodies for 2 h. Additionally, some samples were also incubated with 10 μM BODIPY 493/503 (in DMSO; Thermo Fisher Scientific) and Phalloidin Alexa Fluor 647 or 488 (1:400, Thermo Fisher Scientific) in blocking buffer for 2 h at RT. Lastly, the cells were washed once with 0.45% Triton-X and once with PBS. Gels were clarified with 40% Glycerol (Sigma) in PBS to match the refractive index of the oil. Image analysis was performed on Fiji-ImageJ.</p></sec><sec id="S21"><title>IF of tissue explants</title><p id="P36">Cells were fixed with 4% PFA overnight at 4°C. Samples were quenched with 0.3 M Glycin in PBS for 5 min at RT and washed twice with PBS. Samples were blocked for 1h at RT with 2% FBS in 0.4% Triton X-100 in PBS. Samples were incubated in primary antibody diluted in blocking buffer overnight at 4°C. Then, samples were washed for 5 min once with 0.1% PBS-Tween and twice with PBS. Next, samples were incubated in secondary antibody, 10 μM BODIPY, Hoechst 33342 (1:1000), and Phalloidin Alexa Fluor 647 (1:400) overnight at 4°C. Subsequently, samples were washed for 5 min once with 0.1% PBS-Tween and twice with PBS and mounted in Omnipaque for tissue clearing.</p></sec><sec id="S22"><title>Confocal fluorescence microscopy</title><p id="P37">Hydrogel and tissue samples were transferred into CultureWell gaskets adhered to a glass coverslip. Images were acquired with 10x Air, 20x Air, and 63x Oil objectives in a Zeiss LSM 800 Airy or a Zeiss LSM 900 Airy laser-scanning confocal microscope operated by the ZEN Blue v2.6 software.</p></sec><sec id="S23"><title>Rheology</title><p id="P38">Rheological measurements were carried out using a hybrid rheometer (DHR-3; TA Instruments). Collagen-based OHGs (0.5 ml) were pre-formed and incubated for 1h at 37 °C prior to transfer to the rheometer. Samples were placed between an upper parallel plate geometry (20 mm) and a standard Peltier plate pre-heated at 37 °C. Then, the geometry was lowered to the desired gap. First, frequency sweeps were carried out, recording the storage modulus (G’) and loss modulus (G”) as a function of frequency in a range of 0.1-100 Hz, at 1% strain. Amplitude sweeps from 0.1 to 100 % strain were subsequently carried out, at an oscillating frequency of 1 rad/s. Stress relaxation was performed at 2% strain for 120 s.</p><p id="P39">Photorheological measurements were performed using a hybrid rheometer (DHR-3) fitted with a UV accessory. 100 μL solutions of hydrogel precursors were placed between an upper parallel standard Peltier plate geometry (20 mm) and a bottom quartz window (allowing transmittance of UV light) at a fixed gap of 250 μm. UV irradiation (Omnicure S1500 mercury lamp, λ 280-600 nm, connected via a light guide and calibrated with an ILT 1400-A radiometer) was started after a period of oscillation (30 s) to equilibrate the system. To identify the gelation point and monitor the crosslinking progression, time sweep measurements (10 min) at a controlled strain of 0.4% and a constant angular frequency of 1 Hz (6.28 rad/s) were performed at room temperature. Storage modulus (G’) and loss modulus (G”) were recorded as a function of time in TRIOS software. Subsequently, a frequency sweep was carried out, recording G’ and G” as a function of frequency in a range of 0.1-100 Hz at 0.4% strain.</p><p id="P40">Amplitude sweeps were performed at an oscillating frequency of 1 Hz. Finally, stress relaxation measurements were carried out and gels were subjected to 2.0% strain, which was reached in 2 s and held for 180 s.</p></sec><sec id="S24"><title>Interfacial rheology</title><p id="P41">Interfacial shear rheological measurements were carried out on a Discovery Hydrid-Rheometer (DHR-3) from TA Instruments, using a Du Nouy ring geometry and a Delrin trough with a circular channel. The Du Nouy ring has a diamond- shaped cross section that improves positioning at the interface between two liquids to measure interfacial rheological properties while minimizing viscous drag from upper and sub-phases. The ring has a radius of 10 mm and is made of a platinum-iridium wire of 400 μm thickness. The Derlin trough was filled with 4 mL of fluorinated oil (Novec 7500, ACOTA). Using axial force monitoring, the ring was positioned at the surface of the fluorinated oil and was then lowered by a further 200 μm to position the medial plane of the ring at the fluorinated phase interface. 4 mL of the PBS solution was then gently introduced to fully cover the fluorinated sub-phase. Time sweeps were performed at a frequency of 0.1 Hz and temperature of 25 °C, with a displacement of 10<sup>–3</sup> rad (strain of 1%) to follow the self-assembly of the proteins at corresponding interfaces. 15 min after the beginning of the time sweep, the protein solution (100 mg/mL in PBS) was added in the aqueous phase to a final concentration of 1 mg mL<sup>-1</sup>. In the case of non-crosslinked albumin interfaces, the time sweep was carried out for 3 additional hours.</p><p id="P42">In the case of crosslinked albumin nanosheets, the remaining soluble proteins were removed after 1 h by washing the aqueous phase for 30 min with a microfluidic flow controller (OB1 MK4 pressure controller ElveFlow, Elvesys), which allowed the regulation of inlet and outlet PBS flow rates (overall 1 mL min<sup>-1</sup>). Following this washing cycle, a sulfo-SMCC solution was injected in the aqueous phase to a final concentration of 2 mg mL<sup>-1</sup>. The excess crosslinker was removed by a 30 min washing cycle after 1 h.</p><p id="P43">In both crosslinked and non-crosslinked systems, frequency sweeps (with displacements of 10<sup>-3</sup> rad) and amplitude sweeps (at a frequency of 0.1 Hz) were carried out at 25 °C to examine the frequency-dependent behaviour of corresponding interfaces and to ensure that the selected displacements and frequencies were within the linear viscoelastic region.</p></sec><sec id="S25"><title>Atomic Force Microscopy</title><p id="P44">To perform AFM nanoindentation, samples were placed in a 35-mm petri dish and submerged in PBS. Force–distance measurements were carried out on a JPK NanoWizard 4 (JPK Instruments), with samples submerged in PBS at room temperature. Pyrex-nitride colloidal probes (diameter 15 μm; CP-PNPL-SiO-E-5, NanoAndMore) were used (spring constant (K) was calibrated, 0.08 N m<sup>-1</sup>). Scans of 10 × 10 μm grids of indentation at three different locations across the surface of two different samples were acquired for each condition, and force-displacement curves were recorded. Indentations were carried out with a relative setpoint force of 2 nN and a loading rate of 5 μm s<sup>-1</sup>. Data were collected using JPK proprietary SPM software (JPK Instruments) and Young’s moduli were calculated using the Hertz model for a spherical tip.</p></sec><sec id="S26"><title>Small-molecule inhibitors, agonists, and growth factors</title><p id="P45">The pharmacological and small-molecule inhibitors and agonists used were the following: rat anti-human CD29 (1:100; BD Bioscience) to block integrin β1, blebbistatin (1 μM; Enzo Life Sciences) for myosin II inhibition, GM6001 (10 μM; Calbiochem) as broad-spectrum MMP inhibitor, Y-27632 (10 μM; MedChemExpress) as ROCK inhibitor, Defactinib (10 μM; MedChemExpress) as FAK inhibitor, verteporfin (1 μM; Sigma) as YAP/TAZ inhibitor, arachidonic acid (70 μM; MedChemExpress) to mimic signalling downstream of nuclear mechanosensing, AACOCF3 (28 μM; Tocris) to inhibit signalling downstream of nuclear mechanosensing, 2-aminoethoxydiphenylborane (2APB; 20 μM; MedChemExpress) as IP3 receptor agonist, Xestospongin c (10 μm; Tocris) as IP3 receptor agonist, GSMTx4 (10 μm; MedChemExpress) as Piezo 1 inhibitor, GSK205 (10 μm; MedChemExpress) as TRPV4 inhibitor, and GSK1016790A (50 μm; MedChemExpress) as TRPV4 agonist. The human recombinant TGFβ (1 ng ml<sup>-1</sup>; R&amp;D Systems) was used to induce epithelial-mesenchymal transition.</p></sec><sec id="S27"><title>Bioinformatics</title><p id="P46">Gene expression data of human cell lines were obtained from publicly available datasets including the Gene Expression Omnibus (GEO) GSE50831 and GSE28724 datasets. The RNA raw data were normalized and compared using the Affymetrix Expression Console Software (Thermofisher). Gene Set Enrichment Analysis (GSEA) was performed with significantly upregulated and downregulated genes (&gt; 2-fold; p &lt;0.05).</p></sec><sec id="S28"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="P47">Measurements were performed on at least 2 biological replicates from separate experiments. Statistical tests performed and sample size (N) for each figure are indicated in the figure legends. Data were handled and analysed in Microsoft Excel. The bar plots indicate the mean and the error bar represents the standard deviation, unless otherwise indicated in the figure legends. The individual data points are also represented as circles. In other data points, the mean is represented as a line and individual data points are indicated as circles. In the box plots, boxes represent the interquartile range, the centre of the boxes represent the median, and the cross represents the mean. The whiskers represent the maximum and minimum values within excluding the outliers, which are represented as circles.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="extended-data" id="S29"><title>Extended Data</title><fig id="F6" position="anchor"><label>Extended data Fig. 1</label><caption><title>Comparison between human tissues and collagen-based OHG.</title><p id="P48"><bold>a</bold>, Quantification of human peritoneal adipocyte and silicone oil droplet diameter (N = 170 cells/droplets). <bold>b</bold>, Collagen-I (grey) staining of human peritoneal adipose tissue and OHG. <bold>c</bold>, Storage modulus of human peritoneal and omental adipose tissues (N = 1-3). <bold>d</bold>, AFM quantification of the Young’s modulus (N ≥ 208 measurements from ≥ 4 regions). Scale bars, 50 μm (<bold>b</bold>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS201301-f006"/></fig><fig id="F7" position="anchor"><label>Extended data Fig. 2</label><caption><title>Ovarian cancer spheroid response to collagen and collagen-based OHG.</title><p id="P49"><bold>a</bold>, Total spheroid area comparison of multiple ovarian cancer cell lines in collagen or OHGs (N ≥ 3 spheroids). <bold>b</bold>, Ki67 (green), cleaved-caspase 3 (red) and nuclei (blue) staining of spheroids embedded in collagen or OHG after 7 days. Scale bars, 100 μm (<bold>b</bold>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS201301-f007"/></fig><fig id="F8" position="anchor"><label>Extended data Fig. 3</label><caption><title>Invasion in OHG is enhanced compared to collagen gels.</title><p id="P50"><bold>a</bold>, Collagen-I (grey) and BODIPY (green) staining of a collagen gel and an OHG. <bold>c</bold>, Quantification of collagen density in collagen gels and OHG (N = 4-5 gels). <bold>d</bold>, Quantification of pore size in collagen gels and OHG (N = 4 gels). For the data in <bold>b</bold> and <bold>c</bold>, a two-sided unpaired t-test was performed. Scale bar, 10 μm (<bold>a</bold>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS201301-f008"/></fig><fig id="F9" position="anchor"><label>Extended data Fig. 4</label><caption><title>Ovarian Cancer cell proliferation and apoptosis in collagen and OHGs</title><p id="P51">Average percentage of Ki67+ and cleaved-caspase 3+ cells in collagen or OHG (N &gt; 75 cells).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS201301-f009"/></fig><fig id="F10" position="anchor"><label>Extended data Fig. 5</label><caption><title>Invasion in OHG is enhanced compared to collagen gels.</title><p id="P52"><bold>a</bold>, Collagen-I (grey) and mRFP (red) staining of mRFP-OVCAR8 or mRFP-Tyk-nu cells seeded on peritoneal connective tissue at 28 μm tissue depth. <bold>b</bold>, Quantification of OVCAR8 and Tyk-nu cell invasion depth into peritoneal connective tissue (N = 3 tissues from 1 donor). <bold>c</bold>, Percentage of PAX8- and PAX8+ cells in malignant ascites after 7 days in culture (N ≥ 246 cells). <bold>d</bold>, Quantification of PAX8-cell organotypic invasion depth after 7 days (N = 176 cells from one donor). <bold>e</bold>, Quantification of PAX8+ cell organotypic invasion depth after 7 days (N ≥ 70 cells in 3 donors). <bold>f</bold>, Quantification of invading single CK7+ cells relative to the number of spheroids from HGSC ascites cells embedded in collagen or OHG (N = 4 gels from 1 donor). <bold>g</bold>, Quantification of Ki67+ cells in PAX8+ and PAX8-cells of HGSC ascites cells embedded in collagen or OHG for 7 days (N ≥ 200 cells in two donors). For the data in <bold>b</bold> and <bold>f</bold> a two-sided unpaired t-test was performed. Scale bar, 50 μm (<bold>a</bold>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS201301-f010"/></fig><fig id="F11" position="anchor"><label>Extended data Fig. 6</label><caption><title>FAK-dependent cell invasion causes nuclear flattening but not DNA damage in ovarian cancer cells.</title><p id="P53"><bold>a</bold>, F-actin (grey) and mRFP (red) staining of mRFP-OVCAR8 cells invading human peritoneal adipose tissue explants. <bold>b</bold>, Quantification of nuclear shape parameters in mRFP-OVCAR8 cells invading human peritoneal adipose tissue explants (N = 50-79 cells). <bold>c</bold>, Quantification of Ki67+ cells in PAX8+ and PAX8-cells of HGSC ascites cells embedded in collagen or OHG for 7 days (N ≥ 43 cells in 4 donors). <bold>d</bold>, Normalised intensity of γH2A.X immunofluorescence staining in OVCAR8 cells in collagen or OHG (N ≥ 38 nuclei). <bold>e</bold>, γH2A.X (green) and nuclei (blue) staining of OVCAR8 cells in collagen or OHG. For the data in <bold>b</bold> and <bold>d</bold> a two-sided unpaired t-test was performed. Scale bars, 25 μm (<bold>a</bold>) and 5o μm (<bold>e</bold>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS201301-f011"/></fig><fig id="F12" position="anchor"><label>Extended data Fig. 7</label><caption><title>TGFβ signalling promotes invasion in OHG.</title><p id="P54"><bold>a</bold>, The ten most enriched gene sets from the most significantly upregulated genes in OHG-invasive ovarian cancer cell lines compared to non-invasive lines. <bold>b</bold>, Ten most enriched gene sets from the significantly downregulated genes in OHG-invasive ovarian cancer cell lines compared to non-invasive lines. <bold>c</bold>, CK7 (green), F-actin (grey), and DAPI (blue) staining of HGSC ascites cells embedded in OHG. <bold>d</bold>, Quantification of spheroid area of HGSC ascites cells embedded in OHG (N = 4 gels from 1 donor). <bold>e</bold>, Quantification of invading single CK7+ cells relative to the number of spheroids from HGSC ascites cells embedded in OHG (N = 4 gels from 1 donor). <bold>f</bold>, Quantification of PAX8-cell organotypic invasion depth after 7 days (N = 212 cells from one donor). <bold>g</bold>, Quantification of PAX8+ cell organotypic invasion depth after 7 days (N ≥ 125 cells in 3 donors). For the data in <bold>d</bold> and <bold>e</bold> a two-sided unpaired t-test was performed. Scale bar, 100 μm (<bold>c</bold>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS201301-f012"/></fig><fig id="F13" position="anchor"><label>Extended data Fig. 8</label><caption><title>Cell invasion into adipose tissue is MMP-independent.</title><p id="P55"><bold>a</bold>, Quantification of PAX8-cell organotypic invasion depth after 7 days (N = 504 cells from one donor). <bold>b</bold>, Quantification of PAX8+ cell organotypic invasion depth after 7 days (N ≥ 38 cells in 3 donors). <bold>c</bold>, Quantification of Ki67+ cells in PAX8+ and PAX8-cells of HGSC ascites cells embedded in OHG for 7 days (N ≥ 54 cells in 4 donors). <bold>d</bold>, BODIPY (green), nuclei (red) and F-actin (grey) staining of OVCAR8 spheroids in MMP-Cleavable or non-cleavable (PEGDT) HA-NB OHG. Scale bars, 200 μm (<bold>d</bold>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS201301-f013"/></fig><fig id="F14" position="anchor"><label>Extended data Fig. 9</label><caption><title>Cell invasion into adipose tissue is ROCK-dependent.</title><p id="P56"><bold>a</bold>, BODIPY (green) and nuclei (red) staining of OVCAR8 cells in collagen-based OHG. <bold>b</bold>, Quantification of nuclear aspect ratio of OVCAR8 cells (N = 50 cells). <bold>c</bold>, Quantification of nuclear circularity of OVCAR8 cells (N = 50 cells). <bold>d</bold>, Quantification of PAX8-cell organotypic invasion depth after 7 days (N = 158 cells from one donor). <bold>e</bold>, Quantification of PAX8+ cell organotypic invasion depth after 7 days (N ≥ 79 cells in 3 donors). For the data in <bold>b</bold> and <bold>c</bold> a two-sided unpaired t-test was performed. Scale bars, 50 μm (bottom <bold>a</bold>), 200 μm (top <bold>a</bold>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS201301-f014"/></fig><fig id="F15" position="anchor"><label>Extended data Fig. 10</label><caption><title>Cell-induced deformation is prevented in stiff PDMS microbeads.</title><p id="P57"><bold>a</bold>, <bold>b</bold>, Frequency sweeps (<bold>a</bold>) and shear storage moduli (at 10 rad/s) (<bold>b</bold>) of Sylgard 184 PDMS cured with increasing crosslinker concentrations (N = 3). <bold>c</bold>, Quantification of microbead circularity of microbeads in contact with OVCAR8 cells (N = 25 microbeads). <bold>d</bold>, BODIPY (green), F-actin (grey), and nuclei (red) staining of OVCAR8 spheroids embedded in PDMS OHGs crosslinked with collagen. Yellow arrowheads indicate deformations caused by OVCAR8 cells. One-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) with Tukey’s correction for multiple comparisons was performed for the data in <bold>c</bold>. Scale bar, 100 μm (<bold>d</bold>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS201301-f015"/></fig><fig id="F16" position="anchor"><label>Extended data Fig. 11</label><caption><title>Mechanical characterisation and RGD localisation in NB-HA OHGs.</title><p id="P58"><bold>a</bold>, Quantification of storage modulus of HA-NB OHG formed with emulsions stabilised with BSA or BSA-NB nanosheets and crosslinked with PEGDT (N = 3 gels). <bold>b</bold>, Normalised stress-relaxation curves of HA-NB OHG formed with emulsions stabilised with BSA or BSA-NB nanosheets and crosslinked with PEGDT (N = 3 gels). <bold>c</bold>, F-actin (grey) and nuclei (red) staining of OVCAR8 spheroids after 7 d culture embedded in HA-NB OHG containing BSA or BSA-NB (crosslinked) microdroplets. <bold>d</bold>, Quantification of relative OVCAR8 spheroid area after culture in BSA or BSA-NB NB-HA OHG (N = 11-12 spheroids). <bold>e</bold>, RGD-FITC (green) in HA-NB OHG with controlled RGD localisation. For the data in <bold>a</bold> and <bold>d</bold> a two-sided unpaired t-test was performed. Scale bars, 50 μm (<bold>e</bold>), 200 μm (<bold>c</bold>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS201301-f016"/></fig><fig id="F17" position="anchor"><label>Extended data Fig. 12</label><caption><title>Interfacial protein nanosheet mechanics.</title><p id="P59"><bold>a</bold>, Evolution of the interfacial shear storage modulus of 1 mg/ml BSA and BSA combined with β-casein protein nanosheets formed over NOVEC 7500 oil (0.1 Hz, 1.0x 10<sup>-4</sup> rad). <bold>b</bold>, Evolution of the interfacial shear storage modulus of 1 mg/ml BSA before and after crosslinking with 2 mg/ml sulfo-SMCC. <bold>c</bold>, F-actin (grey) and nuclei (red) of OVCAR8 spheroids in HA-NB OHGs with BSA microdroplet (i.e. RGD presented in the HA phase but not on the microdroplet surface) and varying protein nanosheet interfacial mechanics. <bold>d</bold>, Relative OVCAR8 spheroid area in HA-NB OHGs with HA-presenting RGD and varying protein nanosheet interfacial mechanics (N = 911 spheroids). One-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) with Tukey’s correction for multiple comparisons was performed for the data in <bold>d</bold>. Scale bar, 200 μm (<bold>c</bold>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS201301-f017"/></fig><fig id="F18" position="anchor"><label>Extended data Fig. 13</label><caption><title>Diameter of oil microdroplets used in OHGs.</title><p id="P60">Quantification of droplet diameter of emulsions (N = 170 droplets).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS201301-f018"/></fig><fig id="F19" position="anchor"><label>Extended data Fig. 14</label><caption><title>Droplet size in OHG regulates cell invasion.</title><p id="P61"><bold>a</bold>, Nuclei (grey) staining of OVCAR8 cells at the invasive front of spheroids embedded in OHG of distinct droplet size. <bold>b</bold>, Quantification of nuclear shape descriptors of OVCAR8 cells from the invasive front of spheroids embedded in OHG of varying droplet size. <bold>c</bold>, Nuclei (blue), F-actin (grey), Ki67+, pFAK and pMLC (green, left to right) and pMLC (red) staining of OVCAR8 cells embedded in OHG of 70 or 25 μm diameter droplets. One-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) with Tukey’s correction for multiple comparisons was performed for the data in <bold>a</bold>. Scale bars, 10 μm (<bold>a</bold>), 50 μm (<bold>c</bold>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS201301-f019"/></fig><fig id="F20" position="anchor"><label>Extended data Fig. 15</label><caption><title>TRPV4 activity regulates cell proliferation.</title><p id="P62"><bold>a</bold>, Quantification of OVCAR8 spheroid area in OHG formed with 70 μm droplets upon inhibition with Piezo1 inhibitor GsMTx4 (N = 5-16 spheroids). <bold>b</bold>, OVCAR8 spheroid area in OHG formed with 70 or 25 μm droplets upon treatment with the TRPV4 inhibitor GSK205 or agonist GSK1016790A (N ≥ 15 spheroids). <bold>c</bold>, Nuclei (red) of OVCAR8 cells embedded in OHG. Yellow arrowheads indicate cells at the invasive front. <bold>d</bold>, Cleaved Caspase 3 (grey), nuclei (red) and Ki67 (green) staining of OVCAR8 spheroids embedded in 70 μm droplet OHG for 7 days. <bold>e</bold>, Quantification of Ki67+ and Cleaved caspase 3+ cells from (<bold>d</bold>) (N ≥ 11,779 cells from 9 spheroids). For the data in <bold>a</bold> and <bold>e</bold>, a two-sided unpaired t-test was performed. One-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) with Tukey’s correction for multiple comparisons was performed for the data in <bold>b</bold>. Scale bar, 200 μm (<bold>c</bold> and <bold>d</bold>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS201301-f020"/></fig><fig id="F21" position="anchor"><label>Extended data Fig. 16</label><caption><title>Inhibition of the cPLA2-Arachidonic acid-InsP3Rs pathway does not impair cell invasion.</title><p id="P63"><bold>a</bold>, Quantification of OVCAR8 spheroid area in OHG formed with 70 or 25 μm droplets with perturbed mechanical confinement signalling (N ≥ 16 spheroids). <bold>b</bold>, BODIP (green) and nuclei (red) staining of OVCAR8 cells treated with arachidonic acid and embedded in 70 μm OHG. Yellow arrowheads indicate collectively-invading cells. <bold>c</bold>, BODIPY (green) and nuclei (red) of OVCAR8 cells embedded in 25 μm OHG. Oneway analysis of variance (ANOVA) with Tukey’s correction for multiple comparisons was performed for the data in <bold>a</bold>. Scale bars, 200 μm (<bold>b</bold>, left <bold>c</bold>), 25 μm (right <bold>c</bold>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS201301-f021"/></fig></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="SM"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1"><label>Extended data</label><media xlink:href="EMS201301-supplement-Extended_data.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" id="d17aAcFbB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack id="S30"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank the Biomedicum Imaging Core at Karolinska Institutet for imaging facilities. The authors thank the European Research Council (ProLiCell, 772462; ProBioFac, 966740), the Norwegian Cancer Society (216113), and the Swedish Cancer Society (21 1888 Pj) for support.</p></ack><ref-list><ref id="R1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mazidimoradi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Global patterns and temporal trends in ovarian cancer morbidity, mortality, and burden from 1990 to 2019</article-title><source>Oncologie</source><year>2023</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>641</fpage><lpage>659</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chandra</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Ovarian cancer: Current status and strategies for improving therapeutic outcomes</article-title><source>Cancer Med</source><year>2019</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>7018</fpage><lpage>7031</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6853829</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31560828</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cam4.2560</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schoutrop</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Molecular, cellular and systemic aspects of epithelial ovarian cancer and its tumor microenvironment</article-title><source>Semin Cancer Biol</source><year>2022</year><volume>86</volume><fpage>207</fpage><lpage>223</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35395389</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pradeep</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Hematogenous metastasis of ovarian cancer: rethinking mode of spread</article-title><source>Cancer Cell</source><year>2014</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>77</fpage><lpage>91</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4100212</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25026212</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ccr.2014.05.002</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cortés-Guiral</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Primary and metastatic peritoneal surface malignancies</article-title><source>Nat Rev Dis Prim</source><year>2021</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>91</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34916522</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mistriotis</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Wisniewski</surname><given-names>EO</given-names></name><name><surname>Si</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalab</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Konstantopoulos</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Coordinated in confined migration: crosstalk between the nucleus and ion channel-mediated mechanosensation</article-title><source>Trends Cell Biol</source><year>2024</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11284253</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38290913</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tcb.2024.01.001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Sixt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mechanisms of 3D cell migration</article-title><source>Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol</source><year>2019</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>738</fpage><lpage>752</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31582855</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Charras</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Sahai</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Physical influences of the extracellular environment on cell migration</article-title><source>Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol</source><year>2014</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>813</fpage><lpage>24</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25355506</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Winkler</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Abisoye-Ogunniyan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Metcalf</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Werb</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Concepts of extracellular matrix remodelling in tumour progression and metastasis</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2020</year><volume>11</volume><elocation-id>5120</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7547708</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33037194</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-020-18794-x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McKee</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Perlman</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Komarova</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Extracellular matrix composition of connective tissues: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2019</year><volume>9</volume><elocation-id>10542</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6646303</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31332239</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-019-46896-0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gonzalez-Molina</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>MMP14 in Sarcoma: A Regulator of Tumor Microenvironment Communication in Connective Tissues</article-title><source>Cells</source><year>2019</year><volume>8</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6770050</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31466240</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/cells8090991</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ashkenas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Muschler</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bissell</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The extracellular matrix in epithelial biology: shared molecules and common themes in distant phyla</article-title><source>Dev Biol</source><year>1996</year><volume>180</volume><fpage>433</fpage><lpage>44</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3815653</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8954716</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/dbio.1996.0317</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gillies</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Lieber</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structure and function of the skeletal muscle extracellular matrix</article-title><source>Muscle Nerve</source><year>2011</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>318</fpage><lpage>31</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3177172</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21949456</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/mus.22094</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pearce</surname><given-names>OMT</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Deconstruction of a Metastatic Tumor Microenvironment Reveals a Common Matrix Response in Human Cancers</article-title><source>Cancer Discov</source><year>2018</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>304</fpage><lpage>319</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5837004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29196464</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1158/2159-8290.CD-17-0284</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Elosegui-Artola</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Matrix viscoelasticity controls spatiotemporal tissue organization</article-title><source>Nat Mater</source><year>2023</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>117</fpage><lpage>127</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10332325</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36456871</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41563-022-01400-4</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Irianto</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>DNA Damage Follows Repair Factor Depletion and Portends Genome Variation in Cancer Cells after Pore Migration</article-title><source>Curr Biol</source><year>2017</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>210</fpage><lpage>223</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5262636</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27989676</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2016.11.049</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pfeifer</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Constricted migration increases DNA damage and independently represses cell cycle</article-title><source>Mol Biol Cell</source><year>2018</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>1948</fpage><lpage>1962</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6232975</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29742017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1091/mbc.E18-02-0079</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dongre</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Weinberg</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>New insights into the mechanisms of epithelial-mesenchymal transition and implications for cancer</article-title><source>Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol</source><year>2019</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>69</fpage><lpage>84</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30459476</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Malacrida</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A human multi-cellular model shows how platelets drive production of diseased extracellular matrix and tissue invasion</article-title><source>iScience</source><year>2021</year><volume>24</volume><elocation-id>102676</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8215303</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34189439</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.isci.2021.102676</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yeung</surname><given-names>T-L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>TGF-β modulates ovarian cancer invasion by upregulating CAF-derived versican in the tumor microenvironment</article-title><source>Cancer Res</source><year>2013</year><volume>73</volume><fpage>5016</fpage><lpage>28</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3745588</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23824740</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-13-0023</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamamura</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The activated transforming growth factor-beta signaling pathway in peritoneal metastases is a potential therapeutic target in ovarian cancer</article-title><source>Int J cancer</source><year>2012</year><volume>130</volume><fpage>20</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21503873</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Friedl</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolf</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Proteolytic interstitial cell migration: a five-step process</article-title><source>Cancer Metastasis Rev</source><year>2009</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>129</fpage><lpage>135</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19153672</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wolf</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Physical limits of cell migration: Control by ECM space and nuclear deformation and tuning by proteolysis and traction force</article-title><source>J Cell Biol</source><year>2013</year><volume>201</volume><fpage>1069</fpage><lpage>1084</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3691458</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23798731</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.201210152</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Megone</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Gautrot</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Extreme reversal in mechanical anisotropy in liquid-liquid interfaces reinforced with self-assembled protein nanosheets</article-title><source>J Colloid Interface Sci</source><year>2021</year><volume>594</volume><fpage>650</fpage><lpage>657</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33780768</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chrysanthou</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bosch-Fortea</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gautrot</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Co-Surfactant-Free Bioactive Protein Nanosheets for the Stabilization of Bioemulsions Enabling Adherent Cell Expansion</article-title><source>Biomacromolecules</source><year>2023</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>4465</fpage><lpage>4477</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10565825</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36683574</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.biomac.2c01289</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Mesenchymal Stem Cells Sense the Toughness of Nanomaterials and Interfaces</article-title><source>Adv Healthc Mater</source><year>2023</year><volume>12</volume><elocation-id>e2203297</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11468436</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36717365</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/adhm.202203297</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mojares</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Strong Elastic Protein Nanosheets Enable the Culture and Differentiation of Induced Pluripotent Stem Cells on Microdroplets</article-title><source>Adv Mater</source><year>2024</year><volume>36</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39036832</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chrysanthou</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bosch-Fortea</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nadal</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Zarbakhsh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gautrot</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Interfacial mechanics of β-casein and albumin mixed protein assemblies at liquid-liquid interfaces</article-title><source>J Colloid Interface Sci</source><year>2024</year><volume>674</volume><fpage>379</fpage><lpage>391</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38941932</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Venturini</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The nucleus measures shape changes for cellular proprioception to control dynamic cell behavior</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2020</year><volume>370</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33060331</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lomakin</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The nucleus acts as a ruler tailoring cell responses to spatial constraints</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2020</year><volume>370</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8059074</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33060332</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.aba2894</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nam</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cell cycle progression in confining microenvironments is regulated by a growth-responsive TRPV4-PI3K/Akt-p27Kip1 signaling axis</article-title><source>Sci Adv</source><year>2019</year><volume>5</volume><elocation-id>eaaw6171</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6685709</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31457089</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/sciadv.aaw6171</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>TRPV4 enhances the synthesis of fatty acids to drive the progression of ovarian cancer through the calcium-mTORC1/SREBP1 signaling pathway</article-title><source>iScience</source><year>2023</year><volume>26</volume><elocation-id>108226</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10637939</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37953947</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.isci.2023.108226</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Solbu</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Assessing cell migration in hydrogels: An overview of relevant materials and methods</article-title><source>Mater today Bio</source><year>2023</year><volume>18</volume><elocation-id>100537</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9842866</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36659998</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mtbio.2022.100537</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nih</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name><name><surname>Sideris</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Carmichael</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name><name><surname>Segura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Injection of Microporous Annealing Particle (MAP) Hydrogels in the Stroke Cavity Reduces Gliosis and Inflammation and Promotes NPC Migration to the Lesion</article-title><source>Adv Mater</source><year>2017</year><volume>29</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5595584</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28650574</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/adma.201606471</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Riley</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Schirmer</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Segura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Granular hydrogels: emergent properties of jammed hydrogel microparticles and their applications in tissue repair and regeneration</article-title><source>Curr Opin Biotechnol</source><year>2019</year><volume>60</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6534490</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30481603</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.copbio.2018.11.001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chiu</surname><given-names>Y-C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The role of pore size on vascularization and tissue remodeling in PEG hydrogels</article-title><source>Biomaterials</source><year>2011</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>6045</fpage><lpage>51</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21663958</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Qazi</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Anisotropic Rod-Shaped Particles Influence Injectable Granular Hydrogel Properties and Cell Invasion</article-title><source>Adv Mater</source><year>2022</year><volume>34</volume><elocation-id>e2109194</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8957565</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34932833</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/adma.202109194</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The prognostic values of matrix metalloproteinases in ovarian cancer</article-title><source>J Int Med Res</source><year>2020</year><volume>48</volume><elocation-id>300060519825983</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7140190</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31099295</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0300060519825983</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bruney</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Conley</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name><name><surname>Moss</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Stack</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Membrane-type I matrix metalloproteinase-dependent ectodomain shedding of mucin16/CA-125 on ovarian cancer cells modulates adhesion and invasion of peritoneal mesothelium</article-title><source>Biol Chem</source><year>2014</year><volume>395</volume><fpage>1221</fpage><lpage>31</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5568695</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25205731</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1515/hsz-2014-0155</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kenny</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lengyel</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MMP-2 functions as an early response protein in ovarian cancer metastasis</article-title><source>Cell Cycle</source><year>2009</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>683</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2840625</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19221481</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4161/cc.8.5.7703</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R41"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pietilä</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Co-evolution of matrisome and adaptive adhesion dynamics drives ovarian cancer chemoresistance</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2021</year><volume>12</volume><elocation-id>3904</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8222388</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34162871</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-021-24009-8</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R42"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Turunen</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Tatti-Bugaeva</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Lehti</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Membrane-type matrix metalloproteases as diverse effectors of cancer progression</article-title><source>Biochim Biophys acta Mol cell Res</source><year>2017</year><volume>1864</volume><fpage>1974</fpage><lpage>1988</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28390905</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R43"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gonzalez-Molina</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Chemotherapy as a regulator of extracellular matrixcell communication: Implications in therapy resistance</article-title><source>Semin Cancer Biol</source><year>2022</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35331851</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R44"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zulueta-Coarasa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Fadul</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosenblatt</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Physical confinement promotes mesenchymal trans-differentiation of invading transformed cells in vivo</article-title><source>iScience</source><year>2022</year><volume>25</volume><elocation-id>105330</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9618776</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36325066</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.isci.2022.105330</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R45"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hunter</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Mechanical confinement governs phenotypic plasticity in melanoma</article-title><source>bioRxiv</source><year>2024</year><elocation-id>2024.01.30.577120</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2024.01.30.577120</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R46"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Natarajan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Collagen Remodeling in the Hypoxic Tumor-Mesothelial Niche Promotes Ovarian Cancer Metastasis</article-title><source>Cancer Res</source><year>2019</year><volume>79</volume><fpage>2271</fpage><lpage>2284</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6822898</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30862717</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-18-2616</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R47"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Au-Yeung</surname><given-names>C-L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>ITLN1 modulates invasive potential and metabolic reprogramming of ovarian cancer cells in omental microenvironment</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2020</year><volume>11</volume><elocation-id>3546</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7363861</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32669559</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-020-17383-2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R48"><label>48</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Fibroblasts in omentum activated by tumor cells promote ovarian cancer growth, adhesion and invasiveness</article-title><source>Carcinogenesis</source><year>2012</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>20</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22021907</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R49"><label>49</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nieman</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Romero</surname><given-names>IL</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Houten</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Lengyel</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Adipose tissue and adipocytes support tumorigenesis and metastasis</article-title><source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source><year>2013</year><volume>1831</volume><fpage>1533</fpage><lpage>41</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3742583</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23500888</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbalip.2013.02.010</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R50"><label>50</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moyano-Galceran</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Adaptive RSK-EphA2-GPRC5A signaling switch triggers chemotherapy resistance in ovarian cancer</article-title><source>EMBO Mol Med</source><year>2020</year><volume>12</volume><elocation-id>e11177</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7136956</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32115889</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15252/emmm.201911177</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><title>Ovarian cancer invasive behaviour is reproduced in adipose tissuemimicking OHGs.</title><p><bold>a</bold>, Schematic representation of adipose tissue-mimicking collagen-based OHGs. <bold>b</bold>, BODIPY (green) staining of human peritoneal adipose tissue and OHG. <bold>c</bold>, Storage moduli of hydrogels and human peritoneal tissues (N = 2-3 gels or tissues). <bold>d</bold>, Normalised stress-relaxation curves of hydrogels and human peritoneal tissues (N = 2-3 gels or tissues). <bold>e</bold>, Relative spheroid area comparison of multiple ovarian cancer cell lines after 7 d in collagen or OHGs (N ≥ 3 spheroids). <bold>f</bold>, Ki67 (green) and DAPI (blue) staining of OVCAR8 spheroids in collagen or OHG after 7 days. <bold>g</bold>, Collagen-I (grey) and mRFP-OVCAR8 nuclei (red) staining of OVCAR8 cells seeded on top of collagen or OHG at 25 μm gel depth. <bold>h</bold>, Quantification of invading OVCAR8 cells (N = 3). <bold>i</bold>, BODIPY (green), mRFP-OVCAR8 (red), and collagen I (grey) staining of peritoneal tissue explants and mRFP-OVCAR8 cells. <bold>j</bold>, Quantification of mRFP-OVCAR8 depth of invasion into human peritoneal tissues (N = 3 tissues from distinct donors). For the data in <bold>e, h</bold> and <bold>j</bold>, a two-sided unpaired t-test was performed. Error bars in (<bold>c</bold>) represent the s.e.m. Scale bars, 50 μm (<bold>b, g</bold>), 100 μm (<bold>i</bold>), 200 μm (<bold>f</bold>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS201301-f001"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><title>ECM adhesion and TGFβ signalling regulate cell invasion in OHGs.</title><p><bold>a</bold>, pFAK, pMLC, YAP/TAZ (green; left to right) and nuclei (blue) staining of OVCAR8 cells in collagen or OHG after 24 h in culture. <bold>b</bold>, Normalised intensity of IF stainings of cytoplasmic pFAK, pMLC, and cytoplasmic:nuclear ratio of YAP/TAZ in OVCAR8 cells embedded in collagen or OHG (N ≥ 24 cells). <bold>c</bold>, F-actin (yellow), nucleus (blue) and BODIPY (grey) staining of an OVCAR8 cell spread at the ECM-microdroplet interface. <bold>d</bold>, Shape descriptors of OVCAR8 nuclei in collagen or OHG (N ≥ 53 nuclei). <bold>e</bold>, Relative spheroid area of OVCAR8 after 7 d in OHG (N ≥ 10 spheroids). <bold>f</bold>, BODIPY (green) and mRFP (red) staining of peritoneal adipose tissue explants and mRFP-OVCAR8 cells (49 μm into the tissue from the surface). <bold>g</bold>, Quantification of mRFP-OVCAR8 depth of invasion into human peritoneal tissues (N = 3 tissues from distinct donors). <bold>h</bold>, Nuclei (red) of OVCAR8 cells in OHGs after 7 days treatment. <bold>i</bold>, Quantification of spheroid area relative to DMSO control of OVCAR8 cells in OHGs (N = 14-15 spheroids). <bold>i</bold>, F-actin (green) and nuclei staining of CAOV3 spheroids embedded in OHGs. <bold>k</bold>, Quantification of spheroid area in CAOV3 cells in OHGs (N = 6 spheroids). <bold>l</bold>, F-actin (green) and nuclei (blue) staining of Kuramochi spheroids in collagen or OHG or in OHG and treated with TGFβ. For the data in <bold>b, d, i</bold> and <bold>k</bold> a two-sided unpaired t-test was performed. For data in <bold>e</bold>, a two-sided unpaired t-test was performed. Scale bars, 25 μm (<bold>a, c</bold>), 100 μm (<bold>f, I</bold>), 200 μm (<bold>h, j</bold>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS201301-f002"/></fig><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><title>Cell invasion into adipose tissues is MMP-independent.</title><p><bold>a</bold>, Schematic representation of NB-HA-based OHGs presenting MMP-degradable crosslinking peptides and cell adhesion ligands. <bold>b</bold>, Storage moduli of collagen- and HA-NB OHG (N = 2-3 gels). <bold>c</bold>, Normalised stress-relaxation curves of collagen- and HA-NB OHG (N = 2-3 gels). <bold>d</bold> F-actin (grey) and nuclei (red) in OVCAR8 cells embedded in collagen- or NB-HA-based OHGs for 7 d. <bold>e</bold>, Relative OVCAR8 spheroid area in collagen- or NB-HA-based OHGs (N = 9-10 spheroids). <bold>f</bold>, F-actin (grey) and nuclei (red) of OVCAR8 cells embedded in GFOGER- or RGD-presenting HA-NB OHG. <bold>g</bold>, BODIPY (green), nuclei (red), and F-actin (grey) of OVCAR8 in GFOGER- or RGD-presenting HA-NB OHG. Yellow arrowheads indicate cells in direct contact with oil droplets. <bold>h</bold>, Relative OVCAR8 spheroid area in GFOGER- or RGD-presenting HA-NB OHG (N = 9-11 spheroids). <bold>i</bold>, F-actin (grey) and nuclei (red) in OVCAR8 cells embedded in collagen- based OHGs, <bold>j</bold>, Relative OVCAR8 spheroid area in collagen-based OHGs (N = 8-9 spheroids). <bold>k</bold>, BODIPY (green) and mRFP (red) staining of peritoneal adipose tissue explants and mRFP-OVCAR8 cells. <bold>l</bold>, Quantification of mRFP-OVCAR8 depth of invasion into human peritoneal tissues (N = 3 tissues from distinct donors). <bold>m</bold>, Relative OVCAR8 spheroid area quantifications in MMP-cleavable or non-cleavable HA-NB OHG (N = 11-12 spheroids). For the data in <bold>e, h, j</bold> and <bold>l</bold>, a two-sided unpaired t-test was performed. One-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) with Tukey’s correction for multiple comparisons was performed for the data in m. Scale bars, 100 μm (<bold>g, k</bold>), 200 μm (<bold>d, f, i</bold>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS201301-f003"/></fig><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><title>Microdroplet mechanical anisotropy enables cell invasion.</title><p><bold>a</bold>, F-actin (grey) and DAPI (blue) in OVCAR8 cells embedded in collagen or collagen-based OHG. Microdroplets are indicated with (*). <bold>b</bold>, BODIPY (green), F-actin (grey) and nuclei (blue) staining of OVCAR8 cells embedded in collagen-based OHG (left) or BODIPY (green), mRFP (red) staining of mRFP-OVCAR8 cells invading into peritoneal adipose tissue (right). Arrowheads indicate oil droplet (left) and adipocyte (right) deformations at the contact points with cells. <bold>c</bold>, Quantification OVCAR8 cell invasion depth into peritoneal adipose tissue (N = 3 tissues from 1 donor). <bold>d</bold>, Schematic representation of the Sylgard 184 PDMS-based OGH. <bold>e</bold>, F-actin (grey) and nuclei (red) staining of OVCAR8 spheroids embedded in collagen-based OHGs prepared with PDMS microdroplets of varying stiffness. <bold>f</bold>, Relative OVCAR8 spheroid area in collagen-based OHGs with PDMS microdroplets prepared with varying crosslinker percentage (N = 10-11 spheroids). <bold>g</bold>, Schematic representation of the NB-HA OGH with NB-BSA used for RGD presentation at the microdroplet surface. <bold>h</bold>, F-actin (grey) and nuclei (red) of OVCAR8 spheroids in HA-NB OHG with localised presentation of RGD (left). Relative OVCAR8 spheroid area in HA-NB OHG with localised RGD presentation (N = 11-12 spheroids; top right). BODIPY (green), nuclei (red), and F-actin (grey) staining of OVCAR8 cells in HA-NB OHG presenting RGD on the droplet surface (bottom right). Yellow arrowhead indicates a cell spreading at the droplet-HA interface. <bold>i</bold>, Schematic representation of the system to modulate microdroplet interfacial mechanics. <bold>j</bold>, F-actin (grey) and nuclei (red) of OVCAR8 spheroids in HA-NB OHGs with microdroplet-presenting RGD and microdroplet interfacial modulus. <bold>k</bold>, Relative OVCAR8 spheroid area in HA-NB OHGs with microdroplet-presenting RGD and varying protein nanosheet interfacial mechanics (N = 9-13 spheroids). For the data in <bold>c</bold> and <bold>h</bold>, a two-sided unpaired t-test was performed. One-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) with Tukey’s correction for multiple comparisons was performed for the data in <bold>f</bold> and <bold>k</bold>. Scale bars, 25 μm (<bold>a, b</bold>), 50 μm (<bold>h</bold>; bottom right), 200 μm (<bold>e, h</bold> left, <bold>j</bold>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS201301-f004"/></fig><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><title>Microdroplet size and volume fraction regulate invasion and migration mode.</title><p><bold>a</bold>, Schematic representation of the OHGs with varying microdroplet diameter and volume fraction. <bold>b</bold>, Storage modulus of collagen-based OHG with distinct droplet size. <bold>c</bold>, Normalised stress-relaxation curves of collagen-based OHG with distinct droplet size. <bold>d</bold>, BODIPY (green) and F-actin (red) and nuclei (blue) staining of OVCAR8 cells in collagen-based OHG of 70 or 25 μm diameter droplets. Yellow arrowheads indicate cells at the invasive front. <bold>e</bold>, Quantification of relative OVCAR8 spheroid area in collagen-based OHG of distinct emulsion percentage of volume fraction and droplet diameter (N ≥ 13 spheroids). <bold>f</bold>, Quantification of interdroplet distance in OHG (N = 100 droplets). <bold>g</bold>, Quantification of the percentage of invasive front OVCAR8 cells in contact with droplets in OHG (N ≥ 121 cells in 3 gels). <bold>h</bold>, LAP2 (red) staining of OVCAR8 cells embedded in collagen or in contact with droplets of OHG with distinct droplet size. <bold>i</bold>, Quantification of Ki67+, and relative cytoplasmic expression of pFAK, pMLC, and nuclear:cytoplasmic ratio of YAP/TAZ in OVCAR8 cells embedded in OHG of 70 or 25 μm diameter droplets (N ≥ 55 cells). <bold>j</bold>, F-actin (green) and DAPI (blue) staining of CAOV3 spheroids embedded in collagen-based 25 μm droplet OHG in the presence or absence of TGFβ. <bold>k</bold>, Quantification of CAOV3 spheroid area relative to non-TGFβ-treated control (N = 6 spheroids). <bold>l</bold>, Schematic illustration of the cell force-dependent invasion of adipose tissue enabled by the anisotropic mechanics of OHGs and the generation of migration tracks at the ECM-adipocyte/microdroplet interface. For the data in <bold>f</bold>, <bold>g</bold>, <bold>i</bold> and <bold>k</bold> a two-sided unpaired t-test was performed. Scale bars, 25 μm (<bold>h</bold>) 50 μm (bottom panels in <bold>d</bold>, <bold>j</bold>), 200 μm (top panels in <bold>d</bold>, <bold>j</bold>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS201301-f005"/></fig></floats-group></article>