<!DOCTYPE article
 PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" article-type="preprint"><?all-math-mml yes?><?use-mml?><?origin ukpmcpa?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">bioRxiv</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>bioRxiv : the preprint server for biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2692-8205</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">EMS202329</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2024.12.18.629151</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="archive">PPR958169</article-id><article-version-alternatives><article-version article-version-type="status">preprint</article-version><article-version article-version-type="number">1</article-version></article-version-alternatives><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Scavenger receptor CD163 multimerises to allow uptake of diverse ligands</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Richard X.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Higgins</surname><given-names>Matthew K.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CR1">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Department of Biochemistry, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/052gg0110</institution-id><institution>University of Oxford</institution></institution-wrap>, <addr-line>South Parks Road</addr-line>, <city>Oxford</city><postal-code>OX1 3QU</postal-code>, <country country="GB">United Kingdom</country></aff><aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Kavli Institute for Nanoscience Discovery, Dorothy Crowfoot Hodgkin Building, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/052gg0110</institution-id><institution>University of Oxford</institution></institution-wrap>, <addr-line>South Parks Road</addr-line>, <city>Oxford</city>, <postal-code>OX1 3QU</postal-code>, <country country="GB">United Kingdom</country></aff><author-notes><corresp id="CR1">
<label>*</label>Corresponding author: <email>matthew.higgins@bioch.ox.ac.uk</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted"><day>17</day><month>01</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="preprint"><day>20</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><permissions><ali:free_to_read/><license><ali:license_ref>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is licensed under a <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0 International license</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p id="P1">Scavenger receptors mediate cellular uptake of diverse ligands. CD163 is an archetypal scavenger receptor with a primary role in haemoglobin detoxification. Haemoglobin released from lysed erythrocytes causes oxidative damage. This is countered by formation of haemoglobin-haptoglobin complexes and CD163-mediated uptake into macrophages for degradation. Different haptoglobin isoforms form stoichiometrically diverse haptoglobin-haemoglobin complexes which must all be recognised by CD163. We show that CD163 forms multimeric complexes, with calcium-mediated interactions forming a trimeric base. Arms emerge from this base, moulding around the ligand to form a single promiscuous ligand-binding site. The arms can also bind to arms of adjacent protomers, blocking the ligand-binding surfaces in an autoinhibited state. This results in a scavenger receptor that can recognise diverse haemoglobin-containing complexes, allowing physiologically important detoxification.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec id="S1" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p id="P2">Transport of oxygen in mammalian blood is mediated by haemoglobin (Hb) tetramers which circulate within erythrocytes. But free Hb is toxic, due to the reactive properties of the haem group, which can engage in oxidative reactions and generate free radicals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">3</xref>). Hb can be released from erythrocytes due to haemolysis or tissue damage and free Hb increases in chronic conditions such as sickle cell anaemia (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">4</xref>) or during infections such as malaria (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref>). Mammals have therefore evolved a system to detoxify free Hb.</p><p id="P3">Hb detoxification involves the abundant serum protein, haptoglobin (Hp). The serine protease (SP) domain of Hp binds to an Hb αβ-dimer (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref>). Hp also contains complement control protein (CCP) domains, which differ in number in the two isoforms found in humans (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">8</xref>). In people homozygous for isoform 1, a single CCP domain per Hp chain mediates dimer formation, creating a ‘dumbbell’-shaped haptoglobin-haemoglobin (HpHb) complex with two ‘heads’. In contrast, isoform 2 allows formation of higher-order oligomeric states in individuals who are either homozygous for isoform 2 or heterozygous (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref>). The formation of HpHb complexes buries reactive groups on Hb and reduces their capacity to cause oxidative damage (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref>).</p><p id="P4">The second step in detoxification is uptake of HpHb into macrophages. This is mediated by CD163 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref>), which is the archetypal class I scavenger receptor. CD163 contains an ectodomain consisting of nine scavenger receptor cysteine-rich (SRCR) domains linked to a C-terminal transmembrane helix (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref>). CD163 must bind to very different architectures of HpHb complexes formed from different Hp isoforms and mediate their endocytosis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref>). In contrast, free Hp is not recognised (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref>), ensuring that it is not depleted unnecessarily from the serum. Finally, HpHb complexes should be released in the endosomes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref>), allowing degradation and detoxification of Hb. CD163 is also exploited by viruses for host cell entry. These include the simian haemorrhagic fever virus, which has zoonotic potential (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref>), and the major livestock pathogen, porcine reproductive and respiratory syndrome virus (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref>), which is responsible for estimated annual losses of $600 million (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref>). While the structure of isoform 1 HpHb complex has been determined (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref>), little was known about how CD163 selectively binds to a structurally diverse range of HpHb complexes, why it does not bind to Hp and how it releases its ligand. We therefore combined cryogenic electron microscopy, biophysics and cell-based uptake assays to understand the molecular mechanism of CD163-mediated ligand uptake and release.</p></sec><sec id="S2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="S3"><title>The structural basis for binding of haptoglobin-haemoglobin to CD163</title><p id="P5">To understand how human CD163 binds to HpHb, we expressed the complete ectodomain in HEK293 cells. Hp(1-1)Hb complexes were assembled by mixing human Hp isoform 1 with human Hb and were combined with CD163 ectodomain (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S1a</xref>). The complex was purified by size-exclusion chromatography and grids were prepared for cryogenic electron microscopy. Data were collected on a Titan Krios and processed using SIMPLE (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">20</xref>) and CryoSPARC (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">21</xref>) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S2 and Table S1</xref>), resulting in two predominant three-dimensional classes. In both cases, we observed a single SP domain of Hp bound to an Hb αβ-dimer and this was coordinated by either two or three CD163 ectodomains (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1a,b</xref>). Indeed, size-exclusion chromatography with multi-angle laser light scattering (SEC-MALLS) showed concentration-dependent multimer formation in solution, with addition of HpHb increasing the fraction of multimeric complexes (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S1b,c</xref>).</p><p id="P6">The CD163 ectodomain adopts an architecture consisting of a ‘base’, formed from SRCR domains 5-9, linked to a four-domain ‘arm’ (SRCR1-4), of which two or three domains were ordered (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1c</xref>). The five domains of the base form a compact assembly which folds to bring SRCR5 and SRCR9 from the same monomer together. Multimer-formation is mediated by the base, predominantly due to interactions between SRCR7 of one subunit and SRCR9 of its neighbour (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1d</xref>). These interfaces contain spheres of density, which we attribute to be calcium ions, as calcium is required for HpHb binding and uptake (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">22</xref>). The three interfaces within the trimer differ, with ‘rocking’ motions around these calcium ions leading to different relative positions of the two protomers (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1d</xref>).</p><p id="P7">The CD163 trimer has a flat triangular base, with the C-termini, which link to transmembrane helices, emerging from the flat surface (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1a</xref>). Protruding in the opposite direction are the arms, which extend away from the membrane. These three arms collectively form a binding site for one head of HpHb, with each arm interacting with a different surface of the head. The dimer adopts a similar global architecture, with the CD163<sub>A</sub> arm making the same contacts with HpHb as in the trimer, but with the second arm making different interactions. While each arm adopts a very similar conformation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1c</xref>), flexibility in their relative positions occurs due to the rocking motion within the base (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1e</xref>). This allows the arms to emerge from the base at different angles and to make different contacts with the asymmetric HpHb head. Flexibility of the CD163 base therefore allows its arms to mould to the ligand, likely allowing a scavenger receptor to create different binding sites for differently structured ligands.</p></sec><sec id="S4"><title>Structures of unliganded CD163 suggest a mechanism of autoinhibition</title><p id="P8">To determine whether the HpHb binding site is pre-formed in the absence of ligand, we also used cryogenic electron microscopy to reveal the structure of unliganded CD163. In this case, particles were distributed into three distinct three-dimensional classes (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S3</xref>). The first class showed a trimeric arrangement of CD163 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2a</xref>). Here, the base was well-resolved, adopting a similar conformation to that observed in the presence of ligand. In contrast, the density for the arms was poorly defined.</p><p id="P9">The other two three-dimensional classes revealed dimeric and trimeric arrangements of the unliganded receptor in which the arms of neighbouring protomers form contacts with each other. In the dimeric form, SRCR2 and SRCR3 of CD163<sub>A</sub> interact with SRCR3 and SRCR4 of CD163<sub>B</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2b,c</xref>). In the trimeric form, the same contacts between CD163<sub>A</sub> and CD163<sub>B</sub> are observed, with additional weaker density for the arm of CDI63<sub>C</sub>, showing it to contact the arms of the other two subunits (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S5</xref>). The surfaces of the SRCR domains which mediate contacts between the arms overlap with those which interact with HpHb (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2d</xref>). Contacts between arms will compete with ligand-binding interactions and the arms must move apart to create a ligand-binding site.</p><p id="P10">Unliganded CD163 on the surface of macrophages is therefore likely to exist in an equilibrium in which the arms are either available for ligand binding or interact together, occluding ligand binding. Interactions between arm and ligand will be in competition with interactions between neighbouring arms, providing a mechanism of autoinhibition. This could ensure that very weak ligands, which cannot compete with these arm-arm interactions, are not internalised.</p></sec><sec id="S5"><title>CD163 mediates uptake of ligands with different stoichiometries and structures</title><p id="P11">Analysis of the HpHb-bound trimer shows that each arm of CD163 interacts differently with HpHb (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3a</xref>). CD163<sub>A</sub> interacts with the Hb α-subunit through SRCR3 and SRCR4, and with Hp through SRCR2. CD163<sub>B</sub> recognises the β-subunit of Hb through SRCR3 and SRCR4 and CD163<sub>C</sub> binds to the α-subunit of Hb through SRCR3 and SRCR4 and to Hp through SRCR3. Remarkably, it is the same faces of these SRCR domains which mediate different interactions with different surface features of HpHb, with the plasticity of the HpHb-binding site forming an asymmetric binding site, despite being formed from a homotrimer of receptors.</p><p id="P12">HpHb complexes are found in a variety of multimeric states. The dumbbell-shaped Hp(1-1)Hb is formed when an Hp(1-1) dimer, presenting two protomers of HpSP, binds to an Hb αβ-dimer on each end (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref>). In contrast, higher-order multimeric states of Hp are found in people homozygous for isoform 2, leading to formation of Hp(2-2)Hb (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3b</xref>). We observed that the three arms of CD163 come together to interact with a single head of HpHb, with weak density for the CCP domain of Hp projecting away from the membrane towards the other head (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1b</xref>). This leads to the hypothesis that HpHb complexes formed from different isoforms, and an artificial version containing just the HpSP domain bound to the Hb dimer (HpSPHb), would show similar binding and uptake properties. The structure also showed that the ˜68 % of the CD163 interaction surface on the HpHb complex is mediated by Hb subunits, with ˜32 % due to Hp, suggesting that CD163 might mediate Hb uptake more efficiently than that of Hp. Additionally, human sera contains haptoglobin-related protein (Hpr) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">23</xref>) and a complex of Hpr and Hb is part of the trypanolytic factor which kills African trypanosomes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">25</xref>). It is important that this is not taken up into human macrophages (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref>), where it might cause cell death. Polymorphisms between Hp and Hpr are found in residues which contact CD163 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3c</xref>), suggesting that they might prevent binding. To test these predictions, we developed binding and uptake assays and assessed the outcomes for different ligands.</p><p id="P13">We first assembled Hp(1-1)Hb, Hp(2-2)Hb, HpSPHb and a complex of the SP domain of Hpr bound to Hb (HprSPHb). We coupled the CD163 ectodomain with a biotinylated BAP tag at the C-terminus to a surface plasmon resonance (SPR) chip surface, ensuring presentation with an orientation which matches that on a membrane. We then flowed the different HpHb complexes over the surface. Hp(1-1)Hb, Hp(2-2)Hb and HpSPHb bound with apparent affinities of 0.28, 0.16 and 1.3 nM, supporting the hypothesis that CD163 trimers recognise a single HpHb head (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3d</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S6a and Table S3</xref>). In contrast, HprSPHb showed no binding at a concentration of 20 nM. This assay could not be used to measure the affinity for Hb and Hp, due to irregular shape of the SPR sensorgrams and to high non-specific binding. We instead used microscale thermophoresis (MST), which revealed affinities of 0.19 μM for Hb and 27 μM for Hp (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3e</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S7 and Table S3</xref>). Therefore, HpHb binds to CD163 most tightly, followed by Hb, with little binding observed for Hp or HprSPHb.</p><p id="P14">In addition, we used a cell-based uptake assay in which HEK293 cells were transfected with full-length CD163 modified with a cytoplasmic GFP tag (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref>). We showed that uptake of fluorescently labelled Hp(2-2)Hb in HEK293 cells increases nearly 10-fold in the presence of CD163 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S8a</xref>). We then assessed the ability of different concentrations of heads of unlabelled ligands to compete for the uptake of 50 nM labelled Hp(2-2)Hb, as quantified by fluorescence-activated cell sorting (FACS) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3f</xref>). Our BSA negative control and unconjugated Hp isoform 1 both showed a similar concentration dependence, suggesting no receptor-mediated uptake of Hp at 4 μM concentration. As Hp is normally found in sera at concentrations of 5-30 μM (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">26</xref>), receptor-mediated internalisation will be low. In contrast Hp(1-1)Hb, Hp(2-2)Hb and HpSPHb all competed with similar IC<sub>50</sub> values of 33, 40 and 41 nM, while Hb competed with a greater IC<sub>50</sub> of 0.25 μM. HprSPHb showed some specific uptake at concentrations above 2 μM, which is greater than the normal serum concentration of ˜ 1 μM (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref>). Therefore, uptake experiments and binding studies were consistent, showing that all HpHb variants are equally endocytosed at low concentration, while Hp is not. Free Hb will be endocytosed at higher concentrations, which may be physiologically important in disease or infection where haemolysis results in Hp depletion.</p></sec><sec id="S6"><title>Calcium regulates CD163 multimer formation and HpHb uptake</title><p id="P15">The structure of the CD163 trimer bound to HpHb revealed spheres of density, which we attribute to be calcium ions, present both at the interfaces between the protomers, and at the interface between the arm of CD163<sub>A</sub> and HpHb (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4a</xref>). We therefore assessed whether calcium is important for CD163 multimer formation and for HpHb binding and uptake.</p><p id="P16">We used SEC-MALLS to assess the multimeric state of liganded CD163. In the presence of 2.5 mM CaCl<sub>2</sub> at pH 7.5, the ectodomain showed concentration-dependent multimerisation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4b</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S1c</xref>). In contrast, in the absence of calcium, at a lower pH of 6 or when CaCl<sub>2</sub> is replaced by 2.5 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, CD163 was monomeric. We also used SPR to test whether the presence of calcium is required for HpHb binding. While Hp(1-1)Hb bound with an affinity of 0.28 nM in the presence of calcium (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3d</xref>), no binding was observed in the absence of calcium, in the presence of 2.5 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub> or at pH 6 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4b</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S6b</xref>).</p><p id="P17">Finally, we assessed the importance of calcium for uptake into HEK293 cells expressing CD163. As the media used for these experiments contains ˜ 1.8 mM CaCl<sub>2</sub>, we performed the assays in the presence of 2 mM EGTA to chelate calcium. While EGTA had no effect on uptake of transferrin (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S8b</xref>), suggesting that it did not negatively affect global endocytosis, it resulted in a reduction of HpHb uptake to levels observed for cells lacking CD163 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4c</xref>). Therefore, calcium, together with pH, mediates formation of CD163 multimers and is required for HpHb uptake. As both calcium concentration and pH are low in the endosome, this suggests that CD163 forms multimers in the serum which efficiently take up ligands and that these multimers disassemble in the endosomes, facilitating HpHb release.</p></sec><sec id="S7"><title>Monomeric CD163 is less effective at uptake of lower-avidity ligands</title><p id="P18">Having shown that calcium is important for CD163 multimer formation, we next aimed to determine whether the putative calcium ions at the binding interface between CD163 and HpHb are also important. To achieve this, we developed a monomeric CD163 molecule. As N807 occupies a central location within the multimer interface (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5a</xref>), an R809T mutant was produced to introduce an N-linked glycosylation site at N807, sterically occluding multimer formation. This mutant remained monomeric at a concentration of 2.7 mg/ml, as measured by SEC-MALLS (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5b</xref>). SPR measurements showed that monomeric CD163 bound to Hp(1-1)Hb with an apparent affinity of 1.2 nM in the presence of 2.5 mM CaCl<sub>2</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5c</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S6a and Table S3</xref>), compared with 0.28 nM for the native protein (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3d</xref>). This interaction was abolished in the absence of calcium (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5c</xref>) or when CaCl<sub>2</sub> was replaced with 2.5 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S6b</xref>). Therefore, calcium ions are important for the interaction of CD163 with its ligands.</p><p id="P19">The availability of monomeric CD163 also allowed us to assess the degree to which multimer formation is important for binding and uptake of diverse ligands. We first measured the affinities of different ligands for the R809T mutant, using SPR for HpHb complexes and MST for Hp and Hb. We found that apparent affinities for monomeric CD163 differed more than 1000-fold between Hp(2-2)Hb and HpSPHb, with values at 31 pM and 38 nM, respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5c</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S6a and Table S3</xref>). This stands in contrast to the similar affinities observed between HpHb variants for multimeric CD163 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3d</xref>). The affinity for Hb was estimated to be 1.9 μM, a 10-fold decrease compared to the wild-type receptor and no Hp binding was detected at 96 μM CD163 monomer (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5d</xref>,<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S7 and Table S3</xref>). Therefore, monomeric CD163 bound to all ligands, other than Hp(2-2)Hb, with a lower apparent affinity than multimeric CD163.</p><p id="P20">To assess the impact of the CD163 multimer formation on the uptake of various ligands, we generated a HEK293 cell line in which full-length monomeric R809T was expressed. This allowed us to measure the internalisation of fluorescently labelled Hp(2-2)Hb and to assess how effectively it competes for the uptake of non-fluorescent ligands (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5e</xref>). Fluorescent Hp(2-2)Hb was taken up into cells expressing monomeric CD163 with a similar concentration dependence as into cells which express wild-type CD163 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S8a</xref>). However, while wild-type CD163 showed equivalent uptake of all HpHb variants, and weaker uptake of Hb (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3f</xref>), monomeric CD163 showed uptake of HpHb which varied with the number of HpSPHb heads, with most effective uptake of Hp(2-2)Hb, then Hp(1-1)Hb and finally HpSPHb, with IC<sub>50</sub> values of 27 nM, 0.14 μM and 0.64 μM (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5e</xref>). Monomeric CD163 also showed decreased uptake of Hb, with an IC<sub>50</sub> larger than 4 μM. Therefore while the uptake of high-avidity Hp(2-2)Hb can be mediated by monomeric CD163, multimer formation allows the efficient uptake of lower-affinity or -avidity ligands, making CD163 a more promiscuous scavenger receptor.</p></sec></sec><sec id="S8" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p id="P21">CD163 is the archetypal example of a type I scavenger receptor, with a primary known role in the detoxification of Hb released by erythrocyte damage (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref>). To achieve this, it internalises the ‘essentially irreversible’ complex (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27">27</xref>) between cell-free Hb and serum Hp into macrophages. While free Hb rapidly forms complexes with Hp under healthy conditions, infectious or genetic diseases which increase erythrocyte lysis are associated with Hp depletion. In these circumstances, it is beneficial for CD163 to mediate free Hb uptake. In contrast, uptake of Hp is not beneficial, as it would deplete Hp from the plasma without contributing to Hb detoxification. How does CD163 selectively recognise different HpHb isoforms, as well as Hb, without recognising Hp? The findings presented here allows us to propose a model for how CD163 mediates specific binding and release of diverse ligands (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5f</xref>).</p><p id="P22">Our structural studies of CD163 show how it mediates ligand specificity, allowing uptake of ligands with diverse stoichiometries and architectures. Two or three CD163 protomers form an assembly, with the higher local concentrations on the membrane surface most likely favouring trimers. Each protomer presents an arm which provides potential ligand-contact surfaces and these arms come together in different conformations to create a ligand-binding site for a single HpHb head. This ensures that HpHb variants with different numbers of heads are all endocytosed equally. The interaction between HpHb and CD163 involves eight SRCR domains, which mould around the ligand. This formation of a binding site by bringing together multiple small binding sites will allow promiscuity, with different combinations of these small surfaces creating binding sites for different ligands. Together with flexibility in the trimeric base, this ensures that binding sites can mould to accommodate different ligands and allows a trimeric receptor to recognise asymmetric binding partners. Most of the interactions form between CD163 and the Hb dimer with fewer interactions with Hp. This leads to uptake of free Hb but not unnecessary depletion of free Hp. The CD163 arms can also interact with one another, using the same surfaces which form ligand-binding sites. These arm-arm interactions will compete with arm-ligand interactions and it is likely that this underpins a mechanism of autoinhibition, with weaker ligands being unable to compete with arm-arm interactions for receptor binding, therefore dampening the extent of CD163 promiscuity.</p><p id="P23">The structure also reveals the role of calcium ions, which mediate two distinct functions. Calcium ions are found at the interfaces between protomers in the base of CD163, mediating multimer formation. This allows the uptake of lower-avidity ligands and scavenger receptor promiscuity. The predominance of ion-mediated interactions at these interfaces also gives the interface rotational flexibility, allowing protomers to adopt different relative conformations as the receptor moulds around a ligand. In addition, calcium ions are found within the binding sites between arms and ligands and this most likely makes each of these small interfaces more promiscuous, with stronger electrostatic binding rather than more extensive shape complementarity driving the interaction. Finally, the use of calcium in critical interfaces, together with pH, is important for ligand release. At the calcium concentrations in sera, CD163 will multimerise and bind ligands, while in low calcium, lower pH conditions in the endosomes, ligands will be released for degradation. Therefore, these studies show how the CD163 scavenger receptor is built for promiscuous ligand binding and release, revealing how it mediates the essential physiological process of Hb detoxification.</p></sec><sec id="S9" sec-type="materials | methods"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="S10"><title>Expression and purification</title><p id="P24">The ectodomain of human CD163 (Uniprot Q86VB7-1 residues 46-1050) was cloned into pHLsec(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">28</xref>) and expressed with a C-terminal GAA-linker and a C-tag using the Expi293 Expression System (Gibco) according to the manufacturer’s instructions. Cell supernatant was harvested 6 days after transfection, passed through a 0.45 μm filter and applied to CaptureSelect C-tagXL Affinity Matrix (Thermo Scientific). Subsequently, the resin was washed with 30 column volumes (CV) of 20 mM Tris pH 7.5, 150 mM NaCl, and CD163 was eluted using 5 CV of 20 mM Tris pH 7.5, 2 M MgCl<sub>2</sub>. The protein was further purified on a Superose 6 10/300 column (Cytiva) into 20 mM HEPES pH 7.5, 150 mM NaCl, 2.5 mM CaCl<sub>2</sub>, flash frozen in liquid nitrogen and stored at – 80 °C. CD163-BAP was generated by fusing CD163 to a BAP tag, a GAA linker and the C-tag, and was expressed in the presence of 0.1 mM biotin. Site-directed mutagenesis of CD163-BAP was used to generate the monomeric R809T variant. Both were purified as described for CD163.</p></sec><sec id="S11"><title>Production of HpHb complexes</title><p id="P25">Hb was obtained by injecting the supernatant of freshly lysed human erythrocytes on a Superdex 75 16/600 column (Cytiva) which was run using 20 mM HEPES pH 7.5, 150 mM NaCl, 2.5 mM CaCl<sub>2</sub>. Hp(1-1) and Hp(2-2) extracted from human plasma were purchased from Sigma-Aldrich (SRP6507 and SRP6508). HpSP (Uniprot P00738-2 residues 89-347) and HprSP(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref>) (Uniprot P00739-1 residues 90-348) were cloned into pHLsec with a GAA linker and the C-tag, expressed in Expi293F cells for 6 and 5 days post-transfection, respectively, and C-tag purified as for the CD163 ectodomain. HpSP and HprSP were further purified on a Superdex 200 10/300 column (Cytiva) equilibrated in 20 mM HEPES pH 7.5, 150 mM NaCl, 2.5 mM CaCl<sub>2</sub>.</p><p id="P26">Complexes of various Hp phenotypes with Hb were formed by mixing Hp with a molar excess of Hb. Hp(1-1)Hb and Hp(2-2)Hb were directly injected on a Superdex 200 10/300 and a Superose 6 10/300 column, respectively, and eluted into 20 mM HEPES pH 7.5, 150 mM NaCl, 2.5 mM CaCl<sub>2</sub>. HpSPHb and HprSPHb were first subjected to C-tag purification before application on a Superdex 200 10/300 column.</p><p id="P27">The concentrations of HpHb complexes provided here referred to individual heads rather than entire HpHb molecules. Hb and Hp(1-1) concentrations were given for tetramers and dimer, respectively.</p></sec><sec id="S12"><title>Cryo-EM sample preparation and data collection</title><p id="P28">To prepare samples for cryogenic electron microscopy, CD163 was mixed with a molar excess of Hp(1-1)Hb, injected on a Superose 6 3.2/300 column (Cytiva) and eluted into HBS with calcium. The peak fractions containing CD163:Hp(1-1)Hb were pooled and concentrated to 1.3 mg/ml. Quantifoil R 1.2/1.3 Cu 300 grids were glow-discharged for 40 s at 15 mA and mounted in a Vitrobot Mark IV (Thermo Scientific) operated at 4 °C and 100 % humidity. Concentrated complexes were applied onto the grids, which were blotted for 2.5 – 4 s and plunge-frozen in liquid ethane. The grids were imaged on a Titan Krios G3 microscope (Thermo Scientific) equipped with a 300 kV emission gun, a K3 direct electron detector (Gatan) and a BioQuantum imaging filter (Gatan) with a slit width of 20 eV. EPU (Thermo Scientific) was used for automated data acquisition and was set to faster acquisition. Micrographs were collected with a defocus of -2.0 to -0.4 μm, a magnification of 58,149x, a pixel size of 0.832 Å and a dose of 41.68 e<sup>-</sup>/Å<sup>2</sup> over a period of 2.5 s. Three grids were subjected to data acquisition, yielding 39,445 movies (8,303, 17,714 and 13,428, respectively).</p><p id="P29">Unliganded CD163 was concentrated to 1.3 mg/ml after gel filtration, and corresponding samples were prepared under the same conditions as CD163:Hp(1-1)Hb. Data collection was similar to that for the liganded complex, with the defocus set to -1.8 to -0.6 μm and a dose of 42.82 e<sup>-</sup>/Å<sup>2</sup> over 2.6 s. 19,412 micrographs were collected from a single grid.</p></sec><sec id="S13"><title>Cryo-EM image processing</title><p id="P30">Micrographs from the CD163:Hp(1-1)Hb dataset were pre-processed in SIMPLE 3.0 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">20</xref>). Following motion correction and contrast transfer function (CTF) parameters estimation, micrographs were picked using a template from a previous test data collection. After 2D classification, 1,573,382 particles were extracted and exported into CryoSPARC (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">21</xref>), where the particles were further classified and used for 3D reconstruction. The resulting volume was used to re-pick the full dataset, resulting in 15,666,525 particles with a box size of 512 pixels Fourier-cropped to 384 pixels.</p><p id="P31">Over the course of three rounds of 2D classification, classes containing poor particles were excluded, leaving 3,502,829 particles that were used for 3D reconstruction into seven classes. Classes for dimeric and trimeric CD163:Hp(1-1)Hb complexes containing most features underwent 3D classification via <italic>ab initio</italic> reconstruction and heterogeneous refinement, after which particles with nearly identical features were combined. 463,222 particles corresponding to the trimeric complex were re-extracted to the original pixel spacing of 0.832 Å and subjected to non-uniform refinement with optimisation of CTF parameters. This led to a volume at 3.2 Å resolution according to the gold-standard Fourier Shell Correlation (GSFSC) definition at 0.143. For the dimeric complex, 456,124 particles were re-extracted to remove the Fourier-crop and processed in a final non-uniform refinement step with per-particle defocus and CTF parameters optimisation, yielding a map at 2.8 Å resolution with the original pixel spacing of 0.832 Å.</p><p id="P32">Unliganded CD163 was processed similarly to CD163:Hp(1-1)Hb. After pre-processing and initial 2D classification in SIMPLE, 798,259 particles were exported to CryoSPARC. These particles were used to reconstruct a 3D template used to repick all micrographs. 13,772,487 particles were extracted using a box size of 512 pixels down-sampled to 384 pixels and sorted in two rounds of 2D classification. This resulted in 3,308,159 particles that were used to generate seven <italic>ab initio</italic> volumes. A high-resolution dimer class, a trimer class with disordered arms and a trimer class with arm-arm contacts were identified. Two rounds of 3D classification were performed on particles corresponding to the dimer class while particles corresponding to the trimer classes were 3D-classified once, after which particles with similar features were combined. 723,620 particles corresponding to the dimer class were re-extracted to remove down-sampling and subjected to non-uniform refinement, yielding a volume at 3.1 Å resolution with a pixel size of 0.832 Å. 81,871 particles corresponding to the trimer class with disordered arms and 432,423 particles representing the trimer with arm-arm contacts underwent non-uniform refinement. This resulted in maps at 3.8 and 3.4 Å, respectively. All maps were sharpened by DeepEMhancer (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">29</xref>) using the default seffings and were depicted using ChimeraX v1.7 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">30</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S14"><title>Model building and refinement</title><p id="P33">Trimeric CD163:Hp(1-1)Hb exhibited a higher resolution for the CD163 base while subunit A of dimeric CD163:Hp(1-1)Hb most clearly resolved an arm of CD163. Therefore, SRCR domains 5-9 of the liganded complexes were built using ChimeraX by rigid-body fiffing individual AlphaFold2-predicted domains (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31">31</xref>) into the corresponding densities of trimeric CD163:Hp(1-1)Hb. Domains 2-4 were docked into the densities of the liganded dimer. Falsely built regions were corrected in Coot 0.9.8.8 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32">32</xref>) before docking the corrected SRCR domain models into unmodelled densities of the liganded CD163 maps. These models were then manually readjusted in Coot.</p><p id="P34">A crystal structure of HpSPHb(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref>) (PDB: 4X0L) and Hp(1-1)Hb from a crystal structure of its complex with the <italic>T. brucei</italic> HpHb receptor (PDB: 4WJG) were docked into ligand densities of trimeric and dimeric CD163:Hp(1-1)Hb, respectively. Both models were initially subjected to optimisation using ISOLDE (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33">33</xref>) and subsequent iterative real-space refinement in PHENIX (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34">34</xref>) and manual correction in Coot.</p><p id="P35">To build the unliganded CD163 dimer, SRCR domains from the liganded dimer were individually rigid-body fitted into corresponding densities using ChimeraX (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">30</xref>) and manually adjusted in Coot. The unliganded dimer was refined as the liganded complexes. PDBePISA (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35">35</xref>) was used to calculate ligand-binding interfaces and interfaces of arm-arm contact. Models were displayed using ChimeraX.</p></sec><sec id="S15"><title>Surface plasmon resonance</title><p id="P36">SPR was performed on a Biacore T200 SPR system (Cytiva) operated at 25 °C using the Biotin CAPture Kit, Series S (Cytiva). SPR buffer was either HBST (20 mM HEPES pH 7.5, 150 mM NaCl, 0.005 % Tween-20) or MBST (20 mM MES pH 6.0, 150 mM NaCl, 0.005 % Tween-20) supplemented with either 2.5 mM CaCl<sub>2</sub> or 2.5 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub> or neither. Ligand and analyte were buffer exchanged using 0.5 ml Zeba Spin Desalting columns (7K MWCO, Thermo Scientific) into SPR buffer prior to experimentation.</p><p id="P37">Biotinylated CD163-WT-BAP or CD163-R809T-BAP diluted to 8 μg/ml were captured at 8 μl/min for 160 s. Under binding conditions for CD163-WT-BAP, two-fold dilution series of 10-0.078 nM Hp(1-1)Hb, 10-0.078 nM Hp(2-2)Hb, 20-0.16 nM HpSPHb or 20 nM HprSPHb were flowed through the chip at 30 μl/min for 3 min, followed by dissociation for 5 min. For CD163-R809T-BAP, two-fold dilution series of 5-0.078 nM Hp(1-1)Hb, 2.5-0.019 nM Hp(2-2)Hb and 80-0.63 nM HpSPHb were used. Under non-binding conditions, 10 nM Hp(1-1)Hb and 20 nM HprSPHb were injected onto the chip. The chip surface was regenerated by injecting 6 M guanidine hydrochloride, 0.25 M NaOH at 10 μl/min for 80 s. Under binding conditions, experiments were conducted three times with three independent dilution series. Under non-binding conditions, a single concentration corresponding to the highest concentration observed under binding conditions was injected three times. Kinetic analysis was performed using BIAevaluation software v1.0 (Cytiva). Curves were depicted using GraphPad Prism v10.3.1.</p></sec><sec id="S16"><title>Fluorescent labelling of CD163 ligands</title><p id="P38">For MST, Hb and Hp(1-1) were fluorescently labelled using Alexa Fluor 647 NHS Ester (Thermo Scientific) according to the manufacturer’s instructions. For uptake experiments, Hp(2-2) was labelled using Alexa Fluor 594 NHS Ester (Thermo Scientific). Unbound dye was removed by applying the sample on a Zeba Spin Desalting column and a Superdex 200 10/300 column and eluting it in HBS with calcium. Fluorescent Hp(1-1)Hb and Hp(2-2)Hb were produced by mixing fluorescent Hp(1-1) and Hp(2-2), respectively, with an excess of Hb and subsequent gel filtration.</p></sec><sec id="S17"><title>Microscale thermophoresis</title><p id="P39">MST was carried out on a Monolith NT.115 (NanoTemper) operated at 25 °C. Four different sets of binding partners were prepared in 20 mM HEPES pH 7.5, 150 mM NaCl, 2.5 mM CaCl<sub>2</sub>, incubated for an hour at room temperature and loaded into Monolith Capillaries (NanoTemper) for measurement. In the first set, 200 nM fluorescent Hb was mixed with a two-fold dilution series of CD163-WT (24.4 μM – 0.74 nM), which was measured at 10 % LED and 20 % MST power. In the second set, 500 nM Hp(1-1) was incubated with CD163-WT (37.9 μM – 1.2 nM) and was recorded at 8 % LED and 20 % MST power. In the third set, 200 nM Hb was mixed with CD163-R809T-BAP at 41.5 μM – 1.3 nM and was measured at 10 % LED and 20 % MST power. In the fourth set, 1.0 μM Hp(1-1) was mixed with 96.3 μM – 2.9 nM CD163-R809T-BAP and was analysed at 6 % LED and 20 % MST power. Every interaction was characterised in technical triplicates. Raw data was extracted from NT Analysis v1.5 (NanoTemper) and a fluorescence baseline offset was applied to individual replicates before they were combined and fitted using the ‘Sigmoidal, 4PL, X is concentration’ model in GraphPad Prism.</p></sec><sec id="S18"><title>Size-exclusion chromatography coupled with multi-angle laser light scattering</title><p id="P40">SEC-MALLS was conducted at room temperature on a Shimadzu Prominence UFLC System connected to a Superose 6 10/300 column, a Dawn Helios 8<sup>+</sup> light scattering detector (Wyatt Technology) and an Optilab T-rEX refractive index detector (Wyatt Technology). To test the influence of the CD163 concentration on its multimeric state, duplicates of 100 μl samples containing 0.38, 0.67, 1.3 or 2.7 mg/ml CD163-WT were measured in HBS (20 mM HEPES pH 7.5, 150 mM NaCl) with 2.5 mM calcium. Similarly, duplicates with 0.25, 0.38, 0.51 or 0.76 mg/ml CD163-WT and 0.08 mg/ml Hp(1-1)Hb were analysed. To probe the role of calcium and pH, triplicates containing 0.38 mg/ml CD163-WT and 0.08 mg/ml Hp(1-1)Hb were analysed in HBS, HBS with 2.5 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, MBS (20 mM MES pH 6.0, 150 mM NaCl) or MBS with 2.5 mM CaCl<sub>2</sub>. To characterise the effect of R809T on the multimeric state of CD163, duplicates containing 0.38 or 2.7 mg/ml CD163-R809T-BAP were measured in HBS with calcium. Data were analysed using ASTRA v6.1 (Wyatt Technology) and plotted in GraphPad Prism.</p></sec><sec id="S19"><title>Generation of stably transfected, CD163-expressing HEK293 cells</title><p id="P41">The Flp-In-293 system (Invitrogen) was used to generate stably transfected, CD163-expressing cells according to the manufacturer’s instructions. The secretion signal sequence of pHLsec, full-length human CD163 (Uniprot Q86VB7-1 residues 46-1156, wild-type or R809T), a GSG linker and GFP (Uniprot P42212 residues 2-238) were cloned into pcDNA 5/FRT (Invitrogen). This expression vector and pOG44 were used to transfect ˜600,000 Flp-In-293 T-REx cells (Thermo Scientific) at a 1:9 ratio using TransIT-LT1 Transfection Reagent (Mirus Bio) according to the manufacturer’s instructions. Cells were passaged in Dulbecco’s Modified Eagle Medium (DMEM, Gibco) with 10 % fetal calf serum (FCS, Gibco) a day after transfection and selected in DMEM with 10 % FCS, 15 μg/ml blasticidin S (Gibco) and 100 μg/ml hygromycin B (VWR) two days post-transfection. After selection, cells were sorted using FACSAria Fusion (BD Biosciences) to obtain populations with high, consistent CD163 expression.</p></sec><sec id="S20"><title>Ligand uptake assay</title><p id="P42">For Hp(2-2)Hb uptake in the absence of competitors, ˜200,000 CD163-WT- or CD163-R809T-expressing cells or untransfected cells were washed in PBS. After incubation in DMEM with 25 mM HEPES, 0 – 600 nM Alexa Fluor 594-labelled Hp(2-2)Hb and optionally 2 mM EGTA for 30 min at 37 °C, 5 % CO<sub>2</sub>, cells were washed in PBS, trypsinised and washed again. Following addition of DRAQ7 (Abcam) to 3 μM, cells were measured on a LSRFortessa X-20 Cell Analyzer (BD Biosciences), equipped with a 488 and 561 nm laser to detect CD163-GFP and labelled Hp(2-2)Hb, respectively. For uptake of Alexa Fluor 594-labelled transferrin (Thermo Scientific, T13343), untransfected cells were handled as described for Hp(2-2)Hb uptake.</p><p id="P43">For uptake in the presence of competitors, CD163-WT- or CD163-R809T-expressing cells were incubated with 50 nM Alexa Fluor 594-labelled Hp(2-2)Hb and 0 – 4 μM unlabelled ligand and were processed as described above.</p><p id="P44">All uptake experiments were performed in triplicate, with cells for each sample incubated with fresh ligand and measured on three different days. To quantify uptake, the mean fluorescence of all live, single cells was calculated using FlowJo v10.10 and plotted in GraphPad Prism. In the uptake series performed with competitors, slight batch-to-batch differences were observed in the absolute fluorescence signal for the sample at 0 nM competitor. Therefore, fluorescence values in these series were normalised by defining the fluorescence at 0 nM competitor as 100 %. In competition experiments, IC<sub>50</sub> values were defined as the concentration at which the fluorescence reaches 50 %.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="SM"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1"><label>Supplementary Materials</label><media xlink:href="EMS202329-supplement-Supplementary_Materials.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" id="d62aAcEbB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack id="S21"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>Cryo-EM data was collected at the COSMIC facility and we thank Rishi Matadeen, Teige Matthews-Parmer, Joe Caesar and Ed Lowe for support with data collection and processing. We acknowledge Hannah Ivison for lab management. We are grateful to David Staunton for help with biophysical methods and to Robert Hedley and Vasiliki Tsioligka for assistance with flow sorting. We thank Ian Gibbs-Seymour for advice in generation of stable cell lines and Thomas Carroll for advice on uptake experiments. We thank Dara Thaker for technical assistance.</p><sec id="S22"><title>Funding</title><p>This work was funded by the Wellcome Trust. MKH is a Wellcome Investigator (220797/Z/20/Z) and RXZ was funded by the graduate programme in Cellular Structural Biology (218482/Z/19/Z), Magdalen College and the Clarendon Fund.</p></sec></ack><sec id="S23" sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data and materials availability</title><p id="P45">Cryo-EM maps are deposited in the Electron Microscopy Data Bank under accession codes EMD-52078 for dimeric CD163:HpHb, EMD-52079 for trimeric CD163:HpHb, EMD-52080 for unliganded dimeric CD163 with arm-arm contacts, EMD-52081 for unliganded trimeric CD163 with arm-arm contacts and EMD-52082 for unliganded trimeric CD163 with disordered arms. Atomic coordinates are deposited in the Protein Data Bank under accession codes 9HEJ for the liganded CD163 dimer, 9HEK for liganded trimer and 9HEL for unliganded dimer. All materials are available from the authors on request.</p></sec><fn-group><fn id="FN1" fn-type="conflict"><p id="P46"><bold>Competing interests</bold></p><p id="P47">The authors have no competing interests.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><ref id="R1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bandyopadhyay</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Free heme toxicity and its detoxification systems in human</article-title><source>Toxicol Lett</source><year>2005</year><volume>157</volume><fpage>175</fpage><lpage>188</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15917143</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sadrzadeh</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Graf</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Panter</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Hallaway</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name><name><surname>Eaton</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hemoglobin. A biologic fenton reagent</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1984</year><volume>259</volume><fpage>14354</fpage><lpage>14356</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6094553</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gutteridge</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lipid peroxidation and antioxidants as biomarkers of tissue damage</article-title><source>Clin Chem</source><year>1995</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>1819</fpage><lpage>1828</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7497639</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Steinberg</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Gladwin</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Intravascular hemolysis and the pathophysiology of sickle cell disease</article-title><source>J Clin Invest</source><year>2017</year><volume>127</volume><fpage>750</fpage><lpage>760</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5330745</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28248201</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1172/JCI89741</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pamplona</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanscheid</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Epiphanio</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mota</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Vigario</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cerebral malaria and the hemolysis/methemoglobin/heme hypothesis: shedding new light on an old disease</article-title><source>Int J Biochem Cell Biol</source><year>2009</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>711</fpage><lpage>716</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18930163</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Andersen</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Structure of the haptoglobin-haemoglobin complex</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2012</year><volume>489</volume><fpage>456</fpage><lpage>459</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22922649</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wejman</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Hovsepian</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Wall</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Hainfeld</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Greer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structure of haptoglobin and the haptoglobin-hemoglobin complex by electron microscopy</article-title><source>J Mol Biol</source><year>1984</year><volume>174</volume><fpage>319</fpage><lpage>341</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6716481</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maeda</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Barnett</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Bowman</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name><name><surname>Smithies</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Duplication within the haptoglobin Hp2 gene</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1984</year><volume>309</volume><fpage>131</fpage><lpage>135</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6325933</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smithies</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Zone electrophoresis in starch gels: group variations in the serum proteins of normal human adults</article-title><source>Biochem J</source><year>1955</year><volume>61</volume><fpage>629</fpage><lpage>641</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1215845</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13276348</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1042/bj0610629</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Andersen</surname><given-names>CBF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Haptoglobin</article-title><source>Antìoxid Redox Signal</source><year>2017</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>814</fpage><lpage>831</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27650279</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tamara</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Franc</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Heck</surname><given-names>AJR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A wealth of genotype-specific proteoforms fine-tunes hemoglobin scavenging by haptoglobin</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2020</year><volume>117</volume><fpage>15554</fpage><lpage>15564</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7355005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32561649</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.2002483117</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kristiansen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Identification of the haemoglobin scavenger receptor</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2001</year><volume>409</volume><fpage>198</fpage><lpage>201</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11196644</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Law</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A new macrophage differentiation antigen which is a member of the scavenger receptor superfamily</article-title><source>Eur J Immunol</source><year>1993</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>2320</fpage><lpage>2325</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8370408</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A unique loop extension in the serine protease domain of haptoglobin is essential for CD163 recognition of the haptoglobin-hemoglobin complex</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2007</year><volume>282</volume><fpage>1072</fpage><lpage>1079</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17102136</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schaer</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Schoedon</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Imhof</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kurrer</surname><given-names>MO</given-names></name><name><surname>Schaer</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Constitutive endocytosis of CD163 mediates hemoglobin-heme uptake and determines the noninflammatory and protective transcriptional response of macrophages to hemoglobin</article-title><source>Circ Res</source><year>2006</year><volume>99</volume><fpage>943</fpage><lpage>950</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17008602</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Warren</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Primate hemorrhagic fever-causing arteriviruses are poised for spillover to humans</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2022</year><volume>185</volume><fpage>3980</fpage><lpage>3991</lpage><elocation-id>e3918</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9588614</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36182704</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2022.09.022</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Welch</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Calvert</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A brief review of CD163 and its role in PRRSV infection</article-title><source>Virus Res</source><year>2010</year><volume>154</volume><fpage>98</fpage><lpage>103</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20655964</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Valdes-Donoso</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Jarvis</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Combining epidemiology and economics to assess control of a viral endemic animal disease: Porcine Reproductive and Respiratory Syndrome (PRRS)</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2022</year><volume>17</volume><elocation-id>e0274382</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9462702</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36084100</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0274382</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lane-Serff</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>MacGregor</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Lowe</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name><name><surname>Carrington</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Higgins</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structural basis for ligand and innate immunity factor uptake by the trypanosome haptoglobin-haemoglobin receptor</article-title><source>Elife</source><year>2014</year><volume>3</volume><elocation-id>e05553</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4383175</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25497229</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.05553</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Caesar</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>SIMPLE 3.0. Stream single-partìcle cryo-EM analysis in real time</article-title><source>J Struct Biol X</source><year>2020</year><volume>4</volume><elocation-id>100040</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7695977</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33294840</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.yjsbx.2020.100040</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Punjani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rubinstein</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Fleet</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Brubaker</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>cryoSPARC: algorithms for rapid unsupervised cryo-EM structure determination</article-title><source>Nat Methods</source><year>2017</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>290</fpage><lpage>296</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28165473</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Madsen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Molecular characterization of the haptoglobin.hemoglobin receptor CD163. Ligand binding properties of the scavenger receptor cysteine-rich domain region</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2004</year><volume>279</volume><fpage>51561</fpage><lpage>51567</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15448162</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Drain</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bishop</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Hajduk</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Haptoglobin-related protein mediates trypanosome lytìc factor binding to trypanosomes</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2001</year><volume>276</volume><fpage>30254</fpage><lpage>30260</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11352898</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Haptoglobin-related protein is a high-affinity hemoglobin-binding plasma protein</article-title><source>Blood</source><year>2006</year><volume>108</volume><fpage>2846</fpage><lpage>2849</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16778136</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vanhollebeke</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A haptoglobin-hemoglobin receptor conveys innate immunity to Trypanosoma brucei in humans</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2008</year><volume>320</volume><fpage>677</fpage><lpage>681</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18451305</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Langlois</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Delanghe</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biological and clinical significance of haptoglobin polymorphism in humans</article-title><source>Clin Chem</source><year>1996</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>1589</fpage><lpage>1600</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8855140</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nagel</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>QH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The binding of hemoglobin to haptoglobin and its relation to subunit dissociation of hemoglobin</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1971</year><volume>246</volume><fpage>69</fpage><lpage>73</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5541775</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aricescu</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>EY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A time- and cost-efficient system for high-level protein production in mammalian cells</article-title><source>Acta Crystallogr D Biol Crystallogr</source><year>2006</year><volume>62</volume><fpage>1243</fpage><lpage>1250</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17001101</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sanchez-Garcia</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>DeepEMhancer: a deep learning solution for cryo-EM volume post-processing</article-title><source>Commun Biol</source><year>2021</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>874</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8282847</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34267316</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s42003-021-02399-1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>UCSF ChimeraX: Tools for structure building and analysis</article-title><source>Protein Sci</source><year>2023</year><volume>32</volume><elocation-id>e4792</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10588335</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37774136</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/pro.4792</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jumper</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Highly accurate protein structure prediction with AlphaFold</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2021</year><volume>596</volume><fpage>583</fpage><lpage>589</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8371605</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34265844</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41586-021-03819-2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Emsley</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Lohkamp</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>WG</given-names></name><name><surname>Cowtan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Features and development of Coot</article-title><source>Acta Crystallogr D Biol Crystallogr</source><year>2010</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>486</fpage><lpage>501</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2852313</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20383002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1107/S0907444910007493</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Croll</surname><given-names>TI</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>ISOLDE: a physically realistic environment for model building into low-resolution electron-density maps</article-title><source>Acta Crystallogr D Struct Biol</source><year>2018</year><volume>74</volume><fpage>519</fpage><lpage>530</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6096486</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29872003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1107/S2059798318002425</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liebschner</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Macromolecular structure determination using X-rays, neutrons and electrons: recent developments in Phenix</article-title><source>Acta Crystallogr D Struct Biol</source><year>2019</year><volume>75</volume><fpage>861</fpage><lpage>877</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6778852</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31588918</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1107/S2059798319011471</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krissinel</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Henrick</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inference of macromolecular assemblies from crystalline state</article-title><source>J Mol Biol</source><year>2007</year><volume>372</volume><fpage>774</fpage><lpage>797</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17681537</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><title>The structure of CD163 bound to HpHb.</title><p><bold>a.</bold> The structure of a trimer of the CD163 ectodomain bound to the HpHb complex. The three copies of CD163 are shown in three shades of blue. HpSP domain is green, the α-subunit of Hb is red and the β-subunit of Hb is orange. <bold>b.</bold> The structure of a dimer of the CD163 ectodomain bound to the HpHb complex, coloured as in a. <bold>c.</bold> An alignment of the three CD163 molecules found in the trimeric complex, aligned on SRCR5, with the SRCR domains labelled. <bold>d.</bold> A close-up of the interfaces between two pairs of CD163 subunits with the red dotted line showing the different distances between the Cα atoms of residues 561 and 804 in these two interfaces. <bold>e.</bold> An alignment of each pair of CD163 ectodomains observed in the trimeric and dimeric complex, with each aligned on SRCR7 of the left-hand CD163. The right-hand CD163 molecules from the trimer are coloured as in a. and in pink for the CDI63<sub>A</sub> from the dimer. Dashed lines indicate the maximum degree of tilting of the arm of CD163 in these structures.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS202329-f001"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><title>The structure of unliganded CD163.</title><p><bold>a.</bold> The structure of a trimer of CD163 in the absence of ligand, with disordered arms, coloured as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>. <bold>b.</bold> The structure of a dimer of CD163 in the absence of ligand (left) and in the presence of HpHb (right), showing arm-arm contacts between the CD163 arms in the unliganded dimer, with the arms moving outwards to allow ligand binding. <bold>c.</bold> Close-up on the interface between the arms of CD163<sub>A</sub> and CD163<sub>B</sub> in the unliganded dimer. <bold>d.</bold> A schematic presenting the overlap in residues involved in arm-arm contacts and HpHb binding. The left panel shows SRCR2-4 of CD163 as a surface representation with residues involved in arm-arm contacts in the unliganded dimer coloured red for CD163<sub>A</sub>, green for CD163<sub>B</sub> and yellow if involved in both subunits. In the central panel, residues are labelled if directly contacting HpHb in the liganded dimer and trimer. Red represents CDI63<sub>A</sub>, green CDI63<sub>B</sub>, blue CD163<sub>C</sub>, with yellow depicting residues involved in ligand binding in at least two CD163 subunits. The right-hand panel shows the same surface with residues labelled red if they contact HpHb, green if they are involved in arm-arm contacts in the unliganded dimer and yellow if both.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS202329-f002"/></fig><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><title>Ligand selectivity of CD163.</title><p><bold>a.</bold> The structure of the CD163 trimer bound to HpHb viewed from three directions, showing that each arm of CD163 interacts differently with the HpHb ligand. <bold>b.</bold> Schematic showing the different stoichiometries and structures of the ligands studied here. <bold>c.</bold> A view of SRCR2 of CDI63<sub>A</sub> (violet) bound to Hp (green). Below this is shown a partial sequence alignment of Hp and Hpr. Residues which differ between Hp and Hpr and which might influence binding to CD163 are shown as sticks and labelled. <bold>d.</bold> Assessment of the binding of CD163 ectodomain, immobilised through a C-terminal biotin, to Hp(1-1)Hb, Hp(2-2)Hb, HpSPHb and HprSPHb by SPR analysis. These represent two-fold dilution series from a maximum concentration of 10 nM for Hp(1-1)Hb and Hp(2-2)Hb, 20 nM for HpSPHb as well as an injection at 20 nM for HprSPHb. Data are shown as black lines while fiiffing to a one-to-one binding model is depicted as dashed red lines. These are representative of n = 3. <bold>e.</bold> Assessment of the binding of Hp and Hb to CD163 ectodomain using MST. Each point is the mean of three replicates and the error bars are the standard deviation. <bold>f.</bold> Measurement of the ability of different ligands to compete for the uptake of fluorescently labelled Hp(2-2)Hb into HEK293 cells transfected with CD163. BSA is included as a control for CD163-independent effects. Each point represents the mean of three replicates and the error bars are standard deviations.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS202329-f003"/></fig><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><title>Calcium is required for CD163 multimer formation and for HpHb uptake.</title><p><bold>a.</bold> The central panel shows the structure of the CD163 trimer bound to HpHb, coloured as <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>. The left-hand panel shows Ca<sup>2+</sup> ions at the interface between CD163<sub>A</sub> and HpHb while the right-hand panel shows Ca<sup>2+</sup> ions at the interface between CD163<sub>A</sub> and CD163<sub>C</sub>. <bold>b.</bold> The left-hand panel shows SEC-MALLS data for CD163 in the presence of Hp(1-1)Hb with the left y-axis showing the differential refractive index, while the right y-axis shows the molecular weight. This is representative of 2 repeats for measurements at pH 7.5 with Ca<sup>2+</sup> and 3 repeats for all other buffers. The right-hand panel shows the binding of CD163, coated on the surface of an SPR chip, to Hp(1-1)Hb at 10 nM concentration. This is representative of 3 repeats. In both cases, the key above the graphs indicates the pH and the presence or absence of divalent cations. <bold>c.</bold> Measurement of the uptake of fluorescently labelled Hp(2-2)Hb into HEK293 cells expressing CD163 in the absence (red line) and presence (orange line) of EGTA. The blue line shows non-receptor-mediated uptake into cells not expressing the receptor. Each point represents the mean of three replicates and the error bars depict standard deviations.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS202329-f004"/></fig><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><title>Multimerisation of CD163 allows uptake of lower-avidity ligands.</title><p><bold>a.</bold> A close-up of the interface between CD163<sub>A</sub> and C1I63<sub>B</sub>, showing the location of N807, which becomes modified with an N-linked glycan in the R809T mutant. <bold>b.</bold> SEC-MALLS analysis of wild-type (WT) CD163 ectodomain (blue) and the ectodomain of the R809T mutant (green) with the left y-axis showing the differential refractive index, while the right y-axis displays the molecular weight. This is representative of 2 repeats at a concentration of 2.7 mg/ml. <bold>c.</bold> Assessment of the binding of CD163-R809T ectodomain, immobilised through a C-terminal biotin, to Hp(1-1)Hb, Hp(2-2)Hb and HpSPHb by SPR analysis. In the presence of Ca<sup>2+</sup>, the sensorgrams represent two-fold dilution series from a maximum concentration of 5 nM for Hp(1-1)Hb, 2.5 nM for Hp(2-2)Hb and 80 nM for HpSPHb. In the absence of Ca<sup>2+</sup>, one injection of Hp(1-1)Hb at 10 nM is displayed. Data are shown as black lines while tiffing to a one-to-one binding model is depicted as dashed red lines. These are representative of n = 3. <bold>d.</bold> Assessment of the binding of Hp (green) and Hb (orange) to CD163-R809T ectodomain using MST. Each point represents the mean of three replicates and the error bars are the standard deviation. <bold>e.</bold> Measurement of the ability of different ligands to compete for the uptake of fluorescently labelled Hp(2-2)Hb into HEK293 cells transfected with CD163-R809T. BSA is included as a control for CD163-independent effects. Each point depicts the mean of three replicates and the error bars are standard deviations. <bold>f.</bold> A model for the CD163-mediated uptake of HpHb. At the cell surface, calcium mediates multimerisation of CD163. Two states exist in equilibrium, with the arms either free to bind to ligand or forming arm-arm interactions which occlude ligand-binding sites. On addition of ligand, the free arms of CD163 mould around the ligand to form a complex. On internalisation into the endosome, a drop in calcium concentration and pH results in monomerisation of CD163 and ligand release. CD163 can then be recycled back to the cell surface while HpHb is degraded and detoxified.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS202329-f005"/></fig></floats-group></article>