<!DOCTYPE article
 PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" article-type="preprint"><?all-math-mml yes?><?use-mml?><?origin ukpmcpa?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">bioRxiv</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>bioRxiv : the preprint server for biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2692-8205</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">EMS200141</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2024.11.13.623376</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="archive">PPR940472</article-id><article-version-alternatives><article-version article-version-type="status">preprint</article-version><article-version article-version-type="number">1</article-version></article-version-alternatives><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Pin4 Links Post-transcriptional and Transcriptional Responses to Glucose Starvation in Yeast</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ristová</surname><given-names>Michaela</given-names></name><email>s1507601@ed.ac.uk</email><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bexley</surname><given-names>Katherine</given-names></name><email>s2247997@ed.ac.uk</email><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shchepachev</surname><given-names>Vadim</given-names></name><email>v.shchepachev@gmail.com</email><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>Atlanta G.</given-names></name><email>atlanta.cook@ed.ac.uk</email><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tollervey</surname><given-names>David</given-names></name><email>d.tollervey@ed.ac.uk</email><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN1">2</xref></contrib><aff id="A1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/03xbccz06</institution-id><institution>Wellcome Centre for Cell Biology</institution></institution-wrap>, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/01nrxwf90</institution-id><institution>University of Edinburgh</institution></institution-wrap>, <city>Edinburgh</city>, <country country="GB">UK</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><fn id="FN1"><label>2</label><p id="P1">Lead contact</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted"><day>17</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="preprint"><day>15</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><permissions><ali:free_to_read/><license><ali:license_ref>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is licensed under a <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0 International license</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p id="P2">Adaptation to environmental change is essential in all organisms, with RNA-binding proteins (RBPs) playing critical roles in rapid cellular responses. We analyzed the largely uncharacterized yeast RBP Pin4, and its involvement in adaptation to glucose depletion. A UV crosslinking technique to identify protein-RNA interactions (reCRAC) revealed that in glucose conditions Pin4 selectively binds a specific motif in 3’ UTRs of mRNAs involved in glycolysis, amino acid, and mitochondrial metabolism. Following glucose withdrawal, Pin4-RNA binding was greatly reduced, with residual binding favoring transcripts associated with protein translation. Cells lacking Pin4 were greatly impaired in recovery from nutrient starvation and hypersensitive to oxidative stress, consistent with the mRNA targets. RNAseq and reporter assays indicated that loss of Pin4 caused increased target mRNA abundance. In wildtype yeast, glucose depletion induces “diauxic shift”, with massive changes in transcription patterns. Very unexpectedly, this response was almost entirely abolished in cells lacking Pin4, or carrying a point mutation in its RNA-recognition motif. We conclude that Pin4 contributes to energy homeostasis by regulating post-transcriptional and transcriptional responses, and postulate that this key stress response pathway is riboregulated.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec id="S1" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p id="P3">The capacity to adapt to ever-changing environments is a fundamental trait necessary for the survival of all living organisms. This adaptability encompasses specific responses to a wide range of stressors such as nutrient depletion, temperature fluctuations, and pH changes <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref></sup>. Central to these adaptive responses are RNA-binding proteins (RBPs), which regulate a multitude of critical steps throughout gene expression <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">3</xref></sup>.</p><p id="P4">The budding yeast <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> grows on plant surfaces and is exposed to many environmental insults. For example, a rain shower will result in immediate nutrient deprivation, perhaps only transiently. Yeast has long been used as a model eukaryote, to study responses to a multitude of stressors. Notable among these stress responses is the diauxic shift, the metabolic switch induced by glucose depletion, which drastically affects yeast cell physiology and behavior <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">4</xref></sup>. Under glucose abundant conditions, yeast cells metabolize glucose in preference to any other available carbon sources, utilizing aerobic fermentation. Glycolysis converts the glucose to CO<sub>2</sub> and ethanol, which are excreted despite the availability of oxygen. This metabolic preference for aerobic fermentation – termed the Crabtree effect – has been observed across diverse biological systems, including plant pollen, Trypanosomatids, skeletal muscles, and tumor cells, where it is referred to as the Warburg effect <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">8</xref></sup>. The predominant hypothesis for the emergence of the Crabtree effect centers on the rapid production of ATP and the evolutionary advantage of quickly producing progeny <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref></sup>. Following glucose depletion, the switch from fermentation to respiration involves a two-stage response: a rapid post-transcriptional response, followed by a slower transcriptional response. The initial post-transcriptional response primarily affects protein synthesis, followed by alterations in mRNA splicing, polyadenylation, RNA stability, RNA modifications, spatial localization, and condensate formation <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref></sup>. The subsequent transcriptional response unfolds over several minutes, with upregulation of specific stress-response genes and suppression of those involved in ribosome biogenesis and growth. Central to the regulation of this response are three major signaling pathways associated with yeast glucose metabolism: the Snf1, PKA, and Snf3/Rgt2 pathways <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref></sup>.</p><p id="P5">Supporting RNA binding proteins as central to rapid adaptive responses, a recent study identified extensive remodeling of the yeast RNA-protein interactome in response to glucose withdrawal or heat shock within a 16 min timeframe <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref></sup>. Key factors in protein synthesis were notably affected, consistent with the widespread shutdown of translation during stress. Intriguingly, among the most strongly altered RBPs, several were largely uncharacterized, notably Pin4, Mrn1, Pbp2 and Nab6. Subsequent investigations implicated Mrn1 and Nab6 in a novel post-transcriptional cell wall integrity pathway <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">20</xref></sup>. Here, we characterize the role of Pin4 in the cellular response to glucose withdrawal.</p><p id="P6">Previous screens identified Pin4 as a protein that alters yeast prion formation and as a Rad53 interactor, implicated in the responses to methylmethane sulfonate (MMS) and bleomycin treatment, and normal G2/M cell cycle progression <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">21</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">23</xref></sup>. However, these putative functions were not clearly related to RNA interactions, so we sought to investigate these in detail. We conclude that Pin4 has a pivotal role in yeast energy metabolism, regulating both post-transcriptional and transcriptional adaptations to cellular stress induced by glucose depletion. Identifying the function of this critical protein highlights the potential for a class of previously unidentified RNA binding proteins that connect external signaling to a regulatory RNA interaction network.</p></sec><sec id="S2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="S3"><title>Pin4 has a non-canonical RRM and large unstructured regions</title><p id="P7">Since very little functional information was available for Pin4, we first sought structural features that might point to its role in the cell. Conserved domains were analyzed utilizing multiple sequence alignments from the NCBI Conserved Domain Database <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref></sup>. Pin4 is 668 amino acids in length, with an unstructured Q/N-rich C-terminal region previously identified as a prion-forming domain <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">26</xref></sup>. Database searches and AlphaFold3 predicted three further domains: an RNA Recognition Motif (RRM), a coiled-coil (CC) domain, and an R3H domain with all other parts being largely unstructured (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1A</xref>) <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27">27</xref></sup>.</p><p id="P8">The Pin4 RRM is from the family “RRM_PIN4_like” domain (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1A</xref>) <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref></sup>, which is also present in five annotated proteins from fungal species and one protozoan (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD5">Supp. Figs. 1A and 1B</xref>). Of these, only <italic>Schizosaccharomyces pombe</italic> Cip1 and Cip2 are characterized, and were reported to function in gene regulation during oxidative stress <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">28</xref></sup>. Interestingly, the Pin4 RRM differs from canonical RRM domains, with alterations in the characteristic ribonucleoprotein (RNP) motifs. Positions 3 and 5 in RNP-1 and position 2 in RNP-2 are typically aromatic residues, Phe or Tyr, important for RNA binding. In Pin4, the corresponding amino acids are Leu128 (RNP-1 position 3), Phe130 (RNP-1 position 5), and Val 88 (RPN-2 position 2) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD5">Supp. Figs. 2A and 2B</xref>). Although, the leucine and valine residues are not aromatic, but hydrophobic, it is not completely unusual as equivalent residues can be also found in the same positions in RRMs of other yeast RNA binding proteins, including UPF3 and TAP <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">29</xref></sup>.</p><p id="P9">The Pin4 R3H is from the family of “R3H_RRM” domain, identified in other ten fungal proteins, mostly uncharacterized except for <italic>S.pombe</italic> Cip2 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD5">Supp. Figs. 1A and 1B</xref>). R3H domains can dimerize <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">30</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31">31</xref></sup> and AlphaFold3 reproducibly modeled the R3H domain of Pin4 as a homodimer, with good supporting statistics (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD5">Supp. Fig. 2C</xref>). This suggests that the R3H domain of Pin4 may be a dimerization element rather than a nucleic acid binding domain. The CC domain is predicted to mediate protein interactions, and also lies close to the RRM (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD5">Supp. Fig. 2D</xref>) <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32">32</xref></sup>, indicating a scaffolding role that could facilitate spatial proximity between RNA targets and protein interactors.</p></sec><sec id="S4"><title>Pin4 predominantly binds mRNA 3’ untranslated regions</title><p id="P10">Pin4 was an outlier in the total RNA-bound proteome following stress <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref></sup>. We therefore identified RNAs bound by Pin4 during growth in 2% glucose medium and following transfer to 2% glycerol plus ethanol (Gly/EtOH) medium for 16 min, to induce diauxic shift. To allow purification, we expressed Pin4 as a fusion protein with an N-terminal tandem-affinity tag containing a single FLAG epitope-Ala<sub>4</sub>-His<sub>8</sub> (FH tag) <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref></sup>. The 20 amino acid FH tag was introduced into the chromosomal <italic>PIN4</italic> gene under control of the endogenous promoter, using CRISPR-Cas9 without a selective marker <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33">33</xref></sup>. FH-Pin4 is the only form of Pin4 in these cells, which showed no clear growth defects.</p><p id="P11">We initially applied the published protocol for crosslinking and analysis of cDNA (CRAC) <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34">34</xref></sup>. However, Pin4 underwent substantial degradation during purification (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD5">Supp. Fig. 3A</xref>). We therefore developed a modified protocol, termed reverse CRAC (reCRAC) <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35">35</xref></sup>, which notably enhanced the integrity of Pin4 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1B</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD5">Supp. Fig. 3A</xref>). In reCRAC, the tandem affinity purifications steps are reversed relative to CRAC. Briefly, cells are lysed in highly denaturing buffer, including 6M Guanidine-HCl, to immediately inactivate cellular proteases. FH-Pin4 was recovered on Ni-NTA beads in denaturing buffer. While still immobilized on the Ni-NTA beads, but under non-denaturing conditions, bound RNAs were subjected to partial Benzonase digestion, the 5’ ends were labeled with <sup>[32]</sup>P, and linkers were added to the termini. Protein-RNA complexes were eluted and further purified on an anti-FLAG column. Following elution, complexes were gel purified using the labeled RNA as marker, and the proteins were degraded with proteinase K. RNA was recovered and used for RT-PCR amplification and sequencing. Replicate experiments showed good reproducibility (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD5">Supp. Figs. 3B and 3C</xref>).</p><p id="P12">During reCRAC, samples were barcoded and mixed prior to RT-PCR amplification. In consequence, relative numbers of total reads recovered for each condition approximates to overall crosslinking efficiency. The total number of reads in the FH-Pin4 libraries decreased dramatically following glucose withdrawal, indicating strongly decreased overall RNA binding (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1C</xref>). In glucose rich conditions, Pin4 predominantly targeted mRNAs, which constituted about 70% of its interactions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1D</xref>). Reads were also mapped to “non-coding” RNAs, but these were distributed over a large and heterogeneous set of RNAs, mainly antisense and intergenic, and specific interactions were not evident. Following glucose depletion, there was a 50% reduction in the fraction of reads mapped to mRNA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1D</xref>). Absolute recovery of rRNA was similar to the untagged control, indicating that these represent non-specific interactions (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD5">Supp. Fig. 3D</xref>), and the apparent increase following glucose depletion likely reflects loss of mRNA binding.</p><p id="P13">To assess Pin4 binding specificity, we analyzed the distribution of FH-Pin4 bound sequencing reads across the 5’ untranslated region (UTR), coding sequence (CDS), and 3’ UTR of all annotated mRNAs. In the presence of glucose, Pin4 predominantly bound 3’ UTR regions; these formed 78% of reCRAC reads compared to 12% in total RNA from the RNAseq control (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2A</xref>). This pattern of predominant 3’ UTR binding is apparent in a metagene plot in which reCRAC reads are mapped onto mRNAs aligned at their 3’ ends, revealing a distinct 3’ peak (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2B</xref>). On individual mRNAs with strong Pin4 binding relative to RNAseq, the prominent peak in the 3’ UTR is very clearly visible (shown for <italic>TPI1, ILV5, GPM1</italic> and <italic>RPS12</italic> in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1C</xref>).</p><p id="P14">Following glucose withdrawal, the enrichment for Pin4 binding to 3’ UTRs is notably decreased (49% of all reads) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2A</xref>), although some indication of preferential 3’ binding remained (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2B</xref>). On most top mRNAs, residual Pin4 association remained enriched on the 3’ UTR (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2C</xref>). However, a subset had substantial CDS binding after glucose depletion. These transcripts were generally related to ribosomes and translation (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD5">Supp. Fig. 3E; Supp. Table 4</xref>). As an example, <italic>RPS12</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2C</xref>) has substantial Pin4 binding in the CDS, even though the highest peak was still in the 3’ UTR.</p></sec><sec id="S5"><title>A binding motif for Pin4</title><p id="P15">In reCRAC, the direct sites of RNA-protein crosslinks can be pinpointed by searching for deletions within recovered sequences. At the end of the experimental procedure, the bound protein is degraded by proteinase K treatment, leaving at least one amino acid on the RNA. Due to this, reverse transcriptase can skip the crosslinked nucleotide. Nucleotide substitutions can arise from other causes (PCR, RT, sequencing) but single nucleotide deletions are characteristic, and otherwise very rare. Using this data on Pin4 binding sites to identify potential sequence determinants, we focused on high-confidence Pin4 targets under both glucose and Gly/EtOH conditions; the cut off being at least 0.3% of the library in at least two replicates (35 transcripts in glucose; 38 transcripts following withdrawal) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supp. Table 5</xref>). After identifying the most significant deletion peaks within these transcripts, we ran MEME analysis on the flanking 20 nucleotide sequences. We discovered a consistent T(A/T)ATG(A/T) motif across both conditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2D</xref>). This motif was generally located either precisely at the peak of binding (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2E</xref>), or immediately adjacent to the highest deletion peak (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD5">Supp. Fig. 3F</xref>). The close association of the motif with the peak of Pin4 binding was maintained in glucose replete and depleted conditions.</p><p id="P16">Analysis of the high-confidence Pin4 targets showed no consistent pattern of pairs of binding sites that would indicate binding as a homodimer. Analysis of mRNAs that were well bound by Pin4, but not enriched relative to mRNA abundance (on or below the diagonal in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs. 3A and 3B</xref>), showed no clear motif enrichment.</p><p id="P17">We conclude that the T(A/T)ATG(A/T) motif is very likely to represent a direct Pin4 recognition element.</p></sec><sec id="S6"><title>Pin4 selectively binds metabolic and growth-associated transcripts</title><p id="P18">To assess mRNA target specificity, Pin4-associated RNAs isolated with reCRAC were compared to mRNA abundances from WT RNAseq (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">Supp. Table 6</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs. 3A and 3B</xref>). It showed that majority of mRNAs associate with Pin4: confident strongly bound targets that showed enrichment are highlighted. In glucose medium, the most enriched Pin4-associated transcripts were predominantly involved in metabolic and pro-growth pathways (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3A</xref>). Key glycolytic enzymes emerged as top targets in both conditions, including <italic>TPI1</italic> (triose phosphate isomerase), <italic>ADH1</italic> (alcohol dehydrogenase), and <italic>GPM1</italic> (phosphoglycerate mutase) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3C</xref>). <italic>TPI1</italic> alone represented about 4% of reads, versus 0.5% from RNAseq in glucose (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3D</xref>). Transcripts involved in mitochondrial function (e.g., <italic>ILV5</italic>) and amino acid metabolism (e.g., <italic>HIS4</italic>) were strongly targeted only in glucose-rich conditions.</p><p id="P19">For high confidence interactions (≥0.3% of library in ≥ 2 replicates) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supp. Table 5</xref>) comparing Pin4 binding relative to transcript abundance confirmed significant GO term enrichment: glycolysis (p=0.0288), amino acid metabolism (p=0.0079), and mitochondrial metabolism (p&lt;0.0001) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3E</xref>). This enrichment was also reproduced by grouping the transcripts based on their binding enrichment and GO term analysis using the Proteomaps tool <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36">36</xref></sup> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD5">Supp. Fig. 4A</xref>). These high-confidence targets showed good reproducibility across replicates in both conditions (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD5">Supp. Fig. 4B</xref>).</p><p id="P20">Following glucose withdrawal, there were fewer clearly enriched targets, consistent with the metagene plot, but some of the same genes remained enriched, including the glycolytic enzymes. Representation was strongly increased for several translation-related transcripts (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3F</xref>), which correspond to the mRNAs showing Pin4 association across the CDS (e.g. <italic>RPS12</italic>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2C</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD5">Supp. Fig. 2E</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S7"><title>Pin4-deficient cells are sensitive to glucose depletion and mitochondrial stress</title><p id="P21">As Pin4 binds mRNAs connected to central carbon metabolism and mitochondria, we tested for growth phenotypes after precisely deleting <italic>PIN4</italic> using a KanMX6 cassette <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37">37</xref></sup>. In glucose medium, <italic>pin4Δ</italic> strains showed only a slight increase in doubling time compared to WT (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD5">Supp. Fig. 5A</xref>). However, upon shifting to 2% Gly/EtOH medium, <italic>pin4Δ</italic> cells exhibited greatly increased lag before reinitiation of growth (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD5">Supp Fig. 5B</xref>), followed by a steady-state doubling time of approximately 7 hr versus 6 hr for the WT (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD5">Supp. Fig. 5C</xref>). Under oxidative stress induced by 0.5 mM hydrogen peroxide, <italic>pin4Δ</italic> cells had a lag phase of 30 hr compared to 15 hr for WT (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD5">Supp. Figs. 5D and 5E</xref>). At 1 mM H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>, <italic>pin4Δ</italic> cells showed no growth, whereas WT cells remained viable. Exposure to glyoxal, which collapses mitochondrial membrane potential, also led to slowed growth and increased lag phase in <italic>pin4Δ</italic> cells (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD5">Supp. Fig. 5F</xref>), with growth progressively decreasing at higher concentrations compared to WT (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD5">Supp. Fig 5G</xref>).</p><p id="P22">We conclude that cells lacking Pin4 exhibit hypersensitivity to glucose withdrawal or mitochondrial stress, consistent with the targets for Pin4 binding.</p></sec><sec id="S8"><title>Pin4 negatively regulates target mRNA abundance</title><p id="P23">To determine whether the loss of Pin4 affects target mRNA abundance, we performed RNA sequencing on WT and <italic>pin4Δ</italic> cells in glucose medium. Differential expression (DE) analysis identified 58 mRNAs showing the most altered expression between the WT and <italic>pin4Δ</italic> (fold change ≥ 2.0; adj. p ≤ 0.05) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4A</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD3">Supp. Table 7</xref>). The most upregulated mRNAs were enriched for cell wall components (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD5">Supp. Fig. 6A</xref>), but these generally had very low expression, making the significance unclear. Downregulated genes were preferentially linked to transmembrane transport and vitamin binding (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD5">Supp. Fig. 6B</xref>). The mRNA showing strongest DE were not top Pin4 targets. However, comparison of Pin4 mRNA binding and changes in abundance in <italic>pin4Δ</italic> cells revealed generally increased abundance for preferential Pin4 targets (high confidence mRNA targets with at least 0.3% of the library) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4B</xref>).</p><p id="P24">Analysis of recent proteomic data for <italic>pin4Δ</italic>, based on a genome-wide deletion screen, also showed modestly increased protein abundances for the products of high-confidence Pin4 mRNA targets <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38">38</xref></sup>. This suggested that Pin4 binding might destabilize target mRNAs and/or inhibit translation.</p><p id="P25">To test this hypothesis, we used the MoClo system to generate reporter constructs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4C</xref>). These express the Venus fluorescent protein under the control of the <italic>TEF2</italic> promoter (P<sub>TEF2</sub>), which is characterized by high and stable expression levels in both glucose and Gly/EtOH media, with expression unaffected in <italic>pin4Δ</italic> cells. We incorporated the 3’ UTR and terminator sequences of two strong Pin4 targets, <italic>TPI1</italic> (T<sub>TPI1</sub>) and <italic>GPM1</italic> (T<sub>GPM1</sub>), extending 479 and 500 nucleotides, respectively, beyond the stop codons. As a control, we used the 3’ UTR and terminator sequence of <italic>PNC1</italic> (T<sub>PNC1</sub>; 379 nucleotides), which is not bound by Pin4. The constructs where chromosomally integrated into the yeast HO locus, and Venus expression was monitored for mRNA (RT-qPCR) and protein (western blot levels).</p><p id="P26">In strains lacking Pin4, reporter constructs containing <italic>TPI1</italic> and <italic>GPM1</italic> 3’ UTRs showed a mild increase in mRNA levels in both glucose and following transfer to Gly/EtOH (16 min), which was not observed with the <italic>PNC1</italic> control (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4D</xref>). This result was consistent with our RNAseq data (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4E</xref>). Western blot analysis mirrored these findings at the protein level, displaying a modest increase in the expression of reporters with <italic>TPI1</italic> and <italic>GPM1</italic> 3’ UTRs in <italic>pin4Δ</italic> cells in both nutritional states (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4D</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD5">Supp Fig. 6C</xref>). Although the increases observed by RT-qPCR failed to pass a rigorous test for statistically significance, the trend of upregulation among Pin4 targets was seen across all analyses; PCR and western on reporters; RNAseq and proteomics on endogenous mRNAs and proteins. Together, these data support the conclusion that Pin4 binding modestly destabilizes target mRNAs, with consequent reductions in protein abundance.</p></sec><sec id="S9"><title>Impaired transcriptional response to stress in Pin4-deficient cells</title><p id="P27">Several mRNAs with altered abundance in <italic>pin4Δ</italic> cells were not strongly bound Pin4 targets (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4F</xref>). This indicated that the role of Pin4 involves mechanisms beyond specific interactions with individual mRNA. Wild-type cells undergo profound transcriptional changes following glucose withdrawal, characterized as the integrated stress response (ISR), which alters the abundance of several hundred mRNAs to promote cellular recovery. We analyzed RNA sequencing data following glucose depletion to determine whether the loss of Pin4 affects this response.</p><p id="P28">Principal component analysis (PCA) revealed surprisingly distinctive patterns: WT replicates clustered well in each condition and were clearly separated between glucose replete and glucose depleted conditions. In striking contrast, <italic>pin4Δ</italic> samples clustered together regardless of the treatment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5A</xref>). This clustering suggested minimal transcriptional changes in <italic>pin4Δ</italic> cells following glucose depletion. Spearman correlation heatmaps confirmed the distinction between WT in glucose versus Gly/EtOH, but high similarities in both conditions for <italic>pin4Δ</italic> cells – as well as consistency in the replicates (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5B</xref>). A heatmap of gene expression (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5C</xref>) further confirmed the minimal variation in <italic>pin4Δ</italic> cells following glucose depletion. This indicates a critical role for Pin4 in the transcriptional response to glucose starvation.</p><p id="P29">Detailed analysis of all individual transcripts further underscored these observations. Following glucose depletion, differential gene expression (DE) analysis identified 645 transcripts present at significantly different levels in WT and <italic>pin4</italic>Δ cells (fold change ≥ 2.0; adj. p ≤ 0.05), a strikingly large number (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5D</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD4">Supp. Table 8</xref>). In almost all cases, DE reflects stress-induced changes, up and down, in the WT that are lost in the <italic>pin4</italic>Δ. As expected, stress response genes were strongly upregulated in the WT, whereas pro-growth genes were downregulated, including RNP and ribosome biogenesis. In cells lacking Pin4, the latter were little altered and thus elevated in comparison to the WT (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5E</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD5">Supp. Fig. 7A</xref>). Additionally, mRNAs linked to catabolic and respiration-related processes were lower in <italic>pin4</italic>Δ (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5F</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD5">Supp. Fig. 7B</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S10"><title>Pin4 domains required for the transcriptional response to glucose starvation</title><p id="P30">To better characterize the role of Pin4 in the transcriptional response to glucose starvation, we constructed Pin4 mutant strains lacking functional domains.</p><p id="P31">To assess the role of RNA binding, we created strains precisely lacking the RRM domain (<italic>pin4</italic><sub><italic>RRMΔ</italic></sub>) or with point mutations (<italic>pin4</italic><sub><italic>RRM-M1</italic></sub>: V88A, L128A, F130A) predicted to disrupt RNA binding while maintaining RRM domain structure (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6A</xref>). Unexpectedly, the <italic>pin4<sub>RRM-M1</sub></italic> variant exhibited notably slower growth than WT, <italic>pin4Δ</italic> or pin4<sub><italic>RRMΔ</italic></sub> strains (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD5">Supp. Fig. 7C</xref>). The basis for this is unclear and currently under investigation.</p><p id="P32">The effects of these mutations were tested by RT-qPCR on the <italic>MTH1, HSP12</italic>, and <italic>HXT7</italic> genes, which were strongly upregulated following glucose withdrawal in the WT. Expression was analyzed during growth on glucose, and 16 or 32 min after transfer to Gly/EtOH medium. In glucose medium, the mRNAs were expressed at similar, very low levels in all strains, WT, <italic>pin4</italic>Δ, <italic>pin4</italic><sub><italic>RRM</italic>Δ</sub> or <italic>pin4</italic><sub><italic>RRM-M1</italic></sub>. Following glucose depletion, the mRNAs were strongly induced in the WT, but this was much less marked in <italic>pin4</italic>Δ or <italic>pin4</italic><sub><italic>RRM</italic>Δ</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6B</xref>). In the <italic>pin4</italic><sub><italic>RRM-M1</italic></sub> strain induction of <italic>HSP12</italic> was reduced to a similar extent to <italic>pin4</italic>Δ, while induction of <italic>HXT7</italic> and <italic>MTH1</italic> was even lower in <italic>pin4</italic><sub><italic>RRM-M1</italic></sub>.</p><p id="P33">The Pin4 C-terminal region is intrinsically disordered and potentially prion-forming <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39">39</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41">41</xref></sup>, but includes the R3H domain. To test its function, we created a construct truncated after the N-terminal 200 aa (<italic>pin4</italic><sub>Δ<italic>CT</italic></sub>), fused with GFP to improve stability (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6A</xref>). Following transfer of <italic>pin4</italic><sub><italic>ΔCT</italic></sub> to Gly/EtOH for 16 min, transcriptional induction of <italic>MTH1, HSP12</italic>, and <italic>HXT7</italic> was significantly reduced relative to the WT, and very similar to <italic>pin4</italic>Δ and <italic>pin4</italic><sub><italic>RRM</italic>Δ</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6C</xref>).</p><p id="P34">We conclude that both a functional RRM domain and the disordered C-terminal region of Pin4 are required for the transcriptional response to glucose withdrawal, suggesting functional interactions with both RNA and proteins.</p></sec><sec id="S11"><title>Role of Pin4 in bridging post-transcriptional and transcriptional stress responses</title><p id="P35">To place Pin4 function in the wider context of stress responses we assessed immediate post-transcriptional effects. A very rapid reduction in global protein synthesis normally follows glucose depletion <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref></sup>. Polysome analyses indicated a comparable loss of translation in WT and <italic>pin4</italic>Δ cells (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD5">Supp. Fig. 7D</xref>) following transfer from glucose to Gly/EtOH medium, suggesting that this initial response to glucose starvation is unperturbed.</p><p id="P36">In WT yeast, glucose depletion induces formation of Hsp104 granules, an HSP100-family disaggregase that resolves stress-induced protein aggregates <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42">42</xref></sup>. In live cell imaging of WT cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7A</xref>), 18% of cells had at least one Hsp104 granule on glucose medium, rising to almost 40% during the first 24 min following transfer to Gly/EtOH medium. Granule frequency plateaued around 70% after 90 min (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8B</xref>), as reported <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43">43</xref></sup>. In contrast, <italic>pin4</italic><sub><italic>RRM</italic>Δ</sub> showed a significantly reduced response. The percentage of cells exhibiting at least one Hsp104 granule increased only mildly, from approximately 20% in glucose to a plateau of around 30%, after 45 min in Gly/EtOH medium (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8C</xref>). This muted response was also seen for total Hsp104-GFP induction (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8C</xref>).</p><p id="P37">We conclude that Pin4 is dispensable for the rapid, initial shutdown of protein synthesis following starvation, but required for subsequent post-transcriptional, and longer term, transcriptional responses.</p></sec></sec><sec id="S12" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p id="P38">RNA binding proteins (RBPs) play crucial roles in cellular responses to many environmental stresses. We previously screened for global changes in the RNA-protein interactome on a short timescale following a variety of stresses, including heat shock and glucose withdrawal <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref></sup>. Unexpectedly, a set of largely uncharacterized proteins were among the most stress responsive RBPs. Included in these “unknome” factors was Pin4, which we functionally characterized here.</p><p id="P39">Using the newly developed reCRAC technique,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35">35</xref></sup> Pin4 showed a distinctive pattern of binding to mRNA 3’ UTRs during growth on glucose medium. The mRNAs with strong Pin4 binding, relative to RNA abundance, all carried a clear consensus motif. This was located close to the site of crosslinking, which can be identified at the nucleotide level in reCRAC, strongly supporting its role as a direct Pin4 recognition element. However, 3’ UTRs of almost all mRNA were detectably bound by Pin4, indicating that recognition by Pin4 has at least two components: Recognition of some feature(s) common to all mRNA 3’ UTRs, plus binding to a specific sequence motif. Notably, the functional classes of mRNAs favored for Pin4 binding were not random. They included most glycolytic enzymes, plus several key mitochondrial proteins and a small number of important enzymes in amino acid metabolism.</p><p id="P40">Following glucose depletion, overall RNA crosslinking of Pin4 was substantially reduced, particularly for mRNAs. However, the preference for 3’ UTR binding and the same enriched motif were preserved, suggesting that the recruitment mechanism is retained. The reduced interactions could reflect altered Pin4 affinity, e.g. due to phosphorylation, which is altered at multiple sites in response to stress <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R44">44</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R49">49</xref></sup>, or reductions in the availability of Pin4 and/or mRNAs. mRNA availability might be reduced by sequestration into cytoplasmic condensates <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R50">50</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R51">51</xref></sup>. Pin4 homodimerization through the R3H domain might reduce its availability, but there was no indication of binding RNA as a dimer in our data. Potentially, Pin4 may form aggregates via its prion-like domain, affecting its interactions with RNA <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">26</xref></sup>. We noted that translation-related transcripts showed increased Pin4-binding following glucose withdrawal. This included binding throughout CDS, where we were unable to detect a Pin4-motif. Following glucose withdrawal, these pre-stress mRNAs are still present in large quantities but are largely ribosome-free <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R52">52</xref></sup>. We hypothesize that the CDS signal reflects Pin4 association/close proximity in the absence of sequence-specific binding, potentially within cytoplasmic condensates <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R50">50</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R51">51</xref></sup>.</p><p id="P41">Analyses using reporter constructs indicated that Pin4 binding modestly destabilized mRNA targets, under both glucose-replete and glucose-depleted conditions, with consequent reductions in reporter protein accumulation. This conclusion was supported by RNA sequencing in strains lacking Pin4, and a recent, systematic analyses of protein abundances in yeast deletion mutants <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R53">53</xref></sup>. Previous high-throughput analyses reported protein-protein interactions between Pin4 and components of the CCR4-NOT complex (Caf40, Cdc39, Cdc36, Mot2, Ccr4), which mediates mRNA degradation <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R54">54</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R56">56</xref></sup>. The localization of Pin4 binding sites within the 3’ UTR would be consistent with destabilization of mRNA targets. The retargeting of Pin4 onto the non-ribosome bound, translation-related transcripts following stress might also fit this model. The preferred mRNA targets for Pin4 in glycolysis and mitochondria suggested roles in energy metabolism. In glucose medium, <italic>pin4Δ</italic> cells exhibited hypersensitivity to both H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>, which induces oxidative stress, and glyoxal, a reactive carbonyl species that generates reactive oxygen species and disrupts mitochondrial membrane potential <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R57">57</xref></sup>. We speculate that this hypersensitivity is linked to misregulated mitochondrial function due to imbalances in protein production in the absence of Pin4.</p><p id="P42">Unexpectedly, loss of Pin4 profoundly affected transcriptional adaptation to glucose depletion, almost completely abolishing the induction of stress-responsive mRNAs. We identified 645 mRNAs that were significantly differentially expressed between Pin4-deficient cells and WT cells following starvation. In the WT, mRNAs related to stress response, mitochondria, and respiration were massively upregulated, consistent with the shift from fermentation to respiration. In cells lacking Pin4, these changes were absent, and the transcriptional profile closely resembled glucose-rich conditions. The cells apparently failed to recognize or respond to the stress applied. Given this lack of transcriptional response, it is unsurprising that <italic>pin4Δ</italic> cells displayed greatly impaired recovery of growth following transfer from glucose to non-fermentable carbon sources. However, the exact point at which Pin4 operates within the glucose signaling pathways, and how its absence blocks the transcriptional response, remains unclear. Previous data suggest links between glycolytic flux and signaling of the presence or absence of glucose <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref></sup> and Pin4 might function here.</p><p id="P43">To test whether RNA binding by Pin4 is needed for the transcriptional response, we generated strains lacking the single RRM of Pin4 or carrying RRM point mutations predicted to disrupt protein-RNA binding but not domain structure. Both mutants recapitulated the <italic>pin4Δ</italic> transcription phenotype in response to glucose withdrawal. This strongly indicates that RNA binding of Pin4 is integral to induction of the transcriptional stress response. It could be envisaged that Pin4 has two binding modes – specific binding of particular mRNA targets with biological roles and a “bulk” RNA binding that is non-specific. Major Pin4 target mRNAs did not include key glucose signaling factors or other obvious transcriptional regulators. Moreover, the modest post-transcriptional destabilization of target mRNAs contrasts with the massive loss of transcriptional changes observed in cells lacking Pin4. We would therefore suspect that this “bulk” binding may relate to the transcriptional effects of Pin4 that extend beyond its targets. This suggests that alterations in total RNA interactions might regulate Pin4 function.</p><p id="P44">Deletion of C-terminal region in <italic>pin4</italic><sub>ΔCT</sub> also blocked transcriptional reprograming. The region deleted was previously reported to form prion-like aggregates <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">23</xref></sup>, suggesting that this may be the key missing function in these mutants. However, initial live cell imaging did not reveal clear Pin4 aggregation. The deletion also removes a putative R3H domain, which modelling suggested would support homodimerization. However, the reCRAC data provided no evidence that the RNA-bound form of Pin4 is a homodimer. It is possible that the release of Pin4 from mRNA may allow Pin4 to interact with other factors, and loss of this interaction may contribute to the absence of a transcriptional stress response.</p><p id="P45">To further address the stress responses in the absence of Pin4, or its RRM, we quantified Hsp104 granules, which form in response to protein misfolding following environmental insults <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R58">58</xref></sup>. Live cell imaging revealed that <italic>pin4</italic><sub><italic>RRM</italic>Δ</sub> cells almost entirely failed to induce Hsp104 granule formation, highlighting the loss of stress response.</p><p id="P46">In summary, we propose a dual-function model for Pin4 in glucose-rich and glucose-depleted conditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8</xref>). In glucose conditions, Pin4 binds to the 3’ UTRs of metabolic and pro-growth mRNAs, and regulates gene expression post-transcriptionally by promoting their destabilization. Following glucose withdrawal, Pin4 s required to activate the transcriptional starvation response through mechanisms involving its RNA recognition motif and prion-forming domain. The requirement for RRM function suggests that regulation requires RNA interactions, and represents an example of riboregulation.</p><p id="P47">Glucose signaling pathways have previously been extensively characterized, without identification of a role for Pin4. However, these were based on genetic screens on the timescale of days, whereas we assessed responses over minutes. We note that this is the timescale needed for rapid and reversible responses to environmental stimuli. Loss and restoration of nutrient availability on plant surfaces might occur several times a day, and transient but substantial stresses will be the norm in many biological systems. Post-transcriptional mechanisms likely provide the first responses, on second to minute timescales, followed by longer term transcriptional changes that persist for days. It might be beneficial to have mechanisms that bridge and coordinate these different levels of response, and we predict that Pin4 plays such a role.</p></sec><sec id="S13" sec-type="materials | methods"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="S14"><title>Reagents</title><p id="P48">10 mM dNTP mix (Thermo Scientific, Cat#18427013)</p><p id="P49">10x NEBuffer 2.1 (NEB, Cat#B7202)</p><p id="P50">10x T4 DNA ligase buffer (NEB, Cat# B0202S)</p><p id="P51">5-alpha Competent E.coli High Efficiency (NEB, Cat# C2987I)</p><p id="P52">Act1 primary antibody (Abcam, Cat# 8224)</p><p id="P53">BamHI-HF (NEB, Cat# R3136S)</p><p id="P54">BclI (NEB, Cat#R0160S)</p><p id="P55">BsaI-HF-v2 (NEB, Cat# R3733S)</p><p id="P56">BsmBI-v2 (NEB, Cat# R0739S)</p><p id="P57">Concanavalin A (Sigma, Cat# C2272-2MG)</p><p id="P58">CSM Complete (Formedium, Cat#DCS0011)</p><p id="P59">CSM Single Drop-out -Trp (Formedium, Cat#DCS0149)</p><p id="P60">Cycloheximide – stock of 20 mg/ ml in EtOH prepared and stored at -20C (Sigma-Aldrich, Cat#C7698-5G)</p><p id="P61">D (+) – Glucose Anhydrous (Thermo Scientific, Cat#10141520)</p><p id="P62">DNase/RNase free water</p><p id="P63">EcoRI-HF (NEB, Cat# R3101S)</p><p id="P64">EDTA-free cOmplete protease inhibitor cocktail (Roche, Cat#11836170001)</p><p id="P65">FLAG antibody (Sigma Aldrich, Cat# SAB4200071)</p><p id="P66">Glyoxal solution (Merck, Cat#128465)</p><p id="P67">HindIII-HF (NEB, Cat# R3104S)</p><p id="P68">Hydrogen Peroxide (Acros Organics, Cat#7722-84-1)</p><p id="P69">Klenow exo- (NEB, Cat#M0212L)</p><p id="P70">Microscopy chamber with 8 individual wells high glass bottom (Thistle Scientific, Cat# IB-80807)</p><p id="P71">MOPS running buffer 20x (Invitrogen, NP0001)</p><p id="P72">Nitrocellulose membrane (Thermo Scientific, Cat#88018)</p><p id="P73">NotI-HF (NEB, Cat# R3189S)</p><p id="P74">NuPAGE Bis-Tris 4-12% precast gradient gels (Invitrogen, Cat#NP0321BOX)</p><p id="P75">OneShot Top10 Chemically competent E. coli (Thermo Scientific, Cat#C404003)</p><p id="P76">Phusion High-Fidelity DNA polymerase (NEB, Cat# M0530S)</p><p id="P77">Random hexamers (Thermo Scientific, Cat# 10609275)</p><p id="P78">RNasin (Promega, Cat# N2511)</p><p id="P79">RQ1 DNase (Promega, Cat# M6101)</p><p id="P80">Superscript III RT, 0.1M DTT, 5x First Strand Buffer (Invitrogen, Cat#18080093)</p><p id="P81">SwaI (NEB, Cat#R0604S)</p><p id="P82">T4 DNA ligase (NEB, Cat# M0202L)</p><p id="P83">TRIzol Reagent (Invitrogen, Cat#15596026)</p><p id="P84">Venus primary antibody (Agrisera, Cat# AS184227)</p><p id="P85">Yeast Nitrogen Base (Formedium, Cat#CYN0410)</p><p id="P86">Zirconia beads (Thiste Scientific, Cat#ZrOB05)</p></sec><sec id="S15"><title>Commercial kits</title><p id="P87">Gel extraction kit (QIAGEN, Cat#28704)</p><p id="P88">Min Elute PCR purification kit (QIAGEN, Cat#28004)</p><p id="P89">Plasmid miniprep (ZYMO Research, Cat# D4016)</p><p id="P90">RNA clean &amp; concentrator kit (ZYMO Research, Cat# <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://zymoresearch.eu/collections/rna-clean-concentrator-kits-rcc/products/rna-clean-concentrator-5">R1013</ext-link>)</p><p id="P91">Zymoclean Gel DNA recovery kit (ZYMO Research, Cat# D4007)</p></sec><sec id="S16"><title>Oligonucleotides</title><p id="P92">All oligonucleotides used in this study are listed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD5">Supplementary Table 1</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="S17"><title>Strains</title><p id="P93">All strains generated in this study are listed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD5">Supplementary Table 2</xref> and are available from the lead contact upon request.</p></sec><sec id="S18"><title>Plasmids</title><p id="P94">All plasmids generated in this study are listed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD5">Supplementary Table 3</xref> and are available from the lead contact upon request.</p></sec><sec id="S19"><title>Deposited data</title><p id="P95">reCRAC and RNAseq raw data</p></sec><sec id="S20"><title>Software and Algorithms</title><p id="P96">BEdtools <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R59">59</xref></sup></p><p id="P97">EdgeR <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R60">60</xref></sup></p><p id="P98">Flexbar <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R61">61</xref></sup></p><p id="P99">ggplot2 <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R62">62</xref></sup></p><p id="P100">IGV <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R63">63</xref></sup></p><p id="P101">Metamorph software (Molecular Devices)</p><p id="P102">Novoalign (V2.07.00, Novocraft Technologies)</p><p id="P103">GraphPad Prism Version 10.0.3</p><p id="P104">Proteomaps<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36">36</xref></sup></p><p id="P105">pyCRAC <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R64">64</xref></sup></p><p id="P106">PyMOL 3.1(Molecular Graphics System)</p><p id="P107">Salmon<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R65">65</xref></sup></p></sec></sec><sec id="S21" sec-type="methods"><title>Method Details</title><sec id="S22"><title>Yeast cell culture and media</title><p id="P108">All Saccharomyces cerevisiae strains used in this paper originated from the BY4741 background (MATa his3Δ1 leu2Δ0 met15Δ0 ura3Δ0). Yeast cultures were grown in a growth medium containing 2% D-glucose, 2% yeast nitrogen base, and a 2% complement of amino acids excluding tryptophan (SD-Trp) at 30°C shaking. For all the experiments, the cultures were grown to a stationary phase overnight and then diluted the next morning from OD<sub>600</sub> of 0.05 to OD<sub>600</sub> of 0.45. For experimental treatments, yeast cells were either harvested directly from glucose-supplemented media (Glucose) or subjected to glucose deprivation by transferring to the same media but lacking glucose and instead supplemented with 2% glycerol and 2% ethanol (Glucose starvation). Only for the polysome profiling experiment, the cells were grown in a synthetic complete (SC) medium.</p><p id="P109">For reCRAC, cells were crosslinked with UVC at 254 nm at an OD<sub>600</sub> of 0.45. Harvesting for both reCRAC, RNAseq and qPCR experiments involved rapid filtration of the cultures onto a nitrocellulose membrane, immediate immersion of the membrane into 50 mL of ice-cold water, centrifugation at 4,600 rpm for 2 min at 4°C, and subsequent freezing of the cell pellet.</p></sec><sec id="S23"><title>Gene tagging, mutations and deletion</title><p id="P110">For reCRAC experiment, the chromosomal locus of Pin4 was modified to include an N-terminal FLAG-His (FH) tag. This tag consists of a FLAG sequence (GATTATAAAGATGAC GATGACAAG), a four-alanine spacer (GCCGCAGCCGCA), and a chain of eight histidines (CATCACCACCATCATCACCATCAC).</p><p id="P111">The integration of the FH tag was done using a CRISPR-Cas9 system, utilizing the pML104 plasmid as described <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33">33</xref></sup>. This plasmid is engineered to include the Cas9 sequence, an ampicillin resistance gene, and the URA3 selection marker. It is also optimized for efficient and directional cloning of single guide (sg) RNA. The design features an sgRNA with a GATC overhang compatible for cloning, which is a 20-nucleotide guide sequence that targets genomic DNA (e.g. the N-terminus of Pin4), and a structural segment critical for Cas9 binding (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD5">Supp. Table 1</xref>). The yeast CRISPR-Cas9 system stimulates homologous recombination using a repair template that is co-transformed with the Cas9 and sgRNA expressing vector. This template includes homology regions close to the cleavage site, the sequence to be introduced/changed, and mutations either in the sgRNA target or in the adjacent PAM sequence (NGG) to confer resistance to further Cas9 cleavage in modified cells (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD5">Supp. Table 1</xref>).</p><p id="P112">Briefly, for sgRNA preparation,10 μg of pML104 plasmid was digested overnight at room temperature with 2 μL of SwaI, subsequently inactivated at 65°C for 20 min, and further digested with 2 μL of BclI at 50°C for 2 hours. Following gel extraction with QIAGEN Gel extraction kit, the cut plasmid was ethanol precipitated, resuspended in water, aliquoted and stored at -80°C. The sgRNA oligos (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD5">Supp. Table 1</xref>) were annealed by combining 1 μM of each oligo with 1x T4 DNA ligase buffer in a total volume of 100 μL, heated at 95°C for 5 min, and then allowed to cool gradually to 20°C with the speed of 45s/°C. The annealed oligos were ligated with 66 ng of linearized pML104 plasmid using 0.5 μL T4 DNA ligase and 1x T4 DNA ligase buffer in a reaction volume of 10 μL. The mixture was kept at room temperature for 2 hours, transformed into OneShot Top10 Chemically Competent E. coli cells, and plated on LB-Amp plates. Plasmid DNA was isolated and sequenced to confirm the accurate sgRNA insertion in pML104 plasmid.</p><p id="P113">The FH tag was integrated using two repair templates consisting of the FH sequence flanked by 45 bp homology arms with engineered silent mutation to disrupt the PAM site, and 20 bp overlap at their 3’ ends (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD5">Supp. Table 1</xref>). The repair template was made by annealing two 10 μM repair template oligos in 1x NEBuffer 2.1 in a reaction volume of 50 μL at 95°C for 6 min, and then decreasing the temperature by 1°C every 30s until 20°C was reached. The repair template was then extended with 1 μL of Klenow exo-together with 1.25 μL of 10 mM dNTPs for 1 hour at 37°C. 10 μL of the annealed and extended repair template was then co-transformed with 500 ng of sgRNA containing-pML104 plasmid into BY4741 strain using the standard PEG/LiOAc yeast protocol. Selection occurred twice on -URA plates, with further restreaking on YPD to remove the selection plasmids. Colonies were then restreaked on both YPD and -URA, and the ones that lost the pML104 plasmid and failed to grow on -URA were verified by PCR using the check oligos (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD5">Supp. Table 1</xref>) and sequenced for the correct insertion of the FH tag.</p><p id="P114">The pin4<sub><italic>RRMΔ</italic></sub> strain, which involves deletion of the entire RRM domain from A86 to V158, and the pin4<sub>RRM-M1</sub> strain (V88A, L128A, F130A) was generated in the N-FH Pin4 background using the CRIRPS/Cas9 system, following the protocol described above. See <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD5">Supp. Table 1</xref> for the used oligos. For the complete deletion of the Pin4 gene, we employed conventional homologous recombination, utilizing the KanMX6 cassette from the pFa6a plasmid (Addgene #39296), with oligonucleotides detailed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD5">Supp. Table 1</xref>.</p><p id="P115">The Hsp104 protein was C-terminally tagged with GFP (S65T version) using a PCR-based method from the pFa6A plasmid (Addgene #39293), incorporating the KanMX6 selection marker (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD5">Supp. Table 1</xref>). The resulting construct was transformed into the BY4741 strain and pin4<sub><italic>RRMΔ</italic></sub> strain. The pin4<sub><italic>ΔCT</italic></sub>, where GFP was inserted after the first 200 amino acids of Pin4 was made by taking the GFP (S65T) from the pFa6A plasmid (Addgene #39293) and using it as the repair template utilizing CRISPR-Cas9 system as described above.</p></sec><sec id="S24"><title>Growth curves</title><p id="P116">For the growth curves, yeast strains were inoculated from single colonies and grown overnight in SD-Trp medium. The cultures were then diluted to an optical density OD<sub>600</sub> of 0.05 and grown to an OD<sub>600</sub> of 0.45 in SD-Trp. At this exponential growth phase, cultures were diluted to an OD<sub>600</sub> of 0.025 and 120 μL aliquots were pipetted into a 96-well plate. Stress-inducing agents were added to the wells at varying final concentrations: glyoxal at 0.3, 1,5, 3, 9 and 30 mM; and hydrogen peroxide at 0.5 and 1 mM. The 96-well plate was sealed with a sealing tape to minimize evaporation and placed in a Sunrise TECAN plate reader with a continuous shaking at 30°C. Optical density measurements were taken every 15 min to monitor growth. Each condition was tested in technical triplicate and biological duplicate. Specific strains are provided in the corresponding Fig. legends.</p><p id="P117">For the glucose starvation experiment, overnight saturated BY4741 and <italic>pin4Δ</italic> cells were diluted to an OD<sub>600</sub> of 0.05 and grown to an OD<sub>600</sub> <sub>of</sub> 0.40 in SD-Trp. Cells were then centrifuged, washed, resuspended in a medium containing 2% glycerol and 2% ethanol, and grown in this medium from an OD<sub>600</sub> of 0.075. Growth was monitored over a period of 2.5 days. This condition was tested in a biological duplicate.</p></sec><sec id="S25"><title>reCRAC</title><p id="P118">See Ristová et al,. (2024) for a detailed protocol and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1B</xref> for a visual overview of reCRAC. Briefly, Pin4 was engineered to include an N-terminal FLAG-4xAlanines-8xHistidines (FH) tag expressed from its native promoter to ensure it is the only variant produced. Expression of the tagged construct was verified by western blot (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD5">Supp. Fig. 3A</xref>). The strain was grown in SD-Trp, and upon reaching the exponential growth, cultures were UV crosslinked at 254 nm to stabilize RNA-protein interactions either in glucose medium or shifted to glucose-deprived medium (2%glycerol, 2% ethanol) for 16 min. The lysis step involved highly denaturing conditions with 6 M Guanidine – HCl to prevent protein degradation, with subsequent purification step performed on Ni-NTA beads under similarly stringent conditions. The adapter ligation, radiolabeling with <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32">32</xref></sup>P and partial Benzonase digestion to generate protein-protected RNA fragments were performed on the beads. Following elution from the Ni-NTA beads, a second purification on anti-FLAG beads was performed under more native conditions. The samples were then visualized via autoradiography, the RNA bound to the target protein was cut out and treated with Proteinase K. The RNA was then converted to cDNA, amplified and analyzed by high-throughput sequencing.</p></sec><sec id="S26"><title>Reporter constructs</title><p id="P119">To study the effect of Pin4 binding on its RNA targets, we made reporter constructs using the modular cloning system (MoClo) <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R66">66</xref></sup>. This system involves assembling approximately nine modular parts (Part plasmids) – including different promoters, coding regions, terminators, etc. – in a manner similar to LEGO, creating a complete Cassette reporter plasmid in a single golden gate assembly reaction, which can be chromosomally integrated.</p><p id="P120">All toolkit Part plasmids except the terminator Part plasmids used in this study were obtained from Addgene and are found in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD5">Supp. Table 3</xref>. The terminator Part plasmids containing the sequences of 3’ UTRs of Pin4 reCRAC targets (TPI1, GPM1) and a non-target control (PNC1) were generated for this study using PCR and standard cloning techniques.</p><p id="P121">The process to generate the terminator Part plasmids began by modifying the target terminator sequence to incorporate BsmBI and BsaI restriction sites via PCR amplification. This was done by extracting DNA from the parental By4741 strain using 100 μL of 200 mM LiOAc and 1% SDS solution. The sample was incubated at 70°C for 5 min, then precipitated with ethanol. The purified DNA then served as the template for PCR reactions using Phusion DNA Polymerase, with oligonucleotides listed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD5">Supp. Table 1</xref> (oligos #526, 527, 528, 529, 532, 533). We verified the PCR products on a 1% agarose gel, excised the appropriate bands, and purified the fragments using the Zymoclean Gel DNA Recovery Kit.</p><p id="P122">200 ng of the purified PCR products were digested with 0.5 μL of BsmBI-v2 in a total reaction volume of 40 μL for 2h at 55°C. The restriction enzyme was then heat deactivated at 80°C for 20 min. The reaction products were subsequently purified using the Min Elute PCR Purification Kit. We then ligated 80 ng of the digested inserts with 65 ng of the similarly treated empty entry vector (pYTK001) using 0.5 μL of T4 DNA ligase for 1.5h at room temperature. The ligase was inactivated by putting the samples at 65°C for 10 min. The terminator Part plasmids were then transformed into NEB 5-alpha E. coli competent cells and plated onto LB-25 μg/ml Chloroamphenicol plates, purified and verified by sequencing.</p><p id="P123">For assembling the complete Cassette plasmid, we combined individual Part plasmids in a reaction containing 74 ng of each part plasmid, 1 μL T4 DNA ligase, 2 μL T4 DNA ligase buffer, 1 μL BsaI in 20 μL volume reaction (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD5">Supp. Table 3</xref> for the detail of specific Part plasmids). The samples were incubated in a thermocycler with the setting of 25 cycles of 42°C for 2 min, 16°C for 5 min, with a final digestion step (60°C for 10 min) and heat inactivation (80°C for 10 min). The PCR products were then transformed into NEB 5 alpha E. coli competent cells. The assembly was verified by diagnostic digest using EcoRI-HF, NotI-HF, BamHI-HF, HindIII-HF restriction enzymes. Finally, the confirmed Cassette plasmids were linearized with NotI for 10 min at 37°C, transformed into target yeast strains (By4741, <italic>pin4Δ</italic>), which we plated on YPD plates with 600 μg/ml hygromycin. The integration into the chromosome was confirmed by PCR and sequencing using oligos listed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD5">Supp. Table 1</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="S27"><title>Western blot analysis of reporter constructs</title><p id="P124">For the analysis of the Venus reporter expression via western blot, cells expressing Venus reporters were initially grown overnight in SD-Trp medium. The following morning, the cultures were diluted to an OD<sub>600</sub> of 0.05 and grown until reaching an OD<sub>600</sub> of 0.45. Cells corresponding to 9 ODs were harvested by centrifugation at 4,600 rpm for 2 min and subsequently frozen at -90°C for storage. For glucose starvation experiments, cells were rapidly filtered and resuspended in a medium containing 2% glycerol and 2% ethanol, where they were incubated for 2 hours before spinning them and freezing them the same way as the non-starved samples.</p><p id="P125">Cell pellets were resuspended in 1 mL of 0.2 M NaOH and incubated on ice for 10 min. Subsequently, 100 μL of 50% trichloroacetic acid (TCA) was added to precipitate proteins. After mixing, samples were incubated on ice for an additional 10 min and then centrifuged at 14,000 rpm at 4°C for 10 min to pellet the precipitated proteins. The pellet was resuspended in 35 μL of lysis buffer (0.1 M Tris-HCl pH 6.8, 4 mM EDTA pH 8.0, 4% SDS, 20% glycerol, 2% β-mercaptoethanol). To adjust the pH, 15 μL of 1M Tris base was added to each sample. Samples were then heated at 95°C for 10 min and centrifuged at 10,000 rpm at room temperature for 10 min. The supernatant was kept, and the protein concentration was quantified using the Bradford assay. 25 μg of protein per sample was loaded onto a 4-12% Bis-Tris gel and subjected to electrophoresis at 180V for 1 hour in MOPS buffer. Proteins were then transferred to a nitrocellulose membrane using the i-blot2 system set on the P0 setting. Post-transfer, the membrane was stained with Ponceau S solution for 5 min to visualize total protein transfer and subsequently blocked with 5% milk in PBS for 30 min. The membrane was incubated with primary antibodies against Venus (Agrisera AS18 4227, diluted in 1:1000) and Act1 (Abcam 8224, diluted 1:10,000) for 1 hour. After washing three times for 5 min each with PBS-T (0.1% tween), the membrane was incubated with a fluorescently labelled secondary antibody (LiCor, diluted 1:5,000 in 5% milk PBS-T) for 1 hour. Following three additional washes with PBS-T (0.1% tween), the membrane was scanned using the LI-COR software (LI-COR Biosciences). Act1 served as the loading control, the quantification was done using the ImageStudio (LI-COR Biosciences).</p></sec><sec id="S28"><title>RNAseq</title><p id="P126">BY4741 and <italic>pin4Δ</italic> cells were cultured in 100 mL of SD-Trp to OD<sub>600</sub> of 0.45 from OD<sub>600</sub> of 0.05. Cells were rapidly filtered and immediately immersed in 50 mL of ice-cold water, centrifuged at 4,600 rpm for 2 min at 4°C, and the cell pellet was snap-frozen in a dry-ice and ethanol bath, and stored at -80°C. For glucose starvation stress, cells were incubated in SD-Trp medium without glucose but supplemented with 2% glycerol and 2% ethanol. At the 16 min timepoint, cells were filtered and immersed in 50 mL of ice-cold water, after which they were spun down as described for glucose samples, and snap-frozen. Biological triplicates were collected for each condition.</p><p id="P127">RNA was extracted from 10 OD<sub>600</sub> units of cells using TRIzol reagent with the addition of 0.5% final β-mercaptoethanol. Cells were lysed by bead beating in screw-cap tubes three times in a Fast Prep-24 machine (MP Biomedicals) using 200 μL of Zirconia beads at a setting of 6 m/s for 40 sec. RNA was cleaned twice by chloroform extraction and precipitation was performed using 0.8 vol isopropanol. RNA concentration was quantified using Nanodrop (OD<sub>280</sub>). 6 μg of RNA was treated with DNase I for 30 min and further purified using RNA Clean and Concentrator kit.</p><p id="P128">Libraries for RNAseq were prepared by the Edinburgh Clinical Research Facility at the Institute of Genetics and Cancer (Edinburgh, UK). RNA integrity and quality were assessed using an Agilent 2100 Electrophoresis Bioanalyser Instrument (Agilent Technologies Inc, #G2939AA) with RNA 6000 Nano chips (#5067-1511). RNA quantification was performed with Qubit 2.0 Fluorometer (Thermo Fisher Scientific Inc, #Q32866) using the Qubit RNA broad range assay kit (#Q10210). DNA contamination levels were evaluated using the Qubit dsDNA HS assay kit (#Q32854).</p><p id="P129">Libraries were prepared from 500 ng of total RNA per sample using the NEBNEXT Ultra II Directional RNA Library Prep kit (NEB #7760) and the Poly-A mRNA Magnetic Isolation Module (NEB #E7490) following the manufacturer’s protocols. Sequencing was carried out on the NextSeq 2000 platform (Illumina Inc, #20038897) using NextSeq 2000 P3 Reagents (200 Cycles) (#20040560) with paired-end, 2x 100 nt outputs.</p></sec><sec id="S29"><title>Quantitative PCR (qPCR)</title><p id="P130">Yeast strains BY4741, <italic>pin4Δ</italic>, pin4<sub><italic>RRMΔ</italic></sub>, pin4<sub><italic>RRM-M1</italic></sub>, and Pin4<sub><italic>ΔCT</italic></sub> were cultured overnight in SD-Trp medium. The next day, cultures were diluted to an OD<sub>600</sub> of 0.05 and grown in 100 mL of SD-Trp to an OD<sub>600</sub> of 0.45. For glucose starvation experiments, cells were filtered and resuspended in 100 mL of medium containing 2% glycerol and 2% ethanol for 16 or 32 min. For harvesting, cultures were rapidly filtered, and the cells were immediately immersed in 50 mL of ice-cold water, centrifuged at 4,600 rpm for 2 min at 4°C, and cell pellets were frozen.</p><p id="P131">For RNA extraction, cell pellets corresponding to 10 OD<sub>600</sub> units were lysed using 100 μL of TRIzol reagent in the presence of 200 μL zirconia beads and 0.5% β-mercaptoethanol. The lysis was performed in screw-cap tubes twice using a fast prep machine at 6 m/s for 40 seconds. Extra 500 μL of TRIzol reagent with 0.5% β-mercaptoethanol were added and the bead beating was repeated one more time. The samples were cleared by centrifugation, and RNA was extracted using a chloroform-isopropanol method. The RNA was washed with 70-75% ethanol, dried and resuspended in DNase/RNase-free water. The RNA concentration was quantified using a Nanodrop spectrophotometer.</p><p id="P132">For reverse transcription, the extracted RNA was first treated to remove any contaminating genomic DNA. 15 μg of RNA was mixed with 7 μL of RQ1 DNase and 1x buffer, along with 1 μL of RNasin. This mixture was gently vortexed and incubated at 37°C for 30 min. The DNase was then inactivated by adding 125 μL of water to the mixture, followed by an extraction with equal volume of phenol:chloroform:isoamyl alcohol (25:24:1), vortexed vigorously, and centrifuged at 12,000g for 10 min at 4°C. The aqueous phase was extracted, treated with chloroform and isoamyl alcohol (24:1), and the RNA was precipitated overnight at -20°C using sodium acetate and ethanol. The RNA pellet was washed, dried, and dissolved in DNase/RNase-free water. The concentration and purity of RNA were assessed using a Nanodrop spectrophotometer.</p><p id="P133">Reverse transcription was performed on 1 μg of DNase-treated RNA using random hexamers and Superscript III Reverse Transcriptase (Invitrogen). The reaction mixture included 0.2 μg/μL random hexamers, 10 mM dNTP mix, 5x first-strand buffer, 0.1M DTT, RNasin, and reverse transcriptase. The mixture was incubated at 65°C for 5 min, followed by synthesis conditions of 25°C for 15 min, 55°C for 1 hour, and a final inactivation step at 70°C for 15 min. Finally, 180 μL of water was added to the reaction to obtain a total volume of 200 μL of cDNA.</p><p id="P134">Quantitative PCR was carried out in triplicate using SYBR Green I master mix (Roche) on an MX3005P qPCR system (Agilent Technologies). Each 10 μL reaction contained 4 μL of cDNA, 5 μL of 2x SYBR Green master mix, 0.4 μL of 10 μM primers (forward and reverse mixed at 1:1), 0.04 μL of Rox II and 0.56 μL water. The thermal cycling conditions were as follows: initial denaturation at 95°C for 30 seconds, followed by 38 cycles of 95°C for 5 seconds, 55°C for 15 seconds, and 72°C for 15 seconds.</p></sec><sec id="S30"><title>Microscopy</title><p id="P135">Saccharomyces cerevisiae strains expressing Hsp104-C-GFP in the WT background, and Hsp104-C-GFP in pin4<sub><italic>RRMΔ</italic></sub> background were cultured in 20 mL of SD-Trp medium from OD<sub>600</sub> of 0.05 to OD<sub>600</sub> of 0.45. After reaching this optical density, 175 μL of cell suspension was put onto a chambered coverslip with eight individual wells (Thistle Scientific) that has been pre-coated with 10 μL of Concanavalin A (ConA, 5 mg/mL stock) for 10 min at 32°C and subsequently washed three times with SD-Trp medium. Cells were allowed to adhere to the coverslip surface for 20 min at 32°C. Following adhesion, non-adherent cells were removed with three washes using 500 μL of SD-Trp medium. The adherent cells were then imaged at 25 °C using a spinning disc confocal microscope with a Nikon TE2000 microscope base, a modified Yokogawa CSU-10 spinning disk (Visitech) an iXon + Du888 EMCCD camera (Andor) and a 100x/1.45 NA Plan Apo objective (Nikon). For glucose starvation monitoring, the cells were washed three times with 500 μL of glucose-starvation medium (SD-Trp without glucose, supplemented with 2% glycerol and 2% ethanol), and imaged for further 2-hour period. Metamorph software (Molecular Devices) were used to capture images every three min with an exposure time of 150 ms, 488 nm laser set at 35% power and a 0.6 μm step-size over 11 z-sections at three-minute intervals.</p></sec><sec id="S31"><title>Polysome profiling</title><p id="P136">WT and <italic>pin4Δ</italic> cells were grown in SD-Trp medium overnight to obtain the saturated cultures the following morning. Thes cultures were then diluted in 100 mL of SD-Trp and grown in synthetic complete (SC) medium from OD<sub>600</sub> of 0.05 to OD<sub>600</sub> of 0.45. Cycloheximide was added to the cultures at a final concentration of 0.1 mg/mL for 5 min before harvesting to stabilize ribosomes by blocking them during elongation phase. Cells were subsequently pelleted by centrifugation at 4,600 rpm for 2 min at 4°C, washed once with 20 mL of ice-cold water, snap-frozen in a dry-ice and ethanol bath, and stored at -80°C. Biological duplicates were collected for each condition. For glucose starvation experiments, when reaching the right OD, cells were initially filtered and transferred to 100 mM of SC medium supplemented with 2% glycerol and 2% ethanol instead of glucose, for 16 min. The cells were then harvested as described above.</p><p id="P137">Following the methodology outlined in Winz et al. (2019)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R67">67</xref></sup>, cell lysis was performed by resuspending cell pellets in 300 μL of lysis buffer (20 mM HEPES-KOH pH 7.4, 100 mM potassium acetate, 2 mM magnesium acetate and EDTA-free protease inhibitors). The suspension was transferred to screw-cap tubes containing 200 μL of zirconia beads prepared on ice and subjected to four cycles of bead beating using a Fast Prep-24 machine (MP Biomedicals) set at 6m/s for 40 seconds with a pre-cooled cool adapter. For each of the beating, 8g of dry ice was used to keep the samples cold, but not freezing. An additional 200 μL of lysis buffer was added post-bead beating, and the lysate was cleared twice for 15 min at maximum speed at 4°C. RNA concentration was measured on a Nanodrop spectrophotometer.</p><p id="P138">300 μg of RNA was loaded onto 10%-45% sucrose gradients made in 1x gradient buffer (10 mM Tris-acetate pH 7.4, 70 mM ammonium acetate, 2 mM magnesium acetate). Gradients were first made using a Gradient Master (BioComp) set to the “Short; SW40; Suc10-45%” program and refrigerated for 2 hours. After loading the RNA on the gradients, the gradients were centrifuged at 38,000 rpm for 2.5 hours at 4°C in SW40-Ti rotors using an Optima XPN-100 Ultracentrifuge (Beckmann Coulter) with acceleration set at 1 and deceleration at 9. Post-centrifugation, gradients were fractionated into 60 fractions of 200 μL each using a Piston Gradient Fractionator (BioComp), equipped with a TRIAX flow cell (BioComp) for UV profiling and an FC203B fraction collector (Gilson).</p></sec></sec><sec id="S32"><title>Quantification And Statistical Analysis</title><sec id="S33"><title>Protein domain analysis of Pin4</title><p id="P139">Regions within Pin4 matching protein domain families were identified using the NCBI Conserved Domains database, which revealed predicted RNA recognition motif (RRM) and R3H domains. Domain alignments and phylogenetics trees were constructed based on the information available on the same platform. 3D structure prediction for Pin4 was performed using AlphaFold3.</p><p id="P140">AlphaFold3 modelling was carried out with two copies of the full-length sequences of Pin4 from <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27">27</xref></sup>. After inspection, a sequence encompassing the R3H was also modelled, also with two copies (residues 273-373; R3H designated as residues 306-367). The predicted aligned error was visualised using PAE viewer <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R68">68</xref></sup> and figures were generated using Pymol.</p></sec><sec id="S34"><title>reCRAC sequence data analysis</title><p id="P141">Sequencing of reCRAC libraries was done on the Illumina MiniSeq system, using the High Output Reagent Cartridge. Bioinformatic analysis of reCRAC followed the protocol described by Ristová et al., 2024. Initially, reads were demultiplexed using pyBarcodeFilter.py based on uniquely barcoded 5’ linkers. Quality filtering and 3’ adapter trimming were done using Flexbar with specified settings (--removal-tags -at RIGHT -ao 4 -u 3 -m 7 -n 16 -t), and targeting the adapter sequence TGGAATTCTCGGGTGCCAAGGC. PCR duplicates were removed using pyFastqDuplicateRemover.py, which collapses reads with identical three random nucleotide sequences present in the 5’ linker. These collapsed FASTA reads were then aligned to the Saccharomyces cerevisiae reference genome (SGD v64) using Novoalign (V2.07.00, Novocraft) with Ensembl annotations (EF4.74), applying the Random -r method. Read quantification was executed with pyReadCounters.py, using the Ensembl GTF version EF4.74, which includes mRNA annotations with UTRs, as well as different non-coding RNA categories such as CUTs and SUTs.</p><p id="P142">The output of pyReadCounters.py is a read count file (hittable). One pseudocount was added to each transcript to improve quantification. The reads were RPM normalized due to a very specific Pin4 binding peak and the normalized data were plotted against RPKM normalized RNAseq data. For the distribution of binding, the ratio between 5’UTR, CDS, 3’ UTR over the genomic region was calculated, mean value from the three replicates was taken with SD.</p><p id="P143">Most analysis were done on transcripts that showed the strongest Pin4 binding, for these an arbitrary cut off of at least 0.3% of the library was made from the raw reads. Protein binding sites were visualized using the Integrative Genomics Viewere (IGV). For this purpose, reads aligned with Novoalign were converted from SAM to BAM format, which were then sorted and indexed using samtools. Read normalization was achieved by calculating a scaling factor relative to the library size, and coverage was determined using bedtools for each strand, producing scaled bedgraph files for loading onto IGV. The pyPileup.py tool was utilized to illustrate the distribution of reads with number of deletions and substitutions, which represent the sites of protein-RNA crosslinks, along the TPI1, GPM1 and ALT2 genes. The motif sequence was found by taking the targets that make up 0.3% of the library, identified the highest deletion peak and taking 10 nt from upstream and downstream from this peak and searched for enriched motifs using MEME. 2D plotter was used to generate a metagene plot of reads aligned to their 3’ end. Scatter plots and bar graphs were created using GraphPad Prism 9. Gene ontology representations were generated via the Proteomaps website. Bar graphs display the median values from three experimental replicates, with error bars representing the standard deviation (SD).</p></sec><sec id="S35"><title>RNA-seq analysis</title><p id="P144">The paired-end Illumina RNA-seq data were first pre-processed using Flexbar to trim low quality bases and adapters from raw reads. The specific parameters set for Flexbar included quality filtering of tail bases with a quality threshold of 30 (Sanger scale), adapter removal with a minimum overlap of four bases, and discarding of reads shorter than 18 bases after trimming (-q TAIL -qf sanger -qt 30 -aa TruSeq -ao 4 -m 18 -n 16). The cleaned reads were then aligned to the <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> transcriptome using Salmon <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R65">65</xref></sup> to quantify transcript abundances. For this, the genome GTF file and FASTA files for genes, cDNAs, and ncRNAs were downloaded from Ensembl (version GCF_000146045.2_R64-1-1). These files were used with Salmon’s generateDecoyTranscriptome.sh script to create a hybrid FASTA containing decoy genome sequences concatenated with the transcriptome. Indices for this decoy-aware transcriptome were built using the Salmon indexer. The salmon quant command was then employed to quantify the processed reads against this index. The resulting data were imported into R and processed with the edgeR package. Reads were normalized using the Trimmed Mean of M-values (TMM) method <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R69">69</xref></sup>. Data filtering was performed using the ‘filterByExp’ function in edgeR, applying a count per million (CPM) threshold with a minimum count per sample of 15 and a minimum total count of 30.</p><p id="P145">The experimental design was modelled using the ‘model.matrix’ function in R, which accounted for both sample variations and replicates. Dispersion estimates were obtained using ‘estimateDisp’, and generalized linear models (GLM) were fit to the data using the ‘glmQLFit’ function employing a quasi-likelihood approach. Differential expression analysis was subsequently performed using ‘glmQLFTest’. Visualisation of differentially expressed genes, heatmaps, volcano plots, was performed using ggplot2, with significant genes being identified based on a fold change threshold of 2 and a false discovery rate (FDR) of 0.05. PCA plots were made using the log transformed CPM normalized data.</p><p id="P146">For comparative analysis with reCRAC data, RNAseq datasets of the WT under normal and glucose starvation conditions were mapped using Novoalign to generate SAM files. These files were then processed to produce bedgraph files as described in the <xref ref-type="sec" rid="S34">reCRAC sequence data analysis</xref> section. Visualization of these data was facilitated using the Integrative Genomics Viewer.</p></sec><sec id="S36"><title>qPCRs</title><p id="P147">Each sample was measured in a technical and biological triplicate and a median was taken for the results. The relative expression levels were calculated using the ΔΔCt method with a housekeeping gene (ALG9) as the reference. Data were normalized to the control condition and expressed as fold changes. Bar graphs show the average of three replicates and error bars show SD or SEM. Detailed information is provided in the Fig. captions. GraphPad Prism 9 software was used for the statistical analyses.</p></sec><sec id="S37"><title>Microscopy Image Processing and Analysis</title><p id="P148">Raw microscopy pictures were processed using ImageJ software (Fiji; NIH). Displayed images represent maximum projections of 11 z-sections with a 0.6 μm step-size. To quantitatively assess the presence of Hsp104 protein granules, cells were categorized as either containing or lacking visible granules at each time point. The percentage of cells with at least one granule was calculated and graphically represented using GraphPad Prism 9 software together with the statistical test.</p><p id="P149"><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1B</xref> was made using BioRender.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="SM"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1"><label>Supp Table 5</label><media xlink:href="EMS200141-supplement-Supp_Table_5.xlsx" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.spreadsheetml.sheet" id="d68aAcGbB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD2"><label>Supp Table 6</label><media xlink:href="EMS200141-supplement-Supp_Table_6.xlsx" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.spreadsheetml.sheet" id="d68aAcGcB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD3"><label>Supp Table 7</label><media xlink:href="EMS200141-supplement-Supp_Table_7.xlsx" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.spreadsheetml.sheet" id="d68aAcGdB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD4"><label>Supp Table 8</label><media xlink:href="EMS200141-supplement-Supp_Table_8.xlsx" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.spreadsheetml.sheet" id="d68aAcGeB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD5"><label>Supplementary Material</label><media xlink:href="EMS200141-supplement-Supplementary_Material.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" id="d68aAcGfB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack id="S38"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank Richard Clark from Clinical Research Facility Edinburgh for sequencing services; Shaun Webb and Ola Helwak for answering all our extensive bioinformatics questions; and Adam Kovác and Ye Dee Tay for their help with the spinning disc confocal microscope and with the analysis and processing of raw data images. We thank Ola Helwak and Sophie Giguere for the critical reading of this manuscript. MR was supported by an EASTBIO PhD fellowship [543KOM/G40389]. KB was supported by Wellcome Trust PhD Studentship [218470]. VS and DT were supported by Wellcome Principal Research Fellowships [109916, 222516]. AGC was supported by a Wellcome Senior Fellowship [200898]. This work was facilitated by funding for the Wellcome Discovery Research Platform for Hidden Cell Biology [226791] and we gratefully acknowledge support from the Microscopy and Bioinformatics cores. Work in the Wellcome Centre for Cell Biology was supported by Centre Core Grants (092076 and 203149).</p></ack><ref-list><ref id="R1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fulda</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gorman</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hori</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Samali</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cellular Stress Responses: Cell Survival and Cell Death</article-title><source>Int J Cell Biol</source><year>2010</year><volume>2010</volume><elocation-id>214074</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2825543</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20182529</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2010/214074</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gebauer</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwarzl</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Valcárcel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hentze</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>RNA-binding proteins in human genetic disease</article-title><source>Nat Rev Genet</source><year>2020</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>14</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33235359</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goswami</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Nag</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ray</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fates and functions of RNA-binding proteins under stress</article-title><source>WIREs RNA</source><year>2024</year><volume>15</volume><elocation-id>e1825</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38014833</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Galdieri</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Mehrotra</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Vancura</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transcriptional Regulation in Yeast during Diauxic Shift and Stationary Phase</article-title><source>OMICS J Integr Biol</source><year>2010</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>629</fpage><lpage>638</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3133784</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20863251</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/omi.2010.0069</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liberti</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name><name><surname>Locasale</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Warburg Effect: How Does it Benefit Cancer Cells?</article-title><source>Trends Biochem Sci</source><year>2016</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>211</fpage><lpage>218</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4783224</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26778478</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tibs.2015.12.001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alfarouk</surname><given-names>KO</given-names></name><name><surname>Verduzco</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Rauch</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Muddathir</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Adil</surname><given-names>HHB</given-names></name><name><surname>Elhassan</surname><given-names>GO</given-names></name><name><surname>Ibrahim</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>David Polo Orozco</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Cardone</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Reshkin</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Glycolysis, tumor metabolism, cancer growth and dissemination. A new pH-based etiopathogenic perspective and therapeutic approach to an old cancer question</article-title><source>Oncoscience</source><year>2014</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>777</fpage><lpage>802</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4303887</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25621294</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18632/oncoscience.109</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cazzulo</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Aerobic fermentation of glucose by trypanosomatids</article-title><source>FASEB J</source><year>1992</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>3153</fpage><lpage>3161</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1397837</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tadege</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuhlemeier</surname><given-names>C</given-names><suffix>*</suffix></name></person-group><article-title>Aerobic fermentation during tobacco pollen development</article-title><source>Plant Mol Biol</source><year>1997</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>343</fpage><lpage>354</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9349258</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pfeiffer</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Morley</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An evolutionary perspective on the Crabtree effect</article-title><source>Front Mol Biosci</source><year>2014</year><volume>1</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4429655</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25988158</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmolb.2014.00017</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hernández-Elvira</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sunnerhagen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Post-transcriptional regulation during stress</article-title><source>FEMS Yeast Res</source><year>2022</year><volume>22</volume><elocation-id>foac025</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9246287</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35561747</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/femsyr/foac025</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Huh</surname><given-names>W-K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ksp1-dependent phosphorylation of eIF4G modulates post-transcriptional regulation of specific mRNAs under glucose deprivation conditions</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2018</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>3047</fpage><lpage>3060</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5888036</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29438499</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gky097</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heinrich</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hondele</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Marchand</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Derrer</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name><surname>Zedan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Oswald</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Malinovska</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Uliana</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Khawaja</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mancini</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Glucose stress causes mRNA retention in nuclear Nab2 condensates</article-title><source>Cell Rep</source><year>2024</year><volume>43</volume><elocation-id>113593</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38113140</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kuhn</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>DeRisi</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>PO</given-names></name><name><surname>Sarnow</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Global and Specific Translational Regulation in the Genomic Response of Saccharomyces cerevisiae to a Rapid Transfer from a Fermentable to a Nonfermentable Carbon Source</article-title><source>Mol Cell Biol</source><year>2001</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>916</fpage><lpage>927</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC86682</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11154278</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/MCB.21.3.916-927.2001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ashe</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>De Long</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Sachs</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Glucose Depletion Rapidly Inhibits Translation Initiation in Yeast</article-title><source>Mol Biol Cell</source><year>2000</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>833</fpage><lpage>848</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC14814</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10712503</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1091/mbc.11.3.833</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kayikci</surname><given-names>Ö</given-names></name><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Glucose repression in Saccharomyces cerevisiae</article-title><source>FEMS Yeast Res</source><year>2015</year><volume>15</volume><elocation-id>fov068</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4629793</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26205245</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/femsyr/fov068</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J-H</given-names></name><name><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Jouandot</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The glucose signaling network in yeast</article-title><source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source><year>2013</year><volume>1830</volume><fpage>5204</fpage><lpage>5210</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3785329</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23911748</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbagen.2013.07.025</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rolland</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Winderickx</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Thevelein</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Glucose-sensing and - signalling mechanisms in yeast</article-title><source>FEMS Yeast Res</source><year>2002</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>183</fpage><lpage>201</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12702307</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Conrad</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Schothorst</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kankipati</surname><given-names>HN</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Zeebroeck</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Rubio-Texeira</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Thevelein</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nutrient sensing and signaling in the yeast Saccharomyces cerevisiae</article-title><source>FEMS Microbiol Rev</source><year>2014</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>254</fpage><lpage>299</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4238866</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24483210</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1574-6976.12065</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bresson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Shchepachev</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Spanos</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Turowski</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name><name><surname>Rappsilber</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Tollervey</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Stress-Induced Translation Inhibition through Rapid Displacement of Scanning Initiation Factors</article-title><source>Mol Cell</source><year>2020</year><volume>80</volume><fpage>470</fpage><lpage>484</lpage><elocation-id>e8</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7657445</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33053322</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molcel.2020.09.021</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bresson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Shchepachev</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Tollervey</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A posttranscriptional pathway regulates cell wall mRNA expression in budding yeast</article-title><source>Cell Rep</source><year>2023</year><volume>42</volume><elocation-id>112184</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36862555</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pike</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name><name><surname>Heierhorst</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mdt1 facilitates efficient repair of blocked DNA double-strand breaks and recombinational maintenance of telomeresv</article-title><source>Mol Cell Biol</source><year>2007</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>6532</fpage><lpage>6545</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2099617</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17636027</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/MCB.00471-07</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pike</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name><name><surname>Yongkiettrakul</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Heierhorst</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mdt1, a novel Rad53 FHA1 domain-interacting protein, modulates DNA damage tolerance and G(2)/M cell cycle progression in Saccharomyces cerevisiae</article-title><source>Mol Cell Biol</source><year>2004</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC371128</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15024067</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/MCB.24.7.2779-2788.2004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Derkatch</surname><given-names>IL</given-names></name><name><surname>Bradley</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name><surname>Liebman</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prions Affect the Appearance of Other Prions: The Story of [PIN+]</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2001</year><volume>106</volume><fpage>171</fpage><lpage>182</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11511345</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Chitsaz</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Derbyshire</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonzales</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name><name><surname>Gwadz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Marchler</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Thanki</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamashita</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The conserved domain database in 2023</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2022</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>D384</fpage><lpage>D388</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9825596</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36477806</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkac1096</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Liebman</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prion-promoted phosphorylation of heterologous amyloid is coupled with ubiquitin-proteasome system inhibition and toxicity</article-title><source>Mol Microbiol</source><year>2014</year><volume>93</volume><fpage>1043</fpage><lpage>1056</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4150831</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25039275</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/mmi.12716</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name><surname>Derkatch</surname><given-names>IL</given-names></name><name><surname>Liebman</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Heterologous Gln/Asn-Rich Proteins Impede the Propagation of Yeast Prions by Altering Chaperone Availability</article-title><source>Plos Genet</source><year>2013</year><volume>9</volume><elocation-id>e1003236</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3554615</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23358669</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1003236</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abramson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Adler</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Dunger</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Pritzel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ronneberger</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Willmore</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Ballard</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bambrick</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Accurate structure prediction of biomolecular interactions with AlphaFold 3</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2024</year><volume>630</volume><fpage>493</fpage><lpage>500</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11168924</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38718835</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41586-024-07487-w</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martín</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodríguez-Gabriel</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>McDonald</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name><name><surname>Watt</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yates</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Bähler</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cip1 and Cip2 Are Novel RNA-Recognition-Motif Proteins That Counteract Csx1 Function during Oxidative Stress</article-title><source>Mol Biol Cell</source><year>2006</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>1176</fpage><lpage>1183</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1382307</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16407405</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1091/mbc.E05-09-0847</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maris</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Dominguez</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Allain</surname><given-names>FH-T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The RNA recognition motif, a plastic RNA-binding platform to regulate post-transcriptional gene expression</article-title><source>FEBS J</source><year>2005</year><volume>272</volume><fpage>2118</fpage><lpage>2131</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15853797</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>G-J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>W-F</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>Y-B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Distinct roles of the R3H and RRM domains in poly(A)-specific ribonuclease structural integrity and catalysis</article-title><source>Biochim Biophys Acta BBA - Proteins Proteomics</source><year>2013</year><volume>1834</volume><fpage>1089</fpage><lpage>1098</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23388391</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>W-F</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>G-J</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>Y-B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The R3H domain stabilizes poly(A)-specific ribonuclease by stabilizing the RRM domain</article-title><source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source><year>2007</year><volume>360</volume><fpage>846</fpage><lpage>851</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17624302</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heierhorst</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mdt1/ASCIZ: A new DNA damage response protein family</article-title><source>Cell Cycle</source><year>2008</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>2654</fpage><lpage>2660</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18728389</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Laughery</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Hunter</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoopes</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ostbye</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Shumaker</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Wyrick</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>New vectors for simple and streamlined CRISPR–Cas9 genome editing in Saccharomyces cerevisiae</article-title><source>Yeast</source><year>2015</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>711</fpage><lpage>720</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4715497</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26305040</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/yea.3098</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Granneman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kudla</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Petfalski</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Tollervey</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of protein binding sites on U3 snoRNA and pre-rRNA by UV cross-linking and high-throughput analysis of cDNAs</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2009</year><volume>106</volume><fpage>9613</fpage><lpage>9618</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2688437</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19482942</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0901997106</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ristova</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Shchepachev</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Tollervey</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>reCRAC: A Stringent Method for Precise Mapping of Protein-RNA Interactions in Yeast</article-title><source>bioRxiv</source><year>2024</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39535713</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liebermeister</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Noor</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Flamholz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Davidi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Bernhardt</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Milo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Visual account of protein investment in cellular functions</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2014</year><volume>111</volume><fpage>8488</fpage><lpage>8493</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4060655</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24889604</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1314810111</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bähler</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J-Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Longtine</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>NG</given-names></name><name><surname>Mckenzie</surname><given-names>A</given-names><suffix>III</suffix></name><name><surname>Steever</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Wach</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Philippsen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Pringle</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Heterologous modules for efficient and versatile PCR-based gene targeting in Schizosaccharomyces pombe</article-title><source>Yeast</source><year>1998</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>943</fpage><lpage>951</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9717240</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Messner</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name><name><surname>Demichev</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Muenzner</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Aulakh</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Barthel</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Röhl</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Herrera-Domínguez</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Egger</surname><given-names>A-S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamrad</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The proteomic landscape of genome-wide genetic perturbations</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2023</year><volume>186</volume><fpage>2018</fpage><lpage>2034</lpage><elocation-id>e21</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7615649</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37080200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2023.03.026</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chowdhury</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An intrinsically Disordered RNA Binding Protein Modulates mRNA Translation and Storage</article-title><source>bioRxiv</source><year>2023</year><elocation-id>2023.05.22.541713</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2023.05.22.541713</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Calabretta</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Richard</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Emerging Roles of Disordered Sequences in RNA-Binding Proteins</article-title><source>Trends Biochem Sci</source><year>2015</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>662</fpage><lpage>672</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26481498</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R41"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ottoz</surname><given-names>DSM</given-names></name><name><surname>Berchowitz</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of disorder in RNA binding affinity and specificity</article-title><source>Open Biol</source><year>2020</year><volume>10</volume><elocation-id>200328</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7776568</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33352065</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rsob.200328</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R42"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shorter</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Southworth</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Spiraling in Control: Structures and Mechanisms of the Hsp104 Disaggregase</article-title><source>Cold Spring Harb Perspect Biol</source><year>2019</year><volume>11</volume><elocation-id>a034033</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6671941</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30745294</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/cshperspect.a034033</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R43"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sathyanarayanan</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Musa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bou Dib</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Raimundo</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Milosevic</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Krisko</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>ATP hydrolysis by yeast Hsp104 determines protein aggregate dissolution and size in vivo</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2020</year><volume>11</volume><elocation-id>5226</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7568574</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33067463</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-020-19104-1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R44"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smolka</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Albuquerque</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Proteome-wide identification of in vivo targets of DNA damage checkpoint kinases</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci</source><year>2007</year><volume>104</volume><fpage>10364</fpage><lpage>10369</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1965519</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17563356</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0701622104</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R45"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Soufi</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelstrup</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Stoehr</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Fröhlich</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Walther</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name><name><surname>Olsen</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Global analysis of the yeast osmotic stress response by quantitative proteomics</article-title><source>Mol Biosyst</source><year>2009</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>1337</fpage><lpage>1346</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19823750</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R46"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gnad</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>de Godoy</surname><given-names>LMF</given-names></name><name><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Neuhauser</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Olsen</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name><name><surname>Mann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>High-accuracy identification and bioinformatic analysis of in vivo protein phosphorylation sites in yeast</article-title><source>PROTEOMICS</source><year>2009</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>4642</fpage><lpage>4652</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19795423</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R47"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Soulard</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Cremonesi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Moes</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Schütz</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Jenö</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Rapamycin-sensitive Phosphoproteome Reveals That TOR Controls Protein Kinase A Toward Some But Not All Substrates</article-title><source>Mol Biol Cell</source><year>2010</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>3475</fpage><lpage>3486</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2947482</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20702584</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1091/mbc.E10-03-0182</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R48"><label>48</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bodenmiller</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Wanka</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kraft</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Urban</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Pedrioli</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><name><surname>Gerrits</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Picotti</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Vitek</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Phosphoproteomic Analysis Reveals Interconnected System-Wide Responses to Perturbations of Kinases and Phosphatases in Yeast</article-title><source>Sci Signal</source><year>2010</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>rs4</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3072779</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21177495</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/scisignal.2001182</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R49"><label>49</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Helbig</surname><given-names>AO</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosati</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Pijnappel</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name><name><surname>van Breukelen</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Timmers</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohammed</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Slijper</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Heck</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Perturbation of the yeast N-acetyltransferase NatB induces elevation of protein phosphorylation levels</article-title><source>BMC Genomics</source><year>2010</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>685</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3091791</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21126336</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2164-11-685</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R50"><label>50</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Glauninger</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Bard</surname><given-names>JAM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hickernell</surname><given-names>CJW</given-names></name><name><surname>Airoldi</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Singer</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Paul</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Fei</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sosnick</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><name><surname>Wallace</surname><given-names>EWJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Transcriptome-wide mRNA condensation precedes stress granule formation and excludes stress-induced transcripts</article-title><source>bioRxiv</source><year>2024</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2024.04.15.589678</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R51"><label>51</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Teixeira</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Sheth</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Valencia-Sanchez</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Brengues</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Processing bodies require RNA for assembly and contain nontranslating mRNAs</article-title><source>RNA</source><year>2005</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>371</fpage><lpage>382</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1370727</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15703442</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1261/rna.7258505</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R52"><label>52</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zedan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Schürch</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Heinrich</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>García</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><name><surname>Khawaja</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Weis</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Newly synthesized mRNA selectively escapes translational repression following acute stress</article-title><source>bioRxiv</source><year>2024</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2024.04.14.589419</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R53"><label>53</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Messner</surname><given-names>Christoph</given-names></name></person-group><source>The Proteomic Landscape of Genome-Wide Genetic Perturbations</source><publisher-name>Mendeley</publisher-name><year>2023</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.17632/W8JTMNSZD9.1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R54"><label>54</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Pugh</surname><given-names>BF</given-names></name><name><surname>Reese</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genome-Wide Mapping of Decay Factor–mRNA Interactions in Yeast Identifies Nutrient-Responsive Transcripts as Targets of the Deadenylase Ccr4</article-title><source>G3 GenesGenomesGenetics</source><year>2017</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>315</fpage><lpage>330</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5765359</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29158339</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1534/g3.117.300415</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R55"><label>55</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schlecht</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Miranda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Suresh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name><surname>St Onge</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multiplex assay for condition-dependent changes in protein–protein interactions</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2012</year><volume>109</volume><fpage>9213</fpage><lpage>9218</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3384208</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22615397</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1204952109</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R56"><label>56</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tarassov</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Messier</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Landry</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Radinovic</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Molina</surname><given-names>MMS</given-names></name><name><surname>Shames</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Malitskaya</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Vogel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bussey</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Michnick</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An in Vivo Map of the Yeast Protein Interactome</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2008</year><volume>320</volume><fpage>1465</fpage><lpage>1470</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18467557</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R57"><label>57</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shangari</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>O’Brien</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The cytotoxic mechanism of glyoxal involves oxidative stress</article-title><source>Biochem Pharmacol</source><year>2004</year><volume>68</volume><fpage>1433</fpage><lpage>1442</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15345333</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R58"><label>58</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Uvdal</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Shashkova</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Effect of Calorie Restriction on Protein Quality Control in Yeast</article-title><source>Biomolecules</source><year>2023</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>841</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10216387</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37238710</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/biom13050841</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R59"><label>59</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Quinlan</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>BEDTools: a flexible suite of utilities for comparing genomic features</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2010</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>841</fpage><lpage>842</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2832824</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20110278</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btq033</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R60"><label>60</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>McCarthy</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Smyth</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>edgeR: a Bioconductor package for differential expression analysis of digital gene expression data</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2010</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>139</fpage><lpage>140</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2796818</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19910308</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btp616</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R61"><label>61</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dodt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Roehr</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Dieterich</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>FLEXBAR—Flexible Barcode and Adapter Processing for Next-Generation Sequencing Platforms</article-title><source>Biology</source><year>2012</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>895</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4009805</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24832523</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/biology1030895</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R62"><label>62</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wickham</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><source>ggplot2</source><publisher-name>Springer International Publishing</publisher-name><year>2016</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-3-319-24277-4</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R63"><label>63</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Thorvaldsdóttir</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Winckler</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Guttman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lander</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name><surname>Getz</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Mesirov</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Integrative Genomics Viewer</article-title><source>Nat Biotechnol</source><year>2011</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>24</fpage><lpage>26</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3346182</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21221095</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nbt.1754</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R64"><label>64</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Webb</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hector</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Kudla</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Granneman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>PAR-CLIP data indicate that Nrd1-Nab3-dependent transcription termination regulates expression of hundreds of protein coding genes in yeast</article-title><source>Genome Biol</source><year>2014</year><volume>15</volume><elocation-id>R8</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4053934</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24393166</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/gb-2014-15-1-r8</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R65"><label>65</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Patro</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Duggal</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Love</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name><name><surname>Irizarry</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kingsford</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Salmon provides fast and bias-aware quantification of transcript expression</article-title><source>Nat Methods</source><year>2017</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>417</fpage><lpage>419</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5600148</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28263959</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.4197</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R66"><label>66</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>DeLoache</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name><name><surname>Cervantes</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Dueber</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A Highly Characterized Yeast Toolkit for Modular, Multipart Assembly</article-title><source>ACS Synth Biol</source><year>2015</year><volume>12</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25871405</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R67"><label>67</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Winz</surname><given-names>M-L</given-names></name><name><surname>Peil</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Turowski</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name><name><surname>Rappsilber</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Tollervey</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular interactions between Hel2 and RNA supporting ribosome-associated quality control</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2019</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>563</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6362110</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30718516</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-019-08382-z</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R68"><label>68</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Elfmann</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Stülke</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>PAE viewer: a webserver for the interactive visualization of the predicted aligned error for multimer structure predictions and crosslinks</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2023</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>W404</fpage><lpage>W410</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10320053</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37140053</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkad350</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R69"><label>69</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Oshlack</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A scaling normalization method for differential expression analysis of RNA-seq data</article-title><source>Genome Biol</source><year>2010</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>R25</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2864565</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20196867</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/gb-2010-11-3-r25</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Identification of the Pin4 RNA-bound interactome</title><p>A) Pin4 is a largely unstructured protein with three predicted domains, an RNA Recognition Motif (RRM), a coiled-coil domain (CC), and an R3H domain. The previously identified prion-forming domain is also annotated. The RRM and R3H domain regions belong to two protein domain families: RRM_PIN4_like and R3H_RRM respectively. B) Overview of the reCRAC technique. Briefly, yeast cells were irradiated at 254 nm to induce covalent crosslinks (yellow stars) between proteins and associated RNAs. Cells were lysed in denaturing conditions, to prevent protein degradation and reduce non-specific interactions. The bait protein carries a FLAG-His<sub>8</sub> tag, allowing purification on Ni-NTA beads, where the enzymatic steps of RNA digestion and radiolabeling and linker ligation (red star) were performed. This was followed by elution and purification on Anti-FLAG beads. Complexes were gel-purified, the radioactive RNA visualized by autoradiography and the region corresponding to the RNA-protein complexes excised. The bait protein was treated with Proteinase K, leaving one or more residual aminoacids. RNA was extracted, converted to cDNA by reverse transcription (RT), and sequenced. See the methods section for more detail <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35">35</xref></sup>. Figure created with BioRender. C) Total reads recovered in reCRAC libraries from Glucose and No glucose conditions (16 min in Gly/EtOH) for FH-Pin4 and Untagged control. Each condition was analyzed in triplicate. The Untagged background control had minimal number of reads as expected. D) The relative fraction of reCRAC reads belonging to Glucose and No glucose (16 min in Gly/EtOH) Pin4 libraries. The experiment was performed in triplicate for each condition.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS200141-f001"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Pin4 predominantly targets a single motif in 3’ UTRs</title><p>A) Distribution of Pin4 binding to 5’UTR, CDS, and 3’ UTR of target mRNAs in Glucose and No glucose (16 min in Gly/EtOH) conditions. RNAseq was included as a control. Pin4 targets mainly 3’ UTRs in both conditions. B) Metagene plot showing the total hits across Pin4 reCRAC data aligned to the 3’ end in Glucose (blue) and No glucose (orange) conditions. The highest peak is present close to the 3’ end in both conditions, but substantially lower following glucose depletion. C) Examples of FH-Pin4 binding across its top targets (<italic>TPI1, ILV5, GPM1, RPS12</italic>). Three replicates are plotted on top of each other, each shown in a different color shade. RNA-seq is shown for comparison. The reads are normalized to the size of the library and scaled to the highest peak in Pin4 reCRAC and RNAseq. The autoscaled Pin4 reCRAC peaks are shown on right next to the plots. D) Pin4 motif (MEME) in DNA alphabet found in the 3’ UTR of Pin4 targets (mRNA species that individually comprise ≥ 0.3% of the total library) in Glucose (35 RNAs) and No glucose (38 RNAs) conditions. The E value is given below each motif. E) Close up view of reCRAC pileups of the 3’ UTR of Pin4 target, <italic>ADH1</italic>, in Glucose and No glucose conditions. The motif sequence TA/TATGA/T is marked in red and underlined. The deletion peaks (orange) represent the sites of crosslinks between RNA and protein.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS200141-f002"/></fig><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Pin4 binding is enriched on metabolic and growth-associated mRNAs</title><p>A-B) Scatterplots comparing the changes in Pin4-RNA binding versus the mRNA abundance in Glucose and No glucose (16 min in Gly/EtOH) conditions. The zoomed in window shows the top Pin4-RNA enriched targets colored based on their GO term enrichment. C) Scatterplot showing the top mRNA Pin4 targets (≥ 0.3% of the total library) in glucose and glucose depletion (16 min) conditions. The transcripts fall into four GO term enrichment categories: glycolysis, mitochondrial and amino acid metabolism, and translation. D) Bar graphs showing the percentage of the total Pin4 reCRAC library, in glucose or glucose delpeted, together with the RNAseq control. Mean and individual replicates are plotted. Error bars show SEM (n=3). E-F) Box plots showing scaled, relative abundances of top Pin4-RNA targets (≥ 0.3% of the total library) identified under different GO terms relative to RNAseq. Significant differences between conditions were calculated with the Mann-Whitney statistical test and are indicated by asterisks (* p &lt; 0.05, ** p &lt; 0.01, **** p&lt; 0.0001). Individual replicate values are plotted.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS200141-f003"/></fig><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Pin4 negatively regulates the abundance of target mRNAs</title><p>A) Volcano plot of differential gene expression analysis in <italic>pin4Δ</italic> compared to the WT under glucose conditions. Significantly downregulated and upregulated genes are highlighted in red (adj. p value ≤ 0.05, log2FC ≥ 2). B) Heatmap showing the expression of top Pin4-RNA targets in WT and <italic>pin4Δ</italic> under glucose condition. Each row represents a different gene and each column represents a different experimental replicate. Expression levels are color-coded from blue (low expression) to red (high expression) and normalized. C) Schematic representation of the reporter construct used in this study. The construct contains the P<sub>TEF2</sub> promoter, driving the expression of the Venus fluorescent protein, which is fused to the 3’ UTR from top Pin4-RNA targets: <italic>TPI1</italic> and <italic>GPM1. PNC1</italic> terminator sequence was used as a control. D) Bar graphs showing the levels of RNA (left) and protein (right) for specific genes (<italic>TPI1</italic> and <italic>GPM1</italic>) that are targets of Pin4 regulation, alongside a control (<italic>PNC1</italic>). Data are represented for WT and <italic>pin4Δ</italic> strains under glucose and glucose depletion conditions (16 min for RNA levels (n=3), 2 hr for protein levels (n=2)). Values are normalized to the WT in glucose (dark blue). Significance was calculated using Mann Whitney two-tailed test. Individual replicate values are plotted. E) Bar graphs depicting the mRNA levels of <italic>TPI1</italic> and <italic>GPM1</italic> in WT and <italic>pin4Δ</italic> in glucose and glucose depletion conditions as determined from RNAseq and normalized by counts per million (CPM) (n=3, mean values and replicates plotted; error bars represent SD). Each dot represents an individual replicate. Statistical analyses were performed using EdgeR and significant differences were observed with FDR-adjusted p-values of 2.60 × 10<sup>−8</sup> and 1.98 × 10<sup>−11</sup> for TPI1 in glucose and glucose depletion between WT and <italic>pin4Δ</italic> strains, respectively, and 2.43 × 10<sup>−7</sup> and 3.31 × 10<sup>−9</sup> for GPM1. Mean and individual replicates are plotted. F) Scatterplot showing the relationship between RNA-seq log2FC of gene expression in <italic>pin4Δ</italic> compared to WT in glucose and Pin4-RNA binding in this condition. Each point represents a gene. R<sup>2</sup> value of 0.0056 is shown for the line of best fit.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS200141-f004"/></fig><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>Loss of Pin4 blocks transcriptional responses to glucose depletion</title><p>A) Principal component analysis (PCA) depicting the variation in gene expression profiles between the WT and <italic>pin4Δ</italic> with and without glucose (16 min in Gly/EtOH). Each point represents a biological replicate, showing the distinct clustering of each group based on their overall gene expression. B) Spearman correlation heatmap showing pairwise comparisons of gene expression between WT and <italic>pin4Δ</italic> under different conditions. The heatmap colors represent Spearman correlation coefficients, indicating the degree of similarity between the conditions. C) Heatmap of gene expression across WT and <italic>pin4Δ</italic> strain in glucose and glucose depletion conditions. Genes are clustered by the rows, based on expression patterns. The color scale represents expression levels from low (blue) to high (red). D) Volcano plot of differential gene expression analysis in <italic>pin4Δ</italic> compared to the WT under glucose depletion conditions (16 min in Gly/EtOH). Significantly downregulated and upregulated genes are highlighted in red (adj. p value ≤ 0.05, log2FC ≥ 2). E) Bubble chart representing the GO term enriched biological processes among mRNAs with increased levels in <italic>pin4Δ</italic> relative to the WT. The size of each bubble indicates the gene count, while the color reflects the p-value. Gene ratio is defined as the proportion of differentially expressed genes (DEGs) that are present in a particular gene set, divided by the total number of DEGs. F) As E but showing mRNAs with reduced levels in <italic>pin4Δ</italic>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS200141-f005"/></fig><fig id="F6" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title>Pin4 RRM and prion-forming domains are critical for the transcriptional response to glucose depletion</title><p>A) Schematics of representation of constructs, pin4<sub><italic>RRMΔ</italic></sub>, lacking the RRM domain, pin4<sub><italic>RRM-M1</italic></sub> with mutated RRM domain (in red), and pin4<sub><italic>ΔCT</italic></sub> (green). B) Bar graphs comparing RNA expression levels determined by qRT-PCR normalized to <italic>ALG9</italic>, for strains carrying WT <italic>PIN4, pin4Δ</italic>, pin4<sub><italic>RRMΔ</italic></sub> or pin4<sub><italic>RRM-M1</italic></sub> in glucose medium and following glucose depletion for 16 or 32 min (n=3, mean with SEM). Individual replicate values are plotted. C) As B but with strains WT <italic>PIN4, pin4Δ</italic>, pin4<sub><italic>RRMΔ</italic></sub> or pin4<sub><italic>ΔCT</italic></sub>, with glucose depleted for 16 min. Values are plotted as a fold change to WT in glucose conditions (*** p &lt; 0.001, **** p &lt; 0.0001; n=3, mean with SEM). Ordinary one-way ANOVA with Dunnett’s multiple comparisons test was used for the statistical test. Individual replicate values are plotted.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS200141-f006"/></fig><fig id="F7" position="float"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><title>Loss of the Pin4 RRM reduces Hsp104 granule formation</title><p>A) Microscopy images showing the expression of Hsp104-GFP for WT and pin4<sub><italic>RRMΔ</italic></sub> strains in glucose and following glucose depletion for 30, 60, or 120 min. B-C) Bargraphs showing the percentage of cells with visible Hsp104-GFP foci in WT and pin4<sub><italic>RRMΔ</italic></sub> strains over a time course following glucose depletion. Blue bars represent the temporal dynamics of Hsp104 granule formation in WT cells, and orange bars in pin4<sub><italic>RRMΔ</italic></sub> cells. Statistical significance is indicated (*** p &lt; 0.001, **** p &lt; 0.0001, ns = not significant). Ordinary one-way ANOVA with Dunnett’s multiple comparisons test was used for the statistical test. Mean and individual replicate values are plotted.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS200141-f007"/></fig><fig id="F8" position="float"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><title>Model for Pin4 function</title><p>During growth in glucose, Pin4 functions in post-transcriptional gene regulation by specific binding to the 3’ UTR of mRNA targets, predominantly linked to metabolic and pro-growth processes, favoring their destabilization. Following glucose withdrawal, mRNA binding by Pin4 is greatly decreased. Binding remains 3’ UTR enriched for some transcripts but includes coding sequences of mRNAs related to translation. Pin4 is also required to activate the transcriptional response to glucose deprivation. The mechanism is not yet determined, but both the prion-forming domain and RNA recognition motif (RRM) of Pin4 are necessary. This indicates that the transcriptional stress response is subject to riboregulation.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS200141-f008"/></fig></floats-group></article>