<!DOCTYPE article
 PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" article-type="preprint"><?all-math-mml yes?><?use-mml?><?origin ukpmcpa?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">bioRxiv</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>bioRxiv : the preprint server for biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2692-8205</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">EMS199164</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2024.09.30.615331</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="archive">PPR918287</article-id><article-version-alternatives><article-version article-version-type="status">preprint</article-version><article-version article-version-type="number">1</article-version></article-version-alternatives><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Population genomics uncover loci for trait improvement in the indigenous African cereal tef (<italic>Eragrostis tef</italic>)</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>Maximillian R. W.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Kebede</surname><given-names>Worku</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Teshome</surname><given-names>Abel</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Girija</surname><given-names>Aiswarya</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Teshome</surname><given-names>Adanech</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Girma</surname><given-names>Dejene</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>James K. M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Quiroz-Chavez</surname><given-names>Jesus</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>Chris S.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A6">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wulff</surname><given-names>Brande B. H.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A7">7</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Assefa</surname><given-names>Kebebew</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tadele</surname><given-names>Zerihun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A8">8</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mur</surname><given-names>Luis A. J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A9">9</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chanyalew</surname><given-names>Solomon</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CR1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Uauy</surname><given-names>Cristobal</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CR1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shorinola</surname><given-names>Oluwaseyi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A10">10</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CR1">*</xref></contrib><aff id="A1"><label>1</label>John Innes Centre, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/0062dz060</institution-id><institution>Norwich Research Park</institution></institution-wrap>, <city>Norwich</city><postal-code>NR4 7UH</postal-code>, <country country="GB">UK</country></aff><aff id="A2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/01mhm6x57</institution-id><institution>Ethiopian Institute of Agricultural Research, EIAR</institution></institution-wrap>, <city>Addis Ababa</city>, <country country="ET">Ethiopia</country></aff><aff id="A3"><label>3</label>Institute of Plant Sciences, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/025602r80</institution-id><institution>Scuola Superiore Sant’Anna</institution></institution-wrap>, <city>Pisa</city>, <country country="IT">Italy</country></aff><aff id="A4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/01jxjwb74</institution-id><institution>International Livestock Research Institute, ILRI</institution></institution-wrap>, <city>Addis Ababa</city>, <country country="ET">Ethiopia</country></aff><aff id="A5"><label>5</label>Institute of Biological, Environmental &amp; Rural Sciences (IBERS), Plas Gogerddan, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/015m2p889</institution-id><institution>Aberystwyth University</institution></institution-wrap>, <city>Aberystwyth</city>, Ceredigion, <postal-code>SY23 3EE</postal-code>, Wales, <country country="GB">UK</country></aff><aff id="A6"><label>6</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/01jxjwb74</institution-id><institution>International Livestock Research Institute</institution></institution-wrap>, <city>Nairobi</city>, <country country="KE">Kenya</country></aff><aff id="A7"><label>7</label>Plant Science Program, Biological and Environmental Science and Engineering Division (BESE), <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/01q3tbs38</institution-id><institution>King Abdullah University of Science and Technology (KAUST)</institution></institution-wrap>, <city>Thuwal</city>, <country country="SA">Saudi Arabia</country></aff><aff id="A8"><label>8</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/02k7v4d05</institution-id><institution>University of Bern</institution></institution-wrap>, Institute of Plant Sciences, <addr-line>Altenbergrain 21</addr-line>, <postal-code>3013</postal-code><city>Bern</city>, <country country="CH">Switzerland</country></aff><aff id="A9"><label>9</label>Department of Life Sciences, Penglais Campus, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/015m2p889</institution-id><institution>Aberystwyth University</institution></institution-wrap>, <city>Aberystwyth</city>, <postal-code>SY23 3DA</postal-code>, <country country="GB">UK</country></aff><aff id="A10"><label>10</label>School of Biosciences, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/03angcq70</institution-id><institution>University of Birmingham</institution></institution-wrap>, Edgbaston, <city>Birmingham</city>, <postal-code>B15 2TT</postal-code>, <country country="GB">UK</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="CR1"><label>*</label>Corresponding authors: Solomon Chanyalew (<email>solchk2@gmail.com</email>), Cristobal Uauy (<email>cristobal.uauy@jic.ac.uk</email>), Oluwaseyi Shorinola (<email>o.shorinola@bham.ac.uk</email>)</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted"><day>04</day><month>10</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="preprint"><day>02</day><month>10</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><permissions><ali:free_to_read/><license><ali:license_ref>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is licensed under a <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0 International license</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p id="P1">Tef (<italic>Eragrostis tef</italic>) is an indigenous African cereal that is gaining global attention as a gluten-free “superfood” with high protein, mineral, and fibre contents. However, tef yields are limited by lodging and by losses during harvest owing its small grain size (150x lighter than wheat). Breeders must also consider a strong cultural preference for white-grained over brown-grained varieties. Tef is relatively understudied with limited “omics” resources. Here, we resequenced 220 tef accessions from an Ethiopian diversity collection and also conducted multi-locational phenotyping for 25 agronomic and grain traits. Grain metabolome profiling revealed differential accumulation of fatty acids and flavonoids between white and brown grains. We conducted <italic>k</italic>-mer and SNP-based genome wide association and uncovered novel marker-trait associations. A significant 70 kb peak for panicle morphology contained the tef orthologue of rice <italic>qSH1</italic>, a transcription factor regulating inflorescence morphology in cereals. We also observed a previously unknown relationship between grain size, colour, and fatty acids. These traits were highly associated with retrotransposon insertions in homoeologues of <italic>TRANSPARENT TESTA 2</italic>, a known regulator of grain colour. Our study provides valuable resources for tef research and breeding, facilitating the development of improved cultivars with desirable agronomic and nutritional properties.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>tef</kwd><kwd>population genomics</kwd><kwd>GWAS</kwd><kwd>metabolomics</kwd><kwd>grain size</kwd><kwd>underutilised</kwd><kwd>orphan</kwd><kwd>gluten-free</kwd><kwd>k-mer</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="S1" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p id="P2">Tef (<italic>Eragrostis tef</italic> (<italic>Zucc</italic>.) Trotter) is a cereal crop that has been grown in the Horn of Africa for millennia. It is a self-pollinating allotetraploid grass that is valued by farmers as a ‘fail-safe’ cash crop, resilient to marginal soils, waterlogging, high temperatures, and drought. Tef is particularly vital for Ethiopia, Africa’s second most populous country, where it is grown on 3 million hectares (27% of cereal acreage) by around 6.7 million households, with annual production exceeding 5.5 million tons<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref></sup>. The crop acts as both feed and food, with the straw a prized forage for cattle and the whole-grain flour used to produce a fermented flatbread known as injera, which serves as a staple food for the majority of the country<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">2</xref></sup>. Tef has also gained more global attention as a ‘superfood’ thanks to its high protein, calcium, iron, and fibre contents, its low glycaemic index, and its lack of allergenic gluten<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">2</xref></sup>. Tef is also rich in dietary antioxidants, including polyphenols and flavonoids, and essential polyunsaturated fatty acids like linoleic acid, which are not synthesised by the human body<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">3</xref></sup>. These nutritional features, combined with its climatic resilience, make tef an attractive crop for wider adoption.</p><p id="P3">Tef is considered an underutilised crop because it has, so far, not benefited greatly from modern genomics-based approaches to breeding and research. However, as in other underutilised crops such as grass pea, yam, and lablab, this <italic>status quo</italic> is beginning to shift<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref></sup> with the generation of a high-quality reference genome<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref></sup>, following on from a draft sequence<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref></sup>. Notable progress has been made in breeding improved varieties of tef<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">8</xref></sup>, although advances have not been on the same scale as for major cereals like wheat or rice. Lodging under high nitrogenous fertiliser regimes is a major limiting factor, but has so far been difficult to address through classical semi-dwarfing approaches. Panicle (inflorescence) morphology has been reported as a determinant of lodging tolerance in tef. The species exhibits dramatic panicle diversity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref></sup>, from open, highly lax panicles similar to wild <italic>Eragrostis</italic> species, to short-branched, compact panicles more akin to the spikes of Triticeae species (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1a</xref>). Tef varieties with the former morphology tend to be tolerant to lodging, suggesting an ideotype approach could be used to improve lodging and, ultimately, grain yield<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref></sup>.</p><p id="P4">Another consideration for breeders is grain size. Tef produces the smallest grains of any cultivated cereal, ranging from 1.0 to 1.7 mm in length, with a typical thousand grain weight (TGW) of 0.2-0.4 g, roughly 150-fold lower than that of wheat<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref></sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1b</xref>) Indeed, the name tef is thought to derive from the Amharic word “teffa” meaning “lost”<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref></sup>; likely an allusion to the high levels of harvest and post-harvest losses (~30%) experienced by tef farmers<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref></sup>. Breeding for larger grains could alleviate these losses and boost realised yields by improving grain-chaff separation during winnowing. Tef’s small grain size also makes it difficult to evenly broadcast the recommended &gt;10 kg/ha during sowing. Farmers instead use high sowing rates (up to 30 kg/ha) that ultimately produce overcrowded fields prone to stem lodging<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref></sup>. Lastly, breeders must also address a strong cultural preference for white-grained over brown-grained varieties, which translates into a higher market price<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref></sup>.</p><p id="P5">Here, we conducted re-sequencing of 220 tef accessions from the Ethiopian Institute of Agricultural Research (EIAR) tef diversity collection. We characterise redundancy in this collection and provide a compact SNP panel that uniquely identifies the studied accessions. We combine this sequencing data with extensive in-field phenotyping across three trial locations, including precise grain morphology measurements and grain metabolome profiling (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>). This led to the identification of novel marker-trait associations for panicle morphology, grain size, grain colour, and multiple grain metabolites. Our analyses establish a previously unknown link between grain size and grain colour, including co-association of these traits with multiple genomic loci. However, we also identify regions that decouple these traits, offering potential breeding opportunities. Our work delivers a set of genomic and phenotypic resources for a diverse panel of tef accessions and lays the groundwork for future studies to define causal genes and variants underlying novel loci of agronomic relevance.</p></sec><sec id="S2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="S3"><title>SNP and <italic>k</italic>-mer-based methods identify redundancy in the EIAR core collection</title><p id="P6">Of the 225 accessions in the EIAR core collection, we sequenced (Illumina paired-end 150 bp) the genome of 220 accessions to an average depth of 8.85 Gbp (SD = 0.77 Gbp), equivalent to 14.2-fold the estimated genome size (622 Mb) of the reference genome cultivar ‘Dabbi’<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref></sup>. The reads were mapped against the reference genome and variants called. A quality-filtered and linkage-pruned set of 41,289 SNPs was prepared and used to investigate population structure. ADMIXTURE analysis revealed no clear population structure for two to 20 subpopulations<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref></sup>. Principal component analysis also did not suggest any distinct lineages, although there was a partial separation of brown and white-grained accessions by PC1 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD3">Supplementary Figure 1</xref>). This result was not unexpected, as a lack of strong population structure has previously been reported for other tef panels<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref></sup>.</p><p id="P7">A SNP-based phylogram was computed using IQ-TREE 2. This revealed many groups of highly related accessions, with internal branch lengths close to zero nucleotide substitutions per site (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3a</xref>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref></sup>. A list of redundancy groups was defined such that the total branch length (phylogenetic distance) between any pair of accessions in a group was &lt;0.005 substitutions per base pair. This resulted in 31 redundancy groups containing 2-19 accessions per group (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD4">Supplementary Table 1</xref>). Two accessions were excluded from placement in redundancy groups because they had high apparent heterozygosities (22.7% and 24.9% heterozygous sites, versus an average of 1.5% (standard deviation (SD) = 0.7%) for the other accessions) and likely represent seed mixtures rather than pure accessions.</p><p id="P8">To validate the redundancy groups defined above, a comprehensive <italic>k</italic>-mer (k=51) presence/absence matrix was generated from the sequencing reads of the 220 sequenced accessions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">20</xref></sup>. We tested whether pairs of accessions from the previously defined groups tended to have more <italic>k</italic>-mer states in common than non-group pairs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3b, 3c</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD4">Supplementary Table 2</xref>). We observed that all 264 intra-group pairs had a <italic>k</italic>-mer state identity rate above 96.0%, whereas 23,825 out of the 23,826 other pairs had a <italic>k</italic>-mer state identity rate below this threshold, with a mean and median of 85.4% (SD = 0.02%). The single pair exceeding this threshold (DZ-01-91 and DZ-01-101), still had a very low phylogenetic distance (0.007) compared to the overall distribution, so were added as an additional redundancy group. The broad agreement between these two relatedness metrics suggested that the redundancy groups would be better treated as single accession pools rather than distinct entities. This reduced our effective number of accessions from 220 to 150.</p><p id="P9">One accession, DZ-01-1167, produced notably low shared <italic>k</italic>-mer state rates when paired against all other accessions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3b</xref>, below dashed line). DZ-01-1167 contains 294 million distinct <italic>k</italic>-mers versus an average of 160 million (SD = 3.5 million) for all other accessions (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD3">Supplementary Figure 2</xref>), suggesting it contains many unique <italic>k</italic>-mers. This novel diversity could derive from genetically distant tef accessions not otherwise captured in the panel or from interspecific introgression(s). Its source and utility could be further explored in future studies. This finding highlights the benefits of <italic>k</italic>-mer-based approaches as this introgression is not apparent when comparing SNP-based phylogenetic distances.</p><p id="P10">Given the high levels of redundancy observed in the EIAR core collection, we selected a minimal panel of SNPs capable of distinguishing all 150 accession groups and singlets. This would allow other accessions belonging to the redundancy groups to be identified amongst the wider EIAR collection, as well as potentially facilitating some reconciliation with other tef collections. We identified a panel of 14 biallelic SNPs that could distinguish all 150 accession groups or singlets. To account for potential marker failures, we selected an additional 14 SNPs, making a total of 28. For each of these SNPs, all accession groups and singlets were homozygous for one allele or had missing data (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD4">Supplementary Table 3</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Note 1</xref>). All chromosomes were represented by at least one SNP except 5A, 7B, 8B, and 10A.</p></sec><sec id="S4"><title>Grain colour strongly correlates with plant height and grain morphometric traits</title><p id="P11">Identifying genetic loci underlying variation in consumer and farmer-preferred traits is important for adopting marker-assisted selection. To capture phenotypic variation in the EIAR core collection, we phenotyped 17 phenological and morphological traits at three field sites representing distinct agro-ecological zones (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD3">Supplementary Figure 3</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD3">Supplementary Figure 4</xref>). Using high-resolution grain imaging, we also captured variation in eight grain size parameters relating to grain width, length and area. There was a significant effect (ANOVA <italic>P</italic> value &lt;0.04) of location on all traits except for grain width and length. Trait coefficients of variation at each location ranged from 0.02 - 0.45 with phenology traits showing the least variation.</p><p id="P12">To account for spatial variability within and between experimental locations, we used linear mixed modelling to generate genotypic best linear unbiased predictors (BLUPs) for each trait. Correlation analysis of trait BLUPs revealed expected associations between components of grain size (area, width, length) and weight, as well as between components of plant height (panicle length, plant height) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4a</xref>). Intriguingly, we also identified strong correlations between grain colour and both grain size and plant height. Plants of white-grained varieties were significantly taller than those of brown-grained varieties (Student’s t-test, p &lt; 1x10<sup>-5</sup>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4b</xref>). This has positive implications for straw yields, but may increase lodging susceptibility. Brown-grained accessions are traditionally cultivated on more marginal soils, such as poorly drained vertisols, and, perhaps as a result, have come to be associated with smaller grains. However, our results indicated that brown-grained varieties tended to produce larger seeds than white-grained varieties when grown in common environments (Student’s t-test, p &lt; 1x10<sup>-15</sup>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4c</xref>). Despite this, there was no difference in TGW between white and brown-grained varieties (Student’s t-test, p = 0.22), suggesting that, on average, white-grained varieties produce grains with higher densities.</p><p id="P13">Lodging index was, as expected, positively correlated with above ground biomass, highlighting the trade-off faced by tef breeders between lodging rates and straw yields. However, we did not observe the previously reported correlation between lodging index and panicle morphology. This could be due to the relatively few lines (five) with the highest level of panicle compactness or the lower robustness of our lodging index BLUPs given this trait was only phenotyped at two of the three field sites.</p></sec><sec id="S5"><title>High-resolution metabolite fingerprinting shows differential metabolite accumulation in brown and white tef grains</title><p id="P14">The cultural preference for white-grained varieties in Ethiopia and Eritrea, as well as the growing international interest in tef’s nutritional properties, motivated us to also explore variation in grain metabolomes. We performed untargeted metabolite profiling using Flow Infusion Electrospray High Resolution Mass Spectrometry (FIE-HRMS) analysis on grain samples from each plot of the three trial locations. A total of 1643 positively ionised mass-to-charge ratio (<italic>m/z</italic>) features and 1470 negatively ionised features were captured, of which 209 and 723, respectively, were differentially accumulated in brown and white-grained varieties (Student’s t-test, FDR &lt; 0.05).</p><p id="P15">From these differential <italic>m/z</italic> features, 183 could be tentatively identified using a rice (<italic>Oryza sativa</italic> ssp. <italic>japonica</italic>) reference metabolome library available in the KEGG public database<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">21</xref></sup> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD4">Supplementary Table 4</xref>). These differentially accumulated metabolites (DAMs) produced a clear separation of white and brown-grain samples when assessed by partial least squares discriminant analysis (PLS-DA) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5a</xref>), but did not show differential accumulation between locations, suggesting little effect of locations on these metabolites (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD3">Supplementary Figure 5</xref>). The DAMs were enriched for various processes, including (unsaturated) fatty acid biosynthesis, linoleic acid metabolism, glutathione metabolism, porphyrin metabolism, flavone, and flavonol biosynthesis, and riboflavin metabolism (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5b</xref>).</p><p id="P16">In agreement with other studies<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">3</xref></sup>, our results show that brown-grained varieties tend to have higher proportions of essential polyunsaturated omega-6 and omega-3 fatty acids (e.g. linoleic acid and alpha-linolenic acid, respectively) while white-grained varieties have higher levels of saturated fatty acids (e.g. caprylic acid and 9,10-epoxyoctadecanoic acid (EPOD)). Omega fatty acids have been associated with lowering cardiovascular disease, cancer, and autoimmune diseases<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">22</xref></sup>. However, the high levels of unsaturated fatty acids in brown-grained tef may also contribute to its increased proneness to rancidity and therefore its lower consumer appeal<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">23</xref></sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5c</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD3">Supplementary Figure 6a</xref>).</p><p id="P17">We also found differential accumulation of flavonoids between white and brown-grained varieties. These compounds can affect flavour and colour and act as antioxidants<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref></sup>. We found increased levels of the flavonoids rutin and 3-dehydroshikimate in brown-grained varieties. Meanwhile, in white-grained varieties we observed elevated levels of apigenin and kaempferol 3-O-rhamnoside-7-O-glucoside (KOROG). Flavonols such as the latter have been known to contribute to white pigmentation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">25</xref></sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5c</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD3">Supplementary Figure 6b</xref>).</p><p id="P18">We hypothesised that genomic loci associated with grain colour might also be associated with the differentially accumulated metabolites. To facilitate GWAS analysis, we calculated BLUPs as above for 21 metabolites with high fold-change differences and/or which are known to be involved in pigmentation or important for human nutrition (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD4">Supplementary Table 4</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="S6"><title><italic>k</italic>-mer-based GWAS identifies co-localisation of regions associated with panicle morphology, grain morphology, and grain metabolites</title><p id="P19">To identify genomic regions associated with the agronomic and grain traits, we conducted a <italic>k</italic>-mer-based genome wide association study (kGWAS) using the previously calculated BLUPs and a new <italic>k</italic>-mer matrix to account for the reduced number of non-redundant accessions. Of the agronomic traits tested, we detected significant regions for panicle morphology, grain colour, grain area, and grain width, while from the 21 selected grain metabolites, we detected significant regions for riboflavin, EPOD, primary fluorescent chlorophyll catabolite (PFCC), succinic acid, caprylic acid, and KOROG (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6a</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD4">Supplementary Table 5</xref>). We also carried out a SNP-based GWAS and identified 91 significant associations for nine agronomic traits and eleven metabolites in 62 regions, five of which fell within significant kGWAS regions for the same trait (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD4">Supplementary Table 6</xref>).</p><p id="P20">The control of some traits appeared to be relatively simple, with single highly associated regions that did not overlap with those of other traits. Panicle morphology was associated with a 70 kb region on chromosome 3B (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6b</xref>), with the underlying reference <italic>k</italic>-mers negatively correlated with panicle morphology (scored as 1 to 4 for very lax to compact). This matched our expectations as the reference cultivar Dabbi produces very lax panicles. The significant region contains 13 gene models, including the tef orthologue (Et_3B_031395) of the rice gene <italic>qSH1</italic>/<italic>RIL1</italic> (<italic>QTL for Seed Shattering on chromosome 1</italic> / <italic>RI-LIKE1</italic>; Os01g0848400). <italic>qSH1</italic> is a <italic>BEL1</italic>-like homeobox transcription factor linked with seed shattering and inflorescence architecture<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27">27</xref></sup>. <italic>qSH1</italic> orthologues are also expressed in the inflorescence meristems of maize and wheat suggesting a conserved role in inflorescence development across the grass family.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">29</xref></sup></p><p id="P21">KOROG was associated with a prominent 360 kb region on chromosome 7A (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6c</xref>) containing 26 gene models. This included Et_7A_050580, which encodes a cytochrome P450 (<italic>CYP93G1</italic>) with flavanone 2-hydroxylase (F2H) activity and is involved in the biosynthesis of flavonol glycosides like KOROG<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">30</xref></sup>. Succinic acid was also associated with a single region, in this case spanning 40 kb on chromosome 4A and containing eleven genes. Control of riboflavin accumulation appears more complex, with three regions on chromosomes 1B (1730 kb, 174 genes), 2A (1030 kb, 126 genes), and 4B (420 kb, 75 genes) associated with riboflavin accumulation but that are not associated with other traits.</p><p id="P22">In contrast to the above, there was a set of complex co-localised associations for the other traits (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6a</xref>). Most strikingly, an overlapping and highly significant region supported by tens of thousands of <italic>k</italic>-mers was detected on chromosome 4B for grain colour (690 kb), grain area (430 kb), grain width (710 kb), and the metabolite EPOD (690 kb) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7a-c</xref> peak 7, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD3">Supplementary Figure 7a</xref>). The regions for grain colour and EPOD were identical. There was also a weaker, but still significant, association of caprylic acid with a sub-region of this peak spanning 230 kb which did not contain these gene candidates.</p><p id="P23">These regions displayed partial homology with overlapping regions for the same traits on chromosome 4A (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7a-c</xref> peak 3, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD3">Supplementary Figure 8a</xref>). These regions contained two interesting homoeologous gene pairs; Et_4A_032844/Et_4B_037039 and Et_4A_032842/Et_4B_039404. The former are orthologues of <italic>NUCLEAR FACTOR YA3</italic> (<italic>NF-YA3</italic>), which regulates seed oil content and seed size across diverse angiosperms, including arabidopsis and oil palm<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31">31</xref></sup>. The latter are orthologues of <italic>TRANSPARENT TESTA 2</italic> (<italic>TT2</italic>), a MYB transcription factor that is associated with proanthocyanidin accumulation in the seeds of various Brassicaceae species<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32">32</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33">33</xref></sup>.</p><p id="P24">We compared the gene sequences of the <italic>TT2</italic> orthologues from the Dabbi reference genome (a brown-grained variety) to those from an unpublished high-quality assembly of the white-grained variety ‘Tsedey’. In the latter, we identified striking insertions of long-terminal repeat (LTR) Copia superfamily retrotransposons (RTs) in the third and first exons of the A and B <italic>TT2</italic> homoeologues, respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7d-e</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Files 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD2">2</xref>). The A-subgenome RT introduces an in-frame cysteine and then a premature stop codon, truncating most of the final exon (162 codons). The B-subgenome RT also introduces a cysteine and a stop codon, truncating 86% of the protein. Though the two elements are highly related (98% sequence identity; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD3">Supplementary Figure 8b</xref>) their positions in different exons suggest independent insertions occurring post subgenome divergence. In both RTs the 5 bp target-site duplications and 106 bp LTRs remain undegraded, suggesting a relatively recent insertion<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34">34</xref></sup>. This is consistent with the large number of recently active LTR RT families previously identified in tef.</p><p id="P25">There was an additional region on chromosome 3B (peak 2) co-associated with grain colour, grain width, and EPOD, plus a separate region on 4A (peak 6) associated with grain colour and grain width (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7a-c</xref>). All of the above regions were correlated with brown grain colour, increased grain size parameters, and decreased EPOD. This supports the correlation between grain colour and grain size observed in the plotted BLUPs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4c</xref>).</p><p id="P26">In contrast to the regions discussed above, there were also cases where grain colour and grain size were decoupled. A third positive grain width peak on chromosome 4A (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7b</xref> peak 5) is well-separated from the upstream and downstream grain colour peaks, by 8460 kb and 1580 kb, respectively. This region is also associated with the metabolite PFCC. On chromosome 4B there is a region <italic>negatively</italic> associated with grain width and area (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7b</xref> peak 8) that is separated by just 10 kb from peak 7, a major peak for brown grain colour and higher grain width and area. A marginally insignificant peak for grain width, length, and area exists on chromosome 10A, but is relatively well-supported by our SNP-based GWAS (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7b</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD3">Supplementary Figure 7</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD4">Supplementary Table 6</xref>). Lastly, there are two grain colour peaks on chromosomes with no significant grain size peaks (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Figure 7a</xref>). A 790 kb peak associated with brown grains was detected on chromosome 1B (114 genes) and a 40 kb peak associated with white grains was detected on chromosome 6A (6 genes). These two regions offer the strong possibility of breeding for grain colour independently of grain size.</p></sec></sec><sec id="S7" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p id="P27">Developing genomic resources for orphan and underutilised crops is crucial for accelerating their improvement, adoption, and utilisation, and will in turn boost the resilience of the interconnected global food system<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35">35</xref></sup>. Our extensive phenotyping and whole genome resequencing of a diverse tef collection represents a valuable resource for germplasm characterisation and trait mapping in this locally vital, and globally emerging, crop.</p><p id="P28">Grown in Ethiopia and Eritrea for thousands of years, systematic collection and breeding of tef did not begin until the 1950s with sampling of varieties directly from farmers’ fields. Since then, numerous germplasm collections have been established, containing over 7,000 accessions. These are primarily maintained in Ethiopia but smaller collections exist elsewhere<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36">36</xref></sup>. Correspondence of varieties between these collections is undocumented, preventing cross-utilisation of phenotyping and sequencing data. Genomics approaches have been invaluable for resolving such issues and for identifying redundancy within collections<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37">37</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38">38</xref></sup>. Our work reveals redundancies in the EIAR tef collection, which are likely due to repeated sampling of farmer-traded germplasm across modest geographical ranges. The compact SNP panel we have developed can be used to identify further redundancy within the EIAR collection. The resequencing data presented here can also be combined with existing mid-density genotyping data from other tef collections to assess redundancies, differences, and complementarity between the different tef collections globally<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39">39</xref></sup>. This will shed further light on tef’s breeding history, facilitate germplasm exchange, and inform the selection of accessions for a tef pan-genome to optimally capture tef diversity.</p><p id="P29">High rates of lodging remain a major constraint on tef productivity. Panicle morphology has previously been associated with lodging, with higher panicle compactness tending to be correlated with higher rates of lodging. We identified a strong candidate regulator of panicle morphology, Et_3B_031395, which is orthologous to the rice <italic>qSH1</italic> gene. qSH1 is a BEL1-like homeodomain protein that underlies variation in seed shattering in rice<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">26</xref></sup>, and is regulated by <italic>SUPERNUMERARY BRACT</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40">40</xref></sup>, whose direct orthologue in wheat is the major inflorescence morphology gene <italic>Q</italic> which controls both seed shattering and inflorescence compactness<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41">41</xref></sup>. The arabidopsis orthologue of <italic>qSH1, REPLUMLESS/PENNY</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42">42</xref></sup>, also known as <italic>PENNYWISE</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43">43</xref></sup> or <italic>BELLRINGER</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R44">44</xref></sup>, is important for fruit development and dehiscence. <italic>qSH1</italic> has also been directly connected with inflorescence architecture, with <italic>qsh1 ri</italic> (<italic>verticillate rachis</italic>) double mutants displaying abnormal timing and arrangement of primary branch meristems<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27">27</xref></sup>. <italic>qSH1</italic> also strongly influences bract suppression in the inflorescence<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27">27</xref></sup>. In addition, paralogs and orthologues of <italic>qSH1</italic> have been shown to control inflorescence patterning in maize and arabidopsis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43">43</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R45">45</xref></sup>. Given the established roles of its orthologues in diverse plant species and its localisation within a narrow candidate region, Et_3B_031395 emerges as a promising candidate for the regulation of panicle morphology in tef. Nonetheless, functional validation will be necessary to confirm its role.</p><p id="P30">Lodging could also potentially be reduced by breeding for increased grain size. The tiny grains of tef make even broadcasting difficult and farmers typically sow at higher than recommended rates to ensure good field coverage. However, this produces overcrowded fields of weak-stemmed plants prone to stem lodging<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref></sup>. Additionally, regardless of seeding rates, surface sowing can limit root depth, in turn limiting nutrient and water acquisition and increasing root lodging. Larger grains would facilitate mechanised handling and ensure seedlings have sufficient nutrients for establishment from greater soil depths. Together, this would allow row-based drilling of tef, alleviating the above issues. Indeed, agronomists have already experimented with pelleting tef seeds with inert material to enable mechanised sowing, highlighting the promise of this approach<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R46">46</xref></sup>. Lastly, increasing grain size could help reduce the high grain loss rates experienced by smallholders during traditional threshing and winnowing processes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref></sup>.</p><p id="P31">Our kGWAS approach identified six genomic regions significantly associated with grain width, two of which were also associated with grain area, offering potential breeding targets for increasing grain size. However, we also identified a previously unknown link between grain size and grain colour which could complicate this process. Brown-grained varieties tended to produce larger grains (0.51 mm<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">2</xref></sup>) than white-grained varieties (0.42 mm<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">2</xref></sup>) and this was reflected in the kGWAS; four of the regions positively associated with grain width were also associated with brown grain colour. This co-localisation presents an issue because there is a strong cultural preference in Ethiopia for white tef flour and this translates into a market incentive for farmers to grow white-grained varieties. Introgression of grain size alleles into elite white-grained varieties at the cost of increased pigmentation would therefore not be favourable.</p><p id="P32">However, not all grain size and grain colour loci were co-localised. We identified one grain width locus on chromosome 4A that is very distant from the two grain colour regions on this chromosome, plus two grain colour loci on chromosomes which do not harbour grain size loci (1B and 6A). We also observed a region on chromosome 7A strongly associated with the metabolite KOROG. While our analysis did not find this region to be co-associated with grain colour, flavonols such as KOROG have previously been associated with white pigmentation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">25</xref></sup>. These regions offer opportunities to combine favourable grain size and colour alleles through introgression, though it is yet to be seen if the introduction of ‘white grain’ alleles into a brown-grained background would yield a dominant effect. It is more likely that positive breeding outcomes could be achieved by stacking multiple additive grain size loci. Uncovering further such loci should be a priority for future GWAS studies in tef. The use of a high-throughput and high-accuracy phenotyping platform (MARViN grain analyser) was key to uncovering these grain size variations. While routine for major crops such as wheat, this is the first application of high-resolution, image-based grain measurements to a tef panel to our knowledge. This exemplifies the benefits that adopting robust and well-tested phenotyping methodologies from mainstream crops can bring to the research of underutilised crops<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref></sup>.</p><p id="P33">Another route to achieving large-grained white tef varieties could be to knock out key transcription factors or enzymes linked with pigmentation in a brown-grained background (through mutation breeding, transgenesis, or genome editing). To implement such an approach, the tef research community will need to increase its understanding of relevant genes and their pleiotropic effects. Contributing to this, we identified a candidate pair of homoeologues present within each of two major loci for grain size, colour, and the fatty acid EPOD. Et_4A_032842 and Et_4B_039404 are orthologous to <italic>TRANSPARENT TESTA 2</italic> (<italic>TT2</italic>), a R2R3 MYB transcription factor known to regulate seed coat colour in the Brassicaceae family through proanthocyanidin formation and accumulation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32">32</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33">33</xref></sup>.</p><p id="P34">We propose that variation in the tef orthologues of <italic>TT2</italic> contributes to variation in grain colour. This is supported by our discovery of independent insertions of related LTR-Copia retrotransposons in both homoeologues of the white-grained tef variety Tsedey. These insertions, which are absent in the genome of the brown-grained variety Dabbi, would both lead to truncated, and likely non-functional, proteins. These <italic>TT2</italic> polymorphisms could also underlie the variation in fatty acid content and grain size as has been shown in arabidopsis and <italic>Brassica napus</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R47">47</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R48">48</xref></sup>. This hypothesis could be tested by mutagenising <italic>TT2</italic> in a brown-grained variety. However, currently, we cannot preclude association of these traits with alternative or additional candidate genes. The homoeologues Et_4A_032844 and Et_4B_037039 lie within the same two loci and are orthologous to <italic>NF-YA3</italic>, a gene which activates oil accumulation in oil palm mesocarp and increases oil content and seed size when overexpressed in arabidopsis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31">31</xref></sup>. It is therefore possible that the correlated traits (grain colour, size and fatty acid) are modulated by two separate gene families in linkage blocks.</p><p id="P35">While the above manipulation is an intriguing possibility, we acknowledge that the original cultural preference for white-grained tef varieties is likely linked to flavour and baking properties in addition to aesthetics, although this has not been well-studied. It is therefore also important to study the tef metabolome beyond its direct contribution to colour. Future studies could utilise our extensive metabolome profiling data to conduct a more comprehensive metabolite GWAS (mGWAS) and deepen our understanding of the genetics underpinning differential metabolite accumulation in brown and white-grained tef.</p><p id="P36">Our work demonstrates the value that can be brought to underutilised crops such as tef by applying resequencing and population genomics in combination with large-scale phenotyping and metabolome profiling. We identify multiple novel genetic loci for morphological and nutritional traits and suggest how these could inform future research and breeding efforts, including contribution to new tef varieties with desirable plant architecture and consumer-preferred grain traits. Other orphan and underutilised crops could also benefit greatly from such methods to accelerate their domestication or improvement.</p></sec><sec id="S8" sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec id="S9"><title>Germplasm</title><p id="P37">A core panel of 225 tef accessions was selected from the broader EIAR collection to capture a broad range of phenotypic diversity. This panel consisted of 220 smallholder varieties and 5 improved, registered varieties (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD4">Supplementary Table 7</xref>). The EIAR collection is originally derived from 2,175 tef germplasm accessions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R49">49</xref></sup>, 35 cultivars<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R50">50</xref></sup>, and 10 released improved varieties<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R51">51</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="S10"><title>Field phenotyping</title><p id="P38">The accessions were grown in Ethiopia at three EIAR research sites: Alem Tena, Chefe Donsa, and Debre Zeit. Chefe Donsa and Debre Zeit sites represent non-stressed environments, while Alem Tena represents a moisture-stressed environment (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD4">Supplementary Table 8</xref>). Each field trial was set up using an augmented block design (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD4">Supplementary Table 9</xref>) and consisted of 1 m rows sown with 0.3 g grain and spaced 50 cm apart. Most accessions were sown once per field site, but five improved varieties (Ebba, Boset, Bora, Dagim and Felagot) were sown four times per field site as spatial controls.</p><p id="P39">Data were collected on a range of qualitative and quantitative traits (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD4">Supplementary Table 10</xref>). Phenotyping methodology was derived from the Tef Breeding Manual<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36">36</xref></sup> and is described in detail in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD4">Supplementary Table 11</xref>. Qualitative traits included basal stalk colour, grain colour, panicle colour, and panicle form. Quantitative traits included phenology (days to heading, days to maturity, and grain filling period) and agro-morphology (plant height, panicle length, peduncle length, culm length, first culm internode length, second culm internode length, above-ground shoot biomass, grain yield, harvest index, and lodging index). Lodging index was only assessed at Alem Tena and Debre Zeit.</p></sec><sec id="S11"><title>Grain size measurement</title><p id="P40">Grain samples from each of the 720 rows across the three field trials were analysed using a MARViN Grain Analyzer. For each sample, 0.075-0.085 g of grain (mean of 262 grains) was evenly distributed on the imaging tray. Mean grain area and TGW were recorded, as well as mean, minimum, and maximum values for grain width and length. Insufficient grain was harvested from accession Trotteriana-T-138 for MARViN analysis.</p></sec><sec id="S12"><title>DNA extraction and resequencing</title><p id="P41">For each accession, ~0.7 g fresh leaf tissue was collected from three-week old plants from the Alem Tena field trial. DNA was extracted using DNeasy Plant or DNeasy Plant Pro kits (QIAGEN) and eluted in 50 µL AE buffer. Sufficient high-quality DNA could not be extracted for the accession Trotteriana-T-138. For three further accessions (DZ-01-170, DZ-01-1015, Gealamie-T-111), the observed grain colour at Alem Tena did not match that observed at the other two field locations, suggesting heterogeneity in the seed stock. Given the DNA sample would therefore not represent the majority of the phenotyping data, these accessions were not sequenced. The remaining 221 DNA samples were sequenced by Novogene UK (Illumina paired-end 150 bp) and data was returned for 220 accessions (no data was produced for DZ-01-12).</p></sec><sec id="S13"><title>Phylogenetic analyses</title><p id="P42">Raw sequencing reads were trimmed using fastp<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R52">52</xref></sup> and mapped to the <italic>Eragrostis tef</italic> reference genome (cv. Dabbi) using Bowtie2 (v2.4.1)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R53">53</xref></sup>. The mapped reads were filtered for MAPQ scores &gt; 30 using SAMtools (v1.18) and a VCF file was generated using BCFtools (v1.18)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R54">54</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R56">56</xref></sup>. VCF statistics were generated using VCFtools and examined using base R (v4.1.3)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R57">57</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R58">58</xref></sup>. Empirically derived filters were applied using VCFtools (--max-missing 0.90; --minQ 30; --minGQ 15; --min-meanDP 10; --max-meanDP 18; --minDP 5; --maxDP 23; --maf 0.025)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R59">59</xref></sup> and linkage pruning was conducted using Plink (v1.90b4.6; --allow-extra-chr; --indep-pairwise 20 5 0.5). The final VCF file of 41,289 SNPs was converted to PHYLIP format using the tool vcf2phylip (v2.9)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R60">60</xref></sup>. A phylogram was generated using IQ-Tree 2 and arbitrarily rooted against Ada-T-58 based on alphabetical order (v2.3.2; -B 10000; --msub nuclear; -m MFP+ASC; --seed 42)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref></sup>. The phylogram was visualised in R using ggtree (v3.10.1) and ggtreeExtra (v1.12.0)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R61">61</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R62">62</xref></sup>. Population structure was investigated by applying ADMIXTURE analysis (v1.3.0, K=1:20; --cv=10)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref></sup> and principal component analysis (SNPRelate v1.29.0)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R63">63</xref></sup> to the same VCF file. The results were visualised using Pophelper (v2.3.1) and Plotly (v4.10.1), respectively<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R64">64</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R65">65</xref></sup>. After defining the redundancy groups, the name of a single accession from each group was arbitrarily assigned to represent the group in subsequent analyses (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD4">Supplementary Table 1</xref>).</p><p id="P43">A <italic>k</italic>-mer presence/absence matrix was computed for all 220 sequenced accessions from trimmed reads using scripts from a previously published <italic>k</italic>-mer-GWAS pipeline (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/wheatgenetics/owwc/tree/master/kGWAS">https://github.com/wheatgenetics/owwc/tree/master/kGWAS</ext-link>, section 1)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">20</xref></sup>. Additional guidance on the use of this pipeline is provided at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/quirozcj/kmerGWAS_descriptions">https://github.com/quirozcj/kmerGWAS_descriptions</ext-link>. Default parameters were used for all steps. Notably, the default <italic>k</italic>-mer length and minimum <italic>k</italic>-mer frequency per accession were not modified (-m 51 and -L 4, respectively). Shared <italic>k</italic>-mer state rates were computed using custom bash and R scripts (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/Uauy-Lab/tef_kGWAS_2024">https://github.com/Uauy-Lab/tef_kGWAS_2024</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec id="S14"><title>Minimal SNP panel selection</title><p id="P44">The trimmed reads from accessions belonging to redundancy groups were pooled and subsampled down to the average read number per single library (29,350,529 paired-end reads). A VCF file was generated as above for the 150 redundancy groups and singlets. The same filters and linkage pruning were applied. This VCF file was input to the Minimal Marker pipeline<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R66">66</xref></sup>. This involves conversion to a genotype matrix then selection of SNPs. However, prior to SNP selection, the pipeline was modified to convert all heterozygous calls to missing data. Heterozygous loci are unstable between generations and would therefore be unreliable markers for consistently identifying accessions across generations. In contrast, the original target species for the pipeline, apple (<italic>Malus domestica</italic>), is largely propagated vegetatively, so heterozygous loci are stably inherited between generations. Missing calls are not used by the pipeline to distinguish accessions, so this change forced the pipeline to select a panel of SNPs that uniquely identifies the core collection using only loci homozygous across the 150 tef redundancy groups and singlets. The first run selected 14 SNPs fulfilling this remit. To provide redundancy, these SNPs were removed from the genotype matrix and a second run conducted, leading to selection of a further 14 SNPs.</p><p id="P45">An additional consideration was whether the genotypes of the individual members of the redundancy groups were consistent with the overall group genotype. This was investigated using custom Bash and R scripts (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/Uauy-Lab/tef_kGWAS_2024">https://github.com/Uauy-Lab/tef_kGWAS_2024</ext-link>) and the results are summarised in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD4">Supplementary Table 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Note 1</xref>. There were no cases where group members’ genotypes compromised the utility of the SNP set for unique identification of the 150 non-redundant accessions.</p></sec><sec id="S15"><title>Metabolite extraction and profiling</title><p id="P46">Methanolic metabolite extractions were conducted at the International Livestock Research Institute (ILRI, Ethiopia) on 40 mg grain from each trial plot following a previously published protocol<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R67">67</xref></sup>. Briefly, tissue was ground (Tissue Lyser (QIAGEN), 25 Hz, 2 min), added to 1 mL pre-cooled 100% methanol (-20 °C), and placed on ice for 30 min with vortexing every 5 min. The extracts were then centrifuged, vacuum concentrated, and shipped to Aberystwyth University, Wales, UK for high-resolution metabolite profiling. The samples were resuspended in 300 μL of pre-cooled 100% methanol, vortexed for 5 min and centrifuged at 1000 x <italic>g</italic> at 4°C for 5 min. 200 μL of each sample was used for untargeted metabolite fingerprinting using Flow Infusion Electrospray High-resolution Mass Spectrometry (FIE-HRMS) mode using Q Exactive hybrid quadrupole-Orbitrap mass spectrometer (Thermo-Scientific, UK) where data was captured in negative and positive ionisation mode using Exactive hybrid quadrupole-Orbitrap mass spectrometer (Thermo-Scientific, UK). Quality controls (QC) were derived from a master mix sample where 10 mL of each extract was pooled and also “blanks” of 100% methanol. Three 20 μL injections were performed for each sample as technical replicates. FIE-HRMS metabolite fingerprints in both positive and negative ionisation mode in a single run. 20 μL of samples were injected into a flow of 100 mL min<sup>-1</sup>. The acquisition of mass-to-charge ratio (<italic>m/z</italic>) data and their binning to discrete bins and peaks was conducted as previously described<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R68">68</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R69">69</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="S16"><title>Statistical analysis on annotated metabolites</title><p id="P47">Good quality metabolite data could not be produced for 15 samples (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD4">Supplementary Table 10</xref>). A further set of ten samples were removed because their grain colour at one location did not match the grain colour at the other two locations (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD4">Supplementary Table 10</xref>). <italic>m/z</italic> feature intensities were log10 transformed and Pareto scaled and those differing significantly between brown and white-grained varieties were selected (Student’s t-test, FDR &lt; 0.05, mass tolerance of 5 ppm). Metabolite identities were assigned to the differential <italic>m/z</italic> features using the Mummichog algorithm<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R70">70</xref></sup>, with reference to the latest KEGG version of the <italic>Oryza sativa japonica</italic> (RefSeq) metabolite library <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R71">71</xref></sup>. A mass tolerance of 5 ppm was used and all possible adducts and isotopes were considered. Where <italic>m/z</italic> values could be matched to multiple metabolites, the metabolite with the smallest mass difference to the <italic>m/z</italic> value was selected. Statistical analysis, principal component analysis (PCA), partial least squares discriminant analysis (PLS-DA), variable metabolite prediction, and volcano plot were carried out using the online R-based platform MetaboAnalyst 6.0 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.metaboanalyst.ca">https://www.metaboanalyst.ca</ext-link>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R72">72</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="S17"><title>Statistical modelling for BLUP calculation</title><p id="P48">The original field trial design was updated to reflect the treatment of redundant accessions as combined redundancy groups (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD4">Supplementary Table 12</xref>). Data points were removed as for the metabolite analyses above. Genotypic BLUPs were calculated using the R package lme4 (v1.1.32)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R73">73</xref></sup> by fitting the following model using restricted maximum likelihood (REML): <disp-formula id="FD1"><mml:math id="M1"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mi>Z</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mi>W</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="P49">Where <italic>Y</italic> is the observed trait value, <italic>f()</italic> is a transformation conducted for normalisation (either square root, natural log, or none), <italic>α</italic> is the global mean, <italic>β</italic> is location, <italic>X</italic> is a matrix of location effects, γ is block by location identity, <italic>Z</italic> is a matrix of block by location effects, δ is genotype identity, <italic>W</italic> is a matrix of genotype effects, and <italic>e</italic> is the residual. Location was modelled as a fixed effect due to the low number of factor levels, while block by location and genotype were modelled as random effects. The transformation <italic>f()</italic> applied to each trait was selected to make residuals approximately normally distributed and independent of fitted values. <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD4">Supplementary Table 13</xref> describes the transformation applied to each trait and lists any additional data points removed for specific traits prior to BLUP calculation.</p><p id="P50">Modelling of BLUPs was not deemed appropriate for panicle morphology and grain colour given their ordinal and binary encoding (respectively) and minimal variation between field sites. Instead, simple means were used as the genotypic values.</p><p id="P51">To rationalise trait values for presentation, the global intercepts were added to the BLUPs for plant height, grain area, and thousand grain weight in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figures 4a and 4b</xref>. Raw BLUPs were used for kGWAS and SNP-based GWAS computations.</p></sec><sec id="S18"><title><italic>k</italic>-mer-based GWAS</title><p id="P52">A new <italic>k</italic>-mer presence/absence matrix was generated as above using the previously pooled and subsampled reads for the 150 accessions or redundancy groups. Association mapping, calculation of significance threshold, and plotting were conducted using the same kGWAS pipeline on 141 accessions (nine redundancy groups were excluded because they contained both brown and white-grained accessions; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD4">Supplementary Table 1</xref>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">20</xref></sup>. For the metabolite traits, a further three accessions were excluded because only one datapoint remained for BLUP calculation (DZ-01-517, DZ-01-1376, Hotolla-T-135). <italic>k</italic>-mers were projected onto the Dabbi reference genome and reported as the number of <italic>k</italic>-mers at a given association level per 10 kb genomic bin. The significance threshold for associations was calculated via Bonferroni correction as follows: <disp-formula id="FD2"><mml:math id="M2"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.05</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.36</mml:mn><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>8</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="P53">Where <italic>n</italic> is the number of <italic>k</italic>-mers utilised for association calculations (187,226,135) and <italic>k</italic> is the <italic>k</italic>-mer length (51). This threshold is plotted as -log<sub>10</sub>(1.36×10<sup>-8</sup>) = 7.87 on all Manhattan plots presented. For each trait, putative trait-associated regions were extended from the first bin on a chromosome containing significant <italic>k</italic>-mers and terminated at the point where the subsequent 500 kb contained zero significant <italic>k</italic>-mers. Additional putative regions were then iteratively initiated from the next bin containing significant <italic>k</italic>-mers. Putative regions were then defined as significantly trait-associated if they contained ≥750 significant <italic>k</italic>-mers.</p><p id="P54"><xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD4">Supplementary Table 5</xref> lists all significantly trait-associated regions. Dotplot sequence alignments of significant regions on chromosome 4A (peak 3) and 4B (peak7) and the LTR Copia insertions in the candidate genes in these regions were made with the dotplot function in R package SeqinR (v4.2-36)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R74">74</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="S19"><title>SNP-based GWAS</title><p id="P55">SNP-based GWAS was carried out via GAPIT (v3)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R75">75</xref></sup> with six different models; FarmCPU, BLINK, MLMM, SUPER, CMLM, and ECMLM. The significance threshold for associations was calculated via Bonferroni correction as follows: <disp-formula id="FD3"><mml:math id="M3"><mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.05</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.01</mml:mn><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>6</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="P56">Where n is the number of SNPs utilised for association calculations (49,660). The VCF file used was the same as that used to generate the minimal SNP panel except that during linkage pruning, R<sup>2</sup> was set to 0.7 instead of 0.5. Details of all trait-associated SNPs are provided in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD4">Supplementary Table 6</xref>.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="SM"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1"><label>Supplementary File 1</label><media xlink:href="EMS199164-supplement-Supplementary_File_1.docx" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document" id="d121aAcEbB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD2"><label>Supplementary File 2</label><media xlink:href="EMS199164-supplement-Supplementary_File_2.docx" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document" id="d121aAcEcB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD3"><label>Supplementary Information</label><media xlink:href="EMS199164-supplement-Supplementary_Information.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" id="d121aAcEdB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD4"><label>Supplementary Table</label><media xlink:href="EMS199164-supplement-Supplementary_Table.xlsx" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.spreadsheetml.sheet" id="d121aAcEeB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack id="S20"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The authors would like to thank Corteva for pre-publication access to the improved Tsedey genome assembly, Phil Robiƒnson for help with photography, Martin Vickers for help with depositing sequence data with SRA, and Stephanie Williams for figure design advice. Metabolite profiling was supported by Manfred Beckmann and Helen Phillips (Aberystwyth University). This work was supported by the Royal Society FLAIR Collaboration Grants 2020 (FCG\R1\201032); Biotechnology and Biological Sciences Research Council (BBSRC) through the Delivering Sustainable Wheat (BB/X011003/1) and Building Robustness in Crops (BB/X01102X/1) Institute Strategic Programmes; European Research Council (ERC-2019-COG-866328); CGIAR Initiative on Sustainable Animal Productivity for Livelihoods, Nutrition and Gender inclusion (SAPLING). CGIAR research is also supported by contributions to the CGIAR Trust Fund. O.S was also supported by the Royal Society FLAIR Fellowship (FLR_R1_191850). A.G. was supported European Union’s Horizon 2020 research and innovation programme under the Marie Skłodowska-Curie H2020-MSCA-IF-2018 grant agreement No 842118, SUPERTEFF”. J.Q.C was supported by The Mexican Consejo Nacional de Ciencia y Tecnología (CONACYT; 2018-000009-01EXTF-00306) and the JIC International Scholarship (2018-2022).</p></ack><sec id="S21" sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p id="P57">Sequencing data is available via NCBI SRA under BioProject ID PRJNA1150514. Raw phenotypic data can be found in the <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD4">Supplementary Tables</xref>. Raw metabolomic data and VCF files are available at Zenodo (10.5281/zenodo.13837319). Custom Bash and R scripts are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/Uauy-Lab/tef_kGWAS_2024">https://github.com/Uauy-Lab/tef_kGWAS_2024</ext-link>.</p></sec><fn-group><fn fn-type="con" id="FN1"><p id="P58"><bold>Author Contributions</bold></p><p id="P59"><bold>M.R.W.J</bold>.: Formal Analysis, Software, Investigation, Data Curation, Writing - Original Draft, Visualisation, Project administration; <bold>A.T</bold>.: Formal Analysis, Investigation, Supervision, Writing - Original Draft, Visualisation; <bold>A.G</bold>.:Formal Analysis, Investigation, Data Curation, Writing - Original Draft, Visualisation; <bold>W.K</bold>.: Investigation, Data Curation, Resources, Writing-Original Draft; <bold>A.T</bold>.: Investigation, Data Curation, Writing - Original Draft; <bold>D.G</bold>.: Conceptualisation, Supervision, Resources, Writing - Review &amp; Editing; <bold>J.K.M.B</bold>.: Formal Analysis, Writing - Review &amp; Editing; <bold>J.Q.C</bold>.: Methodology, Software; <bold>C.S.J</bold>.: Resources, Supervision, Writing - Review &amp; Editing; <bold>B.B.H.W</bold>.: Conceptualisation, Writing - Review &amp; Editing, Funding Acquisition; <bold>S.C</bold>.: Conceptualisation, Resources, Investigation, Project Administration, Writing - Review &amp; Editing; <bold>K.A</bold>.: Conceptualisation, Resources, Investigation, Writing - Review &amp; Editing; <bold>Z.T</bold>.: Conceptualisation, Resources, Writing - Review &amp; Editing; <bold>L.A.J.M</bold>.: Conceptualisation, Resources, Formal Analysis, Supervision, Writing - Original Draft, Funding Acquisition. <bold>C.U</bold>.: Conceptualisation, Formal Analysis, Resources, Supervision, Writing - Original Draft, Project Administration, Funding Acquisition; <bold>O.S</bold>.: Conceptualisation, Formal Analysis, Investigation, Supervision, Writing - Original Draft, Visualisation, Project Administration, Funding Acquisition</p></fn><fn fn-type="conflict" id="FN2"><p id="P60"><bold>Competing interests</bold></p><p id="P61">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><ref id="R1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="report"><collab>Ethiopian Statistics Service</collab><article-title>Ethiopian Statistics Service</article-title><source>Report on Area and Production of Major Crops</source><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.statsethiopia.gov.et/our-survey-reports/">https://www.statsethiopia.gov.et/our-survey-reports/</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mayes</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Dalle</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Demissew</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Massawe</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diversifying crops for food and nutrition security - a case of teff</article-title><source>Biol Rev Camb Philos Soc</source><year>2017</year><volume>92</volume><fpage>188</fpage><lpage>198</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26456883</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cotter</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Evaluating the Antioxidant Properties of the Ancient-Crop Tef (Eragrostis tef) Grain Extracts in THP-1 Monocytes</article-title><source>Antioxidants (Basel)</source><year>2023</year><volume>12</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10451390</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37627557</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/antiox12081561</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ramírez Gonzales</surname><given-names>LY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The role of omics in improving the orphan crop tef</article-title><source>Trends Genet</source><year>2024</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>449</fpage><lpage>461</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38599921</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shorinola</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Integrative and inclusive genomics to promote the use of underutilised crops</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2024</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>320</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10774273</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38191605</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-023-44535-x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>VanBuren</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Exceptional subgenome stability and functional divergence in the allotetraploid Ethiopian cereal teff</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2020</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>884</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7021729</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32060277</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-020-14724-z</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cannarozzi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genome and transcriptome sequencing identifies breeding targets in the orphan crop tef (Eragrostis tef)</article-title><source>BMC Genomics</source><year>2014</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>581</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4119204</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25007843</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2164-15-581</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Girma</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The origins and progress of genomics research on Tef (Eragrostis tef)</article-title><source>Plant Biotechnol J</source><year>2014</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>534</fpage><lpage>540</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24891040</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Assefa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genetic diversity in tef [Eragrostis tef (Zucc.) Trotter]</article-title><source>Front Plant Sci</source><year>2015</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>177</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4374454</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25859251</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2015.00177</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blösch</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Panicle Angle is an Important Factor in Tef Lodging Tolerance</article-title><source>Front Plant Sci</source><year>2020</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>61</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7031273</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32117397</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2020.00061</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Woldeyohannes</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Desta</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Fadda</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Pè</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Dell’Acqua</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Value of teff (Eragrostis tef) genetic resources to support breeding for conventional and smallholder farming: a review</article-title><source>CABI Agriculture and Bioscience</source><year>2022</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>27</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zanke</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Analysis of main effect QTL for thousand grain weight in European winter wheat (Triticum aestivum L.) by genome-wide association mapping</article-title><source>Front Plant Sci</source><year>2015</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>644</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4555037</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26388877</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2015.00644</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stallknecht</surname><given-names>GF</given-names></name><name><surname>Gilbertson</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Eckhoff</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Teff: Food crop for humans and animals</article-title><year>1993</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tiguh</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name><name><surname>Delele</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name><name><surname>Kidanemariam</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Fenta</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assessment of harvest and postharvest losses of teff (Eragrostistef (Zucc.)) and methods of loss reduction: A review</article-title><source>Heliyon</source><year>2024</year><volume>10</volume><elocation-id>e30398</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11068822</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38707375</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.heliyon.2024.e30398</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ben-Zeev</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Less is more: Lower sowing rate of irrigated tef (Eragrostis tef) alters plant morphology and reduces lodging</article-title><source>Agronomy (Basel)</source><year>2020</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>570</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jifar</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Assefa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Tadele</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Grain yield variation and association of major traits in brown-seeded genotypes of tef [Eragrostis tef (Zucc.)Trotter]</article-title><source>Agriculture &amp; Food Security</source><year>2015</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>7</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alexander</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Novembre</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lange</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fast model-based estimation of ancestry in unrelated individuals</article-title><source>Genome Res</source><year>2009</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>1655</fpage><lpage>1664</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2752134</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19648217</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gr.094052.109</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alemu</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genomic dissection of productivity, lodging, and morpho□physiological traits in Eragrostis tef under contrasting water availabilities</article-title><source>Plants People Planet</source><year>2024</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ppp3.10505</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Minh</surname><given-names>BQ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>IQ-TREE 2: New Models and Efficient Methods for Phylogenetic Inference in the Genomic Era</article-title><source>Mol Biol Evol</source><year>2020</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>1530</fpage><lpage>1534</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7182206</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32011700</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/molbev/msaa015</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gaurav</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Population genomic analysis of Aegilops tauschii identifies targets for bread wheat improvement</article-title><source>Nat Biotechnol</source><year>2022</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>422</fpage><lpage>431</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8926922</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34725503</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41587-021-01058-4</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kanehisa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Furumichi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawashima</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ishiguro-Watanabe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>KEGG for taxonomy-based analysis of pathways and genomes</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2023</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>D587</fpage><lpage>D592</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9825424</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36300620</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkac963</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Day</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Lipid Chemistry</chapter-title><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Wrigley</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><source>Encyclopedia of Grain Science</source><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc><year>2004</year><fpage>157</fpage><lpage>165</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wallis</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Bengtsson</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Browse</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular Approaches Reduce Saturates and Eliminate trans Fats in Food Oils</article-title><source>Front Plant Sci</source><year>2022</year><volume>13</volume><elocation-id>908608</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9205222</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35720592</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2022.908608</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gebru</surname><given-names>YA</given-names></name><name><surname>Sbhatu</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>K-P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nutritional composition and health benefits of teff (Eragrostis tef (Zucc.) Trotter)</article-title><source>J Food Qual</source><year>2020</year><volume>2020</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>6</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>N-Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>H-X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Contribution of phenylpropanoid metabolism to plant development and plant-environment interactions</article-title><source>J Integr Plant Biol</source><year>2021</year><volume>63</volume><fpage>180</fpage><lpage>209</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33325112</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Konishi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>An SNP caused loss of seed shattering during rice domestication</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2006</year><volume>312</volume><fpage>1392</fpage><lpage>1396</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16614172</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ikeda</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>BELL1-like homeobox genes regulate inflorescence architecture and meristem maintenance in rice</article-title><source>Plant J</source><year>2019</year><volume>98</volume><fpage>465</fpage><lpage>478</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30657229</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Walley</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Integration of omic networks in a developmental atlas of maize</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2016</year><volume>353</volume><fpage>814</fpage><lpage>818</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5808982</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27540173</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.aag1125</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Woodhouse</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A pan-genomic approach to genome databases using maize as a model system</article-title><source>BMC Plant Biol</source><year>2021</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>385</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8377966</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34416864</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12870-021-03173-5</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>PY</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>F-Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Lo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cytochrome P450 93G1 is a flavone synthase II that channels flavanones to the biosynthesis of tricin O-linked conjugates in rice</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>2014</year><volume>165</volume><fpage>1315</fpage><lpage>1327</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4081339</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24843076</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.114.239723</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yeap</surname><given-names>W-C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>WRI1-1, ABI5, NF-YA3 and NF-YC2 increase oil biosynthesis in coordination with hormonal signaling during fruit development in oil palm</article-title><source>Plant J</source><year>2017</year><volume>91</volume><fpage>97</fpage><lpage>113</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28370622</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nesi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Jond</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Debeaujon</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Caboche</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lepiniec</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Arabidopsis TT2 gene encodes an R2R3 MYB domain protein that acts as a key determinant for proanthocyanidin accumulation in developing seed</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2001</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>2099</fpage><lpage>2114</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC139454</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11549766</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/TPC.010098</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characteristics of Color Development in Seeds of Brown- and Yellow-Seeded Heading Chinese Cabbage and Molecular Analysis of Brsc, the Candidate Gene Controlling Seed Coat Color</article-title><source>Front Plant Sci</source><year>2017</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>1410</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5558542</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28855913</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2017.01410</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wicker</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genome-wide comparative analysis of copia retrotransposons in Triticeae, rice, and Arabidopsis reveals conserved ancient evolutionary lineages and distinct dynamics of individual copia families</article-title><source>Genome Res</source><year>2007</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>1072</fpage><lpage>1081</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1899118</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17556529</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gr.6214107</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chapman</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Beyond a reference genome: pangenomes and population genomics of underutilized and orphan crops for future food and nutrition security</article-title><source>New Phytol</source><year>2022</year><volume>234</volume><fpage>1583</fpage><lpage>1597</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9994440</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35318683</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/nph.18021</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chanyalew</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><chapter-title>Tef breeding manual</chapter-title><source>Ethiopian Institute of Agricultural Research, Debre Zeit Agricultural Research Center</source><publisher-name>National Tef Research Program</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Debre Zeit, Ethiopia</publisher-loc><year>2021</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Milner</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genebank genomics highlights the diversity of a global barley collection</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><year>2018</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>319</fpage><lpage>326</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30420647</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mascher</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genebank genomics bridges the gap between the conservation of crop diversity and plant breeding</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><year>2019</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>1076</fpage><lpage>1081</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31253974</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Woldeyohannes</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Data-driven, participatory characterization of farmer varieties discloses teff breeding potential under current and future climates</article-title><source>Elife</source><year>2022</year><volume>11</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9439699</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36052993</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.80009</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The APETALA2-like transcription factor SUPERNUMERARY BRACT controls rice seed shattering and seed size</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2019</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>17</fpage><lpage>36</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6391694</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30626621</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.18.00304</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R41"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Simons</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Molecular characterization of the major wheat domestication gene Q</article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>2006</year><volume>172</volume><fpage>547</fpage><lpage>555</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1456182</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16172507</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1534/genetics.105.044727</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R42"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roeder</surname><given-names>AHK</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferrándiz</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Yanofsky</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of the REPLUMLESS homeodomain protein in patterning the Arabidopsis fruit</article-title><source>Curr Biol</source><year>2003</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>1630</fpage><lpage>1635</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13678595</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R43"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>HMS</given-names></name><name><surname>Hake</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The interaction of two homeobox genes, BREVIPEDICELLUS and PENNYWISE, regulates internode patterning in the Arabidopsis inflorescence</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2003</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>1717</fpage><lpage>1727</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC167164</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12897247</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.012856</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R44"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Byrne</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Groover</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name><surname>Fontana</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Martienssen</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phyllotactic pattern and stem cell fate are determined by the Arabidopsis homeobox gene BELLRINGER</article-title><source>Development</source><year>2003</year><volume>130</volume><fpage>3941</fpage><lpage>3950</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12874117</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R45"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tsuda</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>KNOTTED1 Cofactors, BLH12 and BLH14, Regulate Internode Patterning and Vein Anastomosis in Maize</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2017</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>1105</fpage><lpage>1118</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5466031</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28381444</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.16.00967</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R46"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cannarozzi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Technology generation to dissemination: lessons learned from the tef improvement project</article-title><source>Euphytica</source><year>2018</year><volume>214</volume></element-citation></ref><ref id="R47"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The effect of <italic>TRANSPARENT TESTA2</italic> on seed fatty acid biosynthesis and tolerance to environmental stresses during young seedling establishment in Arabidopsis</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>2012</year><volume>160</volume><fpage>1023</fpage><lpage>1036</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3461527</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22879396</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.112.202945</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R48"><label>48</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Allelic variation of BnaC.TT2.A and its association with seed coat color and fatty acids in rapeseed (Brassica napus L</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2016</year><volume>11</volume><elocation-id>e0146661</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4709174</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26752200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0146661</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R49"><label>49</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ketema</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><source>Tef (Eragrostis Tef): Breeding, Agronomy, Genetic Resources, Utilization, and Role in Ethiopian Agriculture</source><publisher-name>Institute of Agricultural Research</publisher-name><year>1993</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R50"><label>50</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ebba</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>T’ef (Eragrostis Tef) Cultivars: Morphology and Classification Part 2</article-title><year>1975</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R51"><label>51</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Assefa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Breeding tef [Eragrostis tef (Zucc.) trotter]: conventional and molecular approaches</article-title><source>Plant Breed</source><year>2011</year><volume>130</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>9</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R52"><label>52</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>fastp: an ultra-fast all-in-one FASTQ preprocessor</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2018</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>i884</fpage><lpage>i890</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6129281</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30423086</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/bty560</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R53"><label>53</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Langmead</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Salzberg</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fast gapped-read alignment with Bowtie 2</article-title><source>Nat Methods</source><year>2012</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>357</fpage><lpage>359</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3322381</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22388286</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.1923</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R54"><label>54</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bonfield</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>HTSlib: C library for reading/writing high-throughput sequencing data</article-title><source>Gigascience</source><year>2021</year><volume>10</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7931820</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33594436</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/gigascience/giab007</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R55"><label>55</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Danecek</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Twelve years of SAMtools and BCFtools</article-title><source>Gigascience</source><year>2021</year><volume>10</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7931819</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33590861</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/gigascience/giab008</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R56"><label>56</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The Sequence Alignment/Map format and SAMtools</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2009</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>2078</fpage><lpage>2079</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2723002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19505943</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btp352</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R57"><label>57</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Danecek</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The variant call format and VCFtools</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2011</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>2156</fpage><lpage>2158</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3137218</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21653522</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btr330</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R58"><label>58</label><element-citation publication-type="web"><collab>R Core Team</collab><source>R: A Language and Environment for Statistical Computing</source><year>2020</year><comment>Preprint at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.R-project.org/">https://www.R-project.org/</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="R59"><label>59</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Purcell</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>PLINK: a tool set for whole-genome association and population-based linkage analyses</article-title><source>Am J Hum Genet</source><year>2007</year><volume>81</volume><fpage>559</fpage><lpage>575</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1950838</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17701901</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/519795</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R60"><label>60</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ortiz</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>vcf2phylip v2.0: Convert a VCF Matrix into Several Matrix Formats for Phylogenetic Analysis</article-title><source>Zenodo</source><year>2019</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5281/zenodo.2540861</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R61"><label>61</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>TT-Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ggtree: An r package for visualization and annotation of phylogenetic trees with their covariates and other associated data</article-title><source>Methods Ecol Evol</source><year>2017</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>28</fpage><lpage>36</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R62"><label>62</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>GgtreeExtra: Compact visualization of richly annotated phylogenetic data</article-title><source>Mol Biol Evol</source><year>2021</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>4039</fpage><lpage>4042</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8382893</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34097064</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/molbev/msab166</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R63"><label>63</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A high-performance computing toolset for relatedness and principal component analysis of SNP data</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2012</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>3326</fpage><lpage>3328</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3519454</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23060615</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/bts606</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R64"><label>64</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Francis</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>pophelper: an R package and web app to analyse and visualize population structure</article-title><source>Mol Ecol Resour</source><year>2017</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>27</fpage><lpage>32</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26850166</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R65"><label>65</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Bilal</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Interactive web□based data visualization with R, plotly, and shiny (Carson Sievert)</article-title><source>Biometrics</source><year>2021</year><volume>77</volume><fpage>776</fpage><lpage>777</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R66"><label>66</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Winfield</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Development of a minimal KASP marker panel for distinguishing genotypes in apple collections</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2020</year><volume>15</volume><elocation-id>e0242940</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7703965</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33253289</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0242940</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R67"><label>67</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>López-Álvarez</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Zubair</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Beckmann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Draper</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Catalán</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diversity and association of phenotypic and metabolomic traits in the close model grasses Brachypodium distachyon, B. stacei and B. hybridum</article-title><source>Ann Bot</source><year>2017</year><volume>119</volume><fpage>545</fpage><lpage>561</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5458712</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28040672</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/aob/mcw239</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R68"><label>68</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ferreira</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name><surname>Santana</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name><name><surname>Scagliusi</surname><given-names>SMM</given-names></name><name><surname>Beckmann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mur</surname><given-names>LAJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Metabolomics links induced responses to the wheat pathogen – tan spot – (Pyrenophora tritici-repentis) to the biosynthesis of flavonoids and bioenergetic metabolism</article-title><source>Research Square</source><year>2023</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21203/rs.3.rs-3105957/v1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R69"><label>69</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Finch</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Spectral binning as an approach to post-acquisition processing of high resolution FIE-MS metabolome fingerprinting data</article-title><source>Metabolomics</source><year>2022</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>64</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9345815</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35917032</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11306-022-01923-6</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R70"><label>70</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Predicting network activity from high throughput metabolomics</article-title><source>PLoS Comput Biol</source><year>2013</year><volume>9</volume><elocation-id>e1003123</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3701697</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23861661</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003123</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R71"><label>71</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>International Rice Genome Sequencing Project</collab><article-title>The map-based sequence of the rice genome</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2005</year><volume>436</volume><fpage>793</fpage><lpage>800</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16100779</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R72"><label>72</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>MetaboAnalystR 4.0: a unified LC-MS workflow for global metabolomics</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2024</year><volume>15</volume><elocation-id>3675</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11063062</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38693118</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-024-48009-6</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R73"><label>73</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bates</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Mächler</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bolker</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fitting Linear Mixed-Effects Models Using lme4</article-title><source>Journal of Statistical Software</source><year>2015</year><volume>67</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>48</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18637/jss.v067.i01</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R74"><label>74</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Charif</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Lobry</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>SeqinR 1. 0-2: A Contributed Package to the R Project for Statistical Computing Devoted to Biological Sequences Retrieval and Analysis</chapter-title><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Bastolla</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Porto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Roman</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name><name><surname>Vendruscolo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><source>Structural Approaches to Sequence Evolution: Molecules, Networks, Populations</source><publisher-name>Springer Berlin Heidelberg</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Berlin, Heidelberg</publisher-loc><year>2007</year><fpage>207</fpage><lpage>232</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R75"><label>75</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>GAPIT version 3: Boosting power and accuracy for genomic association and prediction</article-title><source>Genomics Proteomics Bioinformatics</source><year>2021</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>629</fpage><lpage>640</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9121400</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34492338</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.gpb.2021.08.005</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Diversity of panicle morphology and grain colour in tef</title><p><bold>a</bold>, Comparison of a bread wheat spike (cv. ‘Paragon’, far left) with tef accessions exemplifying four categories of panicle morphology (from left to right; very lax, lax, semi-compact, and compact) <bold>b</bold>, Comparison of bread wheat grains (cv. Paragon, bottom) with grains from brown and white-grained tef varieties.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS199164-f001"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Resequencing, phenotyping, and GWAS of the EIAR core tef collection</title><p>A representative panel of Ethiopian tef accessions was resequenced and phenotyped for agronomic, grain size, and metabolomic traits. Statistical modelling was used to correct for location and within-site spatial effects. The software and numbers of accessions used for each step are indicated above each box.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS199164-f002"/></fig><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Phylogenetic analyses identify redundancy in the EIAR core collection</title><p><bold>a</bold>, Phylogram of 220 teff accessions, arbitrarily rooted against the accession “Ada-T58”. White and brown-grained varieties are well-distributed across the phylogeny. 32 redundancy groups ranging in size from 2 to 19 accessions were identified on the basis of small phylogenetic distances between pairs of accessions. <bold>b</bold>, Phylogenetic distance plotted against the percentage of k-mer states shared for all 24,090 pairwise comparisons between accessions. There is a strong correlation between these two relatedness metrics. Accession pairs from within the previously defined redundancy groups (purple) cluster together at uniquely high shared kmer state rates, depicted in detail in <bold>c</bold>. The points with particularly low percentages of shared k-mer states (&lt;78%, dashed line) represent the full set of comparisons of “DZ-01-1167” with other accessions.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS199164-f003"/></fig><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Best linear unbiased predictors (BLUPs) reveal correlations between key agronomic traits</title><p><bold>a</bold>, Correlation tests were conducted between the BLUPs for 20 traits of interest. Significant correlations (p &lt;□0.05) are indicated by circles whose size and colour represent the magnitude and direction of correlation. <bold>b</bold>, Boxplot of plant height BLUPs for white and brown-grained varieties, with individual data points overlaid. White-grained accessions tended to produce taller plants. <bold>c</bold>, Scatterplot of grain area BLUPs against thousand grain weight (TGW) BLUPs. A distinctly bimodal distribution is strongly explained by grain colour, with white-grained varieties tending to produce smaller grains. Despite this, their grains are of approximately the same mass as brown-grained varieties, suggesting higher grain densities.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS199164-f004"/></fig><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>Brown and white-grained tef accessions display differential metabolite accumulation</title><p><bold>a</bold>, Partial least squares discriminant analysis (PLS-DA) of metabolites in grain samples of brown and white-grained accessions. Ellipses represent 95% confidence intervals around each group. <bold>b</bold>, Differentially accumulated metabolites show enrichment for several metabolic pathways, notably fatty acid and flavone metabolism. Point size scales with pathway impact and colour intensity scales with significance of pathway enrichment. <bold>c</bold>, Volcano plot for the 183 identifiable differentially accumulated metabolites. Fold-change (FC) was calculated as mean value in brown-grained varieties divided by that in white-grained varieties. Plotted FC thresholds are log<sub>2</sub>(0.83) and log<sub>2</sub>(1.2) and plotted FDR threshold is log<sub>10</sub>(0.05).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS199164-f005"/></fig><fig id="F6" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title><italic>k</italic>-mer-based GWAS identifies multiple marker-trait associations, including regions associated with panicle morphology and grain KOROG</title><p><bold>a</bold>, Plot summarising all trait-associated regions identified by <italic>k</italic>-mer-based GWAS. Regions positively associated with traits are plotted above their respective chromosomes, while negatively associated regions are plotted below. For grain colour, positive and negative associations indicate brown and white, respectively. <bold>b</bold>, A region significantly associated with panicle morphology was detected on chromosome 3B. The arrangement of the 13 genes within this region is displayed below the plot. The candidate gene <italic>qSH1</italic> is highlighted. <bold>c</bold>, A region significantly associated with Kaempferol 3-O-rhamnoside-7-O-glucoside (KOROG) was detected on chromosome 7A. The arrangement of the 26 genes within this region is displayed below the plot. The candidate gene <italic>CYP93G1</italic> is highlighted. In <bold>b</bold> and <bold>c</bold>, <italic>k</italic>-mers are grouped according to their association level and genomic coordinates (10 kb bins) and coloured according to the direction of association; red for panicle laxness or low KOROG, blue for panicle compactness or high KOROG. Point size is proportional to number of <italic>k</italic>-mers rounded upwards to the nearest 10.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS199164-f006"/></fig><fig id="F7" position="float"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><title>Co-association of grain colour, width, and EPOD concentration with multiple regions</title><p>Plots of k-mers associated with <bold>a</bold>, grain colour, <bold>b</bold>, grain width, and c, grain EPOD concentration. k-mers are grouped according to their association level and genomic coordinates (10 kb bins) and coloured according to the direction of association. In <bold>a</bold>, brown denotes association with brown grain colour and white with white grain colour. In <bold>b</bold> and <bold>c</bold>, red denotes association with lower trait values, and blue with higher trait values. Point size is proportional to number of <italic>k</italic>-mers rounded upwards to the nearest 10. Nine regions are labelled with black and green numbers, denoting whether the region is significant or not-significant for the plotted trait, respectively. Diagrams of LTR Copia insertions into TT2 homoeologs on <bold>d</bold>, chromosome 4A, <bold>e</bold>, chromosome 4B. Top: structure of TT2 in Dabbi (brown-grained). Centre: structure of TT2 in Tsedey (white-grained). Bottom: detail of LTR Copia insertions. Narrower exons indicate presumed protein truncations. Black DNA bases denote 5 bp target-site duplications. Green DNA bases denote the start of the retrotransposon insertions. Single-letter amino acid codes show the introduction of premature stop codons (*).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS199164-f007"/></fig></floats-group></article>