<!DOCTYPE article
 PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" article-type="preprint"><?all-math-mml yes?><?use-mml?><?origin ukpmcpa?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">bioRxiv</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>bioRxiv : the preprint server for biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2692-8205</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">EMS201995</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2024.12.10.627701</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="archive">PPR954047</article-id><article-version-alternatives><article-version article-version-type="status">preprint</article-version><article-version article-version-type="number">1</article-version></article-version-alternatives><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>E-cadherin endocytosis promotes non-canonical EGFR:STAT signalling to induce cell death and inhibit heterochromatinisation</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ramirez-Moreno</surname><given-names>Miguel</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN1">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Quinton</surname><given-names>Amy</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jacobsen</surname><given-names>Eleanor</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Stempor</surname><given-names>Przemyslaw A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zeidler</surname><given-names>Martin P.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bulgakova</surname><given-names>Natalia A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN2">4</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CR1">*</xref></contrib><aff id="A1"><label>1</label>School of Biosciences, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/05krs5044</institution-id><institution>University of Sheffield</institution></institution-wrap>, <city>Sheffield</city>, <postal-code>S10 2TN</postal-code>, <country country="GB">UK</country></aff><aff id="A2"><label>3</label>Nonacus Limited, Birmingham, B32 1AF, UK</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="CR1">
<label>*</label>corresponding author: <email>n.bulgakova@qmul.ac.uk</email>
</corresp><fn id="FN1" fn-type="present-address"><label>2</label><p id="P1">current address: School of Biological Sciences, University of Southampton, Southampton, SO17 1BJ, UK</p></fn><fn id="FN2" fn-type="present-address"><label>4</label><p id="P2">current address: School of Biological and Behavioural Sciences, Queen Mary University of London, London, E1 4NS, UK</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted"><day>18</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="preprint"><day>12</day><month>12</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><permissions><ali:free_to_read/><license><ali:license_ref>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is licensed under a <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">CC BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><title>Summary</title><p id="P3">Signalling molecules often contribute to several signalling pathways that produce distinct transcriptional outputs and cellular phenotypes. One of the major unanswered questions in cell biology is how multiple activities of signalling molecules are coordinated in space and time in vivo. Here, we focus on the Signal Transducer and Activator of Transcription (STAT) protein as a paradigm of signalling molecules involved in several independent signalling pathways. In addition to the canonical pathways, whereby STAT is phosphorylated and activated by Janus Kinases, STAT is involved in at least two non-canonical pathways. In one pathway, STAT is activated by the Epidermal Growth Factor Receptor (EGFR) promoting apoptosis. In another, it binds the Heterochromatin Protein 1 (HP1) to enhance heterochromatin formation. Using <italic>Drosophila</italic> wing discs as an epithelial system, we demonstrate that all three STAT activities coexist in this tissue. We provide evidence that while the canonical STAT signalling is dominant over non-canonical pathways, EGFR:STAT and HP1:STAT pathways compete for the availability of unphosphorylated STAT. We also describe the role of the cell-cell adhesion protein E-cadherin in EGFR:STAT signalling. Both EGFR and STAT colocalise with E-cadherin at cell-cell junctions and on intracellular vesicles. Elevated intracellular E-cadherin promotes EGFR:STAT pathway leading to apoptosis, whereas blocking E-cadherin endocytosis prevents apoptosis induction. Altogether, we propose that E-cadherin endocytosis controls the balance between two non-canonical STAT activities in a potential tumour-suppressive mechanism – junctional disassembly in dysregulated epithelial-to-mesenchymal transitions would shift this balance towards the EGFR:STAT signalling to promote apoptosis.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>STAT</kwd><kwd>EGFR</kwd><kwd>E-cadherin</kwd><kwd>adhesion</kwd><kwd>endocytosis</kwd><kwd>heterochromatin</kwd><kwd>apoptosis</kwd><kwd>epithelial cells</kwd><kwd><italic>Drosophila</italic></kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="S1" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p id="P4">Signalling pathways control numerous aspects of cellular behaviour including proliferation, differentiation, morphological changes and cell death. Many of these molecular pathways transduce signals from the environment into the cell nucleus leading to changes in gene expression and chromatin organisation. However, pathways do not have single fixed outcomes but produce a range of qualitatively different transcriptional outputs depending on the temporal, spatial and environmental context of the cell<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref></sup>. One of the major unanswered questions in cell biology is how context-appropriate signalling outputs are selected and coordinated by cells<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">2</xref></sup>.</p><p id="P5">The Janus Kinase/Signal Transducer and Activator of Transcription (JAK/STAT) pathway delivers its effects through several parallel modalities. In ‘canonical’ JAK/STAT signalling, ligand stimulation of cytokine receptors causes the activation of receptor-associated JAKs, leading to the phosphorylation of latent STAT transcription factors on highly conserved tyrosine residues. This induces STAT dimerisation and translocation to the nucleus where the complex directly binds to DNA and activates transcription<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">4</xref></sup>. However, STAT has at least two additional non-canonical activities. In the first of these, non-canonical STAT modulates chromatin organisation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref></sup>. In this pathway, unphosphorylated STAT (not phosphorylated on the canonical C-terminal tyrosine residue) binds to Heterochromatin Protein 1 (HP1) and stabilises heterochromatin in both <italic>Drosophila</italic> and mammalian cells<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">8</xref></sup>. While the binding between STAT and HP1 has a tumour-suppressor role<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">8</xref></sup>, the cellular function of heterochromatin stabilisation by STAT:HP1 interaction is unclear. In the second example of non-canonical STAT activities, the direct activation of STAT1, STAT3 and STAT5 by the Epidermal Growth Factor Receptor (EGFR) promotes apoptosis in human cell lines<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref></sup>. In this pathway, EGFR phosphorylates STAT5 at unique sites distinct from those of the canonical pathway<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref></sup>.</p><p id="P6">There is growing evidence that cell-cell adhesion within epithelia, as mediated by molecules such as the transmembrane protein E-cadherin (E-cad)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref></sup>, contributes to the diversity of transcriptional outputs by modulating various signalling events, thereby influencing cell proliferation, differentiation and apoptosis <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref></sup>. For example, E-cad binds the receptor tyrosine kinase EGFR in both mammalian and fly cells, promoting both inhibition or activation of canonical EGFR signalling in a context-dependent manner<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref></sup>. E-cad has also been linked to STAT protein localisation and canonical signalling in <italic>Drosophila</italic> with STAT and E-cad co-immunoprecipitating and binding Par-3<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">21</xref></sup>. Finally, E-cad overexpression is sufficient to suppress position effect variegation in the developing <italic>Drosophila</italic> eye<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">22</xref></sup>, suggesting that E-cad may also be able to affect heterochromatinisation in vivo.</p><p id="P7">Recent evidence highlights that endocytosis can also change signalling pathway activities and outputs<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">23</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">26</xref></sup>. The internalisation of receptors from the plasma membrane into early endosomes creates intracellular signalling platforms, or “signalosomes”, with high concentrations of pathway components to facilitate signal transduction. As such, endocytosis leads to the compartmentalisation of signalling activities within physically distinct domains inside cells, enabling the specificity and robustness of the signalling response to be controlled<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">23</xref></sup>. Indeed, it is well established that both the canonical JAK/STAT and EGFR signalling pathways are regulated by endocytosis, with recent evidence indicating that endocytosis acts to both prolong signalling activity and quantitatively alter signalling outputs<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27">27</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">28</xref></sup>. Thus, endocytosis is essential for the expression of some, but not all, JAK/STAT pathway target genes. Similarly, endocytic trafficking plays a major role in the regulation of EGFR signalling activities<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">30</xref></sup>. Endocytosis can both enhance and inhibit EGFR signalling depending on the ligand concentration and specific endocytic pathway involved<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">30</xref></sup>. Relevant to this work, non-canonical STAT3 signalling downstream of EGFR is also regulated by endocytosis, with the PYK2 kinase being recruited to sustain this signalling on early endosomes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31">31</xref></sup>.</p><p id="P8">The regulation of signalling by cell-cell adhesion and endocytosis cannot be considered in isolation. In both mammalian and fly cells, E-cad is constantly endocytosed and then recycled in Rab11-positive recycling endosomes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32">32</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33">33</xref></sup>. The p120-catenin (p120ctn) protein is the key inhibitor of E-cad endocytosis in both mammalian and fly cells<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32">32</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34">34</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36">36</xref></sup>, and its overexpression is sufficient to prevent E-cad from being internalised<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35">35</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36">36</xref></sup>. Given this endocytic turnover, E-cad trafficking may directly affect signalling pathways. For example, E-cad and Par-3 co-endocytose together in the <italic>Drosophila</italic> embryonic epidermis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">20</xref></sup>, which opens the possibility that other interacting molecules – including STAT and EGFR – are also being co-internalised. Such cross-talk between cell-cell adhesion and endocytic processes potentially provides an additional level of signalling regulation, which can be investigated by forcing the intracellular accumulation of E-cad. In <italic>Drosophila</italic> wing imaginal discs, E-cad intracellular accumulation due to enhanced endocytosis induced by knocking down the Clathrin adaptor protein AP-1 is sufficient to increase the activity of c-Jun NH2-terminal kinase (JNK) signalling and cellular apoptosis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37">37</xref></sup>. This increase in apoptosis during larval stages leads to a ‘small wing’ phenotype in adults – a phenotype that was rescued by inhibiting E-cad endocytosis using p120ctn overexpression<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37">37</xref></sup>.</p><p id="P9">In this report, we use <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic> to elucidate the in vivo functions and regulation of non-canonical STAT signalling. This is facilitated by the low complexity of the fly genome, which allows us to manipulate each pathway without redundancies. Here we demonstrate that two non-canonical STAT activities – mediated via interactions with EGFR and HP1 – act concurrently and compete for STAT availability. We show that STAT and EGFR are co-endocytosed with E-cad, promoting non-canonical EGFR:STAT signalling. Elevated activity of this signalling caused by increased intracellular accumulation of E-cad, leads to the activation of the JNK pathway and apoptosis. At the same time, increased intracellular accumulation of E-cad also reduces HP1 localisation to the chromatin, suggesting that the activation of EGFR:STAT signalling outcompetes STAT from HP1. Altogether, our work provides evidence that the compartmentalisation of STAT by endocytosis determines the signalling outputs.</p></sec><sec id="S2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><p id="P10">To investigate the cellular and molecular functions of non-canonical STAT signalling, we utilised the <italic>Drosophila</italic> STAT92E variant with the substitution of the conserved tyrosine residue in position 704 for phenylalanine (Y704F). This variant cannot be phosphorylated by JAK and is therefore only able to function non-canonically<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38">38</xref></sup>. To gain an insight into potential transcriptional changes, we performed mRNA sequencing from larval wing discs either overexpressing a short hairpin RNA designed to act as a siRNA targeting HP1 (<italic>HP1</italic> RNAi), overexpressing STAT92E<sup>Y704F</sup> or expressing myr::GFP (control) for 24 hours (see Materials and Methods). Using a statistical cutoff adjusted p&lt;0.05 (see Materials and Methods) we found that downregulation of HP1 changed the expression of 1876 genes, whereas overexpression of STAT92E<sup>Y704F</sup> affected the expression of 4120 genes. Remarkably, 889 genes changed expression in both datasets (p = 2.4e-69, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1A</xref>), indicating that 47% of genes affected by <italic>HP1</italic> RNAi are also regulated by non-canonical STAT signalling. Moreover, the direction of change was consistent for 700 of these 889 genes (79%) – with genes being both upregulated or downregulated (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1B</xref>) and a strong correlation between both datasets (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1B</xref>, r<sup>2</sup> = 0.51, p &lt;2.2e-16).</p><p id="P11">The similarities in gene expression changes following STAT92E<sup>Y704F</sup> overexpression and HP1 knockdown made us hypothesise that non-canonical STAT92E exerts an effect that HP1 normally inhibits in epithelial wing disc cells. To investigate the nature of such a function we examined the localisation of STAT::GFP – STAT tagged via the insertion of GFP at its C-terminal end, expressed under the control of its genomic region and able to rescue the lethality and fertility of <italic>Stat92E</italic> mutant flies<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref></sup>. Here, we focused on the dorsal wing pouch area, where the activity of canonical JAK/STAT signalling is low/undetectable (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1C</xref>), as visualised with an activity reporter containing multiple canonical STAT92E DNA binding sites (<italic>10xSTAT92E</italic>-GFP)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39">39</xref></sup>. Control wing disc cells contained STAT::GFP in the cytosol and nucleus as previously described<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40">40</xref></sup>. Intriguingly, STAT::GFP was also detected at cell-cell boundaries, where it co-localised with E-cad (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1D-E</xref>).</p><p id="P12">As STAT92E and E-cad colocalise, and the Par-3 has previously been shown to bind to both<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">20</xref></sup>, we asked if the localisation of STAT::GFP at cell-cell boundaries depends on E-cad. To manipulate E-cad levels we overexpressed untagged full-length E-cad throughout the developing wing pouch<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41">41</xref></sup>. Such an overexpression moderately increased E-cad levels at cell-cell boundaries (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1D</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S1A</xref>) and substantially increased levels in the cytoplasm where E-cad also appears to be enriched within intracellular vesicles (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1F</xref>). This relative redistribution was reflected by the increase in the ratio of E-cad in the cytoplasm relative to cell-cell borders (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1G</xref>), We found that the localisation of STAT::GFP at cell-cell borders was largely lost upon E-cad overexpression (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1D, F-G</xref>), a change that was accompanied by an increased STAT::GFP ratio in the cytoplasm relative to cell borders (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1G</xref>), similar to that observed for E-cad. In addition, STAT::GFP and E-cad were colocalised in vesicles following E-cad overexpression (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1F</xref>). Based on these findings, we suggest a model whereby E-cad recruits STAT92E to cell-cell borders, potentially via Par-3, from where it also co-traffics with STAT92E in intracellular vesicles upon E-cad overexpression.</p><p id="P13">We next sought to determine how the relocalisation of STAT::GFP by E-cad overexpression might alter its signalling. We used the <italic>ptc-</italic>Gal4 driver expressed in cells along the anterior-posterior compartment boundary in the wing discs<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42">42</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43">43</xref></sup>, to allow the direct comparison of neighbouring cells with either normal or increased E-cad levels (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1C</xref>). Intriguingly, E-cad overexpression did not affect the expression of the canonical activity reporter <italic>10xSTAT92E</italic>-GFP in either the wing disc pouch or the dorsal hinge region (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1H</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S1B</xref>) – areas with low and high canonical JAK/STAT signalling respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1C</xref>). Therefore, if E-cad has any effects on STAT92E activity, then this is likely to be through non-canonical signalling pathways. As there are no reporters for non-canonical STAT92E signalling, we sought to analyse the mRNA transcriptome as a way to identify dysregulated pathways at the whole genome level. To this end, we overexpressed E-cad tagged with monomeric EOS fluorescent protein (E-cad::EOS)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R44">44</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R45">45</xref></sup>, a transgene that increases E-cad protein levels both at cell-cell borders and in the cytoplasm (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S2A-B</xref>). We found that overexpression of E-cad::EOS changed the expression of 1186 genes, of which 765 genes were also affected by STAT92E<sup>Y704F</sup> overexpression (p &lt; 8.552e-151, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2A</xref>). Therefore, nearly 65% of genes affected by E-cad overexpression, are also regulated by non-canonical STAT92E signalling. Out of these 765 genes, the direction of change was consistent for 738 genes (96.5%) with a correlation coefficient of r<sup>2</sup> = 0.85, p &lt;2.2e-16. As expected, comparing the E-cad dataset to our original data (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig 1A</xref>), also identified 421 loci (55% of those affected by both E-cad and STAT92E<sup>Y704F</sup>, p = 4.5e-177) which also changed their expression following HP1 knockdown (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2A</xref>).</p><p id="P14">Given the similarity in gene expression changes identified following E-cad overexpression and HP1 knockdown, we next asked if E-cad overexpression and its recruitment of STAT92E to intracellular vesicles interfere with the recruitment of STAT92E to HP1 and, thus, the chromatin stabilisation activity of non-canonical unphosphorylated STAT92E. To explore this, we tested how changing E-cad expression affects HP1 present in the nuclei of wing disc cells. We found that E-cad overexpression reduced the average HP1 levels, whereas E-cad knockdown had the opposite effect and increased them (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2B-C</xref>). These changes in HP1 levels were consistent with the changes in H3K9me3 staining – the modified Histone 3 bound by HP1 – in the same conditions (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S3A-B</xref>), a finding that aligns with the known HP1 and non-canonical STAT requirement for this histone mark<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R46">46</xref></sup>. These data are consistent with a model in which E-cad in the cytosol sequesters nuclear unphosphorylated STAT92E away from HP1, suggesting that STAT92E fulfils two distinct non-canonical functions – nuclear and cytosolic.</p><p id="P15">Given the established research linking EGFR with both E-cad and non-canonical STAT signalling<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">22</xref></sup>, we next investigated the potential role of EGFR in cytosolic, non-canonical STAT92E activity. We found that an EGFR::GFP fusion protein expressed from the endogenous EGFR locus colocalised with E-cad at both the junctions and intracellular vesicles in wing disc cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2D-F</xref>). Furthermore, overexpression of E-cad exerted a similar effect on EGFR::GFP to STAT::GFP, reducing levels of EGFR::GFP at cell-cell borders with a concomitant increase in the ratio of EGFR::GFP in the cytoplasm (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2D, G</xref>).</p><p id="P16">The colocalisation of both EGFR and STAT92E at cell-cell junctions and their similar redistribution following E-cad overexpression suggested that E-cad, EGFR and STAT92E interact in a single pathway. To explore this possibility, we focused on apoptosis as a functional output as both STAT activation by EGFR and intracellular E-cad accumulation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37">37</xref></sup>. Overexpression of both E-cad::EOS and untagged E-cad reduced the size of the resulting adult wing (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3A</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S4A</xref>) and increased the amount of apoptosis in wing discs as shown by an antibody detecting cleaved <italic>Drosophila</italic> death caspase-1 (Dcp-1, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3B</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S4B-C</xref>). Halving the gene dose of <italic>Egfr</italic> was sufficient to rescue the small adult wing size caused by E-cad overexpression and reduce the number of apoptotic cells detected in larval wing discs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3C-F</xref>, compare <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3A with 3C and Fig. 3B with 3D</xref>). To exclude the possibility that this rescue was due to a reduction in E-cad protein levels rather than downstream signalling by EGFR, we measured potential changes in E-cad levels in heterozygous <italic>Egfr</italic> individuals and following expression of a dominant-negative EGFR variant. Neither of these manipulations altered E-cad levels at cell-cell borders or the cytoplasm to cell-cell border ratio of E-cad (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3G-H</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S4D-E</xref>). Taken together, these findings are consistent with the hypothesis that E-cad and EGFR act in the same pathway to promote apoptosis and demonstrate that adult wing size is a reliable readout for levels of apoptosis in larval wing discs, in agreement with our previous work<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37">37</xref></sup>.</p><p id="P17">Using adult wing size as a proxy for levels of cell death in larval wing discs, we found that reducing the gene dose of <italic>stat92E</italic> also suppressed the adult wing phenotypes caused by E-cad overexpression (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4A-B</xref>), suggesting that STAT92E is also necessary for the induction of apoptosis in an E-cad overexpression background. We confirmed the specificity of EGFR and STAT92E in this phenotype by reducing the doses of genes involved in the Wnt and Hippo pathway previously shown to be regulated by E-cad<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R47">47</xref></sup>. Targeting these pathways did not affect the adult wing size phenotype (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S5A-B</xref>). In agreement with the hypothesis that EGFR acts via STAT92E to promote apoptosis, we did not see any changes in the Ras/MAPK pathway activity following manipulation of E-cad levels as visualised by antibodies against phosphorylated ERK (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S4F-G</xref>). Moreover, reducing the gene dose of <italic>hopscotch</italic> (<italic>hop</italic>) – the gene encoding the single <italic>Drosophila</italic> JAK protein – did not modulate adult wing size following E-cad overexpression (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S5A-B</xref>), further supporting our findings that E-cad overexpression does not affect the canonical JAK/STAT signalling. To test the hypothesis that there are two competing non-canonical STAT92E pathways – nuclear and in the cytoplasm, we downregulated HP1 using RNAi, producing a dose-dependent reduced adult wing size phenotype similar to those of E-cad overexpression (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4C-D</xref>).</p><p id="P18">Next, we tested the contribution of E-cad endocytosis to cell death given that elevated E-cad endocytosis that led to E-cad intracellular accumulation was required to induce apoptosis following AP-1 knockdown<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37">37</xref></sup>. Consistent with this, we found that co-overexpression of p120-catenin – a treatment previously shown to block E-cad endocytosis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35">35</xref></sup> – partly rescued the adult wing size phenotype caused by E-cad overexpression (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5A-B</xref>). Taken together with the observed colocalisation of E-cad with STAT92E and EGFR on intracellular vesicles (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1F</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2E</xref>), we suggest that co-endocytosis of E-cad with STAT92E and EGFR promotes the activation of the EGFR:STAT signalling and apoptosis.</p><p id="P19">Finally, we asked if the changes in gene expression observed upon overexpression of E-cad and STAT92<sup>EY704F</sup> could represent ‘effector genes’ whose changed expression might mediate the cell death phenotype caused by E-cad overexpression. In particular, we found that genes involved in the JNK cascade were over-enriched in the group of transcripts positively regulated by E-cad and STAT92E<sup>Y704F</sup> overexpression (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2A</xref>, p = 0.006) with six genes out of 82 known components of the <italic>Drosophila</italic> JNK pathway increased in both datasets, 23 in the STAT92E and 9 in the E-cad datasets. Of the six genes – <italic>mitogen-activated protein kinase kinase kinase</italic> (<italic>Mekk1</italic>), <italic>Plenty of SH3s</italic> (<italic>POSH</italic>), <italic>spoonbill</italic> (<italic>spoon</italic>), <italic>Growth arrest and DNA damage-inducible 45</italic> (<italic>Gadd45</italic>), <italic>Autophagy-related 9</italic> (<italic>Atg9</italic>), and <italic>fiery mountain</italic> (<italic>fmt</italic>) – five have been described as positive regulators of JNK signalling. To examine whether increased JNK pathway activity, as driven by the expression of JNK pathway regulators, could explain increased apoptosis, we tested the <italic>POSH</italic> gene – whose ectopic expression has previously been shown to be sufficient for JNK activation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R48">48</xref></sup>. Indeed, reducing the gene dose of <italic>POSH</italic> in an E-cad overexpressing background rescued the adult wing phenotype (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5C-D</xref>), suggesting that JNK pathway activity is necessary for apoptosis induction by elevated E-cad and EGFR:STAT signalling.</p></sec><sec id="S3" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p id="P20">In this work, we provide novel, in vivo evidence identifying the biological functions of non-canonical STAT92E activity in <italic>Drosophila</italic> wing development. We demonstrate that these non-canonical roles depend on E-cad, EGFR and JNK-pathway activation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref>) – the first time the trans-membrane adhesion protein E-cad has been demonstrated to play a part in the non-canonical STAT activities. The activation of the non-canonical STAT92E pathway is most clearly demonstrated by the striking overlap in transcriptional targets mediated by STAT92E<sup>Y704F</sup> and E-cad overexpression as well as by the knockdown of HP1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig 1A</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2A</xref>), with the co-localisation of STAT92E and EGFR with E-cad supporting a model in which direct interactions play a role in this novel pathway. In addition, we demonstrate the involvement of EGFR and STAT92E in mediating the small wing size phenotype following E-cad overexpression and endocytosis. Finally, we show that this small wing phenotype is likely mediated by the transcriptional control of JNK-pathway regulators which activate signalling to induce apoptosis. While not considered together, STAT-mediated effects downstream of EGFR signalling<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref></sup>, physical interactions between E-cad and STAT92E<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">21</xref></sup> and the interaction between unphosphorylated STAT92E and HP1 in the regulation of heterochromatinisation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R49">49</xref></sup> have been individually described and support the findings presented here.</p><p id="P21">One key aspect of our study is the role of endocytic trafficking of E-cad, STAT92E and EGFR. While the nature of the E-cad, EGFR and STAT92E-containing vesicles and their fate are yet to be elucidated in vivo, previous reports have demonstrated the importance of endocytosis for both STAT92E<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27">27</xref></sup> and E-cad<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32">32</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37">37</xref></sup> functions. We hypothesise that these vesicles are destined for lysosomal degradation, which likely explains the apparent decrease in EGFR and STAT92E at the plasma membrane upon E-cad overexpression (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1D</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2D</xref>). In addition, the requirement for E-cad endocytosis indicates that specific endocytic compartments may facilitate the EGFR:STAT signalling activity. For example, the tyrosine kinase PYK2 is phosphorylated and recruited to early endosomes by EGFR, where it colocalises with EGFR and sustains EGFR:STAT3 signalling in human mammary MCF10A and MDA-MB-468 cells<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31">31</xref></sup>. As such, regulation of an E-cad:EGFR:STAT92E complex within a particular endocytic compartment would not be an exception. Indeed, the assembly of specific signalling complexes on early endosomes to quantitatively and qualitatively alter signalling outputs is an established paradigm<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R50">50</xref></sup>. Furthermore, endocytosis appears to be an important regulator of not only non-canonical STAT signalling as demonstrated in this work, but also canonical JAK/STAT signalling<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">25</xref></sup>. In the latter case, the activated receptor needs to reach early endosomes to activate the <italic>10xSTAT92E</italic>-Luciferase activity reporter, which utilises the same promoter as the <italic>10xSTAT92</italic>-GFP used in this work. In contrast, the expression of other pathway targets – such as <italic>socs36E</italic> mRNA – was not achieved at early endosomes but rather required further progression of trafficking to late endosomes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">25</xref></sup>. Taken together, these findings support the existence of specialised endosomes, or ‘signalosomes’ that enable distinct signalling activities via both canonical and non-canonical pathways</p><p id="P22">The outcome of many signalling pathways is a change in gene expression. In this work, we identified the extensive overlap in the altered gene expression patterns elicited by manipulations of STAT92E, E-cad and HP1 levels. While we have deposited these data sets in publicly available databases (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/bioproject/1185032">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/bioproject/1185032</ext-link>) to allow future analysis, in this report we have focused specifically on genes encoding components of the JNK pathway. Taken together with the previous report linking elevated intracellular E-cad levels to activation of the JNK pathway<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37">37</xref></sup>, the upregulation of pathway activators such as <italic>POSH</italic> and the rescue of the small wing phenotype support the view that the E-cad:EGFR:STAT92E signalling promotes apoptosis via JNK pathway activity induction (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref>). Additionally, we observed a much greater number of genes changing their expression following modulation of non-canonical STAT or HP1 levels than has been reported in previous experiments<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref></sup>. While we observed 4120 genes with altered expression upon STAT92E<sup>Y704F</sup> overexpression (31.8% of all protein-encoding genes), only 162 genes (0.32% of 47,324 transcripts on the Illumina Human gene chip) displayed altered expression due to overexpression of non-canonical STAT5A<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref></sup>. Such a discrepancy could be due to differences in overexpression levels, compensation by other STATs in mammalian cells or specific cell types used. It is worth noting that the previous work used DLD-1 cells, which have very low basal levels of EGFR<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R51">51</xref></sup>, so are likely to have only marginal levels of EGFR-mediated non-canonical STAT activity. Therefore, our data suggest that the non-canonical STAT92E signalling has a major role in the gene expression landscape in epithelial cells in <italic>Drosophila</italic>, likely through interactions with both EGFR and HP1.</p><p id="P23">Three lines of evidence suggest that non-canonical STAT92E activities compete for STAT92E availability in wing disc cells. For example, modulations of E-cad levels were sufficient to change HP1 present in nuclei (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2B-C</xref>), suggesting that E-cad is able to outcompete STAT92E from HP1 complexes. Consistent with this, the E-cad-induced wing size phenotype was suppressed by reducing STAT92E levels (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4A-B</xref>), indicating that STAT92E is rate-limiting for triggering apoptosis in this tissue. A similar wing size phenotype was achieved by downregulating HP1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4C-D</xref>), which supports a model where HP1 outcompetes STAT92E from EGFR. However, overexpression of E-cad did not alter canonical STAT92E signalling as assessed by the transcriptional reporter <italic>10xSTAT92E-</italic>GFP (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1C</xref>). Therefore, we propose that the canonical JAK/STAT92E signalling is dominant over two other modalities and outcompete STAT92E from both HP1 and EGFR. This view is supported by the observation that the gain-of-function <italic>Hopscotch</italic> mutation inhibits heterochromatin formation and reduces HP1:STAT association<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R52">52</xref></sup>.</p><p id="P24">We propose that the apoptosis induced by E-cad endocytosis and EGFR:STAT92E activation provides a mechanism for the elimination of potential cancer cells undergoing cell-cell adhesion disassembly during epithelial-to-mesenchymal transitions and, thus, is likely to play an important tumour-suppressive role. While the disassembly of E-cad cell-cell adhesion is a known trigger of apoptosis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R53">53</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R55">55</xref></sup>, the molecular basis of this induction was not previously known. In particular, the link between E-cad endocytosis and apoptosis was not examined. At the same time, there must be mechanisms in place that inhibit undesired apoptosis induction. For example, epithelial-to-mesenchymal transitions that occur during midgut formation in early <italic>Drosophila</italic> embryos require adhesion disassembly and E-cad endocytosis but are not accompanied by cell death<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R56">56</xref></sup>. Discovering these inhibitory mechanisms is an important next step as they are likely to present oncogenic pathways that induce apoptosis resistance and help cancer cells avoid death.</p><p id="P25">In summary, we report on two competing non-canonical STAT92E pathways which concurrently act in the epithelial cells of <italic>Drosophila</italic> wing imaginal discs. One pathway is linked to HP-1 and stabilises heterochromatin, while the other is dependent on EGFR to promote apoptosis via the activation of JNK pathway signalling and requires E-cad endocytosis for its activation. Given the high levels of evolutionary conservation of all proteins involved, and interactions already shown to be mirrored in vertebrate systems, we suggest that the induction of apoptosis by E-cad:EGFR:STAT complexes is likely to represent an important tumour suppressor in human epithelia.</p></sec><sec id="S4"><title>Resources availability</title><p id="P26"><bold>Lead contact</bold>: Natalia A. Bulgakova <email>n.bulgakova@qmul.ac.uk</email></p><p id="P27"><bold>Materials availability</bold>: All materials such as fly lines are available from repositories such as the Bloomington Drosophila Stock Centre or by request from the lead contact.</p></sec><sec id="S5" sec-type="methods" specific-use="web-only"><title>STAR methods</title><sec id="S6"><title>Key resources table</title><table-wrap id="T1" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"><table frame="box" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" style="border-top: 1.5px solid #000000;border-bottom: 1.5px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000;border-left: 1px solid #000000">REAGENT or RESOURCE</th><th valign="top" align="left" style="border-top: 1.5px solid #000000;border-bottom: 1.5px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000">SOURCE</th><th valign="top" align="left" style="border-top: 1.5px solid #000000;border-bottom: 1.5px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000">IDENTIFIER</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="3" style="border-left: 1px solid #000000;border-bottom: 1.5px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000"><bold>Antibodies</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-right: 1px solid #000000;border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-left: 1px solid #000000">Rat anti–E-cad 1:200</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000">Developmental Studies Hybridoma Bank</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000">DSHB #DCAD2</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-right: 1px solid #000000;border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-left: 1px solid #000000">Rabbit anti-cleaved Dcp-1 (asp216) 1:100</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000">Cell Signaling Technology</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000">Cat #9578s</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-right: 1px solid #000000;border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-left: 1px solid #000000">Mouse anti-HP-1 (Su(var)205) 1:50</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000">Developmental Studies Hybridoma Bank</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000">DSHB #C1A9</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-right: 1px solid #000000;border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-left: 1px solid #000000">Rabbit anti-H3K9me3 1:500</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000">Active Motif</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000">Cat #39062</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-right: 1px solid #000000;border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-left: 1px solid #000000">Donkey anti-rat Alexa Fluor 488 (1:300)</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000">Jackson ImmunoResearch</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000">Cat #712-545-153</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-right: 1px solid #000000;border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-left: 1px solid #000000">Donkey anti-rat Alexa Fluor 647 (1:300)</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000">Jackson ImmunoResearch</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000">Cat #712-605-153</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-right: 1px solid #000000;border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-left: 1px solid #000000">Donkey anti-rabbit Alexa Fluor 647 (1:300)</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000">Jackson ImmunoResearch</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000">Cat #711-605-152</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-right: 1px solid #000000;border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-left: 1px solid #000000">Donkey anti-mouse Alexa Fluor 647 (1:300)</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000">Jackson ImmunoResearch</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000">Cat #715-605-151</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="3" style="border-left: 1px solid #000000;border-bottom: 1.5px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000"><bold>Chemicals, peptides, and recombinant proteins</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-right: 1px solid #000000;border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-left: 1px solid #000000">PBS</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000">Sigma-Aldrich</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000">Cat #P4417-50TAB</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-right: 1px solid #000000;border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-left: 1px solid #000000">Formaldehyde solution (40%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000">Sigma-Aldrich</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000">Cat #F8775</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-right: 1px solid #000000;border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-left: 1px solid #000000">Triton X-100</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000">Thermo Fisher</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000">Cat #A16046</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-right: 1px solid #000000;border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-left: 1px solid #000000">BSA</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000">New England Biolabs</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000">Cat #B9000S</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-right: 1px solid #000000;border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-left: 1px solid #000000">Vectashield mounting media</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000">Vector Labs</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000">Cat #H-1000</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-left: 1px solid #000000;border-bottom: 1.5px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000">Canada Balsam</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1.5px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000">Sigma-Aldrich</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1.5px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000">Cat#C1795-25ML</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="3" style="border-left: 1px solid #000000;border-bottom: 1.5px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000"><bold>Deposited data</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-right: 1px solid #000000;border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-left: 1px solid #000000">RNA sequencing data</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/bioproject/1185032">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/bioproject/1185032</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000">PRJNA1185032</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-right: 1px solid #000000;border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-left: 1px solid #000000">Microscopy data</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://qmro.qmul.ac.uk/xmlui/handle/123456789/101582">https://qmro.qmul.ac.uk/xmlui/handle/123456789/101582</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="3" style="border-left: 1px solid #000000;border-bottom: 1.5px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000"><bold>Experimental models: Organisms/strains</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-right: 1px solid #000000;border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-left: 1px solid #000000"><italic>MS1096</italic>-Gal4;;</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000">Bloomington Drosophila Stock Center</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000">BDSC #8860;</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-right: 1px solid #000000;border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-left: 1px solid #000000">;;<italic>αTub84B</italic>-Gal80<sup>TS</sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000">Bloomington Drosophila Stock Center</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000"><styled-content style="color:#333333">BDSC</styled-content> #7017</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-right: 1px solid #000000;border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-left: 1px solid #000000">;<italic>patched</italic>-Gal4;</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000">Bloomington Drosophila Stock Center</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000"><styled-content style="color:#333333">BDSC</styled-content> #2017</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-right: 1px solid #000000;border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-left: 1px solid #000000">;;<italic>Act5C-</italic>Gal4</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000">Bloomington Drosophila Stock Center</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000"><styled-content style="color:#333333">BDSC</styled-content> #3954</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-right: 1px solid #000000;border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-left: 1px solid #000000">;;<italic>UAS</italic>-E-cad∷EOS/TM6</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000">from ref<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R45">45</xref></sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000;Color: #333333">N/A</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-right: 1px solid #000000;border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-left: 1px solid #000000">;;<italic>UAS</italic>-E-cad</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000">Bloomington Drosophila Stock Center</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000"><styled-content style="color:#333333">BDSC</styled-content> #65589</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-right: 1px solid #000000;border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-left: 1px solid #000000">;;<italic>UAS</italic>-p120catenin</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000">from ref<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36">36</xref></sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000;Color: #333333">N/A</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-right: 1px solid #000000;border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-left: 1px solid #000000">;<italic>UAS</italic>-EGFR-DN;<italic>UAS</italic>-EGFR-DN</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000">Bloomington Drosophila Stock Center</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000"><styled-content style="color:#333333">BDSC</styled-content> #5364</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-right: 1px solid #000000;border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-left: 1px solid #000000">;;<italic>UAS-shg</italic> RNAi</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000">Vienna Drosophila Resource Center</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000;Color: #333333">VDRC v27082</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-right: 1px solid #000000;border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-left: 1px solid #000000">;;<italic>UAS-AP-1μ</italic> RNAi</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000">Bloomington Drosophila Stock Center</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000"><styled-content style="color:#333333">BDSC</styled-content> #27534</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-right: 1px solid #000000;border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-left: 1px solid #000000">;;<italic>UAS-Ap-1γ</italic> RNAi</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000">Bloomington Drosophila Stock Center</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000"><styled-content style="color:#333333">BDSC</styled-content> #27533</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-right: 1px solid #000000;border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-left: 1px solid #000000">;;<italic>UAS-HP-1</italic> RNAi</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000">Bloomington Drosophila Stock Center</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000"><styled-content style="color:#333333">BDSC</styled-content> #33400</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-right: 1px solid #000000;border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-left: 1px solid #000000">;;<italic>UAS-</italic>STAT92E<sup>Y704F</sup>∷GFP</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000">from ref<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38">38</xref></sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000;Color: #333333">N/A</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-right: 1px solid #000000;border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-left: 1px solid #000000">;;<italic>UAS</italic>-myr∷GFP</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000">Bloomington Drosophila Stock Center</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000"><styled-content style="color:#333333">BDSC</styled-content> #58720</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-right: 1px solid #000000;border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-left: 1px solid #000000">;;<italic>UAS</italic>-CD8∷Cherry</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000">Bloomington Drosophila Stock Center</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000;Color: #333333">BDSC #27392</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-right: 1px solid #000000;border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-left: 1px solid #000000">;<italic>Egfr</italic><sup><italic>f2</italic></sup> / CyO;</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000">Bloomington Drosophila Stock Center</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000;Color: #333333">BDSC #2768</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-right: 1px solid #000000;border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-left: 1px solid #000000">;;<italic>stat92E</italic><sup><italic>397</italic></sup> / <italic>TM3</italic></td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000">from ref<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R57">57</xref></sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000;Color: #333333">N/A</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-right: 1px solid #000000;border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-left: 1px solid #000000">;<italic>wg</italic><sup><italic>l-17</italic></sup> / CyO;</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000">Bloomington Drosophila Stock Center</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000;Color: #333333">BDSC #2980</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-right: 1px solid #000000;border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-left: 1px solid #000000">;<italic>arr</italic><sup><italic>2</italic></sup> / CyO;</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000">Bloomington Drosophila Stock Center</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000;Color: #333333">BDSC #3087</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-right: 1px solid #000000;border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-left: 1px solid #000000">;<italic>hpo</italic><sup><italic>KS240</italic></sup> / CyO;</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000">Bloomington Drosophila Stock Center</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000;Color: #333333">BDSC #25085</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-right: 1px solid #000000;border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-left: 1px solid #000000">;;<italic>wts</italic><sup><italic>x1</italic></sup> / TM6B</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000">Bloomington Drosophila Stock Center</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000;Color: #333333">BDSC #44251</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-right: 1px solid #000000;border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-left: 1px solid #000000"><italic>hop</italic><sup><italic>2</italic></sup> / FM7a;;</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000">Bloomington Drosophila Stock Center</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000;Color: #333333">BDSC #6032</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-right: 1px solid #000000;border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-left: 1px solid #000000">;<italic>POSH</italic><sup><italic>74</italic></sup>;</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000">Bloomington Drosophila Stock Center</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000;Color: #333333">BDSC #58808</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-right: 1px solid #000000;border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-left: 1px solid #000000">;;<italic>10xStat92E</italic>-GFP / TM6</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000">Bloomington Drosophila Stock Center</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000;Color: #333333">BDSC #26200</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-right: 1px solid #000000;border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-left: 1px solid #000000">;EGFR∷sfGFP;</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000">Bloomington Drosophila Stock Center</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000;Color: #333333">BDSC #92329</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-right: 1px solid #000000;border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-left: 1px solid #000000">;STAT92E∷GFP;</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000">Bloomington Drosophila Stock Center</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000;Color: #333333">BDSC #38670</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-right: 1px solid #000000;border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-left: 1px solid #000000">;<italic>shg</italic>-E-cadherin∷GFP;</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000">Bloomington Drosophila Stock Center</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000;Color: #333333">BDSC #60584</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-left: 1px solid #000000;border-bottom: 1.5px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000">;<italic>Ubi-p63E</italic>-E-cadherin∷GFP;</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1.5px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000">Kyoto Stock Center</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1.5px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000;Color: #333333">Kyoto #109007</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="3" style="border-left: 1px solid #000000;border-bottom: 1.5px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000"><bold>Software and algorithm</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-right: 1px solid #000000;border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-left: 1px solid #000000">Custom MATLAB scripts</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/nbul/">https://github.com/nbul/</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000">N/A</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-right: 1px solid #000000;border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-left: 1px solid #000000">Fiji (ImageJ)</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://fiji.sc/">https://fiji.sc/</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000">N/A</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-right: 1px solid #000000;border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-left: 1px solid #000000">FV10-ASW</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000">Olympus</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000">N/A</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-right: 1px solid #000000;border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-left: 1px solid #000000">LAS X</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000">Leica</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000">N/A</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-right: 1px solid #000000;border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-left: 1px solid #000000">R and R Studio</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://posit.co/download/rstudio-desktop/">https://posit.co/download/rstudio-desktop/</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000">N/A</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-right: 1px solid #000000;border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-left: 1px solid #000000">Illustrator 20</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000">Adobe</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000">N/A</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-right: 1px solid #000000;border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-left: 1px solid #000000">Gimp</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.gimp.org/">https://www.gimp.org/</ext-link></td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000">N/A</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-left: 1px solid #000000;border-bottom: 1.5px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000">Microsoft Office 365</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1.5px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000">Microsoft</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1.5px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000">N/A</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="3" style="border-left: 1px solid #000000;border-bottom: 1.5px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000"><bold>Other</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-right: 1px solid #000000;border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-left: 1px solid #000000">FV1000</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000">Olympus</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000">N/A</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-right: 1px solid #000000;border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-left: 1px solid #000000">Stellaris 8</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000">Leica</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000">N/A</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-right: 1px solid #000000;border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-left: 1px solid #000000">DMRA2</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000">Leica</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000">N/A</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-left: 1px solid #000000;border-bottom: 1.5px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000">Axioskop 2 MOT</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1.5px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000">Zeiss</td><td valign="top" align="left" style="border-bottom: 1.5px solid #000000;border-right: 1px solid #000000">N/A</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec id="S7"><title>Fly stocks and husbandry</title><p id="P28"><italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic> flies were raised on standard cornmeal/agar/molasses media at 25°C unless otherwise specified. We used the UAS/Gal4/Gal80 system<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43">43</xref></sup> for the overexpression and knockdown experiments, with <italic>MS1096</italic>-Gal4 (Bloomington 8860), <italic>Act5C</italic>-GAL4 <italic>αTub84B</italic>-Gal80<sup>TS</sup> (recombined Bloomington 3954 and 7017) and <italic>patched</italic>-Gal4 (<italic>ptc</italic>-Gal4) <italic>αTub84B</italic>-Gal80<sup>TS</sup> (Bloomington 2017 and 701) driver lines. The following UAS lines were used: <italic>UAS</italic>-E-cad::EOS<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R45">45</xref></sup>, <italic>UAS</italic>-E-cad (E-cad-65, Bloomington 65589), UAS-p120catenin<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36">36</xref></sup>, <italic>UAS</italic>-EGFR-DN (Bloomington 5364), <italic>UAS</italic>-<italic>shg</italic> RNAi (E-cad-RNAi, VDRC v27082), <italic>UAS-AP-1μ</italic> RNAi (Bloomington 27534), <italic>UAS</italic>-Ap-1γ RNAi (Bloomington 27533), <italic>UAS-HP1</italic> RNAi (Bloomington 33400), and <italic>UAS</italic>-STAT92E<sup>Y704F 38</sup>. The Gal4:UAS ratio was kept constant within each experimental data set using additional copies of <italic>UAS</italic>-CD8::Cherry (Bloomington 27392) or <italic>UAS</italic>-myristoylated::GFP (myr::GFP, Bloomington 58720). The following stocks with mutant alleles were used: <italic>Egfr</italic><sup><italic>f2</italic></sup>/CyO (Bloomington 2768), <italic>stat92E</italic><sup><italic>397</italic></sup>/TM3<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31">31</xref></sup>, <italic>wg</italic><sup><italic>l-</italic>57</sup>/CyO (Bloomington 2980), <italic>arr</italic><sup><italic>2</italic></sup>/CyO (Bloomington 3087), <italic>hpo</italic><sup><italic>KS240</italic></sup>/CyO (Bloomington 25085), <italic>wts</italic><sup><italic>x1</italic></sup>/TM6B (Bloomington 44251), <italic>hop</italic><sup><italic>2</italic></sup>/FM7a (Bloomington 6032), and <italic>POSH</italic><sup><italic>74</italic></sup> (Bloomington 58808). Finally, the following stocks with transgenes encoding for fluorescently tagged proteins were used: <italic>shg</italic>::E-cadherin::GFP (Bloomington 60584), <italic>ubi</italic>-E-cad::GFP (Kyoto Stock Center Kyoto 109007), EGFR::sfGFP (EGFR::GFP, Bloomington 92329), and STAT::GFP (Bloomington 38670). <italic>10xStat92E</italic>-GFP (Bloomington 26200) was used to monitor the canonical JAK/STAT activity. All experiments and relevant controls were done in parallel.</p></sec><sec id="S8"><title>Dissections and immunostaining</title><p id="P29">Wandering third instar larvae were dissected at 6 days after egg laying at 25°C. When <italic>MS1096</italic>-Gal4 was used, only male larvae were selected to ensure the same levels of Gal4 expression across all animals. Cuticles with attached imaginal discs were fixed for 20 min with 4% formaldehyde (Sigma; F8775) in PBS (phosphate buffer saline; Sigma-Aldrich; P4417) at room temperature, washed with PBS with 0.1% Triton X-100 (Thermo Fisher; A16046; hereafter PBST), and incubated with 1% bovine serum albumin (BSA; New England Biolabs; B9000S) in PBST for 1 hour at room temperature. Cuticles were incubated with primary antibodies and 1% BSA in PBST overnight at 4°C, washed in PBST, incubated for 2 hours with secondary antibodies and 1% BSA in PBST, and washed in PBST again. All antibodies and their concentrations are listed in Table 1. Finally, discs were separated from the cuticles and mounted in Vectashield (Vector Labs; H-1000). Only one disc per larvae was taken at this stage. For samples not requiring immunostaining, discs were immediately mounted following fixation and one round of washing in PBST.</p></sec><sec id="S9"><title>Microscopy</title><sec id="S10"><title>Confocal microscopy</title><p id="P30">Most confocal microscopy experiments except colocalisation analyses were done using an upright Olympus FV1000 confocal microscope with either 60×/1.40 NA (fluorescence intensity and colocalisation) or 20×/0.75 NA (apoptosis) objectives. Images for STAT92E::GFP localisation were obtained using an inverted Leica Stellaris 8 confocal microscope with a 63x/1.40 NA objective. For fluorescence intensity and colocalisation, images were taken in the dorsal region of the wing disc pouch (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1C</xref>). For imaging with x60 and x63 objectives, a single z-stack of eight slices (localisation to cell-cell borders and vesicles) or 45 slices (localisation in the nucleus) spaced by 0.38 μm was acquired for each disc capturing the complete span of the cell-cell junctions. For imaging with the x20 objective, a z-stack of 15 slices spaced by 1 μm spacing was acquired capturing the complete wing disc. All the images were at 16-bit depth in Olympus or Leica binary image format.</p></sec><sec id="S11"><title>Adult wing imaging</title><p id="P31">Flies were kept overnight at -20°C, and the wings were dissected and then mounted in Canada Balsam (Sigma; C1795-25ML). Wings were imaged using a Zeiss Axioskop 2 MOT microscope or a Leica DMRA2 upright microscope with a Lumenera Infinity 5-5 camera. For both microscopes, x5 objectives were used.</p></sec></sec><sec id="S12"><title>RNA sequencing</title><p id="P32">Individuals were raised at 17°C inactivating the <italic>Act5C-Gal4</italic> tool using temperature-sensitive tubGal80 until they reached the third instar larval stage (13 days). Larvae were then moved to 29°C for 24 hours before harvesting. RNA was extracted from wing discs dissected on ice using the NucleoSpin RNA XS Kit (Macherey-Nagel; 740902.50). Samples were dissolved in ddH<sub>2</sub>O and stored at -80°C before delivery to Novogene. Input quantities were measured with Qubit<bold>®</bold> Fluorometer to pre-check that they all met the company’s specifications. For each of the four genotypes (<italic>UAS</italic>-myr::GFP, <italic>UAS</italic>-E-cad::EOS, <italic>UAS</italic>-STAT92E<sup>Y704F</sup>::GFP and <italic>UAS</italic>-<italic>HP1</italic> RNAi), three independent biological replicates were extracted. cDNA library sequencing was performed by Novogene, Cambridge, UK. The twelve samples displayed an Effective rate of approx. 99%.</p></sec><sec id="S13"><title>Data analysis</title><sec id="S14"><title>Fluorescence levels at cell borders and in the cytoplasm</title><p id="P33">Average fluorescence intensity was measured on average projections of z-stacks with native GFP fluorescence signal. To classify the signal in images into cell boundaries and the cytoplasm, we created binary masks from average projections of z-stacks with E-cad immunostaining or native fluorescence of E-cad::GFP using the Tissue Analyser plugin in Fiji<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R58">58</xref></sup>. These binary masks were used to measure the fluorescence intensity of average projections using our in-house MATLAB script (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/nbul/Intensity/TotalMean/">https://github.com/nbul/Intensity/TotalMean/</ext-link>). In short, each cell was identified from the mask as an individual object. The boundary of each object was dilated using a diamond-shaped morphological structural element of size 3 to encompass the XY spread of the boundary signal. The mean and total (sum of all pixel intensities) intensities of the dilated boundary (membrane signal) and the object with subtracted boundary (cytoplasm) were calculated. All the values were averaged to produce single values per wing disc, thus testing biological replicates and excluding a variable contribution of individual discs to the result due to differences in cell numbers.</p></sec><sec id="S15"><title>Adult wing size</title><p id="P34">The size of adult wings was measured by manually tracing the wing outlines using the Freehand selection tool in Fiji.</p></sec><sec id="S16"><title>Levels of cleaved Dcp-1</title><p id="P35">The maximum intensity projections with immunostaining for cleaved Dcp-1 were analysed in Fiji. First, the signal was blurred using the Smooth filter that replaces each pixel with the average of its 3x3 neighbourhood. The background intensity was manually measured using a circular region of interest (ROI) outside apoptotic cells. The brightness of 16-bit images was adjusted between 55 (minimum) and 10 x background intensity (maximum) to compensate for potential differences in the staining. The resulting images were thresholded with the minimum set to 15000. The wing pouch area was traced in maximum projections of z-stacks with E-cad immunostaining signal using the Freehand selection tools. The selection was copied over to the threshold images of the cleaved Dcp-1 signal and analysed using the Analyze Particles Tool with the minimum size of a particle limited to 4 pixels. The fraction of area covered by particles within the selection was used as the apoptosis level.</p></sec><sec id="S17"><title>Protein colocalisation</title><p id="P36">For the colocalisation of STAT::GFP with E-cad signal visualised by antibody, we employed the colocalization plug-in Coloc 2 in Fiji (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://imagej.net/Coloc2">https://imagej.net/Coloc2</ext-link>) and performed the analysis section by section. We selected Manders’s colocalization coefficients (MCC) as more informative for probes distributed to more than one compartment than Pearson’s correlation coefficients<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R59">59</xref></sup>.</p><p id="P37">For colocalization of EGFR::GFP with E-cad in the cytoplasm, we analyzed the images section by section, but with an in-house MATLAB script (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/nbul/Localization">https://github.com/nbul/Localization</ext-link>). This script followed the same principle to obtain MCCdiff values as the Coloc 2 plug-in but enabled a manual selection of a threshold method. Such selection is required as the bright signal of E-cad at cell borders limits its detection in the cytoplasm using standard threshold methods. The E-cad signal at cell-cell borders was excluded from the analysis, and the resulting MCCdiff values accounted for the intracellular signal only.</p></sec><sec id="S18"><title>Nuclear protein levels</title><p id="P38">The z-stacks were cropped in Fiji to contain only cells expressing CD8, untagged E-cad or E-cad RNAi. Average projections were made using 4 consecutive z-sections that capture the signal around nuclear centres.</p><p id="P39">For the HP1 signal, projections from images of control wing discs expressing CD8 were segmented using the cyto3 model CellPose 3.0<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R60">60</xref></sup>. The segmentation errors were manually corrected and the resulting masks were used to re-train the model. The new model was validated on images from the CD8 control wing discs and then used to segment nuclei in wing discs with E-cad overexpression and knockdown. Each image segmentation was manually verified and errors were further corrected as needed. The generated masks were used to obtain the nuclei mean intensities on a nucleus-by-nucleus basis with an in-house MATLAB script.</p><p id="P40">For H3K9me3, the projections were analysed using an in-house MATLAB script. First, the projections were filtered using a 2-D Gaussian smoothing kernel with a standard deviation of 2. The images were binarised using an adaptive threshold that is calculated using local first-order image statistics around each pixel. This created masks with H3K9me3 puncta as individual objects. Any objects smaller than 200 px or touching image borders were removed. The above values were empirically determined from a series of tests on images of all three genotypes and determining the most efficient combination. The masks were then used to obtain the puncta mean intensities on a punctum-by-punctum basis with an in-house MATLAB script.</p><p id="P41">The CellPose model HP1_wing and relevant MATLAB scripts are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/nbul/Intensity/tree/master/HP1">https://github.com/nbul/Intensity/tree/master/HP1</ext-link>.</p></sec><sec id="S19"><title>10xSTAT-GFP levels</title><p id="P42">Average fluorescence intensity was measured on average projections of z-stacks of 15 z-sections spaced by 1 μm and spanning the whole depth of the wing disc with native GFP fluorescence signal. A square 50x50 px ROI was manually positioned over overexpressing or control regions using the CD8::mCherry native fluorescence (control) or E-cad signal (E-cad overexpression) in the wing pouch area (as indicated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1C</xref>) or notum.</p></sec><sec id="S20"><title>RNA sequencing: Alignment to the reference genome</title><p id="P43">RNA-seq libraries were sequenced using Illumina HiSeq. Reads were aligned to the dm6 assembly of the <italic>D. melanogaster</italic> genome using BWA v. 0.7.7<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R61">61</xref></sup> with default settings (BWA-backtrack algorithm). The SAMtools v. 0.1.19 ‘view’ utility was used to convert the alignments to BAM format.</p></sec><sec id="S21"><title>RNA sequencing: differential expression analyses for genes</title><p id="P44">We built an exon model based on Ensembl Gene database gene annotation. Tag counts for each gene were extracted from BAM alignment files using the HTSeq method working in union mode and implemented in R. These values were used to build an expression matrix. The differential gene expression between samples was tested using the DESeq2 package<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R62">62</xref></sup>. Reads per kilobase of exon model per million mapped reads (RPKM) normalised expression values were generated using the “median ratio method” (Equation 5 in <sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R63">63</xref></sup>). We used false discovery rate (FDR)-adjusted p-values &lt; 0.05 and maximum posterior estimates of log2 FC (LFC) &gt; 1 to call genes up-regulated, and FDR-adjusted p-values &lt; 0.05 and LFC &lt; -1 to call genes down-regulated.</p></sec><sec id="S22"><title>Statistical analysis and data presentation</title><p id="P45">All statistical analyses and graphs were done in R. Venn diagrams were generated using BsRC tools (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://barc.wi.mit.edu/tools/">http://barc.wi.mit.edu/tools/</ext-link>) and re-coloured to match the colour scheme using Gimp (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.gimp.org/">https://www.gimp.org/</ext-link>). To calculate the significance of the overlap between altered genes in RNAseq experiments and the enrichment of JNK pathway components, we used a hypergeometric distribution probability calculator (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://systems.crump.ucla.edu/hypergeometric/index.php">https://systems.crump.ucla.edu/hypergeometric/index.php</ext-link>). To compare the difference between the population mean and a hypothetical value (for colocalisation), the one-sample t-test was used. For comparing two populations, the unpaired or paired (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S2</xref> only) two-sample Wilcoxon test was used for consistency as several datasets failed the Shapiro-Wilk normality test. For comparing three or more datasets (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2C</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">S3 and S5</xref>), one-way ANOVA and post-hoc t-test with false discovery rate p-value correction were used. For testing phenotype rescue, two-way ANOVA and post-hoc t-test with false discovery rate p-value correction were used.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="SM"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1"><label>Supplemental Figures</label><media xlink:href="EMS201995-supplement-Supplemental_Figures.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" id="d62aAcFbB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD2"><label>Supplemental Figure Legends</label><media xlink:href="EMS201995-supplement-Supplemental_Figure_Legends.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" id="d62aAcFcB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack id="S23"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank the Wolfson Light Microscopy and Fly Facilities at the University of Sheffield and the Microscopy Facility at the School of Biological and Behavioural Sciences, Queen Mary University of London for their technical support. This work was supported by grants from the Biotechnology and Biological Sciences Research Council, UK Research and Innovation BB/P007503/1 and BB/W019698/1.</p></ack><sec id="S24" sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data and code availability</title><p id="P46">The RNA sequencing data is available at PRJNA1185032 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/bioproject/1185032">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/bioproject/1185032</ext-link>. All microscopy data is available at the Queen Mary Research Online repository, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://qmro.qmul.ac.uk/xmlui/handle/123456789/101582">https://qmro.qmul.ac.uk/xmlui/handle/123456789/101582</ext-link>.</p></sec><fn-group><fn fn-type="con" id="FN3"><p id="P47">Author contributions</p><p id="P48">MRM performed RNA isolation. AQ performed <italic>stat92E</italic> rescue experiments in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4A</xref>. EJ performed experiments with HP-1 RNAi in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4C</xref>. PAS analysed RNA sequencing data. NAB performed the remaining experiments. MRM, NB and MPZ conceptualised the work and wrote the manuscript.</p></fn><fn fn-type="conflict" id="FN4"><p id="P49">Declaration of interests</p><p id="P50">The authors declare no conflict of interest.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><ref id="R1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Housden</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name><name><surname>Perrimon</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Spatial and temporal organization of signaling pathways</article-title><source>Trends Biochem Sci</source><year>2014</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>457</fpage><lpage>464</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4477539</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25155749</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tibs.2014.07.008</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Housden</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name><name><surname>Perrimon</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Spatial and temporal organization of signaling pathways</article-title><source>Trends Biochem Sci</source><year>2014</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>457</fpage><lpage>464</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arbouzova</surname><given-names>NI</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeidler</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>JAK/STAT signalling in <italic>Drosophila</italic>: insights into conserved regulatory and cellular functions</article-title><source>Development</source><year>2006</year><volume>133</volume><fpage>2605</fpage><lpage>2616</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16794031</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The JAK/STAT signaling pathway: from bench to clinic</article-title><source>Signal Transduct Target Ther</source><year>2021</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>402</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8617206</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34824210</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41392-021-00791-1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeidler</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Unphosphorylated STATs go nuclear</article-title><source>Curr Opin Genet Dev</source><year>2008</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>455</fpage><lpage>460</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18840523</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Drosophila STAT is required for directly maintaining HP1 localization and heterochromatin stability</article-title><source>Nat Cell Biol</source><year>2008</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>489</fpage><lpage>496</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3083919</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18344984</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncb1713</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Unphosphorylated STAT5A stabilizes heterochromatin and suppresses tumor growth</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci</source><year>2013</year><volume>110</volume><fpage>10213</fpage><lpage>10218</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3690839</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23733954</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1221243110</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dutta</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Unphosphorylated STAT3 in heterochromatin formation and tumor suppression in lung cancer</article-title><source>BMC Cancer</source><year>2020</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>145</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7036253</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32087696</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12885-020-6649-2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Purdy</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Davisson</surname><given-names>VJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wendt</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biased signaling downstream of epidermal growth factor receptor regulates proliferative versus apoptotic response to ligand</article-title><source>Cell Death Dis</source><year>2018</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>976</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6155319</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30250119</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41419-018-1034-7</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ceresa</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>EGFR-mediated apoptosis via STAT3</article-title><source>Exp Cell Res</source><year>2017</year><volume>356</volume><fpage>93</fpage><lpage>103</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5514375</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28433699</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.yexcr.2017.04.016</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Treda</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>EGFR Activation Leads to Cell Death Independent of PI3K/AKT/mTOR in an AD293 Cell Line</article-title><source>PLOS ONE</source><year>2016</year><volume>11</volume><elocation-id>e0155230</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4859505</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27153109</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0155230</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Quesnelle</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Boehm</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Grandis</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>STAT-mediated EGFR signaling in cancer</article-title><source>J Cell Biochem</source><year>2007</year><volume>102</volume><fpage>311</fpage><lpage>319</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17661350</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van Roy</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Berx</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The cell-cell adhesion molecule E-cadherin</article-title><source>Cell Mol Life Sci CMLS</source><year>2008</year><volume>65</volume><fpage>3756</fpage><lpage>3788</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11131785</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18726070</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00018-008-8281-1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Klezovitch</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Vasioukhin</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cadherin signaling: keeping cells in touch</article-title><source>F1000Research</source><year>2015</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>550</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4544379</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26339481</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.12688/f1000research.6445.1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Qian</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Karpova</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Sheppard</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>McNally</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lowy</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>E-cadherin-mediated adhesion inhibits ligand-dependent activation of diverse receptor tyrosine kinases</article-title><source>EMBO J</source><year>2004</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>1739</fpage><lpage>1784</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC394229</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15057284</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.emboj.7600136</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>N-G</given-names></name><name><surname>Koh</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Gumbiner</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>E-cadherin mediates contact inhibition of proliferation through Hippo signaling-pathway components</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci</source><year>2011</year><volume>108</volume><fpage>11930</fpage><lpage>11935</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3141988</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21730131</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1103345108</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ramírez Moreno</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bulgakova</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Cross-Talk Between EGFR and E-Cadherin</article-title><source>Front Cell Dev Biol</source><year>2022</year><volume>9</volume><elocation-id>828673</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8811214</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35127732</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fcell.2021.828673</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dumstrei</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Shy</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Tepass</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Hartenstein</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Interaction between EGFR signaling and DE-cadherin during nervous system morphogenesis</article-title><source>Development</source><year>2002</year><volume>129</volume><fpage>3983</fpage><lpage>3994</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12163402</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sotillos</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Krahn</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Espinosa-Vázquez</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hombría</surname><given-names>JC-G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Src kinases mediate the interaction of the apical determinant Bazooka/PAR3 with STAT92E and increase signalling efficiency in Drosophila ectodermal cells</article-title><source>Development</source><year>2013</year><volume>140</volume><fpage>1507</fpage><lpage>1516</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23462467</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bulgakova</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name><surname>Grigoriev</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Yap</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Akhmanova</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dynamic microtubules produce an asymmetric E-cadherin-Bazooka complex to maintain segment boundaries</article-title><source>J Cell Biol</source><year>2013</year><volume>201</volume><fpage>887</fpage><lpage>901</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3678168</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23751496</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.201211159</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mallart</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>E-cadherin acts as a positive regulator of the JAK-STAT signaling pathway during Drosophila oogenesis</article-title><source>Front Cell Dev Biol</source><year>2022</year><volume>10</volume><elocation-id>886312</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9473917</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36120588</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fcell.2022.886312</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ramirez Moreno</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Stempor</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bulgakova</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Interactions and Feedbacks in E-Cadherin Transcriptional Regulation</article-title><source>Front Cell Dev Biol</source><year>2021</year><comment>0</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8273600</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34262912</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fcell.2021.701175</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Villaseñor</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalaidzidis</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zerial</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Signal processing by the endosomal system</article-title><source>Curr Opin Cell Biol</source><year>2016</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>53</fpage><lpage>60</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26921695</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Pujol</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Smythe</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Lamaze</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Prior</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Interplay of Endocytosis and Growth Factor Receptor Signalling</chapter-title><source>Endocytosis and Signaling</source><publisher-name>Springer International Publishing</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Cham</publisher-loc><year>2018</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>181</fpage><lpage>202</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30097776</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Integration of JAK/STAT receptor-ligand trafficking, signalling and gene expression in Drosophila melanogaster cells</article-title><source>J Cell Sci</source><year>2020</year><elocation-id>jcs.246199</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32917740</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Di Fiore</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name><name><surname>von Zastrow</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Endocytosis, signaling, and beyond</article-title><source>Cold Spring Harb Perspect Biol</source><year>2014</year><volume>6</volume><elocation-id>a016865</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4107983</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25085911</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/cshperspect.a016865</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Devergne</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghiglione</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Noselli</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The endocytic control of JAK/STAT signalling in Drosophila</article-title><source>J Cell Sci</source><year>2007</year><volume>120</volume><fpage>3457</fpage><lpage>3464</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17855388</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cendrowski</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Maminska</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Miaczynska</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Endocytic regulation of cytokine receptor signaling</article-title><source>Cytokine Growth Factor Rev</source><year>2016</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>63</fpage><lpage>73</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27461871</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Caldieri</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Malabarba</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Di Fiore</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name><name><surname>Sigismund</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Lamaze</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Prior</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>EGFR Trafficking in Physiology and Cancer</chapter-title><source>Endocytosis and Signaling</source><publisher-name>Springer International Publishing</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Cham</publisher-loc><year>2018</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>235</fpage><lpage>272</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30097778</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tomas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Futter</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Eden</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>EGF receptor trafficking: consequences for signaling and cancer</article-title><source>Trends Cell Biol</source><year>2014</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>26</fpage><lpage>34</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3884125</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24295852</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tcb.2013.11.002</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Verma</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>PYK2 sustains endosomal-derived receptor signalling and enhances epithelial-to-mesenchymal transition</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2015</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>6064</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25648557</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kowalczyk</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Nanes</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Adherens Junction Turnover: Regulating Adhesion Through Cadherin Endocytosis, Degradation, and Recycling</chapter-title><source>Adherens Junctions: from Molecular Mechanisms to Tissue Development and Disease</source><publisher-name>Springer Netherlands</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Dordrecht</publisher-loc><year>2012</year><volume>60</volume><fpage>197</fpage><lpage>222</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4074012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22674073</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-94-007-4186-7_9</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brüser</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Bogdan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Adherens Junctions on the Move—Membrane Trafficking of E-Cadherin</article-title><source>Cold Spring Harb Perspect Biol</source><year>2017</year><volume>9</volume><elocation-id>a029140</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC5334258</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28096264</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/cshperspect.a029140</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reynolds</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>p120-catenin: Past and present</article-title><source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source><year>2007</year><volume>1773</volume><fpage>2</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2892545</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17175391</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbamcr.2006.09.019</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Iyer</surname><given-names>KV</given-names></name><name><surname>Piscitello-Gómez</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Paijmans</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Jülicher</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Eaton</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Epithelial Viscoelasticity Is Regulated by Mechanosensitive E-cadherin Turnover</article-title><source>Curr Biol</source><year>2019</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>578</fpage><lpage>591</lpage><elocation-id>e5</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30744966</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Greig</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bulgakova</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Interplay between actomyosin and E-cadherin dynamics regulates cell shape in the Drosophila embryonic epidermis</article-title><source>J Cell Sci</source><year>2020</year><volume>133</volume><elocation-id>jcs242321</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32665321</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moreno</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Boswell</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Casbolt</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name><name><surname>Bulgakova</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multifaceted control of E-cadherin dynamics by the Adaptor Protein Complex 1 during epithelial morphogenesis</article-title><source>Mol Biol Cell</source><year>2022</year><elocation-id>mbcE21120598</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9582639</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35609212</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1091/mbc.E21-12-0598</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Karsten</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Plischke</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Perrimon</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeidler</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mutational analysis reveals separable DNA binding and trans-activation of Drosophila STAT92E</article-title><source>Cell Signal</source><year>2006</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>819</fpage><lpage>829</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16129580</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bach</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>GFP reporters detect the activation of the Drosophila JAK/STAT pathway in vivo</article-title><source>Gene Expr Patterns</source><year>2007</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>323</fpage><lpage>331</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17008134</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hatini</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Kula-Eversole</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Nusinow</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Del Signore</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Essential roles for stat92E in expanding and patterning the proximodistal axis of the Drosophila wing imaginal disc</article-title><source>Dev Biol</source><year>2013</year><volume>378</volume><fpage>38</fpage><lpage>50</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3776456</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23499656</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ydbio.2013.02.016</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R41"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Asmar</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Biryukova</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Heitzler</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Drosophila dLMO-PA isoform acts as an early activator of achaete/scute proneural expression</article-title><source>Dev Biol</source><year>2008</year><volume>316</volume><fpage>487</fpage><lpage>497</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18329012</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R42"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eaton</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Auvinen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Jan</surname><given-names>YN</given-names></name><name><surname>Simons</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>CDC42 and Rac1 control different actin-dependent processes in the Drosophila wing disc epithelium</article-title><source>J Cell Biol</source><year>1995</year><volume>131</volume><fpage>151</fpage><lpage>164</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2120599</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7559772</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.131.1.151</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R43"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brand</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>Perrimon</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Targeted gene expression as a means of altering cell fates and generating dominant phenotypes</article-title><source>Dev Camb Engl</source><year>1993</year><volume>118</volume><fpage>401</fpage><lpage>415</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8223268</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R44"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wiedenmann</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>EosFP, a fluorescent marker protein with UV-inducible green-to-red fluorescence conversion</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci</source><year>2004</year><volume>101</volume><fpage>15905</fpage><lpage>15910</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC528746</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15505211</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0403668101</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R45"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cavey</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rauzi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lenne</surname><given-names>P-F</given-names></name><name><surname>Lecuit</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A two-tiered mechanism for stabilization and immobilization of E-cadherin</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2008</year><volume>453</volume><fpage>751</fpage><lpage>756</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18480755</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R46"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maeda</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Tachibana</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>HP1 maintains protein stability of H3K9 methyltransferases and demethylases</article-title><source>EMBO Rep</source><year>2022</year><volume>23</volume><elocation-id>e53581</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8982598</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35166421</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15252/embr.202153581</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R47"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>SHM</given-names></name><name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Chuah</surname><given-names>L-H</given-names></name><name><surname>Leong</surname><given-names>CO</given-names></name><name><surname>Ngai</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>E-cadherin: Its dysregulation in carcinogenesis and clinical implications</article-title><source>Crit Rev Oncol Hematol</source><year>2018</year><volume>121</volume><fpage>11</fpage><lpage>22</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29279096</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R48"><label>48</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tapon</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagata</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Lamarche</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A new rac target POSH is an SH3-containing scaffold protein involved in the JNK and NF-kappaB signalling pathways</article-title><source>EMBO J</source><year>1998</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>1395</fpage><lpage>1404</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1170487</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9482736</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/emboj/17.5.1395</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R49"><label>49</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>WX</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Canonical and non-canonical JAK–STAT signaling</article-title><source>Trends Cell Biol</source><year>2008</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>545</fpage><lpage>551</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3082280</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18848449</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tcb.2008.08.008</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R50"><label>50</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Platta</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name><name><surname>Stenmark</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Endocytosis and signaling</article-title><source>Curr Opin Cell Biol</source><year>2011</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>393</fpage><lpage>403</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21474295</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R51"><label>51</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J-L</given-names></name><name><surname>Qu</surname><given-names>X-J</given-names></name><name><surname>Russel</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldstein</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regulation of epidermal growth factor receptor in human colon cancer cell lines by interferon</article-title><source>Gut</source><year>2004</year><volume>53</volume><fpage>123</fpage><lpage>129</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC1773946</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14684586</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/gut.53.1.123</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R52"><label>52</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>JAK signaling globally counteracts heterochromatic gene silencing</article-title><source>Nat Genet</source><year>2006</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>1071</fpage><lpage>1076</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3092431</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16892059</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng1860</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R53"><label>53</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Na</surname><given-names>T-Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Schecterson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Mendonsa</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Gumbiner</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The functional activity of E-cadherin controls tumor cell metastasis at multiple steps</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci</source><year>2020</year><volume>117</volume><fpage>5931</fpage><lpage>5937</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7084067</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32127478</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1918167117</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R54"><label>54</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fouquet</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Early Loss of E-cadherin from Cell-Cell Contacts Is Involved in the Onset of Anoikis in Enterocytes</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2004</year><volume>279</volume><fpage>43061</fpage><lpage>43069</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15292248</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R55"><label>55</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peluso</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Pappalardo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Fernandez</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>E-Cadherin-Mediated Cell Contact Prevents Apoptosis of Spontaneously Immortalized Granulosa Cells by Regulating Akt Kinase Activity1</article-title><source>Biol Reprod</source><year>2001</year><volume>64</volume><fpage>1183</fpage><lpage>1190</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11259266</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R56"><label>56</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Casanova</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A role for E-cadherin in ensuring cohesive migration of a heterogeneous population of non-epithelial cells</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2015</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>7998</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4557277</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26272476</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncomms8998</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R57"><label>57</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Silver</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Montell</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Paracrine Signaling through the JAK/STAT Pathway Activates Invasive Behavior of Ovarian Epithelial Cells in Drosophila</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2001</year><volume>107</volume><fpage>831</fpage><lpage>841</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11779460</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R58"><label>58</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aigouy</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cell Flow Reorients the Axis of Planar Polarity in the Wing Epithelium of Drosophila</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2010</year><volume>142</volume><fpage>773</fpage><lpage>786</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20813263</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R59"><label>59</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dunn</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamocka</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>McDonald</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A practical guide to evaluating colocalization in biological microscopy</article-title><source>Am J Physiol Cell Physiol</source><year>2011</year><volume>300</volume><fpage>C723</fpage><lpage>742</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3074624</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21209361</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/ajpcell.00462.2010</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R60"><label>60</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stringer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Michaelos</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pachitariu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cellpose: a generalist algorithm for cellular segmentation</article-title><source>Nat Methods</source><year>2021</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>100</fpage><lpage>106</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33318659</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R61"><label>61</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Durbin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fast and accurate long-read alignment with Burrows-Wheeler transform</article-title><source>Bioinforma Oxf Engl</source><year>2010</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>589</fpage><lpage>595</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2828108</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20080505</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btp698</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R62"><label>62</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Love</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name><name><surname>Huber</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Anders</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Moderated estimation of fold change and dispersion for RNA-seq data with DESeq2</article-title><source>Genome Biol</source><year>2014</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>550</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4302049</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25516281</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13059-014-0550-8</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R63"><label>63</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anders</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Huber</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Differential expression analysis for sequence count data</article-title><source>Genome Biol</source><year>2010</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>R106</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3218662</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20979621</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/gb-2010-11-10-r106</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Gene expression changes by non-canonical STAT92E signalling and the control of STAT92E localisation by E-cadherin.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) The Venn diagram depicting genes with significantly changed expression (p&lt;0.05) in wing discs upon overexpression of STAT92E<sup>Y704F</sup> and HP1 knockdown for 24 hours using <italic>Act5C</italic>-Gal4. (<bold>B</bold>) Correlation of gene expression changes in wing discs upon overexpression of E-cad::EOS and STAT92E<sup>Y704F</sup>. Each dot represents an individual gene. (<bold>C</bold>) Representative images of <italic>10xSTAT92E</italic>-GFP (10xSTAT) expression in wing discs expressing CD8 (left) and E-cad::EOS (OE, right). CD8 (bottom left, magenta) and E-cad::EOS (bottom right, blue) were expressed using <italic>ptc</italic>-Gal4 and the levels of GFP (direct fluorescence, top row, grey; bottom row, green) were measured within the expressing stripe in the wing pouch relative to the outside of the stripe. White squares outline the wing pouch area used for quantifications in this and other experiments. (<bold>D</bold>) Representative images of STAT::GFP localisation (bottom row) expressed at the endogenous level in control wing discs (overexpressing CD8::mCherry, left) and those overexpressing E-cad (right). E-cad staining by antibody is in the top row. <italic>MS1096</italic>-Gal4 driver was used. (<bold>E</bold>) Mander’s colocalisation coefficient (MCC, see Materials and Methods) for the total E-cad and STAT::GFP signals (N = 4, sections = 8 per sample). p =8.9e-5 in one-sample t-test in comparison to zero for random colocalisation. (<bold>F</bold>) A single confocal section depicting STAT::GFP expressed at the endogenous level (left, grey; right, magenta) and E-cad (antibody staining, middle, grey; right, green) in wing discs overexpressing E-cad. Arrows highlight examples of their colocalisation on vesicles. (<bold>G</bold>) Quantification of ratios between the cytoplasm and cell-cell border levels of E-cad (left) and STAT::GFP (right) and mean STAT::GFP levels at cell-cell borders in wing discs expressing CD8 (left, black) and E-cad (right, blue). The Wilcoxon test was used to compare the datasets. N = 4 and 8 wing discs. (<bold>H</bold>) Quantification of <italic>10xSTAT92E</italic>-GFP levels (<italic>10xSTAT</italic>) in the wing pouch area of wing discs expressing CD8 and E-cad::EOS as shown in (<bold>C</bold>). The Wilcoxon test was used to compare the datasets. N = 4 and 4 wing discs. The quantification of levels in the notum is in <bold><xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S1B</xref></bold>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS201995-f001"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Changes in gene expression, HP1 and EGFR localisation following E-cad overexpression.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) The Venn diagram depicting genes with significantly changed expression (p&lt;0.05) in wing discs upon overexpression of E-cad::EOS and STAT92E<sup>Y704F</sup> and <italic>HP1</italic>-RNAi for 24 hours using <italic>Act5C</italic>-Gal4. (<bold>B-C</bold>) Representative images (B) and quantification (C) of HP1 levels (antibody staining) in wing discs with E-cad::EOS overexpression (OE, middle), E-cad knockdown (RNAi, right) or overexpression of CD8 as control (left) for 24 hours using <italic>ptc</italic>-Gal4. Each dot represents a single nucleus. One-way ANOVA and post-hoc t-test with false discovery rate p-value correction were used. N = 29/3, 16/3 and 20/4 (nucleus/wing disc). Localisation of E-cad::EOS is shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S2</xref>. Similar data for H3K9me3 is in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S3</xref>. (<bold>D</bold>) Representative images of EGFR::GFP expressed from the endogenous locus in control wing discs (overexpressing CD8::mCherry, top) and those overexpressing E-cad (bottom). (<bold>E</bold>) A single confocal section depicting EGFR::GFP expressed from the endogenous locus (left) and E-cad (antibody staining, right). Arrows highlight examples of their colocalisation on vesicles. Scale bar 1 μm. (<bold>F</bold>) Mander’s Colocalisation Coefficient (MCCdiff) for EGFR::GFP and E-cad in cytoplasm. p-value shows the comparison of MCCdiff with zero (= no colocalisation) using a one-sample t-test (N=7, sections = 8 per sample). (<bold>G</bold>) Quantification of mean levels at cell-cell borders (left) and the ratio between the cytoplasm and cell-cell border levels (right) of EGFR::GFP expressed from the endogenous locus in control wing discs (left, black) and those overexpressing E-cad (right, blue). The Wilcoxon test was used to compare the datasets. N = 13 and 7 wing discs. The <italic>MS1096</italic>-Gal4 driver was used in D-G.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS201995-f002"/></fig><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>EGFR acts downstream of E-cadherin in inducing apoptosis.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>). Representative image of adult wings expressing either myr::GFP (left) or E-cad::EOS (right). (<bold>B</bold>) Representative images of Dcp-1 staining in control wing discs (<italic>white</italic><sup><italic>-/-</italic></sup>, left) or wing discs expressing E-cad::EOS (right). (<bold>C</bold>) Representative image of adult wings expressing either myr::GFP (left) or E-cad::EOS (right) with reduced <italic>Egfr</italic> gene dose. (<bold>D</bold>) Representative images of Dcp-1 staining in control wing discs (<italic>white</italic><sup><italic>-/-</italic></sup>, left) or wing discs expressing E-cad::EOS (right) with reduced <italic>Egfr</italic> gene dose. (<bold>E-F</bold>) Quantification of the adult with sizes (E) and Dcp-1 signal (F) in control wing discs (black) or wing discs expressing E-cad::EOS (blue) in the presence of two or one copies of the <italic>Egfr</italic> gene. Two-way ANOVA and post-hoc t-test with false discovery rate p-value correction were used. p&lt;0.0001 for the interaction between E-cad overexpression and <italic>Egfr</italic> copy number in both E and F. N = 17, 16, 17 and 12, left-to-right (E) and = 15, 7, 8 and 7, left-to-right (F). Data for the overexpression of untagged E-cad is in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S4</xref>. (<bold>G-H</bold>) Representative images (G) and quantification (H) of mean cell-cell border levels (G, left) and the ratio between the cytoplasm and cell-cell border levels (H, right) of E-cad::GFP expressed from the endogenous locus in the presence of two functional copies (G, left, H, black) or one copy (G, right, H, red) of the <italic>Egfr</italic> gene. The Wilcoxon test was used to compare the datasets. N = 12 and 16 wing discs. Similar data for the expression of the dominant-negative variant of EGFR is in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S4</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS201995-f003"/></fig><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>(<bold>A-B</bold>) Representative images (A) and area quantification of adult wings expressing either myr::GFP (A, left column, B, black) or E-cad::EOS (A, right column, B, blue) in the presence of two functional copies (A, top row, B, left) or one copy (A, bottom row, B, right) of the <italic>stat92E</italic> gene. Two-way ANOVA and post-hoc t-test with false discovery rate p-value correction were used. N = 21, 32, 34 and 33, left-to-right. p = 0.02 for the interaction between E-cad::EOS overexpression and <italic>stat92E</italic> copy number. The lack of rescue by reducing doses of components of Wnt and Hippo pathways as well as reducing the gene dose of <italic>hopscotch</italic> (<italic>hop</italic>) encoding for the single <italic>Drosophila</italic> JAK protein is shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S5</xref>. (<bold>C-D</bold>) Representative images (C) and area quantification (D) of adult wings expressing myr::GFP (C, left, D, black) or <italic>HP1</italic> RNAi (C, right, D, green) using one copy of <italic>MS1096</italic>-Gal4 (C, top, D, left) or two copies (C, bottom, D, right). Two-way ANOVA and post-hoc t-test with false discovery rate p-value correction were used in F. N = 17, 19, 15 and 10, left-to-right. p &lt; 0.0001 for the interaction between the presence of <italic>HP1</italic> RNAi and <italic>MS1096</italic>-Gal4 copy number.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS201995-f004"/></fig><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>(<bold>A-B</bold>) Representative images (C) and area quantification of adult wings expressing either myr::GFP (C, left column, D, black) or E-cad::EOS (C, right column, D, blue) together with myr::GFP (C, top row, D, left) or p120-catenin (C, bottom row, D, right, p120ctn) using the <italic>MS1096</italic>-Gal4 driver. Two-way ANOVA and post-hoc t-test with false discovery rate p-value correction were used in D. N = 17, 13, 16 and 12, left-to-right. p&lt;0.0001 for the interaction between E-cad::EOS and p120ctn overexpression. (<bold>C-D</bold>) Representative images (A) and area quantification of adult wings expressing either myr::GFP (A, left column, B, black) or E-cad::EOS (A, right column, B, blue) in the presence of two functional copies (A, top row, B, left) or one copy (A, bottom row, B, right) of the <italic>POSH</italic> gene. Two-way ANOVA and post-hoc t-test with false discovery rate p-value correction were used. N = 18, 27, 33 and 20, left-to-right. p = 0.001 for the interaction between E-cad::EOS overexpression and <italic>POSH</italic> copy number.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS201995-f005"/></fig><fig id="F6" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>The model of three STAT activities in a cell. Three distinct modalities of STAT signalling co-exist in a cell: the canonical JAK/STAT pathway and the non-canonical EGFR:STAT and HP1:STAT pathways. The JAK/STAT pathway is activated by ligand stimulation of cytokine receptors and the activation of receptor-associated JAKs. This pathway is dominant relative to two non-canonical pathways. Non-phosphorylated STAT is available to interact with HP1 in the nucleus to promote heterochromatinisation. Non-phosphorylated STAT is also recruited to E-cad:EGFR. Two non-canonical STAT pathways compete for availability of non-phosphorylated STAT. Upon elevated intracellular E-cad, high levels of EGFR and STAT are recruited to the E-cad containing vesicles. Elevated EGFR:STAT signalling triggers apoptosis through upregulation of the JNK pathway. At the same time, STAT outcompetes HP1 binding, thus reducing HP1 levels on DNA.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS201995-f006"/></fig></floats-group></article>