<!DOCTYPE article
 PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" article-type="preprint"><?all-math-mml yes?><?use-mml?><?origin ukpmcpa?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">bioRxiv</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>bioRxiv : the preprint server for biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2692-8205</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">EMS199401</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2024.10.10.617643</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="archive">PPR923683</article-id><article-version-alternatives><article-version article-version-type="status">preprint</article-version><article-version article-version-type="number">1</article-version></article-version-alternatives><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>HighALPS: Ultra-High-Throughput Marker-Gene Amplicon Library Preparation and Sequencing on the Illumina NextSeq and NovaSeq Platforms</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Flörl</surname><given-names>Lena</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cabrera</surname><given-names>Paula Momo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Moccia</surname><given-names>Maria Domenica</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Plüss</surname><given-names>Serafina</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bokulich</surname><given-names>Nicholas A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CR1">#</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Laboratory of Food Systems Biotechnology, Institute of Food, Nutrition and Health, <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/05a28rw58</institution-id><institution>ETH Zurich</institution></institution-wrap>, <country country="CH">Switzerland</country></aff><aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Functional Genomics Center Zürich (FGCZ), <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/05a28rw58</institution-id><institution>ETH Zurich</institution></institution-wrap> and <institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ror">https://ror.org/02crff812</institution-id><institution>University of Zurich</institution></institution-wrap>, <country country="CH">Switzerland</country></aff><author-notes><corresp id="CR1">
<label>#</label>Corresponding author: Nicholas A. Bokulich. Department of Health Sciences and Technology, ETH Zurich, Switzerland. <email>Nicholas.Bokulich@hest.ethz.ch</email>
</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted"><day>14</day><month>10</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="preprint"><day>12</day><month>10</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><permissions><ali:free_to_read/><license><ali:license_ref>https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is licensed under a <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">CC BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p id="P1">Microbiome research using amplicon sequencing of microbial marker genes has surged over the past decade, propelled by protocols for highly multiplexed sequencing with barcoded primer constructs. Newer Illumina platforms like the NovaSeq and NextSeq series significantly outperform older sequencers in terms of reads, output, and runtime. However these platforms are more prone to index-hopping, which limits the application of protocols designed for older platforms such as the Earth Microbiome Project (EMP) protocols, hence there is a need to adapt these established protocols. Here, we present an ultra-<bold>High</bold>-throughput <bold>A</bold>mplicon <bold>L</bold>ibrary <bold>P</bold>reparation and <bold>S</bold>equencing protocol (HighALPS) incorporating the capabilities of these newer sequencing platforms, designed for both 16S rRNA gene and fungal internal transcribed spacer (ITS) domain sequencing. Our results demonstrate good run performance across different sequencing platforms and flow cells, with successful sequencing of mock communities, validating the protocol’s effectiveness. The new HighALPS library preparation method offers a robust, cost effective, and ultra-high-throughput solution for microbiome research, compatible with the latest sequencing technologies. This protocol allows multiplexing thousands of samples in a single run at a read depth of tens of millions of sequences per sample.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec id="S1"><title>Observation</title><p id="P2">Interest in microbiome research has surged in the last decade, fueled by increasing recognition of the pivotal role that microbiomes play in global ecosystems, including in human health. The most common technology used to study microbial communities is marker-gene amplicon sequencing, e.g., of 16S rRNA genes. This is due to the relatively low cost and high throughput of this approach, as well as availability of mature software pipelines to facilitate relatively rapid analysis of sequencing data (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref>).</p><p id="P3">The popularity of marker-gene sequencing first surged in the early 2010s with the publication of protocols for ultra-high-throughput 16S rRNA sequencing performed using Roche 454 Pyrosequencing (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">2</xref>) and Illumina HiSeq and MiSeq platforms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">4</xref>). A commonly used standard library preparation workflow uses proprietary Illumina Nextera kits and relies on tagmentation of DNA (e.g., marker-gene amplicons) with a set of Nextera unique dual indices (each 8 nt) embedded in the adapter sequence (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>), allowing up to 384 samples to be multiplexed and sequenced in a single run. Conversely, the EMP protocol uses unique indices (12 nt-long Golay error-correcting barcodes) that are embedded in the primer constructs and incorporated into the amplicons during PCR amplification (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). This strategy increases the throughput by allowing for a substantially larger number of samples to be pooled into a single run. Additionally time and labor is reduced, as only a single PCR reaction is necessary. After its original release in 2012, the EMP protocol was slightly updated and a second version was published in 2023. However the protocol is still as originally designed, primarily applicable for Illumina MiSeq and HiSeq, which were launched in 2010 and 2011. These protocols are not directly transferable to newer Illumina platforms, such as the NovaSeq and NextSeq series, as the patterned flow cells used by these devices have a higher risk of index hopping (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref>), which therefore requires a unique dual index (UDI) strategy to minimize read miss-assignment. However, these newer platforms massively outperform the older sequencers in regard to maximal read output and run time (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>), leading to dramatically reduced costs per gigabase.</p><p id="P4">Here, we introduce a new ultra-high-throughput Amplicon Library Preparation and Sequencing method (HighALPS) to profile microbial communities, based on the principles of the EMP protocol, and optimized for cost-effectiveness and compatibility with newer Illumina DNA sequencing platforms. HighALPS is robust against index hopping as the combinatorial unique-dual index (UDI) strategy enables the removal of unexpected index combinations generated by index hopping. This form of sequencing error is more common in novel patterned flow cells and typically ranges between 0.1–2 % of reads affected (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref>). In single index libraries such as the original EMP protocol, this would lead to incorrectly assigned reads in demultiplexing. Using a UDI approach significantly reduces the likelihood of sample misassignments, with the specific rate depending on the number of barcodes and combinations thereof. For instance, with the proposed combination (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Figure 1</xref>), the maximum theoretical misassignment rate is 0.04%. Further, the combinatorial unique dual indexing strategy is particularly economical, as it requires a lower number of individually barcoded primers, which due to the purification requirements and length are more costly. For example, the combination of only 96 unique forward and reverse primers (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Fig. 1</xref>) can result in 1152 unique indices. The cost for these UDI primers is approximately ~0.34 USD (based on current rates) per 96-plate, which is less than 1 % of the cost in comparison to using e.g. the proprietary Illumina Nextera XT Index Kit v2 Set for ~409.55 USD per 96-plate (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary File 1.3.1</xref>). Additionally, when comparing the cost per sequencing run using appropriate flow cells (500-600 cycles) across older and newer Illumina platforms, the cost of a NovaSeq 6000 or NextSeq 1000/2000 run ranges from 7.7% to 20.3% of the price of a MiSeq run per million reads obtained, based on current rates. Similarly, the cost per gigabyte of output data for the NovaSeq 6000 and NextSeq 1000/2000 ranges from only 4.6% to 20.3% respectively of that of a MiSeq run (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary File 1.3.1</xref>). Further, as these library preparation primers are designed for each marker gene separately, amplicons of different marker genes can be multiplexed in a single run (e.g., for simultaneous sequencing of 16S rRNA gene and ITS amplicons). This additional multiplexing does not only reduce costs through enabling combined sequencing runs, but increases sequence diversity within the run, which allows for the reduction of PhiX and can contribute to overall higher read quality.</p><p id="P5">Detailed methodology for the HighALPS protocol development, considerations and validation thereof can be found in the <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary file 1.1</xref>. In brief, we designed library preparation primer constructs to profile bacterial communities incorporating the commonly used 515F (5’-GTGYCAGCMGCCGCGGTAA-3’) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref>) and 806R primer pair (5’-GGACTACNVGGGTWTCTAAT-3’) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">8</xref>). These target the hypervariable V4 region of the 16S rRNA gene and are the same primer pair used in the original EMP protocol (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">4</xref>). For fungal ITS sequencing we designed constructs targeting the ITS1 domain with the following primers: BITS (5′–ACCTGCGGARGGATCA–3′) and B58S3 (5′–GAGATCCRTTGYTRAAAGTT–3′), which demonstrate high coverage of most fungal groups (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref>). However, in theory any other marker-gene primers suitable for Illumina short-read sequencing could be substituted to target, e.g., other 16S rRNA gene domains, fungal ITS2, or other targets (e.g., CO1 for diet metabarcoding). For these constructs we assessed primer interactions and dimerization potential. Library preparation is performed in a single-step PCR, significantly reducing both time and reagent costs compared to a standard 2-step library preparation protocol, which requires two PCRs, and the original EMP protocol, where samples were amplified in triplicates. Given the increased robustness of modern bioinformatic tools in detecting chimeras and jackpot effects, triplicate amplification is no longer necessary (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>). Ultimately this library is sequenced with custom sequencing primers, optimized for the NovaSeq 6000 or NextSeq 2000 platform (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>).</p><p id="P6">We tested the novel HighALPS library preparation method across different sequencing platforms and flow cells which resulted in good run performances. Specifically, we applied the described method on the NextSeq 2000 and NovaSeq 6000 sequencing platforms using different flow cells (P1 and SP) (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>). Further we validated HighALPS with mock communities of various bacteria and yeast as described in Supplementary File 1.1. Both marker genes for profiling bacterial and fungal communities were sequenced within the same run on a NextSeq 2000 as well as a NovaSeq 6000 platform (see run performances in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>). The retrieved bacterial and fungal genera robustly match the theoretical composition of the mock community (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>).</p><p id="P7">In summary, we show that the new HighALPS ultra-high-throughput library preparation and sequencing method can be robustly used across both Illumina Novaseq and Nextseq Series platforms and effectively profiles microbial communities. In contrast to using individual unique barcodes, a combinatorial UDI strategy is adopted to counteract sample misassignment due to index-hopping, as well as to increase cost effectiveness. Further, HighALPS enables multiplexing of multiple marker genes, which additionally reduces costs, and supports higher sequencing data quality due to increased diversity within the run. We provide a detailed step-by-step protocol with automation options and practical tips, as well as custom primer constructs for library preparation and sequencing. In the future, ultra-high-throughput library preparation protocols, such as the presented HighALPS, and decreasing sequencing costs, will make microbiome research more accessible to a broader research community.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="SM"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1"><label>Supplementary Materials</label><media xlink:href="EMS199401-supplement-Supplementary_Materials.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" id="d74aAcBbB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack id="S3"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank the Genomic Diversity Center (GDC) of ETH Zürich as well as the Functional Genomics Center Zürich (FGCZ) for their support.</p><p>This work was financially supported by the Swiss National Science Foundation [Grant Number: 310030_204275] (to NAB) and the Swiss Government Excellence Ph.D. Scholarship (to LF).</p></ack><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>GOI</term><def><p>Gene of Interest</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GB</term><def><p>Gigabyte</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TB</term><def><p>Terabyte</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>M</term><def><p>Million</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>B</term><def><p>Billion</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>bp</term><def><p>basepairs</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>hr</term><def><p>hours</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>EMP</term><def><p>Earth microbiome project</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SBS</term><def><p>Sequencing By Synthesis</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>UDI</term><def><p>Unique Dual Index</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HighALPS</term><def><p>ultra-High-Throughput Amplicon Library Preparation and Sequencing</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>USD</term><def><p>US Dollar</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PCR</term><def><p>Polymerase chain reaction</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><ref-list><ref id="R1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bolyen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Rideout</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Dillon</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Bokulich</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name><surname>Abnet</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Al-Ghalith</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Reproducible, interactive, scalable and extensible microbiome data science using QIIME</article-title><source>Nat Biotechnol</source><year>2019</year><month>Aug</month><volume>37</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>852</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7015180</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31341288</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41587-019-0209-9</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>The Human Microbiome Project Consortium</collab><article-title>Structure, function and diversity of the healthy human microbiome</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2012</year><month>Jun</month><volume>486</volume><issue>7402</issue><fpage>207</fpage><lpage>14</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3564958</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22699609</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature11234</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Caporaso</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Lauber</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Walters</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name><name><surname>Berg-Lyons</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Huntley</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Fierer</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Ultra-high-throughput microbial community analysis on the Illumina HiSeq and MiSeq platforms</article-title><source>ISME J</source><year>2012</year><month>Aug</month><volume>6</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>1621</fpage><lpage>4</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3400413</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22402401</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ismej.2012.8</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Caporaso</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Lauber</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Walters</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name><name><surname>Berg-Lyons</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Lozupone</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Turnbaugh</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Global patterns of 16S rRNA diversity at a depth of millions of sequences per sample</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci</source><year>2011</year><month>Mar</month><day>15</day><volume>108</volume><issue>supplement_1</issue><fpage>4516</fpage><lpage>22</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3063599</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20534432</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1000080107</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="web"><collab>Illumina</collab><source>Effects of Index Misassignment on Multiplexing and Downstream Analysis (Article #770-2017-004-D)</source><year>2017</year><date-in-citation>cited 2024 Sep 20</date-in-citation><comment>[Internet] Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://emea.illumina.com/content/dam/illumina-marketing/documents/products/whitepapers/index-hopping-white-paper-770-2017-004.pdf?linkId=36607862">https://emea.illumina.com/content/dam/illumina-marketing/documents/products/whitepapers/index-hopping-white-paper-770-2017-004.pdf?linkId=36607862</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="web"><collab>Illumina</collab><source>Illumina Sequencing platforms (Article #M-GL-00451 v4 0)</source><year>2024</year><date-in-citation>cited 2024 Sep 20</date-in-citation><comment>[Internet] Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://emea.illumina.com/content/dam/illumina/gcs/assembled-assets/marketing-literature/sequencing-platforms-brochure-m-gl-00451/sequencing-platforms-brochure-m-gl-00451.pdf">https://emea.illumina.com/content/dam/illumina/gcs/assembled-assets/marketing-literature/sequencing-platforms-brochure-m-gl-00451/sequencing-platforms-brochure-m-gl-00451.pdf</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parada</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Needham</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Fuhrman</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Every base matters: assessing small subunit rRNA primers for marine microbiomes with mock communities, time series and global field samples</article-title><source>Environ Microbiol</source><year>2016</year><month>May</month><volume>18</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>1403</fpage><lpage>14</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26271760</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Apprill</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>McNally</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Parsons</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Weber</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Minor revision to V4 region SSU rRNA 806R gene primer greatly increases detection of SAR11 bacterioplankton</article-title><source>Aquat Microb Ecol</source><year>2015</year><month>Jun</month><day>4</day><volume>75</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>129</fpage><lpage>37</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bokulich</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mills</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Improved Selection of Internal Transcribed Spacer-Specific Primers Enables Quantitative, Ultra-High-Throughput Profiling of Fungal Communities</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>2013</year><month>Apr</month><day>15</day><volume>79</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>2519</fpage><lpage>26</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC3623200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23377949</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.03870-12</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marotz</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Humphrey</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Gottel</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Daum</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Gilbert</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Triplicate PCR Reactions for 16S rRNA Gene Amplicon Sequencing are Unnecessary</article-title><source>BioTechniques</source><year>2019</year><month>Jul</month><volume>67</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>29</fpage><lpage>32</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7030937</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31124709</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2144/btn-2018-0192</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="web"><collab>Illumina</collab><source>How to troubleshoot low percent clusters passing filter (%PF) on the NovaSeq X/X Plus (Article #7783)</source><year>2024</year><date-in-citation>cited 2024 Sep 20</date-in-citation><comment>[Internet] Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://knowledge.illumina.com/instrumentation/novaseq-x-x-plus/instrumentation-novaseq-x-x-plus-troubleshooting-list/000007783">https://knowledge.illumina.com/instrumentation/novaseq-x-x-plus/instrumentation-novaseq-x-x-plus-troubleshooting-list/000007783</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><boxed-text id="BX1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Importance</label><p>Marker gene amplicon sequencing on Illumina devices remains the most commonly used technology to profile microbial communities. Yet, most library preparation protocols are not adapted to harness the capabilities and deal with the caveats of the latest Illumina sequencing platforms, which highly outperform older platforms in terms of speed, quality and output. Here we present an ultra-high-throughput, cost effective and robust library preparation protocol (HighALPS) optimized to fully leverage the capabilities of these advanced Illumina sequencing technologies. The combinatorial unique dual index (UDI) strategy effectively combats miss-assignment of reads due to index-hopping, which is more prevalent in newer platforms. The HighALPS protocol incorporates technological (e.g. novel sequencing chemistry, lab automation platforms) as well as bioinformatics advances (e.g. denoising algorithms which make triplicate amplifications unnecessary) of the last years to optimize and streamline library preparation for bacterial and fungal communities.</p></boxed-text><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Comparison of different library preparation strategies.</title><p>The genomic DNA to be amplified is depicted as the black strand and the coloured blocks indicate the primer constructs. (i) Amplification and barcoding: For the Standard 2-step NGS Amplicon Library Preparation protocol e.g. using an Illumina Nextera kit, in the first PCR the marker gene of interest (GOI) is amplified with a primer for the region of interest (red), linked to the primer pad (green) where the sequencing primers ultimately bind, as well as an overhang adapter (blue) for the 2nd PCR. In the subsequent 2nd PCR, which typically entails only 8-10 cycles, two barcodes for unique dual indexing (purple, light blue) as well as the flow cell adapters (gold) are attached. These p5 and p7 adapters attach the nucleotide strand to the flow cell and are universal between all Illumina instruments. In comparison the EMP protocol requires only a single PCR reaction as the primer constructs already contain the adapters, a unique barcode in the forward primer, a custom primer pad as well as the GOI specific primers. Similarly in our new HighALPS protocol, solely a single PCR step is required, however the forward primer as well as the reverse primer carry a unique barcode which enables combinatorial unique dual indexing. (ii) Sequencing: In older Illumina platforms, Index Reads were generated from primers anchored to the adapters. In contrast, dual-indexed sequencing runs on NovaSeq and NextSeq platforms employ a Reverse Complement Workflow. The index primers therefore are the reverse complements of the read primers, i.e. index primer 1 being the reverse complement of read primer 2 and vice versa.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS199401-f001"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Taxa barplot of the microbial features retrieved in comparison to the theoretical composition of the mock community (Zymo_Mock, very right bar respectively) show that across both runs all bacterial (A) and fungal (B) genera were successfully identified. Differences between the theoretical composition (based on cell count) and retrieved composition are likely due to differences in DNA extraction efficiencies, copy number variations, and PCR amplification bias that is independent of the sequencing platform used. Particularly for fungal ITS reads, the disparity between expected and observed relative frequencies most likely reflects the wide variation in ITS copy numbers in different fungal species, rather than sequencing-based effects.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS199401-f002"/></fig><table-wrap id="T1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>A comparison of Illumina sequencers based on their release years shows differences in output, run time, read length, and the underlying technologies. (* data output for dual flow cells) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref>).</title></caption><table frame="box" rules="all"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left">Platform</th><th valign="top" align="left">Launched</th><th valign="top" align="left">Max reads per run</th><th valign="top" align="left">Max output per flow cell</th><th valign="top" align="left">Run Time</th><th valign="top" align="left">Max read length</th><th valign="top" align="left">Chemistry</th><th valign="top" align="left">Flow Cell</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left">NovaSeq X Series</td><td valign="top" align="left">2022</td><td valign="top" align="left">52 B*</td><td valign="top" align="left">8 TB</td><td valign="top" align="left">~17–48 hr</td><td valign="top" align="left">2 × 150 bp</td><td valign="top" align="left">XLEAP-SBS</td><td valign="top" align="left">ultra high density patterned flow cell</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">NextSeq 1000 and 2000</td><td valign="top" align="left">2020</td><td valign="top" align="left">1.8 B</td><td valign="top" align="left">540 GB</td><td valign="top" align="left">~8–44 hr</td><td valign="top" align="left">2 × 300 bp</td><td valign="top" align="left">XLEAP-SBS</td><td valign="top" align="left">patterned flow cell</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">NovaSeq 6000</td><td valign="top" align="left">2017</td><td valign="top" align="left">20 B*</td><td valign="top" align="left">3 TB</td><td valign="top" align="left">~13–44 hr</td><td valign="top" align="left">2 × 250 bp</td><td valign="top" align="left">SBS</td><td valign="top" align="left">patterned flow cell</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">MiSeq</td><td valign="top" align="left">2011</td><td valign="top" align="left">25 M</td><td valign="top" align="left">15 GB</td><td valign="top" align="left">~4–56 hr</td><td valign="top" align="left">2 × 300 bp</td><td valign="top" align="left">SBS</td><td valign="top" align="left">non-patterned flow cells</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left">HiSeq</td><td valign="top" align="left">2010</td><td valign="top" align="left">3 B*</td><td valign="top" align="left">600 GB</td><td valign="top" align="left">~11 days</td><td valign="top" align="left">1 x 100 bp</td><td valign="top" align="left">SBS</td><td valign="top" align="left">non-patterned flow cells</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Key run quality parameters for the sequencing of libraries created with HighALPS. Run performance is considered good when at least 80 % of reads have a quality score of 30 or higher (% &gt;= Q30 bases) which both runs easily surpassed. Both runs also show a fairly high amount of percentage of clusters occupied and clusters passing the filter. A low percentage of clusters passing filter could be due to a low library quality and or over clustering, and values above 60-65 % are typically considered successful runs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref>).</p></caption><table frame="box" rules="all"><thead><tr><th valign="middle" align="left">Platform</th><th valign="middle" align="left">Flowcell</th><th valign="middle" align="left">Yield (GBases)</th><th valign="middle" align="left">% &gt;= Q30 bases</th><th valign="middle" align="left">% Clusters occupied</th><th valign="middle" align="left">% Clusters passing filter</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="middle" align="left">NextSeq 2000</td><td valign="middle" align="left">P1, 600 cycles</td><td valign="middle" align="right">81.98</td><td valign="middle" align="right">90.22</td><td valign="middle" align="right">91.23</td><td valign="middle" align="right">81.55</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left">NovaSeq 6000</td><td valign="middle" align="left">SP, 500 cycles</td><td valign="middle" align="right">490.72</td><td valign="middle" align="right">85.59</td><td valign="middle" align="right">94.78</td><td valign="middle" align="right">73.61</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></floats-group></article>