<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="preprint">
<?all-math-mml yes?>
<?use-mml?>
<?origin ukpmcpa?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">bioRxiv</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>bioRxiv : the preprint server for biology</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub"/>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">EMS103436</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2020.11.01.363812</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="archive">PPR233572</article-id>
<article-version article-version-type="publisher-id">1</article-version>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Structural basis for repurpose and design of nucleoside drugs for treating COVID-19</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Yin</surname>
<given-names>Wanchao</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN1">*</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Luan</surname>
<given-names>Xiaodong</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN1">*</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>Zhihai</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">5</xref>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN1">*</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Xie</surname>
<given-names>Yuanchao</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN1">*</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zhou</surname>
<given-names>Ziwei</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">5</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A6">6</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>Jia</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Gao</surname>
<given-names>Minqi</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A7">7</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>Xiaoxi</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zhou</surname>
<given-names>Fulai</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>Qingxia</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">5</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>Qingxing</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A8">8</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Shen</surname>
<given-names>Dandan</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A9">9</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>Yan</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A9">9</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A10">10</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Tian</surname>
<given-names>Guanghui</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A11">11</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Aisa</surname>
<given-names>Haji A.</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A6">6</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A12">12</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hu</surname>
<given-names>Tianwen</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A6">6</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A12">12</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wei</surname>
<given-names>Daibao</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A6">6</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A12">12</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Jiang</surname>
<given-names>Yi</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A6">6</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Xiao</surname>
<given-names>Gengfu</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A8">8</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Jiang</surname>
<given-names>Hualiang</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A6">6</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>Leike</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A8">8</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CR1">#</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Yu</surname>
<given-names>Xuekui</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">5</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A6">6</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CR1">#</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Shen</surname>
<given-names>Jingshan</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A6">6</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CR1">#</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>Shuyang</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CR1">#</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Xu</surname>
<given-names>H. Eric</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A6">6</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CR1">#</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="A1">
<label>1</label>The CAS Key Laboratory of Receptor Research, Shanghai Institute of Materia Medica, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Shanghai 201203, China</aff>
<aff id="A2">
<label>2</label>School of Medicine, Tsinghua University, Haidian District, Beijing, China</aff>
<aff id="A3">
<label>3</label>Department of Cardiology, Peking Union Medical College Hospital, Peking Union Medical College and Chinese Academy of Medical Sciences, Beijing, China</aff>
<aff id="A4">
<label>4</label>Tsinghua-Peking Center for Life Sciences, Tsinghua University, Beijing, China</aff>
<aff id="A5">
<label>5</label>Cryo-Electron Microscopy Research Center, Shanghai Institute of Materia Medica, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Shanghai 201203, China</aff>
<aff id="A6">
<label>6</label>University of Chinese Academy of Sciences, Beijing 100049, China</aff>
<aff id="A7">
<label>7</label>WuxiBiortus Biosciences Co. Ltd., 6 Dongsheng West Road, Jiangyin 214437, China</aff>
<aff id="A8">
<label>8</label>State Key Laboratory of Virology, Wuhan Institute of Virology, Center for Biosafety Mega-Science, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Wuhan, Hubei, 430071, P. R. China</aff>
<aff id="A9">
<label>9</label>Department of Biophysics, and Department of Pathology of Sir Run Run Shaw Hospital, Zhejiang University School of Medicine, Hangzhou 310058, China</aff>
<aff id="A10">
<label>10</label>Key Laboratory of Immunity and Inflammatory Diseases of Zhejiang Province, Hangzhou 310058, China</aff>
<aff id="A11">
<label>11</label>Vigonvita Life Science Co., Ltd., Suzhou 215123, China</aff>
<aff id="A12">
<label>12</label>Key Laboratory of Plant Resources and Chemistry in Arid Regions, Xinjiang Technical Institute of Physics and Chemistry, Chinese Academy of Sciences, South Beijing Road 40-1, Urumqi, Xinjiang 830011, P. R. China</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="CR1">
<label>#</label>Co-corresponding authors: H. Eric Xu, <email>eric.xu@simm.ac.cn</email>; or Shuyang Zhang (<email>shuyangzhang103@nrdrs.org</email>); or Jingshan Shen (<email>shenjingshan@simm.ac.cn</email>), or Xuekui Yu (<email>xkyu@simm.ac.cn</email>); or Leike Zhang (<email>zhangleike@wh.iov.cn</email>)</corresp>
<fn id="FN1" fn-type="equal">
<label>*</label>
<p id="P1">These authors contributed equally to this work</p>
</fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted">
<day>04</day>
<month>11</month>
<year>2020</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="preprint">
<day>02</day>
<month>11</month>
<year>2020</year>
</pub-date>
<permissions>
<license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">
<license-p>This work is licensed under a <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">CC BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license</ext-link>.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p id="P2">SARS-CoV-2 has caused a global pandemic of COVID-19 that urgently needs an effective treatment. Nucleoside analog drugs including favipiravir have been repurposed for COVID-19 despite of unclear mechanism of their inhibition of the viral RNA polymerase (RdRp). Here we report the cryo-EM structures of the viral RdRp in complex with favipiravir and two other nucleoside inhibitor drugs ribavirin and penciclovir. Ribavirin and the ribosylated form of favipiravir share a similar ribose scaffold that is distinct from penciclovir. However, the structures reveal that all three inhibitors are covalently linked to the primer strand in a monophosphate form despite the different chemical scaffolds between favipiravir and penciclovir. Surprisingly, the base moieties of these inhibitors can form mismatched pairs with the template strand. Moreover, in view of the clinical disadvantages of remdesivir mainly associated with its prodrug form, we designed several orally-available remdesivir parent nucleoside derivatives, including VV16 that showed 5-fold more potent than remdesivir in inhibition of viral replication. Together, these results demonstrate an unexpected promiscuity of the viral RNA polymerase and provide a basis for repurpose and design of nucleotide analog drugs for COVID-19.</p>
</abstract>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p id="P3">Severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2), which causes the pandemic of COVID-19, has continued to infect many people across the world (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">2</xref>). SARS-CoV-2 is related to the highly pathogenic beta-coronaviruses that include SARS-CoV and Middle East respiratory syndrome coronavirus (MERS-CoV)(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">3</xref>). These viruses are positive-sense, single-stranded RNA viruses and their infections could lead to severe acute respiratory syndrome, which could result in loss of lung function and death. Among these related coronaviruses, SARS-CoV-2 has much higher activity to spread among humans, resulting in a global scale of health crisis, which still needs an effective treatment. Drug development usually requires a decade long of effort and it is unfit for current medical crisis. Repurpose of existing drugs that bypass regular preclinical and clinical research is of tremendous medical importance to combat the pandemics of COVID-19.</p>
<p id="P4">The viral RNA-dependent RNA polymerase (RdRp) is essential for viruses to replicate and has served as a major drug target for antiviral therapy. Numerous nucleotide analogs, including favipiravir(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref>), ribavirin(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref>), and penciclovir(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">8</xref>), have been developed to target the polymerase of different viruses such as influenza virus, hepatitis C virus (HCV), and Zika virus (ZIKV). The recent structure of the SARS-CoV-2 RdRp in complex with RNA substrate and nucleotide inhibitor remdesivir has revealed a conserved active site(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>), which is highly similar to the active site of the RdRp from several viruses, suggesting that nucleotide inhibitors might have broad antiviral activity. Indeed, favipiravir and ribavirin, which are well established drugs for influenza virus and hepatitis C virus (HCV), have been repurposed for the treatment of SARS-CoV-2(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref>). Remdesivir has been approved by FDA for treating COVID-19 and favipiravir has been approved in China, Russia, and India for COVID-19(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref>). In addition, in this paper we also found that penciclovir, a nucleotide analog drug for herpesvirus, is an inhibitor of the SARS-CoV-2 RdRp, despite that penciclovir lacks a ribose scaffold like ribavirin. However, the lack of structural details of how these nucleotide analog drugs are recognized by RdRp has hampered the development of more potent and effective inhibitors to treat SARS-CoV-2 infections. In this paper, we report three structures of the SARS-CoV-2 RdRp in complex with RNA substrate and favipiravir, ribavirin, and penciclovir, respectively. Based on these structures and previous remdesivir-bound structures, we have designed several orally-available derivatives of remdesivir with potent antiviral activity. Together, these results reveal an unexpected promiscuity of the viral RNA polymerase and provide structural mechanisms for repurpose and design of nucleotide analog drugs for treating COVID-19.</p>
<p id="P5">The functional assembly of the SARS-CoV-2 RNA polymerase requires minimal three non-structural proteins, the RdRp subunit nsp12 with two accessary subunits nsp7 and nsp8(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref>). Incubation of the purified nsp12-7-8 complex (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">fig. S1A-S1B</xref>) with a 30-base template, which had been annealed with a 20-base primer (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig.1A</xref>), allowed the primer extension to the same length as the template in the presence of NTP (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig.1B-1D</xref>). Interestingly, we also observed a product with one nucleotide longer than the template, indicating that RdRp may have a template-independent terminal nucleotide transferase activity (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">fig. S1C</xref>). It has been known that nucleotide analog drugs need to be converted into the active triphosphate form (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">fig. S2</xref>). Consistently, incubation of favipiravir, ribavirin, and penciclovir did not inhibit the primer extension by the RdRp (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">fig. S3</xref>). However, when favipiravir, ribavirin, and penciclovir were made with their corresponding triphosphate forms, they were able to inhibit the RdRp primer extension activity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig.1B-1D</xref>). The triphosphate form of favipiravir (FAV-TP), as expected, acted like an ATP analog and was able to inhibit the RdRp extension on a poly-U template (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig.1B</xref>). Unexpectedly, FAV-TP was also able to inhibit the RdRp activity on poly-A, poly-G, and poly-C templates (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig.1B</xref>), indicating that the base analog of favipiravir is able to form non-selective base pairing interactions with A, G, C, U bases. We also noticed that the SARS-CoV-2 RdRp had a relatively low processivity on a poly-G template when compared to poly-U and poly-A templates (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig.1B-1D</xref>).</p>
<p id="P6">In parallel, the triphosphate forms of ribavirin (RBV-TP) and penciclovir (PEV-TP) were also able to inhibit the RdRp primer extension activity. Surprisingly, RBV-TP exerted the most potent inhibition on the poly-G template(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig.1C</xref>), in contrast to the proposed model of ribavirin as a guanosine analog(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref>). PEV-TP showed comparable inhibition on poly-U and poly-C templates (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig.1D</xref>), suggesting that guanine base can form mismatched pairing with pyrimidine base. The potency of PEV-TP is in the same range of FAV-TP and RBV-TP. To corroborate these biochemical data, we tested the ability of favipiravir, ribavirin, and penciclovir to inhibit viral replication in Vero E6 cells, in which the nucleotide prodrugs can be metabolized into the active triphosphate forms. In these cell-based assays, favipiravir, ribavirin, and penciclovir exhibited similar antiviral activity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1E</xref>) with EC<sub>50</sub> values of 96, 40, and 12 μM, respectively. In comparison, remdesivir has an EC<sub>50</sub> value of 1.57 μM in cell-based anti-viral assays (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1E</xref>), suggesting remdesivir is more potent than favipiravir, ribavirin, and penciclovir. However, remdesivir has higher cell toxicity (CC<sub>50</sub>=264 μM) than favipiravir, ribavirin, and penciclovir, all three of them have CC<sub>50</sub> values higher than 1000 μM (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1E</xref>).</p>
<p id="P7">To determine the structural basis of RdRp inhibition, we prepared the purified nsp12-7-8 complex (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">fig. S1A-1B</xref>) in the presence of an RNA template-primer duplex (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">fig. S1D</xref>) and the triphosphate forms of nucleotide inhibitors, which were added in more than 300 fold of molar excess to the RdRp to obtain a stable and completely inhibited complex for cryo-EM studies. For the FAV-bound RdRp complex, we collected over 3,209 micrograph movies of more than 5.303 million particle projections. Of these, 116,511 particles were used to yield a density map of 2.7 Å resolution (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">fig. S4</xref>). For the RBV-bound RdRp complex, we collected over 4,297 micrograph movies of more than 4.974 million particle projections. Of these, 196,511 particles were used to yield a density map of 2.97 Å resolution (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">fig. S5</xref>). For the PEV-bound RdRp complex, we collected over 3,913 micrograph movies of more than 5.240 million particle projections. Of these, 142,242 particles were used to yield a density map of 2.6 Å resolution for the overall conformation, and 139,773 particles were used to yield a density map of 2.74 Å resolution for the extended conformation (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">fig. S6</xref>). Because of the relatively high resolutions of all three structures, the key components of the RdRp complexes are well defined by clear EM density maps (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2A-AC, 2D-2E</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">fig. S7-9</xref>), including the RNA-template-primer duplex, one molecule of nsp12 and nsp7, and two molecules of nsp8.</p>
<p id="P8">The overall structures of the three nucleotide inhibitor-RdRp complexes are similar to each other with the RMSD values less than 0.3 Å for all Cα atoms of nsp12 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">fig. S10</xref>). All three structures also resemble the previous remdesivir bound RdRp complex but the N-terminal NiRAN domain of nsp12 was completely resolved in the current three structures (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">fig. S7E, S8E and S9E</xref>). For the PEV-TP bound RdRp complex, the N-terminal segments of both nsp8 form two extended helices, acting like a pair of chopstick that clamp on the upstream RNA double strand (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">fig. S11</xref>), which is similar to the recent structures of RdRp in a transcribing conformation(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">20</xref>). For all three structures, the nucleotide inhibitors are in their monophosphate forms (FAV-MP, RBV-MP, and PEV-MP), which are located at the catalytic active site and covalently linked to the 3’ end of the primer strand (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2G-I</xref>). In addition, a pyrophosphate and two magnesium ions are observed at the active site in all three structures (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2G-I</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">fig. S7G, S8G and S9G</xref>), similar to the previous remdesivir-bound structure(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref>).</p>
<p id="P9">In addition to the covalent link of the monophosphate forms of the nucleotide inhibitors to the primer strand, the binding poses of these nucleotide inhibitors are stabilized by base pairing and stacking interactions with the double strand RNA, as well as interactions with protein residues at the catalytic center (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2G-I</xref>). For the FAV-bound RdRp complex, FAV-MP mimics an adenosine analog to form two hydrogen bonds with +1 uridine from the template strand (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2G</xref>). In addition, the FAV base forms hydrogen bond with K545 and S682 of nsp12 whereas the phosphor-ribose makes interactions with D623, N691 and the catalytic D760 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2G</xref>). For the RBV-bound RdRp complex, RBV-MP mimics a guanosine analog to form two hydrogen bonds with +1 cytosine from the template strand (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2H</xref>). In addition, the RBV base forms hydrogen bond with K545 and S682 of nsp12, and stacking interaction with R555, whereas the phosphorribose makes interactions with D623, N691 and the catalytic D760, (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2H</xref>). For the PEV-bound RdRp complex, the guanosine from PEV-MP forms two hydrogen bonds with +1 mismatched uridine from the template strand (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2I</xref>). In addition, the guanosine base forms hydrogen bonds with S682 main chain CO of nsp12 whereas the phosphate backbone makes interactions with the catalytic D760 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2I</xref>). The hydroxyl of penciclovir forms additional hydrogen bonds the side chain of D623 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2I</xref>).</p>
<p id="P10">RNA replication by the viral RdRp involves at least two critical conformation states(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">21</xref>), the pre-translocated conformation state in which the newly incorporated nucleotide is the +1 position within the catalytic site and the post-translocated conformation state in which the newly incorporated nucleotide is translocated into the -1 position, which will empty the +1 position to allow a new incoming nucleotide into the catalytic center. Currently the structures of SARS-CoV-2 RdRp have been solved with four different nucleotide inhibitors, FAV, RBV, PEV, and RDV. Comparison of these inhibitor-bound structures with the RdRp structure with native RNA(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">20</xref>) reveals that these nucleotide inhibitors are located at +1 position in the pre-translocated conformation state despite that FAV-TP, RBV-TP, and PEV-TP were added in vast excess during the complex formation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3A</xref>). The positions of the base analogs, ribose and phosphate backbone of FAV-MP, RBV-MP, and RDV-MP are nearly overlapped with each other (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3A</xref>). PEV-MP does not have a ribose but its guanine base and phosphate backbone are also overlapped with FAV-MP and RBV-MP. The concentrations of the triphosphate form of these nucleotide inhibitors used in complex assembly were at 1 mM, which are comparable to the in vivo concentrations of natural NTP, thus it is surprised to observed that only a single base of nucleotide inhibitor was added to the 3’ end of the primer strand despite the availability of the 3’ OH from the nucleotide inhibitors to couple with the incoming 5’ triphosphate of the next inhibitor. Therefore, these inhibitors act like immediate chain terminators in the experimental conditions we used. Our structures are different from a recent structure of the RdRp in complex with RDV-TP in the presence of excess amount of GTP (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3B</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">fig. S12A</xref>), in which RDV-MP is at the -1 position and only one GMP at the +1 position despite the +2 position is a cytosine in the template strand, which is compatible with an incoming GTP. Thus, this inhibitor-RdRp complex is also stalled at the pre-translocated conformation despite an excess amount of native NTP for primer extension. This is in contrast to the RdRp RNA complex in the presence of only natural NTP (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3C-3E</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">fig. S12B-S12D</xref>), which structure reveals a post-translocated conformation, readily to adopted a new nucleotide for primer extension. Despite these structural differences, these nucleotide inhibitors seem to act through a common mechanism by stalling the RdRp complex at the stage of pre-translocated conformation.</p>
<p id="P11">Among the above four nucleotide analog drugs, remdesivir is the first one that has been approved by FDA for COVID-19 through vein injection. This is probably that remdesivir has the most potent EC<sub>50</sub> against SARS-CoV-2 in cell-based assays(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">22</xref>) (EC<sub>50</sub> of remdesivir is ~1-2 μM vs 10-100 μM for FAV, RBV, and PEV, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1E</xref>). However, remdesivir has disadvantages of difficulties in chemical synthesis and obligatory intravenous (IV) injection that requires hospital settings. In addition, pharmacokinetics of remdesivir shows that it is rapidly metabolized into its nucleotide form and it is highly enriched in liver that can cause hepatotoxicity(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">23</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref>). Thus, it has been argued that parent nucleoside of remdesivir should have advantage for COVID-19 treatment(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">25</xref>). Indeed, cell-based inhibition assays of viral replication reveals that the parent nucleoside is about 3-fold more potent than remdesivir (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1E</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4A-B</xref>)(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">22</xref>). The deuterated analog bearing a deuterium atom at the C5 position of the base moiety further improve oral bioavailability (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4A and 4C</xref>). Prodrug modification of the deuterated nucleoside that is esterified with isobutyric acid further improved the viral inhibition potency (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4A and 4B</xref>). Together, the final modified compound X3 has an overall 5-fold potency improvement in inhibiting the viral replication over the original remdesivir (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4A and 4B</xref>).</p>
<p id="P12">More importantly, compound X3 can be delivered via oral route with excellent bioavailability up to 56% (X3, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4C</xref>) and good retention time. In contrast to liver-enriched remdesivir, X3 achieves a well distribution of the nucleoside and nucleotide metabolite in the blood plasma as well as in many critical organs including lung that is vulnerable to SARS-CoV-2 infection, suggesting that X3 is a good drug candidate for treating COVID-19. A pilot experiment of inhibition of SARS-CoV-2 in mice transfected with human ACE2 demonstrated that mice treated with an acid salt form of X3 (development code: VV116) had 50-fold lower in viral load than the untreated mice (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig S13A-C</xref>). The lung tissues of untreated mice were positive in immune staining of viral antigen of N protein but were negative in lung tissues from VV116-treated mice (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig S13D</xref>). Together, these initial data demonstrated the antiviral efficacy of VV116 in the mouse model transfected with human ACE2.</p>
<p id="P13">The ongoing COVID-19 pandemic by no-stop infections of SARS-CoV-2 has caused a global health crisis that urgently request for an effective treatment. Because drug development normally takes a decade long of preclinical and clinical research, which is clearly unfit for current medical emergency. Drug repurposing that could bypass regular preclinical and clinical research is of critical importance in the current situation to combat the pandemics of COVID-19. In this paper, we demonstrated three existing drugs, favipiravir, ribavirin, and penciclovir, all nucleotide analogs, are inhibitors of the SARS-CoV-2 RdRp, an essential enzyme for the viral replication. We have further determined the structures of these three nucleotide analog drugs in complex with the SARS-CoC-2 RdRp and a template-primer RNA. Despite that penciclovir does not have a ribose scaffold that is shared by favipiravir and ribavirin, all nucleotide inhibitors are covalently linked to the primer strand in a monophosphate form, in which the RdRp RNA template-primer complex is stalled at the pre-translocated conformation state, revealing a common RdRp-inhibition mechanism that is also shared by the remdesivir bound RdRp complex. In addition, we discovered a terminal nucleotide transferase activity of the SARS-CoV-2 RdRp, which can add an additional nucleotide to the primer strand beyond the template end. The SARS-CoV-2 RdRp also display a remarkable promiscuity with respect to the incorporation of nucleotides that are unmatched with bases from the template strand. Based on these structures and previous remdesivir-bound structures, we designed several orally-available remdesivir derivatives that showed potent inhibition of viral replication in cell-based assays and animal models of SARS-CoV-2 infections. Our results provide a rational basis for repurpose of favipiravir, ribavirin, and penciclovir for treating COVID-19. The structures also provide a set of templates for designing the next generation of orally-available nucleotide analog drugs for COVID-19.</p>
<sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="SM">
<title>Supplementary Material</title>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1">
<label>Supplementary Materials</label>
<media xlink:href="EMS103436-supplement-Supplementary_Materials.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" id="N66551" position="anchor"/>
</supplementary-material>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack id="S1">
<title>Acknowledgments</title>
<p>The cryo-EM data were collected at the Cryo-Electron Microscopy Research Center, Shanghai Institute of Materia Medica. This work was partially supported by National Key R&amp;D Program of China (2020YFC0861000), CAMS Innovation Fund for Medical Sciences No. 2020-I2M-CoV19-001, and Tsinghua University-Peking University Center for Life Sciences 045-160321001 to S. Z.; the National Key R&amp;D Programs of China 2018YFA0507002; Shanghai Municipal Science and Technology Major Project 2019SHZDZX02 and XDB37030103 to H.E.X.; Zhejiang University special scientific research fund for COVID-19 prevention and control E33 and the National Science Foundation of China 81922071 to Y.Z.; the 2020 ANSO Collaborative Research Project (ANSO-CR-SP-2020-03) to J. S.; the 100 Talents Program of the Chinese Academy of Sciences, Chinese Academy of Sciences grant (XDA12010317), Natural Science Foundation of Shanghai (18ZR1447700) to X.Y; the National Natural Science Foundation of China (31900869) and Shanghai Sailing Program (19YF1456800) to Z.L; National Science &amp; Technology Major Project “Key New Drug Creation and Manufacturing Program” of China (2018ZX09711002), Science and Technology Commission of Shanghai Municipal 20431900100 and Jack Ma Foundation 2020-CMKYGG-05 to H.J.; National Natural Science Foundation 31770796, National Science and Technology Major Project 2018ZX09711002, and K.C. Wong Education Foundation to Y.J, the National Natural Science Foundation of China (31970165) to L. Z.</p>
</ack>
<sec id="S2" sec-type="data-availability">
<title>Data and materials availability</title>
<p id="P14">Density maps and structure coordinates have been deposited with immediate release. The accession numbers of Electron Microscopy Database and the Protein Data Bank are EMD-XXXX and PDB ID XXXX for the FAV-RdRp complex; EMD-XXX and PDB ID XXXX for the RBV-RdRp complex; EMD-XXX/ and PDB ID XXXX/ for the two PEV-RdRp complexes. Materials are available up on request.</p>
</sec>
<fn-group>
<fn fn-type="con" id="FN2">
<p id="P15">
<bold>Author contributions:</bold> W.Y. designed the expression constructs, purified the RdRp complex, prepared samples and cryo-EM grids, performed data collection and processing toward the structure determination, analyzed the structures, and prepared figures and manuscript. X.L. designed RdRp activity assays, participated in data interpretation and figure preparation; Z.L., Z.Z., Q. W., and X.Y. evaluated the specimen by negative-stain EM, screened the cryo-EM conditions, prepared the cryo-EM grids and collected cryo-EM images, performed data processing, density map calculations, model building, and figure preparation; Y.Z. and D.-D.S, analyzed EM data; Y.X., G.T., H.A.A., T.H., D.W., and J.S. designed and prepared nucleotide derivatives; J.L. performed PK of nucleotide derivatives; L.Z., Q.W., and G.X. designed and performed cell-based viral inhibition assays; X. W., F. Z., and M.G. participated in expression, purification and functional assays of the RdRp; Y.J. participated in experimental design and manuscript editing; H.J. conceived and coordinated the project; S.Z. conceived the project, initiated collaboration with H.E.X. and supervised X.L.; H.E.X. conceived and supervised the project, analyzed the structures, and wrote the manuscript with inputs from all authors.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="FN3" fn-type="conflict">
<p id="P16">
<bold>Competing interests:</bold> The authors declare no competing interests. Y.X. and J.S. filed a patent application on nucleotide derivatives.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<ref id="R1">
<label>1</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Gorbalenya</surname>
<given-names>AE</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>Severe acute respiratory syndrome-related coronavirus: The species and its viruses – a statement of the Coronavirus Study Group</article-title>
<source>bioRxiv</source>
<year>2020</year>
<comment>2020.2002.2007.937862</comment>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R2">
<label>2</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Dong</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Du</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gardner</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>An interactive web-based dashboard to track COVID-19 in real time</article-title>
<source>The Lancet Infectious Diseases</source>
<year>2020</year>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R3">
<label>3</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>Q</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Guo</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Emerging coronaviruses: Genome structure, replication, and pathogenesis</article-title>
<source>Journal of medical virology</source>
<year>2020</year>
<volume>92</volume>
<fpage>418</fpage>
<lpage>423</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R4">
<label>4</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Furuta</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Komeno</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Nakamura</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Favipiravir (T-705), a broad spectrum inhibitor of viral RNA polymerase</article-title>
<source>Proc Jpn Acad Ser B Phys Biol Sci</source>
<year>2017</year>
<volume>93</volume>
<fpage>449</fpage>
<lpage>463</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R5">
<label>5</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hayden</surname>
<given-names>FG</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Shindo</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Influenza virus polymerase inhibitors in clinical development</article-title>
<source>Curr Opin Infect Dis</source>
<year>2019</year>
<volume>32</volume>
<fpage>176</fpage>
<lpage>186</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R6">
<label>6</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Te</surname>
<given-names>HS</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Randall</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Jensen</surname>
<given-names>DM</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Mechanism of action of ribavirin in the treatment of chronic hepatitis C</article-title>
<source>Gastroenterol Hepatol (N Y)</source>
<year>2007</year>
<volume>3</volume>
<fpage>218</fpage>
<lpage>225</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R7">
<label>7</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Mathur</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kottilil</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wilson</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Use of Ribavirin for Hepatitis C Treatment in the Modern Direct-acting Antiviral Era</article-title>
<source>J Clin Transl Hepatol</source>
<year>2018</year>
<volume>l6</volume>
<fpage>431</fpage>
<lpage>437</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R8">
<label>8</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Pastuch-Gawołek</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gillner</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Król</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Walczak</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Wandzik</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Selected nucleos(t)ide-based prescribed drugs and their multi-target activity</article-title>
<source>European journal of pharmacology</source>
<year>2019</year>
<volume>865</volume>
<fpage>172747</fpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R9">
<label>9</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Yin</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>Structural basis for inhibition of the RNA-dependent RNA polymerase from SARS-Cov-2 by remdesivir</article-title>
<source>Science</source>
<year>2020</year>
<volume>368</volume>
<fpage>1499</fpage>
<lpage>1504</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R10">
<label>10</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>Q</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>Structural basis for RNA replication by the SARS-CoV-2 polymerase</article-title>
<source>Cell</source>
<year>2020</year>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R11">
<label>11</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Elfiky</surname>
<given-names>AA</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Ribavirin, Remdesivir, Sofosbuvir, Galidesivir, and Tenofovir against SARS-CoV-2 RNA dependent RNA polymerase (RdRp): A molecular docking study</article-title>
<source>Life sciences</source>
<year>2020</year>
<fpage>117592</fpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R12">
<label>12</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Agrawal</surname>
<given-names>U</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Raju</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Udwadia</surname>
<given-names>ZF</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Favipiravir: A new and emerging antiviral option in COVID-19</article-title>
<source>Med J Armed Forces India</source>
<year>2020</year>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mjafi.2020.1008.1004</pub-id>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R13">
<label>13</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Shannon</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>Favipiravir strikes the SARS-CoV-2 at its Achilles heel, the RNA polymerase</article-title>
<source>bioRxiv : the preprint server for biology</source>
<year>2020</year>
<comment>2020.2005.2015.098731</comment>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R14">
<label>14</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hung</surname>
<given-names>IF-N</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>Triple combination of interferon beta-1b, lopinavir–ritonavir, and ribavirin in the treatment of patients admitted to hospital with COVID-19: an open-label, randomised, phase 2 trial</article-title>
<source>The Lancet</source>
<year>2020</year>
<volume>395</volume>
<fpage>1695</fpage>
<lpage>1704</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R15">
<label>15</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Agrawal</surname>
<given-names>U</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Raju</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Udwadia</surname>
<given-names>ZF</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Favipiravir: A new and emerging antiviral option in COVID-19</article-title>
<source>Med J Armed Forces India</source>
<year>2020</year>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R16">
<label>16</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hu</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Guo</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Zhou</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Shi</surname>
<given-names>Z-L</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Characteristics of SARS-CoV-2 and COVID-19</article-title>
<source>Nature Reviews Microbiology</source>
<year>2020</year>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R17">
<label>17</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Kirchdoerfer</surname>
<given-names>RN</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ward</surname>
<given-names>AB</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Structure of the SARS-CoV nsp12 polymerase bound to nsp7 and nsp8 co-factors</article-title>
<source>Nat Commun</source>
<year>2019</year>
<volume>10</volume>
<fpage>2342</fpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R18">
<label>18</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Quecini</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Lopes</surname>
<given-names>ML</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Pacheco</surname>
<given-names>FTH</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ongarelli</surname>
<given-names>MDG</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Ribavirin, a guanosine analogue mammalian antiviral agent, impairs tomato spotted wilt virus multiplicationin tobacco cell cultures</article-title>
<source>Archives of Phytopathology and Plant Protection</source>
<year>2008</year>
<volume>41</volume>
<fpage>1</fpage>
<lpage>13</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R19">
<label>19</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hillen</surname>
<given-names>HS</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>Structure of replicating SARS-CoV-2 polymerase</article-title>
<source>Nature</source>
<year>2020</year>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R20">
<label>20</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>Structural Basis for Helicase-Polymerase Coupling in the SARS-CoV-2 Replication-Transcription Complex</article-title>
<source>Cell</source>
<year>2020</year>
<volume>82</volume>
<fpage>1560</fpage>
<lpage>1573.e1513</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R21">
<label>21</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Gong</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Visualizing the Nucleotide Addition Cycle of Viral RNA-Dependent RNA Polymerase</article-title>
<source>Viruses</source>
<year>2018</year>
<volume>10</volume>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R22">
<label>22</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>Remdesivir and chloroquine effectively inhibit the recently emerged novel coronavirus (2019-nCoV) in vitro</article-title>
<source>Cell research</source>
<year>2020</year>
<volume>30</volume>
<fpage>269</fpage>
<lpage>271</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R23">
<label>23</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Jorgensen</surname>
<given-names>SCJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kebriaei</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Dresser</surname>
<given-names>LD</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Remdesivir: Review of Pharmacology, Pre-clinical Data, and Emerging Clinical Experience for COVID-19</article-title>
<source>Pharmacotherapy</source>
<year>2020</year>
<volume>40</volume>
<fpage>659</fpage>
<lpage>671</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R24">
<label>24</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zampino</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>Liver injury in remdesivir-treated COVID-19 patients</article-title>
<source>Hepatology international</source>
<year>2020</year>
<fpage>1</fpage>
<lpage>3</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R25">
<label>25</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Yan</surname>
<given-names>VC</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Muller</surname>
<given-names>FL</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Advantages of the Parent Nucleoside GS-441524 over Remdesivir for Covid-19 Treatment</article-title>
<source>ACS medicinal chemistry letters</source>
<year>2020</year>
<volume>11</volume>
<fpage>1361</fpage>
<lpage>1366</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R26">
<label>26</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Mastronarde</surname>
<given-names>DN</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Automated electron microscope tomography using robust prediction of specimen movements</article-title>
<source>J Struct Biol</source>
<year>2005</year>
<volume>152</volume>
<fpage>36</fpage>
<lpage>51</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R27">
<label>27</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zheng</surname>
<given-names>SQ</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>MotionCor2: anisotropic correction of beam-induced motion for improved cryo-electron microscopy</article-title>
<source>Nature methods</source>
<year>2017</year>
<volume>14</volume>
<fpage>331</fpage>
<lpage>332</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R28">
<label>28</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Rohou</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Grigorieff</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>CTFFIND4: Fast and accurate defocus estimation from electron micrographs</article-title>
<source>J Struct Biol</source>
<year>2015</year>
<volume>192</volume>
<fpage>216</fpage>
<lpage>221</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R29">
<label>29</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zivanov</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>New tools for automated high-resolution cryo-EM structure determination in RELION-3</article-title>
<source>Elife</source>
<year>2018</year>
<volume>7</volume>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R30">
<label>30</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Punjani</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rubinstein</surname>
<given-names>JL</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Fleet</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Brubaker</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>cryoSPARC: algorithms for rapid unsupervised cryo-EM structure determination</article-title>
<source>Nature methods</source>
<year>2017</year>
<volume>14</volume>
<fpage>290</fpage>
<lpage>296</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R31">
<label>31</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Rosenthal</surname>
<given-names>PB</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Henderson</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Optimal determination of particle orientation, absolute hand, and contrast loss in single-particle electron cryomicroscopy</article-title>
<source>J Mol Biol</source>
<year>2003</year>
<volume>333</volume>
<fpage>721</fpage>
<lpage>745</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R32">
<label>32</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Pettersen</surname>
<given-names>EF</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>UCSF chimera - A visualization system for exploratory research and analysis</article-title>
<source>J Comput Chem</source>
<year>2004</year>
<volume>25</volume>
<fpage>1605</fpage>
<lpage>1612</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R33">
<label>33</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Emsley</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Cowtan</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Coot: model-building tools for molecular graphics</article-title>
<source>Acta Crystallogr D</source>
<year>2004</year>
<volume>60</volume>
<fpage>2126</fpage>
<lpage>2132</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R34">
<label>34</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Adams</surname>
<given-names>PD</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>PHENIX: a comprehensive Python-based system for macromolecular structure solution</article-title>
<source>Acta crystallographica. Section D, Biological crystallography</source>
<year>2010</year>
<volume>66</volume>
<fpage>213</fpage>
<lpage>221</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R35">
<label>35</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>VB</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>MolProbity: all-atom structure validation for macromolecular crystallography</article-title>
<source>Acta crystallographica. Section D, Biological crystallography</source>
<year>2010</year>
<volume>66</volume>
<fpage>12</fpage>
<lpage>21</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R36">
<label>36</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Goddard</surname>
<given-names>TD</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>UCSF ChimeraX: Meeting modern challenges in visualization and analysis</article-title>
<source>Protein Sci</source>
<year>2018</year>
<volume>27</volume>
<fpage>14</fpage>
<lpage>25</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
<floats-group>
<boxed-text id="BX1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
<caption>
<title>One Sentence Summary</title>
</caption>
<p>Cryo-EM structures of the RNA polymerase of SARS-CoV-2 reveals the basis for repurposing of old nucleotide drugs to treat COVID-19.</p>
</boxed-text>
<fig id="F1" position="float">
<label>Fig. 1</label>
<caption>
<title>Specific Inhibition of RdRp by nucleotide drugs.</title>
<p>A, Diagram of the 30-base template and 20-base primer duplex RNAs with a FAM at the 5’ of the primer used in the gel-based elongation assay.</p>
<p>B-D, Inhibitions of RNA elongation with different substrates by FAV-TP (B), RBV-TP (C), and PEV-TP (D). The EP means the elongated product, while the P means the primer RNA strand.</p>
<p>E, Inhibition of SARS-CoV-2 replication (EC<sub>50</sub>) and cellular toxicity (CC<sub>50</sub>) of remdesivir, favipiravir, ribavirin, and penciclovir.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="EMS103436-f001"/>
</fig>
<fig id="F2" position="float">
<label>Figure 2</label>
<caption>
<title>Cryo-EM Structures of the RdRp complex with RNA and nucleotide inhibitors</title>
<p>A-F, the cryo-EM map and structure of the nsp12-nsp7-nsp8-template-primer RNA complex bound to FAV (A and D), RBV (B and E), and PEV (C and F).</p>
<p>G-I, A close view of the RdRp active site, showing the covalently bound FAV-MP (G), RBV-MP (H), PEV-MP (I), pyrophosphate, and magnesium ions.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="EMS103436-f002"/>
</fig>
<fig id="F3" position="float">
<label>Figure 3</label>
<caption>
<title>A common inhibition mechanism of nucleotide inhibitors</title>
<p>A, Comparisons of FAV/RBV/PEV bound SARS-CoV-2 RdRp complex with the RDV bound SARS-CoV-2 RdRp complex (PDB ID: 7BV2), with a close view of the RdRp active site, showing nucleotide inhibitors are covalently linked at the +1 site of the primer RNA strands.</p>
<p>B-E, A close view of the RdRp active site from comparisons of FAV bound SARS-CoV-2 RdRp complex with the RDV bound SARS-CoV-2 RdRp complex (PDB ID: 7C2K, B), RNA bound SARS-CoV-2 RdRp complex (PDB ID: 7BZF, C), RNA bound SARS-CoV-2 RdRp complex (PDB ID: 6XEZ, D), RNA bound SARS-CoV-2 RdRp complex (PDB ID: 6YYT, E).</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="EMS103436-f003"/>
</fig>
<fig id="F4" position="float">
<label>Figure 4</label>
<caption>
<title>Modifications of GS-441524 provided novel and promising anti-SARS-CoV-2 nucleotide analogs</title>
<p>(A) The chemical structures of GS-441524, the deuterated derivative X1 and two isobutyrate prodrugs (X2 and X3) of X1.</p>
<p>(B) Inhibition of SARS-CoV-2 replication and cellular toxicity of GS-441524, X1, X2 and X3.</p>
<p>(C) Mean plasma concentrations of the corresponding nucleosides, following single intravenous (2 mg/Kg) and oral (10 mg/Kg) administration to SD rats</p>
<p>(D) Tissue Distribution of X1, X1-MP, and X1-TP after oral administration of X3 to CD-1 mice at a single dose of 200 mg/kg (n = 5, Mean ± SD).</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="EMS103436-f004"/>
</fig>
</floats-group>
</article>
