<!DOCTYPE article
 PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" article-type="preprint"><?all-math-mml yes?><?use-mml?><?origin ukpmcpa?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">bioRxiv</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>bioRxiv : the preprint server for biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub"/></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">EMS108620</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2020.12.13.422511</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="archive">PPR254336</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="europepmc-category"><subject>Covid-19</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Hepatitis C Virus Drugs Simeprevir and Grazoprevir Synergize with Remdesivir to Suppress SARS-CoV-2 Replication in Cell Culture</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bafna</surname><given-names>Khushboo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN1">#</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>Kris</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN1">#</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Harish</surname><given-names>Balasubramanian</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rosales</surname><given-names>Romel</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ramelot</surname><given-names>Theresa A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Acton</surname><given-names>Thomas B.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Moreno</surname><given-names>Elena</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kehrer</surname><given-names>Thomas</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Miorin</surname><given-names>Lisa</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Royer</surname><given-names>Catherine A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>García-Sastre</surname><given-names>Adolfo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">5</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CR1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Krug</surname><given-names>Robert M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A6">6</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CR1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Montelione</surname><given-names>Gaetano T.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CR1">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Department of Chemistry and Chemical Biology, and Center for Biotechnology and Interdisciplinary Sciences, Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute, Troy, New York, 12180 USA</aff><aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Department of Microbiology, and Global Health and Emerging Pathogens Institute, Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai, New York, NY10029, USA</aff><aff id="A3"><label>3</label>Department of Biology, and Center for Biotechnology and Interdisciplinary Sciences, Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute, Troy, New York, 12180 USA</aff><aff id="A4"><label>4</label>Department of Medicine, Division of Infectious Diseases, Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai, New York, NY 10029, USA</aff><aff id="A5"><label>5</label>The Tisch Cancer Institute, Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai, New York, NY 10029, USA</aff><aff id="A6"><label>6</label>Department of Molecular Biosciences, John Ring LaMontagne Center for Infectious Disease, Institute for Cellular and Molecular Biology, University of Texas at Austin, Austin, Texas 78712 USA</aff><author-notes><corresp id="CR1">
<label>*</label>Correspondence: <email>monteg3@rpi.edu</email>, <email>rkrug@austin.utexas.edu</email>, <email>adolfo.garcia-sastre@mssm.edu</email>
</corresp><fn id="FN1" fn-type="equal"><label>#</label><p id="P1">These two investigators made equal contributions to this project.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted"><day>19</day><month>12</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="preprint"><day>14</day><month>12</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><permissions><ali:free_to_read/><license><ali:license_ref>https://europepmc.org/downloads/openaccess</ali:license_ref><license-p>This preprint is made available via the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://europepmc.org/downloads/openaccess">Europe PMC open access subset</ext-link>, for unrestricted research re-use and secondary analysis in any form or by any means with acknowledgement of the original preprint source.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><title>Summary</title><p id="P2">Effective control of COVID-19 requires antivirals directed against SARS-CoV-2 virus. Here we assess ten available HCV protease inhibitor drugs as potential SARS-CoV-2 antivirals. There is a striking structural similarity of the substrate binding clefts of SARS-CoV-2 M<sup>pro</sup> and HCV NS3/4A proteases, and virtual docking experiments show that all ten HCV drugs can potentially bind into the M<sup>pro</sup> binding cleft. Seven of these HCV drugs inhibit SARS-CoV-2 M<sup>pro</sup> protease activity, while four dock well into the PL<sup>pro</sup> substrate binding cleft and inhibit PL<sup>pro</sup> protease activity. These same seven HCV drugs inhibit SARS-CoV-2 virus replication in Vero and/or human cells, demonstrating that HCV drugs that inhibit M<sup>pro</sup>, or both M<sup>pro</sup> and PL<sup>pro</sup>, suppress virus replication. Two HCV drugs, simeprevir and grazoprevir synergize with the viral polymerase inhibitor remdesivir to inhibit virus replication, thereby increasing remdesivir inhibitory activity as much as 10-fold.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>COVID-19</kwd><kwd>SARS-CoV-2 3CL/M<sup>pro</sup> Protease</kwd><kwd>SARS-CoV-2 PL Protease</kwd><kwd>HCV protease inhibitors</kwd><kwd>molecular docking</kwd><kwd>SARS-CoV-2 virus replication</kwd><kwd>synergism</kwd><kwd>remdesivir</kwd><kwd>antivirals</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="S1" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p id="P3">The COVID-19 pandemic has caused more than one million deaths worldwide and crippled the global economy. Effective control of the SARS-CoV-2 coronavirus that causes COVID-19 requires antivirals, especially until safe and effective vaccines are available. Considering the urgency to identify effective antiviral drugs, and the usually lengthy process involved in approving candidate drugs for human use, our goal is to identify existing drugs already approved for use in humans that can be repurposed as safe and effective therapeutics for treating COVID-19 infections, and which may also be useful as lead molecules for novel drug development.</p><p id="P4">SARS-CoV-2 is an enveloped RNA virus which causes COVID-19 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">Wu et al., 2020</xref>). Its genome is comprised of a single, large positive-sense single-stranded RNA, which is directly translated by host cell ribosomes. The SARS-CoV-2 genome encodes 4 structural proteins, 16 non-structural proteins (NSPs) which carry out crucial intracellular functions, and 9 accessory proteins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">Gordon et al., 2020</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">Wu et al., 2020</xref>). Many of these proteins, and their host binding partners, are potential targets for development of antivirals for SARS-CoV-2. For example, the repurposed drug remdesivir, which inhibits the viral RNA-dependent RNA polymerase, is the current FDA-approved antiviral standard of care for COVID-19 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">Eastman et al., 2020</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">Pan et al., 2020</xref>).</p><p id="P5">Translation of the viral genomic RNA results in the biosynthesis of two polyproteins that are processed into the 16 separate NSPs by two virus-encoded cysteine proteases, the papain-like protease (PL<sup>pro</sup>) and a 3C-like protease (3CL<sup>pro</sup>). The latter is also referred to as the main protease (M<sup>pro</sup>). M<sup>pro</sup> and PL<sup>pro</sup> are essential for the virus life cycle, specifically including the production of a functional viral RNA polymerase, and are hence attractive targets for antiviral development. M<sup>pro</sup> cleavages generate several NSPs including the three subunits nsp7, nsp8 and nsp12 of the viral RNA polymerase complex, as well as nsp4 and nsp6 integral membrane proteins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">Peng et al., 2020</xref>). PL<sup>pro</sup> cleavages generate integral membrane nsp3 protein. The nsp3 – nsp4 – nsp6 complex is required for forming replication organelles, also known as double membrane vesicles, that are required for the function of the viral RNA polymerase (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">Angelini et al., 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">Oudshoorn et al., 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32">Snijder et al., 2020</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35">Wolff et al., 2020a</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36">Wolff et al., 2020b</xref>). Considering that both M<sup>pro</sup> and PL<sup>pro</sup> generate either the RNA polymerase itself, or the replication organelles required for polymerase function, we reasoned that inhibitors of one or both of these proteases might be synergistic with inhibitors of the viral polymerase, such as remdesivir.</p><p id="P6">We observed that the substrate binding cleft and active site of the SARS-CoV-2 M<sup>pro</sup> has remarkable structural similarity with the active site of the hepatitis C virus (HCV) NS3/4A protease, suggesting that drugs that inhibit the HCV protease might also inhibit SARS-CoV-2 M<sup>pro</sup> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">Bafna et al., 2020</xref>). Consistent with this hypothesis, recent studies have reported that one of these available HCV drugs, boceprevir, inhibits M<sup>pro</sup> proteolytic activity and SARS-CoV-2 replication in Vero cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">Anson et al., 2020</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">Fu et al., 2020</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">Ma et al., 2020</xref>). Several other HCV protease inhibitors have also been reported to inhibit M<sup>pro</sup> proteolytic activity to various extents (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">Anson et al., 2020</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">Fu et al., 2020</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">Ma et al., 2020</xref>), while other studies report that some of these same HCV protease inhibitors did not significantly inhibit M<sup>pro</sup> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">Fu et al., 2020</xref>).</p><p id="P7">In this study we assess the abilities of ten available HCV protease inhibitors to suppress the replication of SARS-CoV-2. Virtual docking experiments predict that all ten HCV drugs can bind snuggly into the M<sup>pro</sup> binding cleft with docking scores comparable to a known M<sup>pro</sup> inhibitor, suggesting that any of these ten HCV drugs are potential inhibitors of M<sup>pro</sup>. Surprisingly, we found that some of these HCV drugs also dock well into the PL<sup>pro</sup> substrate binding cleft. Seven of these HCV drugs inhibit both SARS-CoV-2 M<sup>pro</sup> protease activity, and SARS-CoV-2 virus replication in Vero and/or human 293T cells expressing the SARS-CoV-2 ACE2 receptor. Three of these seven also inhibit PL<sup>pro</sup> protease activity. Consequently, HCV drugs that inhibit M<sup>pro</sup>, or inhibit both M<sup>pro</sup> and PL<sup>pro</sup>, can suppress SARS-CoV-2 virus replication, v<italic>iz,</italic> boceprevir (BOC), narlaprevir (NAR), vaniprevir (VAN), telaprevir (TEL), simeprevir (SIM), grazoprevir (GRZ), and asunaprevir (ASU).</p><p id="P8">Further, we demonstrate that two HCV drugs which inhibit the proteolytic activities of both M<sup>pro</sup> and PL<sup>pro</sup>, simeprevir and grazoprevir, act synergistically with remdesivir to inhibit SARS-CoV-2 virus replication, thereby increasing remdesivir antiviral activity as much as 10-fold. In contrast, boceprevir, which inhibits M<sup>pro</sup> but not PL<sup>pro</sup>, acts additively, rather than synergistically with remdesivir to inhibit virus replication. Simeprevir provides synergy with remdesivir at significantly lower concentrations than grazoprevir. Our results suggest that the combination of a HCV protease inhibitor with a RNA polymerase inhibitor could potentially function as an antiviral against SARS-CoV-2. In particular, the combination of two FDA-approved drugs, namely, simeprevir and remdesivir, could potentially function as a therapeutic for COVID-19 while more specific SARS-CoV-2 antivirals are being developed. More generally, our results strongly motivate further studies of the potential use of M<sup>pro</sup> and/or PL<sup>pro</sup> protease inhibitors in combination with RNA polymerase inhibitors as antivirals against SARS-CoV-2.</p></sec><sec id="S2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="S3"><title>Similarity of the substrate-binding clefts and active sites of SARS-CoV-2M<sup>pro</sup> and HCV protease NS3/4A</title><p id="P9">The SARS-CoV-2 main protease (M<sup>pro</sup>) is a 67.6 kDa homodimeric cysteine protease with three domains (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">Jin et al., 2020</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39">Zhang et al., 2020b</xref>). Domains I and II adopt a double β-barrel fold, with the substrate binding site located in a shallow cleft between two antiparallel β-barrels of Domain I and II (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1A</xref>). C-terminal domain III stabilizes the homodimer. The fold architecture of domains I and II are similar to picornavirus cysteine proteases and chymotrypsin serine proteases (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">Anand et al., 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">Gorbalenya et al., 1989</xref>). A three-dimensional structural similarity search of the Protein Data Bank using the <italic>DALI</italic> program (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">Holm and Sander, 1993</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">1999</xref>), with domains I and II (excluding domain III) of the SARS-CoV-2 M<sup>pro</sup> as the three-dimensional structural query, identified several proteases, including the HCV NS3/4A serine protease, as structurally similar. These two enzymes have a structural similarity Z score (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">Holm and Sander, 1993</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">1999</xref>) of +8.4, and overall backbone root-mean-squared deviation for structurally similar regions of ~ 3.1 Å. The HCV serine protease also has a double β-barrel fold, with relative orientations of several secondary structure elements similar to those of the SARS-CoV-2 M<sup>pro</sup> cysteine protease, and a substrate binding site located in a shallow cleft between its two six-to eight-stranded antiparallel β-barrels (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1B</xref>). Superimposition of the analogous backbone structures of these two proteases results in superimposition of their substrate binding clefts and their active-site catalytic residues, His41 / Cys145 of the SARS-CoV-2 M<sup>pro</sup> cysteine protease and His57 / Ser139 of the HCV NS3/4A serine protease (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1C</xref>). Because of these structural similarities, we proposed that some HCV protease inhibitors might bind well into the substrate binding cleft of the SARS-CoV-2 M<sup>pro</sup> and inhibit virus replication.</p></sec><sec id="S4"><title>Docking the M<sup>pro</sup> inhibitor 13b into the substrate binding cleft of M<sup>pro</sup> validates the <italic>AutoDock</italic> docking protocol</title><p id="P10">The potential of HCV inhibitors to bind into the substrate-binding cleft of M<sup>pro</sup> was assessed using <italic>AutoDock</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">Forli et al., 2016</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">Morris et al., 2009</xref>). To test the validity of our docking protocol, we carried out docking of a previously described inhibitor of the SARS-CoV-2 M<sup>pro</sup>, compound 13b (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Figure S1A</xref>), that also inhibits virus replication (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38">Zhang et al., 2020a</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39">Zhang et al., 2020b</xref>). Details of these control docking studies are provided in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Figures S1A – D</xref>, and in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Results</xref>.</p><p id="P11">In the 1.75-Å X-ray crystal structure of the 13b-M<sub>pro</sub> complex (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39">Zhang et al., 2020b</xref>), approximately 50% of the 13b compound forms a reversible thiohemiketal covalent bond with the Sγatom of catalytic residue Cys145 of the protease (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39">Zhang et al., 2020b</xref>). The contribution of this partial covalent bond formation is difficult to assess, and our docking calculations determine only how well these drugs fit into the active site without the additional stabilization energy that may result from any covalent bond formation. The best-scoring docked conformation of 13b (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Figure S1C</xref>), has an <italic>AutoDock</italic> binding energy of −9.17 kcal/mol, and is similar but not identical to the pose observed in the X-ray crystal structure. Because the experimentally-determined pose is often not the one with the lowest docking energy, but rather is found among other highly-ranked poses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">Kolb et al., 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">Kolb and Irwin, 2009</xref>), we also examined other low energy poses. One such pose, which has a slightly higher binding energy of -9.03 kcal/mol, is almost identical to the pose observed in the crystal structure (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Figure S1D</xref>). Hence, binding poses very similar to that observed in the crystal structure are indeed included among the low energy poses generated by our <italic>AutoDock</italic> protocol.</p></sec><sec id="S5"><title>HCV protease inhibitors are predicted to bind snuggly into the substrate binding cleft of M<sup>pro</sup>
</title><p id="P12">Having validated the use of <italic>AutoDock</italic> for docking of inhibitor 13b to M<sup>pro</sup>, and determining a representative <italic>AutoDock</italic> score for functionally-inhibitory binding (~ −9.0 kcal / mol) we carried out docking simulations with 10 HCV NS3/4A protease inhibitor drugs (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27">Ozen et al., 2019</xref>). These 10 drugs have been approved for at least Phase 1 clinical trials, and some are FDA-approved prescription drugs used in treating HCV-infected patients (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). The resulting docking scores are summarized in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1D</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table S1</xref>; and details of these docking poses are summarized in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table S2</xref>. These results demonstrate that all of these HCV protease inhibitors have the potential to bind snuggly into the binding cleft of M<sup>pro</sup>, with extensive hydrogen-bonded and hydrophobic contacts, and predicted <italic>AutoDock</italic> energies of -8.37 to -11.01 kcal/mol, comparable to those obtained for the functional 13b inhibitor (~ −9.0 kcal/mol).</p><p id="P13">As we were preparing our work for publication, a 1.44 Å X-ray crystal structure of the complex of boceprevir bound to the SARS-CoV-2 M<sup>pro</sup> was released in the Protein Data Bank [PDB id 6WNP (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">Anson et al., 2020</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">Anson and Mesecar, 2020</xref>)]. The boceprevir pose observed in this X-ray crystal structure is almost identical to the lowest energy pose (−9.03 kcal/mol) predicted by <italic>AutoDock</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1E</xref>). In addition, both the docked and crystal structure binding poses for boceprevir near the active site of M<sup>pro</sup> are very similar to its binding pose in the substrate binding cleft of HCV protease (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1F</xref>), with an essentially identical hydrogen-bonding network between boceprevir and corresponding residues in each protease. Boceprevir is a alpha-ketoamide which potentially forms a covalent bond with the active site residue Cys145. Although this docking protocol does not include energetics or restraints for covalent bond formation, in the low energy pose of boceprevir bound to M<sup>pro</sup>, the alpha-keto amide carbon is positioned within 3.8 Å of the active site thiol sulfur atom. These blind tests of our docking results for boceprevir support the predictive value of docking results for the other HCV protease inhibitors.</p><p id="P14">Detailed images of the lowest-energy pose for seven of the ten complexes are shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Figure S2</xref>, and three representative complexes, for vaniprevir, simeprevir, and narlaprevir are illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1G - I</xref>. In addition, a summary of <italic>AutoDock</italic> scores (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table S1</xref>), key intermolecular contacts in each of the ten complexes (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table S2</xref>), and descriptions of these binding poses, are presented in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Information</xref>. In this analysis, we paid particular attention to key details of the lowest energy pose for each inhibitor, including interactions with the sidechains of catalytic dyad residues His41 and Cys145, and hydrogen-bonded interactions with the backbone amides of Gly143, Ser144 and Cys145, which form the oxyanion hole of this cysteine protease (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39">Zhang et al., 2020b</xref>). All these HCV protease inhibitors form extensive hydrogen-bonded networks and hydrophobic interactions within the substrate binding cleft, and would occlude access of polypeptide substrates to the active-site residues His41 and Cys145 (as shown for example in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1G-I</xref>). While the three HCV protease inhibitors with alpha-keto amide functional groups, namely, boceprevir, narlaprevir, and telaprevir, have lowest-energy or low-energy poses that could form covalent bonds with the active-site Cys145 thiol, the seven other HCV protease inhibitors are non-covalent inhibitors that would not form such thioester bonds. From these virtual docking studies, we conclude that all ten of these HCV protease inhibitors have the potential to bind snuggly into the substrate binding cleft of M<sup>pro</sup>, and to inhibit binding of its substrates.</p></sec><sec id="S6"><title>Seven HCV drugs inhibit M<sup>pro</sup> protease activity</title><p id="P15">Inhibition activity of HCV drugs against M<sup>pro</sup> was initially assessed using a protease assay based on Föster resonance energy transfer (FRET) using the peptide substrate Dabsyl-KTSAVLQ/SGFRKME-(Edans), containing a canonical M<sup>pro</sup> protease recognition site. Rates of hydrolysis were determined for 90 minutes, and initial velocities were used to assess the relative inhibitory activities of the ten HCV protease inhibitors. The percent M<sup>pro</sup> activity denotes the ratio of initial hydrolysis velocities in the presence of 20 μM drug to the velocities in the presence of only the DMSO solvent. These assays used 10 nM M<sup>pro</sup> and 20 μM peptide substrate, at a final DMSO concentration of 1.0%. Under these conditions, HCV protease inhibitors narlaprevir, boceprevir, and telaprevir have significant enzyme inhibition activity, with IC<sub>50</sub> values of 2.2 ± 0.4 μM, 2.9 ± 0.6 μM, and 18.7 ± 6.4 μM, respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figures 2A, B</xref>). In contrast, little or no inhibition activity was detected with the other seven HCV protease inhibitors (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2A</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Figure S3A</xref>).</p><p id="P16">While very sensitive, this FRET assay is complicated by the fact that, aside from narlaprevir, boceprevir, and telaprevir, the other HCV drugs have significant intrinsic fluorescence that interferes with FRET measurements using this peptide substrate (compare fluorescence intensity at time t = 0 sec in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Figure S3A</xref>). Consequently, M<sup>pro</sup> inhibition by some of these drugs might be masked or interfered with by fluorophore interactions. To overcome this, we also developed a 1D <sup>1</sup>H-NMR assay, using the peptide substrate KTSAVLQ/SGFRKME that lacks the Dabsyl and Edans N-terminal and C-terminal tags, as outlined in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2C</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Figure S4</xref>. In this 1D <sup>1</sup>H-NMR assay, M<sup>pro</sup> activity was defined as the ratio of hydrolyzed peptide observed after 30 min in the presence of drug, to the amount of hydrolyzed peptide observed when the enzyme is incubated with DMSO alone. These assays used 100 nM M<sup>pro</sup>, 50 μM peptide substrate, and 50 μM drug (or DMSO solvent alone), at a final DMSO concentration of 1.0%. Under these conditions, narlaprevir, boceprevir, and telaprevir have substantial enzyme inhibition activity, as was the case in the FRET assay. In addition, in the NMR assay substantial inhibitory activity was also observed for vaniprevir, and moderate inhibitory activity was observed for grazoprevir, simeprevir, and asunaprevir (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2D</xref>). This moderate inhibition was not detected in the FRET assay. Danoprevir, paritaprevir, and glecaprevir had little or no detectable M<sup>pro</sup> inhibitory activity. From these studies we conclude that seven HCV drugs (<italic>viz</italic> boceprevir, narlaprevir, telaprevir, vaniprevir, grazoprevir, simeprevir, and asunaprevir) inhibit SARS-CoV-2 M<sup>pro</sup> strongly or moderately under the conditions tested.</p></sec><sec id="S7"><title>Three HCV protease inhibitors inhibit not only M<sup>pro</sup> but also PL<sup>pro</sup>
</title><p id="P17">Although the active site of PL<sup>pro</sup> does not share structural similarity with the HCV protease, it is possible that some HCV protease inhibitors can also bind into the active site of PL<sup>pro</sup>. Accordingly, we carried out virtual docking studies of these same ten HCV drugs into the substrate binding cleft of PL<sup>pro</sup>, using protocols similar to those developed in virtual docking studies with M<sup>pro</sup>. The PL<sup>pro</sup> inhibitor GRL-0617, for which a crystal structure bound to PL<sup>pro</sup> is available in the PDB (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">Fu and Huang, 2020</xref>), was used to assess the docking protocol and to determine a reference <italic>AutoDock</italic> score of -7.54 kcal / mol. The scores of docking poses for HCV drugs, summarized in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3A</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Table S1</xref>, range from – 5.56 kcal / mole for boceprevir and narlaprevir, to much more favorable values of *#x003C; – 8 kcal / mol for others including vaniprevir, grazoprevir, simeprevir, and paritaprevir. The most favorable docking poses for simeprevir and vaniprevir are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figures 3B - C</xref>, and for the remaining complexes in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Figure S5</xref>. These results indicate that, surprisingly, some HCV protease inhibitors may bind in the active sites of both M<sup>pro</sup> and PL<sup>pro</sup>.</p><p id="P18">Based on these docking results, we anticipated that several HCV protease inhibitors, not including bocepriver or narlaprevir, might inhibit PL<sup>pro</sup> protease activity. To test this hypothesis, fluorescence assays of PL<sup>pro</sup> inhibition were carried out, using the substrate ZRLRGG/AMC (Z - carboxybenzyl; AMC - 7-Amino-4-methylcoumarin) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">Anson et al., 2020</xref>) containing a natural/canonical PL<sup>pro</sup> protease recognition site. In this assay, the AMC group is quenched when covalently attached to the peptide, and increases fluorescence upon proteolytic cleavage. Of the HCV drugs tested, four drugs predicted to bind well into the active site of PL<sup>pro</sup>, vaniprevir, simeprevir, paritaprevir, and grazoprevir, inhibit PL<sup>pro</sup> protease activity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3C</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Figure S3B</xref>). Hence, vaniprevir, simeprevir, and grazoprevir inhibited both M<sup>pro</sup> and PL<sup>pro</sup>, while paritaprevir inhibited PL<sup>pro</sup>, but not M<sup>pro</sup>. Vaniprevir and simeprevir are more effective PL<sup>pro</sup> inhibitors than grazoprevir or paritaprevir under these assay conditions.</p></sec><sec id="S8"><title>Seven HCV drugs inhibit SARS-CoV-2 replication in Vero and/or human 293T cells</title><p id="P19">The motivation for the docking and biophysical studies described above was to identify HCV drugs with the potential to inhibit SARS-CoV-2 virus replication. For antiviral assays, Vero E6 cells, or human 293T cells expressing the SARS-CoV-2 ACE2 receptor, were grown in 96-well plates, and were incubated with various levels of a HCV protease inhibitor for 2 hours. Cells were then infected with SARS-CoV-2 virus at the indicated multiplicity of infection [moi, plaque-forming units (pfu)/cell] and incubated for the indicated times at 37° C in the presence of the inhibitor. Virus-infected cells were then identified by immunofluorescence using an antibody specific for the viral nucleoprotein. Inhibition of viral replication was quantified by determining the percentage of positive infected cells at the end of the incubation period in the presence of the compound, as compared with the number of infected cells in its absence. To determine whether a HCV drug was cytotoxic, uninfected Vero E6 or human 293T cells were incubated with the same levels of the compounds for the same length of time, and cytotoxicity was measured using an MTT assay (Roche). In all of these replication assays, remdesivir was used as a positive control. Further details of these replication assays are provided in <xref ref-type="sec" rid="S11">STAR Methods</xref>.</p><p id="P20">Viral replication inhibition data in Vero E6 cells are presented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>. Three of the HCV protease inhibitors tested, grazoprevir, asunaprevir, and boceprevir, inhibited SARS-CoV-2 virus replication at concentrations lower than the concentrations that cause significant cytotoxicity. Two other HCV protease inhibitors, simeprevir and vaniprevir, inhibited virus replication with even lower IC<sub>50</sub> values, but some cytotoxicity was also observed. These five HCV drugs have IC<sub>50</sub> values for inhibiting SARS-CoV-2 replication of 4.2 to 19.6 μM. The remaining three HCV drugs tested, telaprevir, glecaprevir, and danoprevir, did not inhibit virus replication in Vero E6 cells, even at a maximum drug concentrations of 50 μM.</p><p id="P21">We next determined whether the inhibition of SARS-CoV-2 replication by a representative HCV drug occurs at steps after virus entry, as would be expected for inhibitors of a viral protease that is produced only after infection. Accordingly, we performed a time of addition assay using grazoprevir as the inhibitor. In a single cycle (moi of 2 pfu/cell) infection, grazoprevir was added 2 hours prior to infection, at the time of infection, or at 2 or 4 hours post infection. Grazoprevir inhibited virus replication at all time points tested (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4J</xref>). Because virus replication was inhibited by the addition of grazoprevir as late as 4 hours post infection, it is unlikely that grazoprevir is inhibiting viral entry, which should be completed by this time post-infection. These results indicate that grazoprevir inhibits steps during the replication stage of the viral life cycle, hence implicating virus-encoded proteases in the inhibition of virus replication.</p><p id="P22">We also determined whether the HCV drugs exhibited similar antiviral activities in human cells, specifically human 293T cells expressing the ACE2 receptor (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>). We included in these antiviral assays another HCV protease inhibitor, narlaprevir, which we observed to be a strong M<sup>pro</sup> inhibitor (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2B</xref>). Again, simeprevir and vaniprevir were the most effective inhibitors of virus replication, with IC<sub>50</sub> values of 2.3 and 3.0 μM, respectively, and with considerably reduced cytotoxicity as compared to that in Vero cells. Boceprevir and narleprevir, which are strong M<sup>pro</sup> inhibitors (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2A,B</xref>), were less effective inhibitors of virus replication, with IC<sub>50</sub>s of 5.4 and 15 μM. The other reversible covalent M<sup>pro</sup> inhibitor, telaprevir, had an even lower IC<sub>50</sub> of 20.5 μM. Grazoprevir had considerably lower antiviral activity in human 293T cells than in Vero cells (compare <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figures 4D</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5F</xref>). Thus, six HCV drugs inhibited SARS-CoV-2 replication in human 293T cells, with IC<sub>50</sub> values ranging from 2.3 to 20.5 μM. Glecaprevir and danoprevir did not inhibit virus replication in 293T cells, as was also the case in Vero cells.</p></sec><sec id="S9"><title>Simeprevir, and grazoprevir synergize with remdesivir to increase inhibition of SARS-CoV-2 virus replication</title><p id="P23">Because M<sup>pro</sup> and PL<sup>pro</sup> generate either the RNA polymerase itself, or the proteins that constitute the replication organelles required for polymerase function, we predicted that HCV drugs that inhibit one or both of these viral proteases might be synergistic with inhibitors of the viral polymerase like remdesivir. To test this hypothesis, we carried out antiviral combination assays in Vero cells of simeprevir, grazoprevir, or boceprevir with remdesivir (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6</xref>). To assess synergy, two analyses are required. In one analysis the IC<sub>90</sub> of the remdesivir was measured in the presence of increasing concentrations of each of these HCV drugs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6A-C</xref>). These results demonstrate that simeprevir or grazoprevir increase the antiviral activity of remdesivir. For example, in the presence of 1.25 μM simeprevir, approximately 10-fold less remdesivir is required for the same antiviral effect achieved in the absence of simeprevir (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6A</xref>). Surprisingly, although boceprevir is a much better inhibitor of M<sup>pro</sup> than either simeprevir or grazoprevir, boceprevir did not significantly affect the antiviral activity of remdesivir (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6C</xref>). In the second analysis, the IC<sub>90</sub> concentration of each HCV drug was determined in the presence of increasing concentrations of remdesivir (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figures 6D-F</xref>). Remdesivir increased the antiviral activity of simeprevir and grazoprevir. For example addition of 1.25 μM remdesivir substantially reduces the concentration of simeprevir needed to achieve IC<sub>90</sub> conditions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6D</xref>). In contrast, remdesivir did not significantly affect the antiviral activity of boceprevir (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6F</xref>).</p><p id="P24">These combination antiviral assays indicate that simeprevir and grazoprevir, but not boceprevir, act synergistically with remdesivir to inhibit virus replication. As confirmation, we subjected these results to analysis by the Zero Interaction Potency (ZIP) model for synergy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">Ianevski et al., 2020</xref>). In the landscapes generated by this model that are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6G - I</xref>, red denotes a synergistic interaction, and green denotes an antagonistic interaction. In this model a synergistic interaction between drugs has a score greater than +10; an additive interaction has a score between −10 to +10; and an antagonistic interaction has a score of less than −10. The landscapes for the interaction of remdesivir with both simeprevir and grazoprevir are red, with synergy scores of +30.2 and +25.0, respectively, denoting moderate synergism. In contrast, although the landscape for the interaction of remdesivir with boceprevir suggests weak antagonism (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figure 6I</xref>), the score of the interaction is −7.6, which we interpret as an additive interaction.</p><p id="P25">We also carried out combination antiviral assays in human 293T cells. The interaction between remdesivir and grazoprevir in inhibiting virus replication in the human cells was also synergistic, with a red landscape and a synergy score of +20.3 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Figure S6A</xref>). The interaction between remdesivir and vaniprevir in inhibiting virus replication was also analyzed in 293T cells; it was weakly synergistic, with a score of +10.9. Vaniprevir has an additive effect or, at best, very weak synergy with remdesivir in human 293T cells. Consequently, two HCV drugs, simeprevir and grazoprevir, act synergistically with remdesivir to inhibit SARS-CoV-2 virus replication in Vero and/or human 293T cells.</p></sec></sec><sec id="S10" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p id="P26">To provide antiviral drugs that can be rapidly deployed to combat the COVID-19 pandemic, we carried out the present study to identify currently available drugs that could potentially be repurposed as inhibitors of the pandemic SARS-CoV-2 virus that causes COVID-19 disease. Instead of screening libraries of current drugs, we took a different approach to identify candidate drugs. Specifically, we initiated our search based on the striking similarity of the substrate binding clefts of the SARS-CoV-2 M<sup>pro</sup> and HCV proteases. The HCV protease is a serine-protease, with catalytic triad His57, Asp81, and Ser139, while the SARS-CoV-2 M<sup>pro</sup> is a cysteine protease, with catalytic dyad residues His41, Cys145 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">Jin et al., 2020</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39">Zhang et al., 2020b</xref>), While the two structures have similar structural architectures (i.e. organization of secondary structure elements) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">Orengo et al., 1997</xref>), their secondary structure topologies (i.e. how the secondary structure elements are linked together) are very different (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Figure S7A</xref>), and do not indicate a divergent evolutionary relationship. However, a structure-based sequence alignment, generated from these superimposed three-dimensional structures, aligns catalytic residues His41 / His57 and Cys145 / Ser139 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Figure S7B</xref>), where each aligned pair is found in a similar secondary structure element. Hence, it appears that the similarities in the overall structures and relative orientations of domains I and II, the features of the substrate binding cleft located between these domains, and the relative positions of catalytic residues in these enzymes, is a result of convergent evolution (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">Kester and Matthews, 1977</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">Robertus et al., 1972</xref>) to create a similar protease active site.</p><p id="P27">As predicted by the striking similarity of the substrate binding clefts of the SARS-CoV-2 M<sup>pro</sup> and HCV proteases, our virtual docking experiments showed that ten HCV protease inhibitors can be docked snuggly into the substrate binding cleft of M<sup>pro</sup>, and hence would have the potential to inhibit binding of the M<sup>pro</sup> substrate, thereby inhibiting proteolytic cleavage of the substrate. In fact, we showed that four HCV drugs, boceprevir, narlaprevir, telaprevir, and vaniprevir strongly inhibit SARS-CoV-2 M<sup>pro</sup> protease activity, and that three other HCV drugs, grazoprevir, simeprevir and asunaprevir moderately inhibit M<sup>pro</sup> activity. Boceprevir, narleprevir and telaprevir are α-keto amides, which can form a reversible covalent bond with the active site Cys thiol of M<sup>pro</sup>. The other four HCV drugs that inhibit the M<sup>pro</sup> protease cannot form a covalent bond active site Cys thiol of M<sup>pro</sup>. These seven HCV drugs inhibit virus replication in Vero and/or human 293T cells expressing the ACE2 receptor. Although the active site of PL<sup>pro</sup> does not share structural similarity with the HCV NS3/4A protease, four HCV drugs, simeprevir, grazoprevir, vaniprevir, and paritaprevir can be docked with energetically-favorable scores into the active site of PL<sup>pro</sup>, and inhibit PL<sup>pro</sup> protease activity <italic>in vitro</italic>. None of these four inhibitors can form covalent bonds with the active-site Cys residue of PL<sup>pro</sup>. Vaniprevir is the only one of the tested HCV drugs that strongly inhibits both M<sup>pro</sup> and PL<sup>pro</sup>, presumably accounting for its strong inhibition of virus replication.</p><p id="P28">Other groups have also recently reported that some of these same HCV protease inhibitors can inhibit M<sup>pro</sup> or PL<sup>pro</sup> protease activities, and that boceprevir can inhibit SARS-CoV-2 replication (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">Anson et al., 2020</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">Fu et al., 2020</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">Ma et al., 2020</xref>). While all of these studies report boceprevir as a moderately-potent inhibitor of M<sup>pro</sup>, there are inconsistent reports of the effectiveness of some of the other HCV protease inhibitors reported here as inhibitors of M<sup>pro</sup> and/or PL<sup>pro</sup>. These inconsistencies likely arise from details of the different assays that have been used. For example, our <sup>1</sup>H-NMR assay could identify moderate inhibition of M<sup>pro</sup> by simeprevir, grazoprevir, and asunaprevir HCV drugs that was not detected by our FRET assay. This is not surprising, since both the FRET and NMR assays are competition assays, which will give different results for substrates that have different binding affinities. The ability of HCV drugs to inhibit M<sup>pro</sup> may also depend on other details of the assay conditions, most notably the enzyme, substrate, and drug concentrations which may affect the monomer-dimer equilibrium of M<sup>pro</sup> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">Grum-Tokars et al., 2008</xref>).</p><p id="P29">PL<sup>pro</sup> not only cleaves viral polyproteins to generate crucial viral proteins, but also cleaves the ubiquitin-like ISG15 protein from viral proteins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">Daczkowski et al., 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">Lindner et al., 2007</xref>). ISG15 conjugation in infected cells results in a dominant-negative effect on the functions of viral proteins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40">Zhao et al., 2016</xref>), and removal of ISG15 from viral proteins by PL<sup>pro</sup> would restore these functions of these viral proteins. In addition, the resulting free ISG15 would be secreted from infected cells and would bind to the LFA-1 receptor on immune cells, causing the release of interferon-γand inflammatory cytokines (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33">Swaim et al., 2020</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34">Swaim et al., 2017</xref>). The release of these cytokines could contribute to the strong inflammatory response, the so-called cytokine storm, that has been implicated in the severity of COVID-19 disease (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">McGonagle et al., 2020</xref>). Inhibition of PL<sup>pro</sup> by a HCV drug should also inhibit the release of interferon-γand inflammatory cytokines, potentially mitigating the cytokine storm.</p><p id="P30">HCV drugs that inhibit M<sup>pro</sup> and/or PL<sup>pro</sup> would be expected to inhibit viral RNA polymerase function in infected cells by inhibiting the generation of protein subunits of the viral polymerase and/or by inhibiting the generation of the integral-membrane non-structural viral proteins that form the replication organelles (double membrane vesicles) required for polymerase function. Because of the resulting reduction of functional viral polymerase, the amount of remdesivir needed for inhibition of virus replication would likely be reduced. Viral replication assays using combinations of drugs allowed us to assess if the interactions between HCV drugs and remdesivir are additive or synergistic, i.e. resulting in an inhibition of virus replication that is greater than the sum of the inhibitions caused by the HCV drug and remdesivir. Surprisingly, we found that these inhibitory effects are additive or synergistic depending on which HCV drug is used to inhibit virus replication. Boceprevir, which strongly inhibits only M<sup>pro</sup>, and vaniprevir, which strongly inhibits both M<sup>pro</sup> and PL<sup>pro</sup>, act additively with remdesivir to inhibit virus replication. In contrast, simeprevir and grazoprevir, which moderately inhibit M<sup>pro</sup> and either strongly or moderately inhibit PL<sup>pro</sup>, act synergistically with remdesivir to inhibit virus replication. The basis for the different interactions between remdesivir and particular HCV drugs, and the mechanism(s) of synergy, needs to be further explored.</p><p id="P31">The HCV drugs that are strongly synergistic with remdesivir are most pertinent for the goal of the present study to identify available drugs that can be repurposed as SARS-CoV-2 antivirals and/or as lead molecules for new drug development.</p><p id="P32">Repurposed drugs like the HCV drugs in the present study may not have sufficient inhibitory activity on their own to achieve clinical efficacy. Synergy with remdesivir increases the potency of both the repurposed HCV drug and remdesivir. We identified two HCV drugs, simeprevir and grazoprevir, that act synergistically with remdesivir to inhibit SARS-CoV-2 virus replication. Of these two, simeprevir may be the better choice as a repurposed drug because it effectively inhibits SARS-CoV-2 virus replication in human cells at much lower concentrations than grazoprevir. Consequently, the combination of simeprevir and remdesivir could potentially function as an antiviral against SARS-CoV-2 while more specific SARS-CoV-2 antivirals are being developed. Simeprevir, which is an oral drug, might also be combined with an oral polymerase inhibitor rather than with remdesivir, which has to be administered intravenously. One such oral polymerase inhibitor, molnupiravir (EIDD-2801) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31">Sheahan et al., 2020</xref>), which is currently in late stage clinical trials, could potentially be combined with for clinical applications. Accordingly, a combination of simeprevir and molnupiravir, both of which have oral bioavailability, could be assessed for outpatient use.</p></sec><sec id="S11" sec-type="methods" specific-use="web-only"><title>STAR METHODS</title><table-wrap id="T2" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"><label>Table SM1</label><caption><title>Key Resources</title></caption><table frame="box" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top">REAGENT or RESOURCE</th><th align="left" valign="top">SOURCE</th><th align="left" valign="top">IDENTIFIER</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top">
<bold>Cell Lines</bold>
</td></tr></tbody><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top">
<italic>E. coli</italic> BL21(DE3)</td><td align="left" valign="top">New England Biolabs Inc</td><td align="left" valign="top">C2527</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">Vero E6 cells</td><td align="left" valign="top">ATCC</td><td align="left" valign="top">CRL-1586</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">HEK293T cells</td><td align="left" valign="top">ATCC</td><td align="left" valign="top">CRL-3216</td></tr></tbody><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top">
<bold>Chemicals</bold>
</td></tr></tbody><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top">Luria Broth (LB)</td><td align="left" valign="top">Fischer BioReagents</td><td align="left" valign="top">BP1426-2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">LB Agar</td><td align="left" valign="top">VWR Amresco</td><td align="left" valign="top">J104</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">Ampicilin</td><td align="left" valign="top">Research Products</td><td align="left" valign="top">A40040</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top"> </td><td align="left" valign="top">International</td><td align="left" valign="top"> </td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">IPTG</td><td align="left" valign="top">Research Products</td><td align="left" valign="top">156000</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top"> </td><td align="left" valign="top">International</td><td align="left" valign="top"> </td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">Sodium chloride</td><td align="left" valign="top">VWR Amresco</td><td align="left" valign="top">X190</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">Tris</td><td align="left" valign="top">MP Biomedicals LLC</td><td align="left" valign="top">819263</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">TCEP</td><td align="left" valign="top">VWR Amresco</td><td align="left" valign="top">K831</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">Imidazole</td><td align="left" valign="top">Alfa Aesar</td><td align="left" valign="top">A10221</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">DTT</td><td align="left" valign="top">VWR Life Sciences</td><td align="left" valign="top">0281</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">EDTA</td><td align="left" valign="top">VWR Amresco</td><td align="left" valign="top">M101</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">HEPES</td><td align="left" valign="top">Chem Impex Int’l Inc</td><td align="left" valign="top">00174</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">Bovine Serum Albumin</td><td align="left" valign="top">VWR Amresco</td><td align="left" valign="top">0322</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">D<sub>2</sub>O</td><td align="left" valign="top">Sigma-Aldrich</td><td align="left" valign="top">343773</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">d<sub>6</sub>DMSO</td><td align="left" valign="top">Cambridge Isotope</td><td align="left" valign="top">DLM-10</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top"> </td><td align="left" valign="top">Laboratories Inc.</td><td align="left" valign="top"> </td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">Ni-NTA resin</td><td align="left" valign="top">MCLAB</td><td align="left" valign="top">NiNTA-100</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">Sodium Azide</td><td align="left" valign="top">VWR Amresco</td><td align="left" valign="top">0639</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">NaOH</td><td align="left" valign="top">VWR Life Sciences</td><td align="left" valign="top">M137</td></tr></tbody><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top">
<bold>SDS PAGE gel and staining</bold>
</td></tr></tbody><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top">Acrylamide/bis-acrylamide</td><td align="left" valign="top">VWR Life Sciences</td><td align="left" valign="top">0311</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">Sodium Dodecyl Sulphate</td><td align="left" valign="top">VWR Life Sciences</td><td align="left" valign="top">0837</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">Ammonium persulphate (APS)</td><td align="left" valign="top">VWR Amresco</td><td align="left" valign="top">M133</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">TEMED</td><td align="left" valign="top">Thermo Scientific</td><td align="left" valign="top">17919</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">Bromophenol blue</td><td align="left" valign="top">VWR Amresco</td><td align="left" valign="top">M131</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">Glycerol</td><td align="left" valign="top">Fisher Chemical</td><td align="left" valign="top">G33</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">Glycine</td><td align="left" valign="top">VWR Life Sciences</td><td align="left" valign="top">0176</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">Glacial acetic acid</td><td align="left" valign="top">Fisher Chemical</td><td align="left" valign="top">A38-212</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">Isopropanol</td><td align="left" valign="top">Fisher Bioreagents</td><td align="left" valign="top">BP2618</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">HCl</td><td align="left" valign="top">MP Biomedicals LLC</td><td align="left" valign="top">194054</td></tr></tbody><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top">
<bold>Inhibitors</bold>
</td></tr></tbody><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top">Asunaprevir</td><td align="left" valign="top">Selleckchem Inc.</td><td align="left" valign="top">S4935</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">Boceprevir</td><td align="left" valign="top">Selleckchem Inc.</td><td align="left" valign="top">S3733</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">Danoprevir</td><td align="left" valign="top">Selleckchem Inc.</td><td align="left" valign="top">S1183</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">Glecaprevir</td><td align="left" valign="top">Selleckchem Inc.</td><td align="left" valign="top">S5720</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">Grazoprevir</td><td align="left" valign="top">Selleckchem Inc.</td><td align="left" valign="top">S3728</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">Paritaprevir</td><td align="left" valign="top">Selleckchem Inc.</td><td align="left" valign="top">S5404</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">Simeprevir</td><td align="left" valign="top">Selleckchem Inc.</td><td align="left" valign="top">S5015</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">Telaprevir</td><td align="left" valign="top">Selleckchem Inc.</td><td align="left" valign="top">S1538</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">Narlaprevir</td><td align="left" valign="top">MedChemExpress</td><td align="left" valign="top">HY-10300</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">Vaniprevir</td><td align="left" valign="top">Addoq</td><td align="left" valign="top">A11600-5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">Remdesivir</td><td align="left" valign="top">Medkoo Bioscience Inc.</td><td align="left" valign="top">329511</td></tr></tbody><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top">
<bold>Plasmids</bold>
</td></tr></tbody><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top">M<sup>pro</sup> expression vector GTM_COV2_NSP5_001</td><td align="left" valign="top">GenScript Inc.</td><td align="left" valign="top">Custom synthesis</td></tr></tbody><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top">
<bold>Peptide substrates</bold>
</td></tr></tbody><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top">KTSAVLQ/SGFRKME</td><td align="left" valign="top">GenScript Inc.</td><td align="left" valign="top">Custom synthesis</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">Dabcyl-KTSAVLQ/SGFRKME-Edans</td><td align="left" valign="top">GenScript Inc.</td><td align="left" valign="top">Custom synthesis</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">zRLRGG/AMC</td><td align="left" valign="top">Bachem Americs Inc.</td><td align="left" valign="top">4027158.0025</td></tr></tbody><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top">
<bold>Software and Algorithms</bold>
</td></tr></tbody><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top">Topspin 3.2.6</td><td align="left" valign="top">Bruker Biospin</td><td align="left" valign="top">www.bruker.com</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">AutoDock 4.2</td><td align="left" valign="top">The Scripps Research Institute</td><td align="left" valign="top">
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://autodock.scripps.edu/">http://autodock.scripps.edu/</ext-link>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">AutoDockTools 1.5.6</td><td align="left" valign="top">The Scripps Research Institute</td><td align="left" valign="top">
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://autodock.scripps.edu/resources/adt">http://autodock.scripps.edu/resources/adt</ext-link>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">Synergy Finder</td><td align="left" valign="top">Institute for Molecular Medicine Finland</td><td align="left" valign="top">
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://synergyfinder.fimm.fi/">https://synergyfinder.fimm.fi/</ext-link>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">Prism</td><td align="left" valign="top">GraphPad</td><td align="left" valign="top">
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.graphpad.com/">https://www.graphpad.com/</ext-link>
</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><sec id="S12" sec-type="methods"><title>Method Details</title><sec id="S13"><title>Molecular Docking</title><p id="P33">We used the free open source <italic>Autodock</italic> suite (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">Morris et al., 2009</xref>). <italic>AutoDockTools</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R48">Sanner, 1999</xref>) was used for coordinate preparation, docking, and analysis of results.</p><p id="P34">The computational docking program <italic>AutoDock v4.2.6</italic>. is based on an empirical free-energy force field and uses a search method based on Lamarckian genetic algorithm (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R45">Morris et al., 1998</xref>). Target protein coordinates were obtained from SARS-CoV-2 M<sup>pro</sup> X-ray crystal structure (PDB id 6Y2G) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R49">Zhang et al., 2020</xref>), and structural water was removed. Three-dimensional coordinates for ligand molecules were obtained from PDB (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.rcsb.org/">http://www.rcsb.org/</ext-link>) or from chemical structure databases, ChemSpider (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.chemspider.com/">http://www.chemspider.com/</ext-link>) and DrugBank (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.drugbank.ca/">https://www.drugbank.ca/</ext-link>). Protein and ligand coordinates were then prepared using <italic>AutoDockTools</italic>; polar hydrogens were added to protein structures, and Gasteiger-Marsili empirical atomic partial charges were added to ligands. Torsional degrees of freedom (dihedral angles) were identified for each ligand. These data and parameters for each protein and ligand were saved as individual PDBQT files. In these studies, ligand dihedral angles were allowed to vary (except where stated otherwise), and all protein dihedral angles were kept rigid. The program <italic>Autogrid</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R48">Sanner, 1999</xref>) was used to prepare affinity maps for all atom types in the receptor and ligands. A grid of 56, 40 and 48 points in x, y and z direction, with a grid spacing of 0.375 Å was used to compute electrostatic maps. The grid center was placed on the center of the inhibitor 13b molecule in its complex with M<sup>pro</sup> (PDB id 6Y2G) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R49">Zhang et al., 2020</xref>). The Lamarckian genetic algorithm (LGA) method was used for sampling ligand binding conformation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R45">Morris et al., 1998</xref>), with the following LGA parameters: 150 individuals in population; 2,500,000 energy evaluations; 27,000 maximum number of generations; and with mutation and crossover rates of 0.02 and 0.08, respectively. A maximum of 300 iterations per local search was used. The calculations were repeated for 100 docking simulations for each complex. For a comparative analysis, docking simulations of the α-ketoamide inhibitor 13b (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R49">Zhang et al., 2020</xref>) were also performed using the same protocol used for docking the protease inhibitor drugs. All docking simulations were analyzed using the <italic>AutoDockTools.</italic> Atomic coordinates for best scoring conformation obtained in each docking simulation, for each drug-protein complex, were saved in PDB format for analysis. These protein-ligand complexes were analyzed in detailed using open source <italic>PyMol</italic> molecular visualization tool (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42">DeLano, 2009</xref>) and fully automated <italic>Protein-Ligand Interaction Profiler</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R47">Salentin et al., 2015</xref>) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://projects.biotec.tu-dresden.de/plip-web/plip">https://projects.biotec.tu-dresden.de/plip-web/plip</ext-link>).</p><p id="P35">PL<sup>pro</sup> inhibitor complexes in the PDB revealed that the BL2 loop present at the entrance of active site adopts significantly different conformations depending on the size of the inhibitor bound to the PL<sup>pro</sup>. This plasticity in the BL2 loop suggests an induced fit mechanism of ligand binding to PL<sup>pro</sup> active site. To avoid a closed conformation of the BL2 loop found in protein ligand complex we chose SARS-CoV-2 PL<sup>pro</sup> X-ray crystal structure in its apo form (PDB id 6W9C) as the target to dock HCV protease inhibitors. The docking protocol was same as above, except a larger grid of size 56, 56, and 58 points in the x, y and z direction respectively was used to compute electrostatic maps for PL<sup>pro</sup> target. For a comparative analysis, docking simulations of PL<sup>pro</sup> inhibitor GRL0617 (PDB id 7CJM) were also performed using the same protocol.</p></sec><sec id="S14"><title>M<sup>pro</sup> expression and purification</title><p id="P36">The full length SARS-CoV-2 M<sup>pro</sup> gene was ordered from GenScript USA Inc. in pGEX-6P-1 vector, as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R49">Zhang et al., 2020</xref>). This expression vector is designated GTM_COV2_NSP5_001. This plasmid, expressing SARS-CoV-2 M<sup>pro</sup> as a self-cleaving (using its native cleavage site) GST-fusion were transformed into competent <italic>E. coli</italic> BL21(DE3) cells. A single colony was picked and inoculated in 2 mL LB supplemented with 0.1 mg/ml Ampicillin at 37 °C and 225 rpm. The 2 mL inoculum was added to 1L LB broth with 0.1 mg/mL Ampicilin. The cells were allowed to grow to an optical density of 0.6 at 600 nm at 37 °C and 225 rpm, and induced with 1 mM IPTG. The induced cells were incubated overnight at 18 °C and 225 rpm. The cells were harvested and resuspended in lysis buffer (20 mM Tris pH 8.0, 300 mM NaCl) and then lysed by sonication. The cell debris was removed by centrifugation at 14000 rpm for 40 mins. The supernatant was then added to a Ni-NTA column. The Ni-NTA column was then washed with wash buffer (20 mM Tris pH 8.0, 300 mM NaCl, 10 mM Imidazole) and eluted with 20 mM Tris pH 8.0, 100 mM NaCl, 100 mM imidazole. The elution fractions that contained M<sup>pro</sup> were simultaneously buffer exchanged (20 mM Tris pH 8.0, 100 mM NaCl, 1 mM EDTA, 1 mM DTT) and concentrated using a swinging bucket centrifuge at 4000 rpm. The final M<sup>pro</sup> concentration was 23.3 μM, determined by absorbance at 280 nm using a calculated extinction coefficient of 33,640 M<sup>−1</sup> cm<sup>−1</sup>. Homogeneity was validated by SDS-PAGE (&gt; 95% homogeneous) and the construct was validated by MALDI-TOF mass spectrometry.</p></sec><sec id="S15"><title>M<sup>pro</sup> proteolysis inhibition assays</title><p id="P37">The proteolysis of substrate KTSAVLQ/SGFRKME was studied using Fluorescence Resonance Energy Transfer (FRET) and Nuclear magnetic Resonance (NMR) assays. For the FRET assay the substrate was labeled with Dabcyl and Glu-Edans FRET pair on the N and C-termini of the peptide, respectively, as described elsewhere(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">Ma et al., 2020</xref>). Both, labeled and unlabeled substrates were ordered from GenScript USA Inc. For all assays, the specific activity of the enzyme was checked at the beginning and end of the data collection session, or back-to-back with each measurement, in order to avoid spurious results due to enzyme inactivation during a measurement session.</p><p id="P38">All M<sup>pro</sup> proteolysis assays were carried out in Reaction Buffer containing 20 mM HEPES pH 6.5, 120 mM NaCl, 0.4 mM EDTA and 3 mM TCEP. Additionally, 1 mg/mL BSA was added to the buffer for FRET assays. For the FRET assay, 10 nM M<sup>pro</sup> was incubated with 20 μM of HCV drugs. The reaction was initiated by addition of 20 μM FRET substrate and monitored for 2 hours on an Infinite M1000 TECAN plate reader, exciting at 360 nm and detecting donor emission at 460 nm. The initial velocity of the reaction was calculated as the slope obtained from linear fits of emission intensity vs time plots for the first 15 minutes of the reaction. All FRET data were analyzed and plotted for initial velocity on Microsoft Excel.</p><p id="P39">In the FRET assays, the percent proteolytic activity in presence of each drug was calculated as a ratio of initial velocity in presence if inhibitor (<italic>v<sub>i</sub></italic>) to initial velocity in absence of inhibitor (<italic>v<sub>i0</sub></italic>) i.e. <italic>v<sub>i</sub> / v<sub>i0</sub></italic>. A histogram plot of <italic>v<sub>i</sub> / v<sub>i0</sub></italic> for each inhibitor was used to compare relative inhibition activities. All FRET proteolysis reaction curves were measured twice, and the uncertainty in <italic>v<sub>i</sub> / v<sub>i0</sub></italic>, estimated from the standard deviation of 2 independent measurements, is shown as error bars.</p><p id="P40">For IC<sub>50</sub> measurements of HCV inhibitors BOC, NAR and TEL, 10 nM of M<sup>pro</sup> was incubated with a range of inhibitor concentrations in the same Reaction Buffer described above. The inhibitor concentration ranges were 0.1 – 200 μM for BOC, 0.1 to 100 μM for NAR, and 0.2 to 100 μM for TEL. The reaction was initiated by adding 20 μM FRET substrate and monitored for 1 hr. Each measurement was repeated three times. The % inhibition at each inhibitor concentration was calculated as: <disp-formula id="FD1"><mml:math id="M1"><mml:mtext>% Inhibition = 100*</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>where v<sub>i</sub> = initial velocity at a given inhibitor concentration</p><p id="P41">
<italic>v</italic>
<sub>i0</sub> = initial velocity in absence of inhibitor</p><p id="P42">
<italic>v</italic>
<sub>imax</sub> = initial velocity at maximum inhibition</p><p id="P43">The % inhibition was plotted as a function of inhibitor concentration to obtain a dose-response curve using Graphpad Prism 8 software. IC<sub>50</sub> was calculated from fitting to the equation: <disp-formula id="FD2"><mml:math id="M2"><mml:mtext>% Inhibition = 100*</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>[Inhibitor]</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>(IC</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>50</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mtext> + [Inhibitor])</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
</p><p id="P44">For the <sup>1</sup>H NMR proteolysis assay the reaction was performed at 100 nM M<sup>pro</sup> in the same assay buffer described above, along with 5% D<sub>2</sub>O and 50 μM HCV inhibitors dissolved in d<sub>6-</sub>DMSO (for the control experiments where no inhibitor is added, the same quantity of d<sub>6-</sub>DMSO was added). 50 μM of unlabeled substrate was added and immediately transferred to a 5-mm NMR tube. The final volume of each reaction mixture was 600 μL. The NMR tube was quickly placed in a 600 MHz Bruker Avance II spectrometer equipped with a 5-mm TCI cryoprobe, equilibrated at 298K. The homogeneity of the magnetic field was adjusted by gradient shimming on the z-axis and in each case an array of 24 <sup>1</sup>H experiments was acquired with 1D <sup>1</sup>H NMR using excitation sculpting for water suppression. The probe had previously been tuned and matched with a sample of similar composition. The delay between initiation of the reaction and starting acquisition was ~ 5 mins for most of the reaction conditions. The duration of each NMR experiment was also taken into account to obtain accurate time values. All <sup>1</sup>H spectra were acquired, processed, and analyzed in Bruker TopSpin 3.6.2 software. The regions of interest were integrated, and the values obtained were transferred for further analysis and plotting.</p><p id="P45">These <sup>1</sup>H NMR spectra were used to monitor the evolution of substrate and product as a function of time. Resonance assignments (discussed below) of the cleaved and uncleaved KTSAVLQ/SGFRKME peptide identified the amide H<sup>N</sup> resonances that were monitored during the reaction. The H<sup>N</sup> resonances for amino-acid residues Phe-10 (uncleaved) and Gln-7 (cleaved) were used to quantify substrate utilization and product formation, respectively, during the reaction. The H<sup>N</sup> preak intensity of residue Glu-14, which did not shift upon cleavage, was monitored as an internal control. The percent substrate cleavage in the presence of inhibitors at 30 min was calculated as a ratio of the H<sup>N</sup> resonance integrals of Gln-7 in presence of inhibitor to the corresponding resonance integral with no inhibitor.</p></sec><sec id="S16"><title>Amide <sup>1</sup>H and <sup>15</sup>N chemical shift assignments for M<sup>pro</sup> peptide substrate</title><p id="P46">Chemical shift assignments of backbone amide <sup>1</sup>H and <sup>15</sup>N resonances in the 14-residue peptide KTSAVLQSGFRKME in 20 mM HEPES pH 6.5, 100 mM NaCl, 0.4 mM EDTA, 3 mM TCEP and 5% <sup>2</sup>H<sub>2</sub>O were determined at 298 K using 2D COSY, TOCSY, and <sup>1</sup>H-<sup>15</sup>N HSQC, along with 1D <sup>1</sup>H NMR experiments, and referenced to internal DSS. Backbone amide <sup>1</sup>H and <sup>15</sup>N resonances were assigned for 12/14 and 10/14 residues in the uncleaved and cleaved peptide respectively, and deposited in the BioMagResDB as BMRB entries 50568 and 50569, respectively</p></sec><sec id="S17"><title>PL<sup>pro</sup> proteolysis inhibition assay</title><p id="P47">SARS-CoV-2 PL<sup>pro</sup> enzyme was provided as a generous gift by Prof. John Hunt (Columbia University). The construct was produced in expression vector pET21_NESG with a C-terminal purification tag LEHHHHHH. Homogeneity (&gt;95%) was validated by SDS-PAGE. The fluorogenic substrate zRLRGG/AMC was ordered from Bachem. All PL<sup>pro</sup> proteolysis assays were carried out in buffer containing 50 mM HEPES, pH 7.5, 5 mM DTT, 1 mg/ml BSA. For the fluorescence assay, 20 nM of PL<sup>pro</sup> was incubated with 20 μM of HCV drugs. 20 μM substrate was added and the reaction was monitored for 2 hrs using the Infinite M1000 TECAN plate reader compatible with Magellan ™ software with filters for excitation at 360 nm and emission at 460 nm. The data points for the first 10 mins of the proteolysis reaction progression curves were used to calculate the initial velocity (<italic>v<sub>i</sub></italic>) in presence and absence of inhibitors. The percent proteolytic activity in presence of each drug is calculate as a ratio of initial velocity in presence of inhibitor (<italic>v<sub>i</sub></italic>) to initial velocity in absence of inhibitor (<italic>v<sub>i0</sub></italic>), i.e. <italic>v<sub>i</sub> / v<sub>i0</sub></italic>. A histogram plot of <italic>v<sub>i</sub> / v<sub>i0</sub></italic> for each inhibitor was used to compare relative inhibition activities. All proteolysis reaction curves were measured twice, and the range in <italic>v<sub>i</sub> / v<sub>i0</sub></italic> is shown as error bars.</p></sec><sec id="S18"><title>Cells and Viruses</title><p id="P48">Vero E6 (ATCC, CRL-1586) and HEK293T (ATCC, CRL-3216; kind gift of Dr. Viviana Simon), were maintained in DMEM (Corning) supplemented with 10% FB (Peak Serum) and Penicillin/Streptomycin (Corning) at 37°C and 5% CO<sub>2</sub>. hACE2-293T cells were generated for this study. Briefly, HEK293T cells were transduced with a lentiviral vector expressing human ACE2. Puromycin resistant cells with hACE2 surface expression were sorted after staining with AlexaFluor 647-conjugated goat anti-hACE2 antibodies. Cells were then single-cell-cloned and screened for their ability to support SARS-CoV-2 replication. All cell lines used in this study were regularly screened for mycoplasma contamination using the Universal Detection Kit (ATCC, 30-1012K). Cells were infected with SARS-CoV-2, isolate USA-WA1/2020 (BEI Resources NR-52281) under biosafety level 3 (BSL3) containment in accordance to the biosafety protocols developed by the Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai. Viral stocks were grown in Vero E6 cells as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41">Amanat et al., 2020</xref>) and were validated by genome sequencing.</p></sec><sec id="S19"><title>Viral growth and cytotoxicity assays in the presence of inhibitors</title><p id="P49">2,000 Vero E6 or hACE2-293T cells were seeded into 96-well plates in DMEM (10% FBS) and incubated for 24 h at 37C, 5% CO2. Two hours before infection, the medium was replaced with 100 μl of DMEM (2% FBS) containing the compound of interest at concentrations 50% greater than those indicated, including a DMSO control. Plates were then transferred into the BSL3 facility and 100 PFU (MOI = 0.025) was added in 50 μl of DMEM (2% FBS), bringing the final compound concentration to those indicated. Plates were then incubated for 48 h at 37C. After infection, supernatants were removed and cells were fixed with 4% formaldehyde for 24 hours prior to being removed from the BSL3 facility. The cells were then immunostained for the viral NP protein (an in-house mAb 1C7, provided by Dr. Thomas Moran (MSSM) with a DAPI counterstain. Infected cells (488 nM) and total cells (DAPI) were quantified using the Celigo (Nexcelcom) imaging cytometer. Infectivity was measured by the accumulation of viral NP protein in the nucleus of the Vero E6 cells (fluorescence accumulation). Percent infection was quantified as [(Infected cells/Total cells) – Background] *100 and the DMSO control was then set to 100% infection for analysis. The IC<sub>50</sub> and IC<sub>90</sub> for each experiment were determined using the Prism (GraphPad Software) software.</p><p id="P50">Cytotoxicity was also performed using the MTT assay (Roche), according to the manufacturer's instructions. Cytotoxicity was performed in uninfected VeroE6 cells with same compound dilutions and concurrent with viral replication assay. All assays were performed in biologically independent triplicates. Remdesivir was purchased from Medkoo Bioscience inc. Time of addition experiments were performed using the same immunofluorescence-based assay with the following alterations: Vero E6 cells we infected with 8000 PFU (MOI of 2) of SARS-CoV-2, compound was added at different times relative to infection as indicated, and the infection was ended by fixation with 4% formaldehyde after 8 hours (single cycle assay).</p></sec><sec id="S20"><title>Antiviral combination assay</title><p id="P51">Like previous antiviral assay, 2,000 Vero E6 cells were seeded into 96-well plates in DMEM (10% FBS) and incubated for 24 h at 37°C, 5% CO<sub>2</sub>. Two hours before infection, the medium was replaced with 100 μl of DMEM (2% FBS) containing the combination of HCV protease inhibitors and remdesivir following a dilution combination matrix. A 6 by 6 matrix of drug combinations was prepared in triplicate by making serial two-fold dilutions of the drugs on each axis, including a DMSO control column and row. The resulting matrix had no drug in the right upper well, a single drug in rising 2-fold concentrations in the vertical and horizontal axes starting from that well, and the remaining wells with rising concentrations of drug mixtures reaching maximum concentrations of the drugs at the lower left well. Plates were then transferred into the BSL3 facility and SARS-CoV-2 (MOI 0.025) was added in 50 μl of DMEM (2% FBS), bringing the final compound concentration to those indicated in the figures. Plates were then incubated for 48 h at 37 °C. After infection, cells were fixed with final concentration of 5% formaldehyde for 24 hours prior to being removed from the BSL3 facility. The cells were then immunostained for the viral NP protein (an in-house mAb 1C7, provided by Dr. Thomas Moran, MSSM) with a DAPI counterstain. Infected cells (AlexaFluor 488) and total cells (DAPI) were quantified using the Celigo (Nexcelcom) imaging cytometer. Infectivity was measured by the accumulation of viral NP protein in the nucleus of the Vero E6 cells (fluorescence accumulation). Percent infection was quantified as [(Infected cells/Total cells) – Background] *100 and the DMSO control was then set to 100% infection for analysis. The combination antiviral assay was performed in biologically independent triplicates. The apparent IC<sub>90</sub> for each combination in the matrix was determined using the Prism (GraphPad Software) software. The IC<sub>90</sub> for HCV drugs and remdesivir were calculated for each drug treatment alone and in combination. This combination data was analyzed using SynergyFinder by the ZIP method (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">Ianevski et al., 2020</xref>), and combination indices were calculated as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41">Amanat et al., 2020</xref>).</p></sec></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="SM"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1"><label>Supplementary Information</label><media xlink:href="EMS108620-supplement-Supplementary_Information.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" id="d5aAdEbB" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack id="S21"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>Drs. G. Chalmers, Y.P. Huang, G. Liu, L. Ma, C. Sander, S. Shukla, G.V.T Swapna, and R. Xiao for helpful discussions, suggestions, and comments on the manuscript. We also thank J. Hunt, S. Krishna, D. Aalberts, Greg Boël for a generous gift of SARS-CoV2 PL<sup>pro</sup> enzyme, and R. Albert for support with the BSL3 facility and procedures at the Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai, New York. This research was supported by grants from the National Institutes of Health (R01-GM120574 to GTM) and RPI Center for Computational Innovations (to KB and GTM). This research was also partly funded by CRIP (Center for Research for Influenza Pathogenesis), a NIAID supported Center of Excellence for Influenza Research and Surveillance (CEIRS, contract # HHSN272201400008C), by DARPA grant HR0011-19-2-0020, by supplements to NIAID grant U19AI142733 U19AI135972 and DoD grant W81XWH-20-1-0270, and by the generous support of the JPB Foundation, the Open Philanthropy Project (research grant 2020-215611 (5384)), and anonymous donors to AG-S.</p></ack><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="S23"><title>Resource Availability</title><sec id="S24"><title>Lead Contact</title><p id="P52">Further information and requests for resources and reagents should be directed to and will be fulfilled by the designated contacts Gaetano T. Montelione (<email>monteg3@rpi.edu</email>).</p></sec><sec id="S25"><title>Materials Availability</title><p id="P53">All materials generated in this study are available upon request.</p></sec></sec><fn-group><fn id="FN2" fn-type="con"><p id="P54">
<bold>Author Contributions (Categories are defined by Cell Journal)</bold>
</p><p id="P55">Conceptualization, KB, KW, BH, CAR, AG-S, RMK, GTM; Methodology, KB, KW, BH, TBA, TR, RR, CAR, AG-S, RMK, GTM; Validation, KB, KW, BH, CAR, AG-S, RMK, GTM; Formal Analysis, KB, KW, BH, TR, CAR, AG-S, RMK, GTM; Investigation, KB, KW, BH, RR, TR, EM, TK, LM; Resources, CAR, AG-S, and GTM; Writing-original draft, KB, KW, AG-S, RMK, GTM; Writing, Review and Editing: KB, KW, BH, CAR, AG-S, RMK, GTM; Visualization, KB, KW, BH, CAR, AG-S, RMK, GTM; Supervision, KW, CAR, AG-S, GTM; Funding Acquisition, CAR, AG-S, GTM.</p></fn><fn id="FN3" fn-type="conflict"><p id="P56">
<bold>Conflict of Interest Statement</bold>: A provisional patent application related to these studies has been filed. GTM is a founder of Nexomics Biosciences, Inc. This relationship has no conflict of interest with respect to this study. GTM and RMK are inventors in patents owned jointly by Rutgers University and the University of Texas at Austin concerning the use of specific compounds as antivirals against influenza virus. These patents have no conflict of interest for this study. AG-S is inventor in patents and patent application owned by the Icahn School of Medicine concerning the use of specific antiviral compounds. This inventorship has no conflict of interest with respect to this study.</p></fn><fn id="FN4"><p id="P57">
<bold>Data Deposition</bold>
</p><p id="P58">BioMagResDB accession number: 50568 Title: “<sup>1</sup>H and <sup>15</sup>N assignments for 14-residues peptide that is cleaved by SARS-CoV-2 M<sup>pro</sup>.“</p><p id="P59">BioMagResDB accession number: 50569. Title: “<sup>1</sup>H and <sup>15</sup>N assignments for 14-residue peptide after cleavage by SARS-CoV-2 M<sup>pro</sup>”</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><ref id="R1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anand</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Palm</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Mesters</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Siddell</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name><surname>Ziebuhr</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hilgenfeld</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structure of coronavirus main proteinase reveals combination of a chymotrypsin fold with an extra alpha-helical domain</article-title><source>EMBO J</source><year>2002</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>3213</fpage><lpage>3224</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/emboj/cdf327</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Angelini</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Akhlaghpour</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Neuman</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></name><name><surname>Buchmeier</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus nonstructural proteins 3, 4, and 6 induce double-membrane vesicles</article-title><source>mBio</source><year>2013</year><volume>4</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/mBio.00524-13</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Chapman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lendy</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Pshenychnyi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Richard</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Satchell</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>D Mesecar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Broad-spectrum inhibition of coronavirus main and papain-like proteases by HCV drugs Research Square (Preprint)</article-title><year>2020</year><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://assets.researchsquare.com/files/rs-26344/v1_stamped.pdf">https://assets.researchsquare.com/files/rs-26344/v1_stamped.pdf</ext-link></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Mesecar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>X-ray structure of SARS-CoV-2 main protease bound to boceprevir at 1.45 A</article-title><source>PDB ID 6WNP:</source><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2210/pdb6WNP/pdb</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bafna</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Krug</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Montelione</surname><given-names>GT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structural similarity of SARS-CoV2 M(pro) and HCV NS3/4A proteases suggests new approaches for identifying existing drugs useful as COVID-19 therapeutics (Preprint)</article-title><source>ChemRxiv</source><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.26434/chemrxiv.12153615.v1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Daczkowski</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Dzimianski</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name><name><surname>Clasman</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Goodwin</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Mesecar</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Pegan</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structural insights into the interaction of coronavirus papain-like proteases and Interferon-Stimulated Gene Product 15 from different species</article-title><source>J Mol Biol</source><year>2017</year><volume>429</volume><fpage>1661</fpage><lpage>1683</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jmb.2017.04.011</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eastman</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name><name><surname>Roth</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Brimacombe</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name><surname>Simeonov</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Patnaik</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Remdesivir: A review of Its discovery and development leading to emergency use authorization for treatment of COVID-19</article-title><source>ACS Cent Sci</source><year>2020</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>672</fpage><lpage>683</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acscentsci.0c00489</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Forli</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Huey</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Pique</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanner</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Goodsell</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Computational protein–ligand docking and virtual drug screening with the AutoDock suite</article-title><source>Nature Protocols</source><year>2016</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>905</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nprot.2016.051</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Niu</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Both Boceprevir and GC376 efficaciously inhibit SARS-CoV-2 by targeting its main protease</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2020</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>4417</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-020-18233-x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>SARS CoV-2 PLpro in complex with GRL0617</article-title><source>PDB ID 7CJM</source><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2210/pdb7CJM/pdb</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gorbalenya</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Koonin</surname><given-names>EV</given-names></name><name><surname>Donchenko</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Blinov</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Coronavirus genome: prediction of putative functional domains in the non-structural polyprotein by comparative amino acid sequence analysis</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>1989</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>4847</fpage><lpage>4861</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/17.12.4847</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Jang</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bouhaddou</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Obernier</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Meara</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Rezelj</surname><given-names>VV</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>JZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Swaney</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A SARS-CoV-2 protein interaction map reveals targets for drug repurposing</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41586-020-2286-9</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grum-Tokars</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Ratia</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Begaye</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Mesecar</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluating the 3C-like protease activity of SARS-Coronavirus: recommendations for standardized assays for drug discovery</article-title><source>Virus Res</source><year>2008</year><volume>133</volume><fpage>63</fpage><lpage>73</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.virusres.2007.02.015</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Holm</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Sander</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Protein structure comparison by alignment of distance matrices</article-title><source>J Mol Biol</source><year>1993</year><volume>233</volume><fpage>123</fpage><lpage>138</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/jmbi.1993.1489</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Holm</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Sander</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Protein folds and families: sequence and structure alignments</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>1999</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>244</fpage><lpage>247</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/27.1.244</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ianevski</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Giri</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Aittokallio</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>SynergyFinder 2.0: visual analytics of multi-drug combination synergies</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2020</year><volume>48</volume><fpage>W488</fpage><lpage>W493</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkaa216</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Structure of M(pro) from COVID-19 virus and discovery of its inhibitors</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41586-020-2223-y</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kester</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name><name><surname>Matthews</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparison of the structures of carboxypeptidase A and thermolysin</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1977</year><volume>252</volume><fpage>7704</fpage><lpage>7710</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kolb</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferreira</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Irwin</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Shoichet</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Docking and chemoinformatic screens for new ligands and targets</article-title><source>Curr Opin Biotechnol</source><year>2009</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>429</fpage><lpage>436</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.copbio.2009.08.003</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kolb</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Irwin</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Docking screens: right for the right reasons?</article-title><source>Curr Top Med Chem</source><year>2009</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>755</fpage><lpage>770</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2174/156802609789207091</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lindner</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lytvyn</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Lachance</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Ziomek</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Menard</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Selectivity in ISG15 and ubiquitin recognition by the SARS coronavirus papain-like protease</article-title><source>Arch Biochem Biophys</source><year>2007</year><volume>466</volume><fpage>8</fpage><lpage>14</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.abb.2007.07.006</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Sacco</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Hurst</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Townsend</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Szeto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Tarbet</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Marty</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Boceprevir, GC-376, and calpain inhibitors II, XII inhibit SARS-CoV-2 viral replication by targeting the viral main protease</article-title><source>Cell Res</source><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41422-020-0356-z</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McGonagle</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharif</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Regan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bridgewood</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of cytokines including Interleukin-6 in COVID-19 induced pneumonia and macrophage activation syndrome-like disease</article-title><source>Autoimmun Rev</source><year>2020</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>102537</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.autrev.2020.102537</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Huey</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindstrom</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanner</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Belew</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Goodsell</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>AutoDock4 and AutoDockTools4: Automated docking with selective receptor flexibility</article-title><source>J Comput Chem</source><year>2009</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>2785</fpage><lpage>2791</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jcc.21256</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Orengo</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Michie</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name><name><surname>Swindells</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Thornton</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>CATH--a hierarchic classification of protein domain structures</article-title><source>Structure</source><year>1997</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>1093</fpage><lpage>1108</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0969-2126(97)00260-8</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oudshoorn</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Rijs</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Limpens</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Groen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Koster</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Snijder</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kikkert</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Barcena</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Expression and cleavage of Middle East Respiratory Syndrome Coronavirus nsp3-4 polyprotein induces the formation of double-membrane vesicles that mimic those associated with coronaviral RNA replication</article-title><source>mBio</source><year>2017</year><volume>8</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/mBio.01658-17</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ozen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Prachanronarong</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Matthew</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name><name><surname>Soumana</surname><given-names>DI</given-names></name><name><surname>Schiffer</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Resistance outside the substrate envelope: hepatitis C NS3/4A protease inhibitors</article-title><source>Crit Rev Biochem Mol Biol</source><year>2019</year><volume>54</volume><fpage>11</fpage><lpage>26</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/10409238.2019.1568962</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Peto</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Abdool Karim</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Alejandria</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>HenaoRestrepo</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hernández García</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kieny</surname><given-names>M-P</given-names></name><name><surname>Malekzadeh</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Murthy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Preziosi</surname><given-names>M-P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Repurposed antiviral drugs for COVID-19 – interim WHO SOLIDARITY trial results (preprint)</article-title><source>MedRciv</source><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2020.10.15.20209817</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Structural and biochemical characterization of the nsp12-nsp7-nsp8 core polymerase complex from SARS-CoV-2</article-title><source>Cell Rep</source><year>2020</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>107774</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.celrep.2020.107774</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Robertus</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Alden</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Birktoft</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kraut</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Powers</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilcox</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An x-ray crystallographic study of the binding of peptide chloromethyl ketone inhibitors to subtilisin BPN'</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><year>1972</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>2439</fpage><lpage>2449</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/bi00763a009</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sheahan</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name><name><surname>Sims</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Pruijssers</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Agostini</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Leist</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Schafer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Dinnon</surname><given-names>KH</given-names><prefix>3rd</prefix></name><name><surname>Stevens</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>An orally bioavailable broad-spectrum antiviral inhibits SARS-CoV-2 in human airway epithelial cell cultures and multiple coronaviruses in mice</article-title><source>Sci Transl Med</source><year>2020</year><volume>12</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/scitranslmed.abb5883</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Snijder</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Limpens</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>de Wilde</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>de Jong</surname><given-names>AWM</given-names></name><name><surname>Zevenhoven-Dobbe</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Maier</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Faas</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Koster</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Barcena</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A unifying structural and functional model of the coronavirus replication organelle: Tracking down RNA synthesis</article-title><source>PLoS Biol</source><year>2020</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>e3000715</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.3000715</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Swaim</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Canadeo</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Monte</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Khanna</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lenschow</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Huibregtse</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Modulation of extracellular ISG15 signaling by pathogens and viral effector proteins</article-title><source>Cell Rep</source><year>2020</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>107772</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.celrep.2020.107772</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Swaim</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><name><surname>Canadeo</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Huibregtse</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Extracellular ISG15 signals cytokine secretion through the LFA-1 integrin receptor</article-title><source>Mol Cell</source><year>2017</year><volume>68</volume><fpage>581</fpage><lpage>590 e585</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molcel.2017.10.003</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wolff</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Limpens</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Zevenhoven-Dobbe</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Laugks</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>de Jong</surname><given-names>AWM</given-names></name><name><surname>Koning</surname><given-names>RI</given-names></name><name><surname>Agard</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Grunewald</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Koster</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A molecular pore spans the double membrane of the coronavirus replication organelle</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2020a</year><volume>369</volume><fpage>1395</fpage><lpage>1398</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.abd3629</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wolff</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Melia</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Snijder</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Barcena</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Double-membrane vesicles as platforms for viral replication</article-title><source>Trends Microbiol</source><year>2020b</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>1022</fpage><lpage>1033</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tim.2020.05.009</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R37"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>ZG</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Tao</surname><given-names>ZW</given-names></name><name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Pei</surname><given-names>YY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A new coronavirus associated with human respiratory disease in China</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2020b</year><volume>579</volume><fpage>265</fpage><lpage>269</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41586-020-2008-3</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R38"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kusov</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Nian</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>von Brunn</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Leyssen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Lanko</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Neyts</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>alpha-Ketoamides as broad-spectrum inhibitors of Coronavirus and Enterovirus replication: Structure-based design, synthesis, and activity assessment</article-title><source>J Med Chem</source><year>2020a</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.jmedchem.9b01828</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R39"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Curth</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Drosten</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Sauerhering</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rox</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hilgenfeld</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Crystal structure of SARS-CoV-2 main protease provides a basis for design of improved alpha-ketoamide inhibitors</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2020b</year><volume>368</volume><fpage>409</fpage><lpage>412</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.abb3405</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R40"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Sridharan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Krug</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Influenza B virus non-structural protein 1 counteracts ISG15 antiviral activity by sequestering ISGylated viral proteins</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2016</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>12754</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncomms12754</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><ref-list><title>STAR Methods References</title><ref id="R41"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Amanat</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Miorin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Strohmeier</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>McMahon</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Meade</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name><name><surname>Albrecht</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Martinez-Sobrido</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>An In Vitro Microneutralization Assay for SARS-CoV-2 Serology and Drug Screening</article-title><source>Curr Protoc Microbiol</source><year>2020</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>e108</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cpmc.108</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R42"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>DeLano</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The PyMOL Molecular Graphics System, Version 1.2r3pre, Schrödinger, LLC</article-title><year>2009</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R43"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lanevski</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Giri</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Aittokallio</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>SynergyFinder 2.0: visual analytics of multi-drug combination synergies</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2020</year><volume>48</volume><fpage>W488</fpage><lpage>W493</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkaa216</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R44"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Sacco</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Hurst</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Townsend</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Szeto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Tarbet</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Marty</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Boceprevir, GC-376, and calpain inhibitors II, XII inhibit SARS-CoV-2 viral replication by targeting the viral main protease</article-title><source>Cell Res</source><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41422-020-0356-z</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R45"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Goodsell</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Halliday</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Huey</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Hart</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name><name><surname>Belew</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Automated docking using a Lamarckian genetic algorithm and an empirical binding free energy function</article-title><source>J Comput Chem</source><year>1998</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>1639</fpage><lpage>1662</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/(SICI)1096-987X(19981115)19:14&lt;1639::AID-JCC10&gt;3.0.CO;2-B</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R46"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Huey</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindstrom</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanner</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Belew</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Goodsell</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>AutoDock4 and AutoDockTools4: Automated docking with selective receptor flexibility</article-title><source>J Comput Chem</source><year>2009</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>2785</fpage><lpage>2791</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jcc.21256</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R47"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Salentin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Schreiber</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Haupt</surname><given-names>VJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Adasme</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Schroeder</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>PLIP: fully automated protein-ligand interaction profiler</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2015</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>W443</fpage><lpage>447</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkv315</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R48"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sanner</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Python: a programming language for software integration and development</article-title><source>J Mol Graph Model</source><year>1999</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>57</fpage><lpage>61</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R49"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Curth</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Drosten</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Sauerhering</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rox</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hilgenfeld</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Crystal structure of SARS-CoV-2 main protease provides a basis for design of improved alpha-ketoamide inhibitors</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2020</year><volume>368</volume><fpage>409</fpage><lpage>412</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.abb3405</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><boxed-text id="BX1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><sec id="S26"><title>Highlights</title><list list-type="bullet" id="L1"><list-item><p>Several HCV protease inhibitors are predicted to inhibit SARS-CoV-2 M<sup>pro</sup> and PL<sup>pro</sup>.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Seven HCV drugs inhibit M<sup>pro</sup> enzyme activity, four HCV drugs inhibit PL<sup>pro</sup>.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Seven HCV drugs inhibit SARS-CoV-2 replication in Vero and/or human cells.</p></list-item><list-item><p>HCV drugs simeprevir and grazoprevir synergize with remdesivir to inhibit SARS-CoV-2.</p></list-item></list></sec><sec id="S27"><title>eTOC blurb</title><p>Bafna, White and colleagues report that several available hepatitis C virus drugs inhibit the SARS-CoV-2 M<sup>pro</sup> and/or PL<sup>pro</sup> proteases and SARS-CoV-2 replication in cell culture. Two drugs, simeprevir and grazoprevir, synergize with the viral polymerase inhibitor remdesivir to inhibit virus replication, increasing remdesivir antiviral activity as much as 10-fold.</p></sec></boxed-text><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><title>The substrate binding cleft and active site of SARS-CoV-2 M<sup>pro</sup> and HCV protease NS3/4A have remarkable structural similarity.</title><p>(A) SARS-CoV-2 M<sup>pro</sup> (PDB 6Y2G) and (B) HCV protease NS3/4A (PDB 2P59) both have a double β-barrel fold architecture, with a substrate binding site located in a shallow cleft between two the antiparallel β-barrels (shown in cyan and blue). Only one protomer is shown for both structures. The a-helical dimerization domain III of M<sup>pro</sup> is shown in green. The structures of bound inhibitors in these crystal structures are illustrated as magenta sticks. (C) The backbone structure of the SARS-CoV-2 M<sup>pro</sup> (green) is superimposed on the backbone structure of HCV protease NS3/4A (orange). The regions identified by DALI as structurally-analogous are shown in color (green and orange), and the regions that are not structurally-analogous are shown in gray. This superimposition of backbone atoms results in superimposition of the catalytic residues Cys145 and His41 of the SARS-CoV-2 M<sup>pro</sup> with Ser139 and His57 of HCV protease. Asp81 of the HCV protease catalytic triad is also shown. (D) <italic>AutoDock</italic> docking scores for 10 HCV protease inhibitors in the substrate binding cleft of SARS-CoV-2 M<sup>pro</sup>. The docking score for M<sup>pro</sup> inhibitor 13b (<italic>AutoDock</italic> score = −9.03 kcal/mol) is also shown as a horizontal red dashed line. (E) Comparison of the boceprevir (BOC) binding pose in best-scoring <italic>AutoDock</italic> complex (magenta) with the X-ray crystal structure of BOC-M<sup>pro</sup> complex (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">Anson and Mesecar, 2020</xref>) (green, PDB id 6WNP). (F) Comparison of BOC binding poses in X-ray crystal structures complexes with HCV NS3/4A protease (orange, PDB id 2OC8) and SARS-CoV-2 M<sup>pro</sup> protease (green, PDB id 6WNP). (G - I) Best-scoring <italic>AutoDock</italic> poses for complexes of vaniprevir (VAN), simeprevir (SIM), and narlaprevir (NAR) with M<sup>pro</sup>. Residues forming hydrogen bonds (yellow solid line) and hydrophobic interactions (black dash) are labelled.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS108620-f001"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><title>HCV protease inhibitors inhibit SARS-CoV-2 M<sup>pro</sup>.</title><p>(A) Initial rates of proteolysis of a peptide substrate by M<sup>pro</sup> in the presence of 20 mM inhibitor concentrations (v<sub>i</sub>) relative to initial rate in the absence of inhibitor (v<sub>i,o</sub>), at 25° C. (B) Dose response curves based on FRET assay for inhibition of M<sup>pro</sup> using the indicated peptide substrate, by narlaprevir (NAR), boceprevir (BOC), and telaprevir (TEL). In these FRET assays, the M<sup>pro</sup> concentration is 10 nM, and the substrate concentration is 20 mM. (C) 1D <sup>1</sup>H-NMR assay for hydrolysis of the indicated peptide substrate. The amide proton doublets of Phe-10 prior to cleavage (F10_uncleaved) or of Gln-7 after cleavage (Q7_cleaved) provide well-resolved resonances for monitoring the proteolysis reaction. The amide proton doublet of Glu-14 (E14) is not perturbed by cleavage, and provides an internal intensity calibration control. Grazoprevir (GRZ) has resonances (labeled by *) that overlap with the upfield component of the E14 doublet. (D) Percent cleavage of the indicated peptide substrate by M<sup>pro</sup> after 30 min at 25° C. These NMR studies used an M<sup>pro</sup> enzyme concentration of 100 nM, peptide substrate concentration of 50 mM, and inhibitor drug concentrations of 50 mM.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS108620-f002"/></fig><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Fig 3</label><caption><title>HCV protease inhibitors also inhibit SARS-CoV-2 PL<sup>pro</sup>.</title><p>(A) <italic>AutoDock</italic> docking scores for 10 HCV protease inhibitors in the substrate binding cleft of SARS-CoV-2 PL<sup>pro</sup>. The docking score for PL<sup>pro</sup> inhibitor GRL-0617 (<italic>AutoDock score</italic> = −7.54 kcal / mol) is also shown as a horizontal red dashed line. (B) Best-scoring <italic>AutoDock</italic> poses for complexes of simeprevir (SIM) and vaniprevir (VAN) with PL<sup>pro</sup>. (C) Initial rates of proteolysis of a peptide substrate by PL<sup>pro</sup> in the presence of 20 μM inhibitor concentrations (<italic>v</italic>
<sub>i</sub>) relative to initial rate in the absence of inhibitor (<italic>v</italic>
<sub>i,o</sub>), at 25° C. Grazoprevir inhibition of PL<sup>pro</sup> was even stronger (<italic>v</italic>
<sub>o</sub>/<italic>v</italic>
<sub>o,i</sub> = 32 ± 7%) at 100 μM drug concentration (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Figure S3B</xref>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS108620-f003"/></fig><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><title>Antiviral activity of HCV protease inhibitors in Vero E6 cells.</title><p>(A – I) Inhibition of viral replication was determined in a concentration-dependent matter in Vero E6 cells. Replication assays were performed at multiplicity of infection (moi) of 0.025 plaque forming units (pfus) /cell. In all panels, viral infectivity is shown as a solid line and cell viability as a dashed line. Data = mean ± SD; n = 3 independent samples. The estimated IC<sub>50</sub> is labeled in the upper left corner of each plot. Remdesivir is included as a standard of care control. (J) Time of addition assay. 10 mM of remdesivir or 50 mM of grazoprevir were added to cells at the indicted time points before (−2 hrs), at (0 hrs), or after (+2 or +4 hrs) viral infection.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS108620-f004"/></fig><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><title>Antiviral activity of HCV protease inhibitors in HEK293T cells.</title><p>(A – J) Inhibition of viral replication was determined in a concentration-dependent matter in HEK293T cells. Replication assays were performed at multiplicity of infection (moi) of 0.025 plaque forming units (pfus) /cell. In all panels, viral infectivity is shown as a solid line and cell viability as a dashed line. Data = mean ± SD; n = 3 independent samples. Calculated IC<sub>50</sub> is indicated in the upper left corner of each plot. Remdesivir is included as a standard of care control.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS108620-f005"/></fig><fig id="F6" position="float"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><title>Simeprevir and grazoprevir are synergistic with remdesivir in Vero E6 cells.</title><p>(A - C) SARS-CoV-2 inhibition by remdesivir in the presence of increasing concentrations of simeprevir, grazoprevir, or boceprevir. (D - F) SARS-CoV-2 inhibition by simeprevir, grazoprevir, or boceprevir in the presence of increasing concentrations of remdesivir. (G - I) Synergy landscapes and combination scores generated by the ZIP method using the program <italic>SynergyFinder</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">Ianevski et al., 2020</xref>). Red surfaces denote a synergistic interaction, and green surfaces an antagonistic interaction. In this model a synergistic interaction between drugs has a score greater than +10; an additive interaction has a score between −10 to +10; and an antagonistic interaction has a score of less than −10 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">Ianevski et al., 2020</xref>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="EMS108620-f006"/></fig><table-wrap id="T1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>HCV 3C/4A Protease Inhibitors</title></caption><table frame="box" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="center" valign="top">Inhibitor (Trade Name)</th><th align="center" valign="top">Identifier of Protease Inhibitor</th><th align="center" valign="top">Trade Name Manufacturer</th><th align="center" valign="top">Drug Status</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center" valign="top">Vaniprevir</td><td align="center" valign="top">VAN</td><td align="center" valign="top">MK-7009 Merck</td><td align="center" valign="top">Investigational</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top">Simeprevir</td><td align="center" valign="top">SIM</td><td align="center" valign="top">Olysio / Medivir Janssen</td><td align="center" valign="top">Prescription Drug</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top">Paritaprevir</td><td align="center" valign="top">PAR</td><td align="center" valign="top">Veruprevir / ABT-450 Abbott Laboratories</td><td align="center" valign="top">Prescription Drug</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top">Danoprevir</td><td align="center" valign="top">DAN</td><td align="center" valign="top">Ganovo Array / Pfizer, Roche / Ascletis</td><td align="center" valign="top">Investigational</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top">Narlaprevir</td><td align="center" valign="top">NAR</td><td align="center" valign="top">Arlansa Merck / R-Pharm</td><td align="center" valign="top">Prescription Drug</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top">Grazoprevir</td><td align="center" valign="top">GRZ</td><td align="center" valign="top">Zepatier Merck</td><td align="center" valign="top">Prescription Drug</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top">Glecaprevir</td><td align="center" valign="top">GLE</td><td align="center" valign="top">Mavyret<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFN1">a</xref> Maviret<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TFN1">a</xref> AbbVie / Enanta</td><td align="center" valign="top">Prescription Drug</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top">Boceprevir</td><td align="center" valign="top">BOC</td><td align="center" valign="top">Victrelis Merck</td><td align="center" valign="top">Prescription Drug</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top">Telaprevir</td><td align="center" valign="top">TEL</td><td align="center" valign="top">Incivek / Incivo Vertex / J&amp;J</td><td align="center" valign="top">Prescription Drug</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="top">Asunaprevir</td><td align="center" valign="top">ASU</td><td align="center" valign="top">Sunvepra Bristol-Myers Squibb</td><td align="center" valign="top">Investigational</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TFN1"><label>a</label><p id="P65">Mavyret (or Maviret) is a multidrug formulation including glecaprevir and pibrentasvir.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></floats-group></article>