<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="preprint">
<?all-math-mml yes?>
<?use-mml?>
<?origin ukpmcpa?>
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">bioRxiv</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>bioRxiv : the preprint server for biology</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="ppub"/>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">EMS96076</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2020.09.21.306357</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="archive">PPR217216</article-id>
<article-version article-version-type="publisher-id">1</article-version>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Article</subject>
</subj-group>
</article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Cryo-EM structure of S-Trimer, a subunit vaccine candidate for COVID-19</article-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
<name>
<surname>Ma</surname>
<given-names>Jiahao</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes">
<name>
<surname>Su</surname>
<given-names>Danmei</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Huang</surname>
<given-names>Xueqin</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Liang</surname>
<given-names>Ying</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Ma</surname>
<given-names>Yan</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Liang</surname>
<given-names>Peng</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CR1">†</xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zheng</surname>
<given-names>Sanduo</given-names>
</name>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CR1">†</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="A1">
<label>1</label>National Institute of Biological Sciences, 102206 Beijing, China</aff>
<aff id="A2">
<label>2</label>Tsinghua Institute of Multidisciplinary Biomedical Research, Tsinghua University, 102206 Beijing, China</aff>
<aff id="A3">
<label>3</label>Clover Biopharmaceuticals, Chengdu, China</aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="CR1">
<label>†</label>Corresponding authors. <email>zhengsanduo@nibs.ac.cn</email> and <email>liang.peng@cloverbiopharma.com</email>
</corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted">
<day>24</day>
<month>09</month>
<year>2020</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="preprint">
<day>21</day>
<month>09</month>
<year>2020</year>
</pub-date>
<permissions>
<license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">
<license-p>This work is licensed under a <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">CC BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license</ext-link>.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<abstract>
<p id="P1">Less than a year after its emergence, the severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) has infected over 22 million people worldwide with a death toll approaching 1 million. Vaccination remains the best hope to ultimately put this pandemic to an end. Here, using Trimer-Tag technology, we produced both wild-type (WT) and furin site mutant (MT) S-Trimers for COVID-19 vaccine studies. Cryo-EM structures of the WT and MT S-Trimers, determined at 3.2 Å and 2.6 Å respectively, revealed that both antigens adopt a tightly closed conformation and their structures are essentially identical to that of the previously solved full-length WT S protein in detergent. These results validate Trimer-Tag as a platform technology in production of metastable WT S-Trimer as a candidate for COVID-19 subunit vaccine.</p>
</abstract>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<p id="P2">The emergence of SARS-CoV-2 in late 2019 has led to a global pandemic and has disrupted lives and global economies on a scale unseen in recent human history. This is not the first time when a new coronavirus has posted as a major threat to public health; both SARS-CoV and Middle East Respiratory Syndrome (MERS-CoV) caused human infections within past 17 years (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1">1</xref>). The fact that no licensed vaccines have ever been approved for these highly similar viruses is a reminder for the great challenges we face when hundreds of companies and institutions worldwide rush to develop COVID-19 vaccines with multiple strategies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2">2</xref>).</p>
<p id="P3">A successful vaccine that could truly impact the course of this ongoing COVID-19 pandemic has to have four key characteristics: safety, efficacy, scalability (to billions of doses to meet global demand), and speed. Although protein subunit vaccines have excellent track records for the first three requirements, exemplified by the highly successful vaccine Gardasil used to prevent HPV infections (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R3">3</xref>) and Shingrix vaccine for containing herpes zoster virus infections (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4">4</xref>), subunit vaccine development can take years to decades to complete. Many of the difficulties reside in the manufacturing processes that have to ensure a fully native-like antigen structure is retained, starting from subunit vaccine designs. Similar to other enveloped RNA viruses such as HIV, RSV and influenza, coronaviruses including SARS-CoV-2 also use a ubiquitous trimeric viral surface antigen (Spike protein) to gain entry into host cells. In the case of SARS-CoV-2, this occurs via binding to ACE2 receptor expressed in target cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref>). Approaches for using a non-covalent trimer-foldon from bacterial phage GCN4 protein to stabilize the trimer conformation while simultaneously introducing mutations in viral antigens to abolish furin cleavage and stabilize the antigen in pre-fusion forms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref>) are common strategies inherited from decades of HIV and RSV vaccine studies, but these have yet to yield a successful vaccine.</p>
<p id="P4">Using Trimer-Tag technology (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8">8</xref>), we produced both soluble wild-type (WT) and a furin site mutant (MT) (R685A) forms of S-Trimer from CHO cells in serum-free fed-batch processes in bioreactors with protein yield ranging from 0.5 -1 g/L (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">fig. S1A</xref>). These antigen titers are three orders of magnitude higher than that reported previously for foldon derived S proteins with two Pro mutations (S-2P) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref>), laying a solid foundation for scalability requirement of a successful COVID-19 vaccine. Both S-Trimers consist of the ectodomain (amino acid residues 1-1211) of SARS-CoV-2 Spike protein fused in-frame to the C-terminal region of human type I (α) collagen, which spontaneously form a disulfide-bond linked homo-trimer, thereby stabilizing the antigens in trimeric forms (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig.1A-B</xref>). Using a tailored affinity purification scheme that employs a collagen receptor Endo180-Fc fusion protein that binds to the Trimer-Tag with high affinity, the secreted S-Trimers were purified to near homogeneity in a single step (see accompanying paper). Reducing SDS-PAGE analysis of the purified S-Trimers revealed that the WT S-Trimer was metastable and partially cleaved precisely at S1/S2 boundary by furin, while a single point mutation (R685A) in MT S-Trimer fully abolished the protease cleavage (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig.1C</xref>). WT spike proteins from live SARS-CoV-2 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9">9</xref>) or recombinant full-length S (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>) were all previously shown to be partially cleaved apparently at S1/S2 boundary by furin proteases. In contrast, an S-Trimer derived from wild-type SARS-CoV-1 S-protein produced in the same manner was essentially uncleaved by furin protease, like the MT S-Trimer from SARS-CoV-2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig.1C</xref>). Receptor binding studies using ForteBio BioLayer interferometry showed that all three S-Trimers had similar high affinity to ACE2-Fc with 1.2 nM (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">fig. S1B</xref>), similar to previous reports using purified S-2P protein (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref>). Furthermore, our finding of SARS-CoV-1 S-Trimer having a similar, if not higher affinity to ACE2-Fc than that of SARS-CoV-2, seems to be contradictory to the hypothesis that the difference in virulence between the two viral strains stems from difference in their receptor binding affinities (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5">5</xref>). Instead, our finding supports that the much higher infectivity of SARS-CoV-2 is more likely attributed to furin cleavage of the spike protein that is largely absent in that of SARS-CoV-1 and other earlier stains of coronaviruses (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref>).</p>
<p id="P5">Negative staining electron microscopy (EM) analysis of the MT S-Trimer revealed homogeneous particles consistent with trimeric spike proteins connected to the Trimer-Tag (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1D</xref>). Particles with similar structural features have also been observed by negative-stain EM for WT S-Trimer (see accompanying paper).</p>
<p id="P6">To further investigate structural details of these vaccine candidates, we first sought to determine the cryo-EM structure of the MT S-Trimer which is more tractable for structural determination. While the particles showed preferred top-view orientation when embedded in ice, they preferentially adopted side view orientation on graphene oxide-coated grids (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">fig. S2</xref>). Combination of the two datasets enabled us to obtain a structure at 2.6 Å resolution (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2A</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">fig. S3</xref>). Due to the high resolution, the EM density for side chains was clear and water molecules could be observed in the structure (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">fig. S3D-3H and Table S1</xref>). In addition to all the glycosylation sites and disulfide bonds previously observed in the S-2P structure (PDBID: 6VXX), the disulfide bond between Cys15 and Cys136 and the N-linked glycan at Asn17, both in the NTD domains, were well resolved in our structure (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">fig. S4 and Table S2</xref>). The Trimer-Tag was invisible in our structure due to highly flexible nature of the linker between the soluble S and the C-prodomain of collagen. After 3D classification without imposing three-fold symmetry (C3), we found that all three RBD domains in our map adopt a closed conformation (RBD down) without any open conformation (RBD up) that was previously observed in the S-2P structure (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6">6</xref>). Moreover, when the S2 domains were aligned, three S1 domains shift toward the three-fold axis compared to that in the S-2P structure, forming a tightly closed trimer (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">fig. S5</xref>). Surprisingly, we observed unaccounted for EM density in both the NTD and RBD region of the S1 domain. The presence of polysorbate 80 (PS80) during the purification process suggested that the bulky EM density in the NTD region could be accounted for by PS80 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">fig. S3E</xref>). The EM density in the RBD region is elongated and in close proximity to R408, we speculate it may be oleic acid or linoleic acid which is present in the culture medium (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">fig. S3F</xref>). Indeed, PS80 and oleic acid could be well fitted into the density of the NTD domain and the RBD domain, respectively, owing to the excellent quality of EM map (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2A</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">fig. S3D-3F</xref>). Mass spectrometry analysis further confirmed their identities (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">fig. S6</xref>). Interestingly, instead of oleic acid seen in our structure, linoleic acid as well as PS80 were also observed in the recently published structure of a full-length mutant S protein (3Q-2P-FL) produced from insect cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref>). PS80 is buried deeply in the hydrophobic pocket residues with a few hydrophilic residues including N99, N121, R190 and H207 making hydrogen bonds with the hydroxyl group of the PS80 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2B</xref>). Notably, PS80 engages hydrophobic interactions with F175 and M177 which are invisible in the S-2P structure (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2C</xref>). Since no small molecule was shown to bind to the S-2P structure, PS80 likely stabilizes the disordered loops of the NTD domain, making them more ordered (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2B and 2C</xref>). The oleic acid located in the hydrophobic pocket of the RBD domain engaged a salt bridge interaction with R408 at the adjacent protomer through its carboxylic acid group, bringing the RBD domain in close proximity and resulting in the tightly closed conformation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2D</xref>).</p>
<p id="P7">Recent studies have shown that low pH can stabilize the S-Trimer (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref>). Indeed, negative staining EM analysis of WT S-Trimer at pH 5.5 revealed more homogenous trimer than that at physiological pH (See accompanying paper). In light of this finding, we were able to determine the cryo-EM structure of the WT S-Trimer at 3.2 Å resolution at pH 5.5 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Fig. S7 and Table S1</xref>). The structure of the WT S-Trimer resembled that of the MT form with a root mean square deviation of 0.5 Å over 2773 Ca atoms (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3A</xref>). Oleic acid was well resolved in the WT structure but the density for the PS80 was weak, likely due to the low resolution or low occupancy. As a result, the NTD domain of the WT S-Trimer was less well resolved than that of MT (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3A</xref>). It has been shown that a pH-dependent switch domain (residue 824-848, pH switch 1) undergoes dramatic conformational change at different pH values (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref>). However, this region was nearly identical between our two structures (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3B</xref>). Instead, a fragment (residue 617-639) we named pH switch 2 at the CTD1 region of the S1 domain before the furin cleavage site displays significant structural arrangement. Whereas this region appeared disordered in the MT structure at physiological pH conditions, it was well ordered and formed a helix-turn-helix structural motif in the WT structure at pH 5.5 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3C</xref>). From structural perspective, lower pH likely contributes to this structural arrangement. At physiological pH, R319 forms salt bridge interactions with D737 and D745 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3D</xref>). At lower pH, the protonation of D737 and D745 weakens these interactions. As a result, R319 flips to the other side and makes hydrophobic interactions with W633 and L629 through its aliphatic chain, leading to the ordered helix-turn-helix motif (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3E</xref>). The newly-formed structural motif makes direct contact with the previously identified pH switch 1 of the adjacent protomer, accounting for the enhanced stability of the WT S-Trimer at lower pH (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3A</xref>). The structural arrangement of pH switch 2 in different pH was also observed in previous studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref>), further supporting the conformational change between the MT and WT S-Trimer structures was due to the different pH but not to the mutation in the furin site.</p>
<p id="P8">In contrast to the structural differences described above for S-2P protein, both of our WT and MT S-Trimer were nearly identical to the recently published structures of full-length wild-type S (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>) and 3Q-2P-FL (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R7">7</xref>) purified in detergent from HEK293 and sf9 insect cell membranes, respectively. When revisiting the electron density map for full-length wild-type S protein (EMDB: 22292), we spotted unassigned density at the same position as oleic acid which was absent in the S-2P map (EMDB: 21452) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">fig. S8</xref>). Therefore, fatty acid binding at the RBD domain may stabilize the tightly closed conformation, accounting for the conformational difference from S-2P. Based on the structural similarity among all published structures of SARS-CoV-2 S protein, we can classify them into three distinct states: a tightly closed state, a loosely closed state and an open state (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4A</xref>). A conformational switch (residue 835-858) previously known as the pH switch or the fusion-peptide proximal region (FPPR) is critical for conformational transition from the tightly closed state to the open state (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4B</xref>). In the tightly closed state which is less accessible to the receptor, three RBDs are down and in closer proximity to one another. The conformational switch region is well ordered and stabilizes this tightly closed state. Recently, D614G mutation has become predominant over the ancestral form worldwide and has been shown to increase viral infections (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref>). In the tightly closed state, D614 makes a salt bridge interaction with K854 at the conformational switch region (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4C</xref>). From the tightly to the loosely closed state, the conformational switch undergoes a large conformational arrangement and becomes disordered (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4D</xref>). K854 flips to the opposite side and interacts with D568 and D574 of the CTD1, causing the S1 to move downwards relative to the S2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4A</xref>). Finally, the CTD1 domain further moves downwards and causes the RBD to adopt an open conformation for receptor binding (Movie S1). Therefore, D614G mutation abolishes the salt bridge interaction with K854 which in turn engages the CTD1 domain, thus favoring the open state.</p>
<p id="P9">To our knowledge, this is the first cryo-EM structure of the wild-type S protein in soluble and cleavable form without the transmembrane domain, confirming structural integrity of this metastable wild-type form of COVID-19 subunit vaccine candidate. While most vaccine candidates currently in clinical trials incorportated furin site and double proline mutations, our wild-type S-Trimer offers a more native-like antigen for potentially more effective and broader protection against SARS-CoV-2 infection. Thus, Trimer-Tag technology that has been proven here to be able to rapidly produce large quantities of native-like S-Trimer antigen, may offer a platform technology for subunit vaccine development for enveloped RNA viruses that use ubiquitous trimeric antigens to invade host cells.</p>
<p id="P10">Like the previously reported structure of full-length WT S protein purified in detergent micelles, it is unclear whether the furin cleavage site in our resolved WT S-Trimer structure is cleaved. Moreover, we could not exclude the possibility that other conformational states exist in the WT sample that were not captured in our cryo-EM study since partial cleavage of the furin site may lead to some S1 dissociation from S-Trimer. Nevertheless, we are certain that the highly purified WT S-Trimer predominately adopts a pre-fusion state, unlike the full-length wild-type spike protein which forms both pre- and post-fusion states in the presence of detergent (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>).</p>
<p id="P11">Consistent with structural studies reported here showing that WT S-Trimer is native-like, preclinical studies showed that this COVID-19 vaccine candidate resulted in rapid and high-level induction of both neutralizing antibodies and Th1-biased cellular immune responses in mice, rats and nonhuman primates. Non-human primates immunized with WT S-Trimer were fully protected from SARS-CoV-2 viral challenge (See accompanying paper). Currently, an S-Trimer subunit vaccine candidate is under clinical investigation.</p>
<sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="SM">
<title>Supplementary Material</title>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1">
<label>Supplementary Material</label>
<media xlink:href="EMS96076-supplement-Supplementary_Material.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" id="N66074" position="anchor"/>
</supplementary-material>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack id="S1">
<title>Acknowlegements</title>
<p>We thank Xiaodong Wang for his coordination and input in this study. We thank Maofu Liao and Andrew C. Kruse for critical reading of the manuscript. We thank Hongwei Wang for providing graphene oxide coated grids. We also thank staff at Shuimu BioSciences for their assistance with cryo-EM data collection. All EM data were collected at Shuimu BioSciences.</p>
<sec id="S2">
<title>Funding</title>
<p>This work was supported by grants from Coalition for Epidemic Preparedness Innovations (CEPI), Chinese Ministry of Science and Technology, Beijing Municipal Commission of Science and Technology, Tsinghua University and Chengdu Bureau of Science &amp;Technology (2020-YF08- 00024-GX).</p>
</sec>
</ack>
<sec id="S3" sec-type="data-availability">
<title>Data and materials availability</title>
<p id="P12">The atomic structures have been deposited at the Protein Data Bank (PDB) under the accession codes XXX and XXX. The EM maps have been deposited at the Electron Microscopy Data Bank (EMDB) under the accession numbers XXX and XXX.</p>
</sec>
<fn-group>
<fn id="FN1" fn-type="con">
<p id="P13">
<bold>Author Contribution:</bold>
</p>
<p id="P14">D. S. expressed and purified the S-Trimers, J.M. collected negative stain EM images. J.M and S.Z. prepared cryo grids and collected cryo-EM data. X. H and Y. L performed ForteBio affinity analysis. S.Z. performed cryo-EM data processing and model building. Y.M. did mass spectrometry experiments. S.Z. and P.L conceived this project, directed the experiments and wrote the manuscript with input from all other authors.</p>
</fn>
<fn id="FN2" fn-type="conflict">
<p id="P15">
<bold>Competing interests:</bold>
</p>
<p id="P16">P.L. has ownership interest in Clover Biopharmaceuticals. All other authors declare no competing interests.</p>
</fn>
</fn-group>
<ref-list>
<title>References and notes</title>
<ref id="R1">
<label>1</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>de Wit</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>van Doremalen</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Falzarano</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Munster</surname>
<given-names>VJ</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>SARS and MERS: recent insights into emerging coronaviruses</article-title>
<source>Nat Rev Microbiol</source>
<year>2016</year>
<volume>14</volume>
<fpage>523</fpage>
<lpage>534</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R2">
<label>2</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Corey</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Mascola</surname>
<given-names>JR</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Fauci</surname>
<given-names>AS</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Collins</surname>
<given-names>FS</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>A strategic approach to COVID-19 vaccine R&amp;D</article-title>
<source>Science</source>
<year>2020</year>
<volume>368</volume>
<fpage>948</fpage>
<lpage>950</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R3">
<label>3</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Einstein</surname>
<given-names>MH</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>Comparison of the immunogenicity and safety of Cervarix and Gardasil human papillomavirus (HPV) cervical cancer vaccines in healthy women aged 18–45 years</article-title>
<source>Hum Vaccin</source>
<year>2009</year>
<volume>5</volume>
<fpage>705</fpage>
<lpage>719</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R4">
<label>4</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bharucha</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Ming</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Breuer</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>A critical appraisal of ‘Shingrix’, a novel herpes zoster subunit vaccine (HZ/Su or GSK1437173A) for varicella zoster virus</article-title>
<source>Hum Vaccin Immunother</source>
<year>2017</year>
<volume>13</volume>
<fpage>1789</fpage>
<lpage>1797</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R5">
<label>5</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Walls</surname>
<given-names>AC</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>Structure, Function, and Antigenicity of the SARS-CoV-2 Spike Glycoprotein</article-title>
<source>Cel</source>
<year>2020</year>
<volume>181</volume>
<fpage>281</fpage>
<lpage>292 e286</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R6">
<label>6</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wrapp</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>Cryo-EM structure of the 2019-nCoV spike in the prefusion conformation</article-title>
<source>Science</source>
<year>2020</year>
<volume>367</volume>
<fpage>1260</fpage>
<lpage>1263</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R7">
<label>7</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Bangaru</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>Structural analysis of full-length SARS-CoV-2 spike protein from an advanced vaccine candidate</article-title>
<source>bioRxiv</source>
<year>2020</year>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R8">
<label>8</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Liu</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>Improvement of Pharmacokinetic Profile of TRAIL via Trimer-Tag Enhances its Antitumor Activity in vivo</article-title>
<source>Sci Rep</source>
<year>2017</year>
<volume>7</volume>
<comment>8953</comment>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R9">
<label>9</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>Development of an Inactivated Vaccine Candidate, BBIBP-CorV, with Potent Protection against SARS-CoV-2</article-title>
<source>Cell</source>
<year>2020</year>
<volume>182</volume>
<fpage>713</fpage>
<lpage>721 e719</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R10">
<label>10</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Cai</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>Distinct conformational states of SARS-CoV-2 spike protein</article-title>
<source>Science</source>
<year>2020</year>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R11">
<label>11</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Hoffmann</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Kleine-Weber</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Pohlmann</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>A Multibasic Cleavage Site in the Spike Protein of SARS-CoV-2 Is Essential for Infection of Human Lung Cells</article-title>
<source>Mol Cel</source>
<year>2020</year>
<volume>78</volume>
<fpage>779</fpage>
<lpage>784 e775</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R12">
<label>12</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zhou</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>A pH-dependent switch mediates conformational masking of SARS-CoV-2 spike</article-title>
<source>bioRxiv</source>
<year>2020</year>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R13">
<label>13</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</name>
<etal/>
</person-group>
<article-title>The D614G mutation in the SARS-CoV-2 spike protein reduces S1 shedding and increases infectivity</article-title>
<source>bioRxiv</source>
<year>2020</year>
</element-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="R14">
<label>14</label>
<element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<name>
<surname>Grubaugh</surname>
<given-names>ND</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Hanage</surname>
<given-names>WP</given-names>
</name>
<name>
<surname>Rasmussen</surname>
<given-names>AL</given-names>
</name>
</person-group>
<article-title>Making Sense of Mutation: What D614G Means for the COVID-19 Pandemic Remains Unclear</article-title>
<source>Cel</source>
<year>2020</year>
<volume>182</volume>
<fpage>794</fpage>
<lpage>795</lpage>
</element-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
<floats-group>
<fig id="F1" position="float">
<label>Fig. 1</label>
<caption>
<p>Structural design of the trimerized SARS-CoV-2 spike protein. (A) Schematic representation of the full-length spike protein, WT S-Trimer and MT S-Trimer. The ectodomain of full-length S is fused with a trimer tag derived from the C-terminal domain of human type I(a) collagen to produce WT S-Trimer. A single point mutation R685A at the S1/S2 cleavage site was introduced in the WT S-Trimer to generate MT S-Trimer. The full-length S protein includes: S1, S2, S1/S2 cleavage site, transmembrane domain (TM) and cytoplasmic tail (CT). (B) Cartoon representation of the WT and MT S-Trimer. Structure of the ectodomain of the spike protein (PDB: 6VXX) and the C-terminal domain of collagen (PDB ID: 5K31) are shown as surface. Dashed line represents region not resolved in the structure. (C) The purified WT S-Trimer, MT S-Trimer of SARS-CoV-2 and SARS-CoV-1 are analyzed by Coomassie stained SDS-PAGE. (D) A representative negative-stain EM image of the MT S-Trimer.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="EMS96076-f001"/>
</fig>
<fig id="F2" position="float">
<label>Fig. 2</label>
<caption>
<p>Cryo-EM structure of the MT S-Trimer. (A) Ribbon representation of the MT structure colored by subunit from two orthogonal views. Oleic acid and PS80 are shown as spheres and colored in orange and yellow respectively. (B) Detailed view of the NTD domain bound to the PS80. Structure colored by magenta corresponds to the flexible region at the NTD of the S-2P structure. (C) Structure of the NTD domain of the S-2P (PDB ID: 6VXX). Dashed line represents disordered region. (D) Oleic acid bridges the two adjacent RBD domains. Oleic acid is colored in yellow and the side chains of the two adjacent RBDs colored in green and blue respectively. The EM density for oleic acid is shown.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="EMS96076-f002"/>
</fig>
<fig id="F3" position="float">
<label>Fig. 3</label>
<caption>
<p>Cryo-EM structure of the WT S-Trimer at pH 5.5. (A) Structural overlay of the MT and WT S-Trimer. MT was colored in grey, and WT colored by subunits. Two pH switches in the WT S-Trimer structure are boxed and colored in blue and orange respectively. Comparison of pH switch 1 (B) and pH switch 2 (C) between MT and WT S-Trimer. Dashed line represents disorder region in pH switch 2 of the MT structure. (D) pH switch 2 is flexible in the MT structure where R319 makes electrostatic interactions with D737 and D745. (E) At low pH, the switch 2 forms a helix-turn-helix motif in the WT structure in which R319 flips and stabilizes it.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="EMS96076-f003"/>
</fig>
<fig id="F4" position="float">
<label>Fig. 4</label>
<caption>
<p>Conformational change of the SARS-CoV-2 spike protein before engaging ACE2 receptor. (A) Conformation transition from the tightly closed conformation (WT/MT structure) to the loosely closed conformation (PDB ID: 6VXX), and finally to the open conformation (PDB ID: 6VYB). The direction of movement of the NTD and CTD1 of the S1 domain during conformational change is marked with an arrow. The conformation switch region boxed is disorder in both the loosely closed and open conformation and is represented as dashed line. (B) A close-up view of the conformational switch in three conformations. The ordered switch would clash with CTD1 domain in the loosely closed and open conformation (C) K854 in the switch region engages D614 in the tightly closed conformation. (D) In the loosely closed conformation, the switch region undergoes structural arrangement, in which K854 flips and pulls S1 domain downwards through interacting with D574 and D568 in the CTD1 region.</p>
</caption>
<graphic xlink:href="EMS96076-f004"/>
</fig>
</floats-group>
</article>
